Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast where I interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
Contest alert.
This week we have a jam-packed intro, including a new contest we're launching.
So please bear with me, you don't want to miss this one.
First, a bit about this week's shows.
As you may know, I spent a few days at CES earlier this month.
While there, I spoke with a bunch of folks applying AI in the consumer electronics industry,
and I'm including you in those conversations via this series of shows.
Stay tuned as we explore some of the very cool ways that machine learning and AI are being
used to enhance our everyday lives.
This includes work being done at Anki, who built Cosmo, the cutest little computer vision-powered
robot.
Nighthouse, whose smart home security camera combines 3D sensing with deep learning and NLP.
Intel, who's using the single-shot multi-box image detection algorithm to personalize video
fees for the Ferrari Challenge North America.
First beat, a company whose machine learning algorithms analyzed your heartbeat data to
provide personalized insights into stress, exercise, and sleep patterns.
3AI and Koito, who have partnered to bring machine learning-based adaptive driving beams
or automatically adjusting high beams to the US.
And last but not least, aerial.ai, who applies sophisticated analytics to Wi-Fi signals
to enable some really interesting home automation and healthcare applications.
Now, as if six amazing interviews wasn't enough, a few of these companies have been so
kind as to provide us with products for you, the Twimmel community.
And keeping with the theme of this series, our contest will be a little different this
time.
To enter, we want to hear from you about the role AI is playing in your home and personal
life, and where you see it going.
Just head on over to twimmelai.com slash myaicontest, fire up your webcam or smartphone camera,
and tell us your story in two minutes or less.
Go post the videos to YouTube, and the video with the most likes wins their choice of
great prizes, including an Anki Cosmo, a lighthouse smart home camera, and more.
Submissions will be taken until February 11th, and voting will remain open until February
18th.
Good luck.
Before we dive into today's show, I'd like to thank our friends at Intel AI for their
continued support of this podcast.
Intel was extremely active at this year's CES, with a bunch of AI autonomous driving
and VR related announcements.
One of the more interesting partnerships they announced was a collaboration with the Ferrari
Challenge North America race series.
Along with the folks at Ferrari Challenge, Intel AI aspires to make the race viewing experience
more personalized by using deep computer vision to detect and monitor individual race
cars via camera feeds, and allow viewers to choose the specific cars feeds that they'd
like to watch.
Look for my conversation with Intel's Andy Keller and Emil Chindicki earlier in this series
for an in-depth discussion about this project, and be sure to visit ai.intel.com where you'll
find Andy's technical blog post on the topic.
Now about today's show.
In this episode, I'm joined by Oka Koronen, Vice President of Technology at First
Speed, a company whose algorithms are embedded in fitness watches from companies like Garmin
and Sunto, and which use your heartbeat data to offer personalized insights into stress,
fitness, recovery, and sleep patterns.
We cover a ton about first beat in the conversation, including how they transform the center readings
into more actionable data, their use of a digital physiological model of the human body,
how they use center data to identify and predict physiological changes within the body,
and some of the opportunities that first beat has to further apply machine learning in
the future.
And now on to the show.
Alright everyone, I am on the line with Oka Koronen, Oka is Vice President of Technology
at First Beat, a company that I first met with at CES, in fact I met Oka at CES, and
he was kind enough to agree to jump on the line for an interview.
Oka, welcome to this week in machine learning in AI.
Thank you very much.
So why don't we get started by having you tell us a little bit about your background?
Yeah, so my background is that I've been doing biomedical engineering for basically
in time, my professional career I did on 90s, I was working on biomedical engineering
and ambulatory heart rate variability monitoring, believe it or not, and activity tracking,
but the technologies were quite different at that time.
So gradually I moved in, I did research at that time, but then gradually moving towards
wellness and preventative care, while finally later in 2009 I decided to take a career
move and went to industry first for Nokia and later I spent some colleagues, a company
called Pulse on which is an optical, one of the pioneers in optical heart rate tracking
and later on about a year ago I quit that and now I'm with First Beat on doing the next
level of the, in the stack, so to say the heart rate analysis rather than measurements.
So that's in brief my background.
And for those who aren't familiar with First Beat maybe a little bit more about what that
company does, I happen to know a teeny bit about it because First Beat's embedded in the
fitness watch that I use the Garmin Vivo Active 3.
Yeah, that's correct.
So our core business is that we are doing heart rate analytics, so we transform the heart
rate reading into something actionable and meaningful for the user.
We were established in 2002 as a spin of the University of Yvescola and we first looked
at heart rate variability as a pramder or method for controlling the athletes overtraining
but soon we realized that actually while we try to detect and prevent overtraining with
heart rate variability based methods, those are also applicable for regular people who
are struggling with stress and recovery.
So that's where we started and gradually we have been moving into other domains from
elite sports.
We still do have this elite sport, so we are serving elite teams like NHL, NBA, etc kind
of teams and their coaches for optimizing the training and recovery of the athletes.
But more I think better known area where we are is that we do develop and license the
heart rate analytics algorithms for wearables.
So for example, Garmin, Huawei, Sunt and some other brands they are using our analytics
to transform the sensor reading into more actionable information like fitness level,
color consumption, stress and recovery metrics, etc.
Now I've had a couple of conversations on the podcast about IoT and some of the challenges
of analytics in an IoT environment and I guess when I think about this device on my
wrist it's kind of like an IoT in the small and all of the challenges, well not all of
them, but some of the challenges that are typical for IoT in particular, the noisiness
of the sensor readings and things like that, I get the impression that there's a lot
of that going on in the with regards to kind of the heart rate sensor in the wearables.
That's very correct, so that's absolutely true.
So the typical limitations or requirements of the IoT are that the sensor is very power
limited or resource limited environment in that sense that you don't have the supercomputer
power there, you have limited amount of battery you want to use as efficiently as possible
to have the battery lifetime as long as possible, still you want to have a reach information
from multiple of sensors.
So for example, typical Garmin sports, what has a motion sensor and barometer in addition
to heart rate, monitor and GPS and then of course all these radios.
So it's quite interesting from 80s or 90s perspective, in fact it would be a supercomputer
but it's not and things with what are being done there are quite fascinating.
The other thing I think which is very different from for example, as I told I started with
biomedical engineering on 90s when we were working with hospital systems and monitoring
of who patient in a hospital, the monitoring was continuous and controlled in a way but
here it's very liberal or there are a lot of decrease of freedom in the sensor use also
that it's people are wearing the sensor not continuously but sometimes they are wearing
sometimes they are not and also the way how they wear it how they attach the sensor to
their wrist and how snug it fits to the wrist and so on they are not so well controlled
and that causes a lot of variation in the single quality also ambient prongers like
temperature ambient light and motion and so on they affect a lot the sensor reading.
So it's quite challenging data what is measured by the sensors and there's quite sophisticated
algorithms and detection technologies which are required to make sense out of that.
And so for the devices that first beat is embedded in are you pulling data directly off
of the sensors and kind of responsible for giving the watch kind of everything from the
ground up the the heart rate itself plus the higher level metrics that you're providing
or does the watch or the sensor provide some of those metrics in year doing higher level
analytics on top of that.
It's rather the latter so our interface to the sensor is typically the heart rate
and there be to beat heart rate and also we use motion and GPS speed and things like
that but we don't do the heart rate detection but we do the as I said we transform the
heart rate and heart rate variability data into actionable information so it's a little
bit higher level analytics based on the physiological model of how the human physiology works
and how the autonomic nervous system controls the heart rate and heart rate variability
and how this kind of data can be interpreted in terms of physiology and behavior.
Okay so before we get into the company's approach to the analytics maybe take a moment
to talk about heart rate variability and how that's calculated and why that number is
important.
Yeah so heart rate variability refers to beat to beat variation in the in the interval
between the heart beats so each successive heart beat is having certain time instant
in between them and this time difference between successive heart beats is varying as a
function of time so and this variation is related to the functioning of the so-called
autonomic nervous system which controls all our autonomic body functions like respiration,
perspiration and blood pressure and heart rate among others so this autonomic nervous system
is usually divided into two branches which are sympathetic and parasympathetic branch
so this sympathetic branch is responsible for so-called fight-of-flight response so whenever
our physiological resources are needed the sympathetic nervous system activates and prepares
the body for the for the new requirements like increased energy expenditure or increased
physical activity or increased mental activity and that is actually what happens when we
have a body physical activity or when we have mental activity or in elevated stress for
example it's the sympathetic nervous system which is activated which activates and that
can be seen as an elevated heart rate and in broad terms reduced amount of heart rate
variability the parasympathetic part is the other other nervous branch and that is responsible
for cooling down the body after the requirements or immediate requirements of the situation are
over so to basically recover the resources and reduce the heart rate, increase the heart rate
variability rate and so on and I said this is in broad terms the functioning of these autonomic
nervous system branches are seen in the heart rate and heart rate variability it sounds simple
and the principle is quite simple but the challenge is that of course there's huge inter individual
and also inter individual variants between in this especially heart rate variability they are affected
by several factors like different substances and in addition to stress and physical or mental
requirements also also our metabolism and and so on play a role there and people are different
so their interpretation is quite challenging in fact this phenomena was identified years ago
and there's been active research in the heart rate variability since early 70s but only
quite recently during last last ten years so we have learned how to how to truly manage all
these different factors which affect the phenomenon and how we can transform the information into
something which is useful and in order to do that it requires an approach analytics that
takes into account not just the you know not just kind of the raw data that you're pulling off
of the sensors but also a model of how the body works is that right yeah that's right so for example
our app wrote for the for the heart rate variability analytics is that we have constructed a digital
physiological model of the human human body or body functions so we we have have figured out
the physiological mechanisms for example how respiration physical activity heart rate mental activity
how they affect each other how they are related and and and how heart rate variability reflects
these activities and and based on this physiological model we can we can interpret the data
we that's that's the that's the physiology part but then we use the data and data driven driven
machine learning basically to tune the data in to be physiology or to be relevant for for its
individual and and we have in fact a database of 250,000 individuals where where we have white
reigns of people with different age both chambers different physical fitness and different BMI
or weight and weight and and by using that data measured in in in daily during daily life in
different conditions we can we can numerically adapt this model for it so that it fits for its
individual and and produces kind of a personalized but yet standardized outputs can you talk a
little bit about the physiological model to get us started what's the how is that expressed
I'm imagining it's a mathematical model of some sort what's its kind of size shape level of
complexity and is this something that ultimately lives in the device that that the and users
wearing yeah if I start from from from the end of a question so yes yes it relies in it we have
implemented this model into into software library and it indeed it is embedded into the
these wearable devices these these two days super computers in a way and and and how it works is
basically that that for each time instant we have a first first level is that we have a active
segmentation of the data that that that we segment the data and and after that we classify
calculate certain certain features of the data and and these physiological motivated features
based on the physiological model like for example we transform the hard rate and hard rate
rivalry data into into oxygen consumption or momentary oxygen consumption v02 or v02 and then we
detect based on the hard rate rivalry we detect respiratory rate and and based on these these
basically these two parameters described the level of of physical activity and and also
respiratory rate is related to the also the physical activity and based on that we can classify
whether a certain time instant is physical activity or or mental activity and after that we can also
by looking at the hard rate variability and and whether they're very sympathetic or
very sympathetic dominance we can classify its time instant whether that is more of physical
mental stress or or physiological recovery and and accumulating from that we can calculate
different kind of things like like a level of stress in during the day and amount of recovery
from the from the v02 levels we also can calculate energy expenditure etc and when we combine
issues like speed or or physical effort which is measured by the motion sensor we can also
calculate what and and using the information like personal hard rate maximum and agent
gender and so on we can we can calculate estimate the v02 max which is the fitness level of the
individuals and things like that so it's it is there is actually we have certain white papers
describing that but there is actually a multitude of different physiological mechanisms embedded
I don't I think it doesn't make sense to go to details but just just to take as an example is
that that we we have modeled that when you start a physical activity there is certain
the hard rate increase is not immediate but gradual and it also depends on your previous
physiological state for example in interval training we know that that the previous interval
affects to the next one and we can have this kind of a on of kind of of mechanisms in the model
and and those are taken into account so it's it's it's kind of a state state compartment model
heavily heavily based on the physiology which is behind there and so you mentioned that there's
a the physiological model and then more of a data driven model all of the metrics that you
just mentioned are those all coming out of the physiological model before you even get to the
data driven piece how it works it's basically that we have the principles are physiological but
but the parameters or how it really works how you how the input data is processed and how the
classification and and quantification of the different physiological parameters goes that's
that's heavily data driven so we have used the big amount of data what we have to tune the
parameters of the model and tune it also or to adapt it to its individual so that let's say that
it data driven personalization of the model which is done there I don't know if you if that makes
sense but well in in what way is it how personalized like is this
machine learning type of a model that is running you know on the device itself or is it you know
you're doing analytics using some type of machine learning that that spits out some number of
different models and the you can choose between models on the watch how personalized are you
able to to go with it we are using both approaches so when you take a new device into use you are
asked to provide your background parameters like gender weight age hate and activity level and
those are used to to put you broadly to the scale that what is typical for for an individual
of your age and gender and fitness level but then when and that is kind of a
machine learning or or database driven learning with what what we continuously update based on
the data what we we accumulate from from our users but then then it's also adaptive model in the
sense that that we use the we have algorithms which adapt the computation to your daily physiological
or your normal physiological and and physical activity levels and and heart rate variability
levels and so and so basically the devices get more accurate after couple of days of use when they
have the algorithms have learned what is your typical level of heart rate variability and what is
your your typical responses and your your real true heart rate minimums and maximums during
different daily activities so so the model adapts to the user and that is why also these these
devices are are typically designed for personal use if you would use for example share that
these wearable devices with with some of your colleagues or your wife that would be suboptimal
in the sense that that the the learning would not converge. The the learning that we're talking
about here it's um I don't put sorry we asked this question we're not talking about like training
in the sense of training a machine learning model that's certainly not happening on the on the
wearable device it's more like tracking the the individuals data and adapting the model to the
data over time. Yeah that is that's probably more accurate description of that yes so so they are
there's in in the physiological model and which is being being broadly optimized for for your
age and gender and weight and etc so so that is being more fine tuned to do their
your exact characteristics based based on the adaptation there but it is correct it's more like
adaptation. And you mentioned classifying a few times are you ending up having to do things like
like uh like uh outlier detection and things like that where you're getting rid of noisy data
from the sensor itself or does that happen at a lower level. We hope that most most of that happens
in a lower level but in fact we we have a lot of that happening in the analytics layer as well
so especially with optical sensors there is a lot of a lot of noise a lot of poor data and in fact
we can we have we have built quite a lot of intelligence into into the separation or detection of
poor and good appropriate quality data and what we actually do in the model is that when we detect
that the input data is is not valid we we have a serum mechanisms to to bridge those gaps or
or survive without without providing false outputs in in fact to an extent that for example our stress
and recovery analysis is still still providing a quite valid outputs up to the error level of 50
percent which is quite high so so as long as as more data which is coming in is is reflecting
the real heart rate then we can we can provide reasonable analytics of course when when there is more
false data than than real data then there's little one to do but right right right and so we've
talked about primarily about the things that are happening on the device itself but you've also got
this warehouse so to speak of data from individuals what are you you know in addition to kind of the
work you're doing to develop the models for the device are there other things that the company is
doing to you know with machine learning and analytics to take advantage of that data
yeah so we have we have two other businesses and one is we provide corporate wellness service
called a lifestyle assessment and there the idea is is that we basically sell for cooperates
why interested to improve or promote their employer well being an assessment service where
employers employees get a heart rate monitor special heart rate monitor for three days it's
based on easy chisel it's very accurate to one millisecond time resolution and they do three
day heart rate variability recording together with the diary and by using those those heart rate
data and the diary data we construct a report and and give feedback to individuals about their
physical activity sleep stress and recovery and fitness level and things like that and that
those are also compared to the recommendations like physical activity recommendations sleep
recommendations and what is normal at their age and gender and that is used very often in this
kind of wellness campaigns where where people are are motivated to improve their lifestyles
and improve their stress management skills so it can be used as an initial initial
measure to to assess the starting point and identify the exact activities they should they
should do to improve their lifestyles and and that is something as we sell as a service and that
is actually a one source where we get a lot of data we we do we did last year about 50,000 such
assessments of both in in Europe in Finland UK Germany Sweden now in Singapore as well not so
much in US yet but that is actually a good source for data for us so because we we get this kind
of a last year we got like 150,000 new datasets with with documentation and background information
and diary and that is actually what we learn used for for the optimization and further further
development of our our technologies which we use then for for consumer devices so yeah that is
that is an interesting area but that that's not to say that that is just this this service is
actually used and developed on its own it's not just for data collection but it's really just
just to for corporate wellness business and and we we see that actually there are there's a lot
of a lot of interest there about 95% of the people who who make the assessment are find it very
very useful and and they recommend it for the others so so it's we looking at the at how to how
to scale it up and how to bring make it more broadly available at the moment. How does the company
organize to tackle analytics types of problems or challenges given the the strong domain expertise
required but also the you know the analytical requirements to for machine learning and in
traditional analytics. Yeah so we have a here in Finland we have a team of of data analytics
analysis experts and and then we have a team of physiologists and in fact we have organized it
so that these two teams are working as a single single bigger team so they work on a daily basis
with each other so they are people who are who are from data science and and they are sports
physiologists and and physiologists who are expert in the physiology and and and that's the big
big thing what we are doing doing that that they are they are not they are basically never doing
a single project that that only only one one size of that expertise would be present then of
course we have engineers with software software background and I'm so on to transform all of that
into into something which can be delivered to customers and or or implemented into our
services but but the core thing there is that the maturity of that R&D or intellectual work is done
by by the this data scientists or physiologists. I guess I'm curious about the opportunities that are
created as you know we advance you continue to advance in our knowledge of applying machine
learning and you know even some of the newer techniques like deep learning that you know might
not necessarily be applicable to running on a watch but do you have any perspectives on what
opportunities these technologies and the increased focus on these technologies creates for first
beat. Yeah certainly I think we are we are just getting there that even though we have data from
roughly to 250,000 individuals in our databases and so on it's still it's it's it's it's only today
I think it starts to be in the scale where I would really truly call it as a big data. Also I
do recognize that it's probably quite unique resource that very few few organizations would have
or if if not if anybody would have have that amount of hard rate variability and background data
available. So we are actually applying at the moment we're looking at things like how we could
apply more more machine learning type of things and we have done some experimentation but
but I have to say that to to date our perspective is very much that there are
challenges with applying just pure machine learning without having having some kind of a domain
knowledge to to constrain the this kind of a machine learning methods. There is a risk that you
over over optimize to certain data sets and data on generalize and I think one of the one of the
learnings what we have done and how why why our methods also work in the wearable environment and
why they work in in almost all the individuals is that that they are based on this kind of a
physiological principles and we use only only data to to kind of optimize those principles and
make them numerically work and and in that sense we are not very heavily using using for our hard
rate data we are not using this kind of pure machine learning like deep learning kind of methods.
We have it and we are experimenting on that but I'm actually not the great believer that that
would be the optimal way to go great great well okay this is a really fascinating conversation and I
I appreciate the way that you're combining the physiological models with the the data driven
models and I think clearly the domain knowledge is important here as is the case in in you know
many if not all of the the use cases that folks are having success with so thanks for taking the
time out thank you very much it was good for me as well all right everyone that's our show
for today thanks so much for listening and for your continued feedback and support remember
for your chance to win in our AI at home giveaway head on over to twimmolayi.com slash my AI
contest for complete details for more information on ilka first beat or any of the topics covered
in this episode head on over to twimmolayi.com slash talk slash 106 thanks once again to intel AI
for their sponsorship of this series to learn more about their partnership with Ferrari North
America Challenge and the other things they've been up to visit ai.intel.com of course we'd be
delighted to hear from you either via a comment on the show notes page or via twitter directly to
me at at sam sharrington or to the show at at twimmolayi. thanks once again for listening
and catch you next time