Hey everybody, Sam here. We've got some great news to share, and also a favorite
to ask. We're in the running for this year's People's Choice Podcast Awards, in both the
People's Choice and Technology categories, and we would really appreciate your support.
To nominate us, you'll just head over to twimlai.com slash nominate, where we've linked to and
embedded the nomination form from the award site. There, you'll need to input your information
and create a listener nomination account. Once you get to the ballot, just find and select
this week in machine learning and AI on the nomination list for both the Adam Curry People's
Choice Award and the this week in tech technology category. As you know, we really, really appreciate
each listener and would love to share in this accomplishment with you. Remember that url is
twimlai.com slash nominate. Feel free to hit pause and take a moment to nominate us now.
Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimletalk, the podcast why interview interesting people,
doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence. I'm your host Sam
Charrington. If you follow us on Twitter, you might have seen this announcement, but as of last week,
the pod is available on both the new Google Podcast app and wait for it, Spotify. If you've
been waiting on that update, make sure you give us a quick search and subscribe on either or both
of these platforms. Spotify in particular was a long time in the works and ultimately required
a big shift in the way the podcast is published, so you may notice other changes as well. Let us know
if something seems amiss. In this episode, I'm joined by Ajibuso Zhang, PhD student in the Department
of Statistics at Columbia University. In this interview, Ajie and I discuss two of her recent papers,
the first and accepted paper from this year's ICML conference titled Noison, Unbiased Regularization
for Recurrent Neural Networks, which as the name implies, presents a new way to regularize RNNs
using noise injection. The second paper, an ICLR submission from last year titled Topic RNN,
a recurrent neural network with long-range semantic dependency. They've used an RNN-based
language model designed to capture the global semantic meaning relating words and a document
via latent topics. We dive into the details behind both of these papers and I learn a ton
along the way. Enjoy.
All right, everyone. I am on the line with Ajibuso Zhang. Ajie is a PhD student in the Department
of Statistics at Columbia University. Ajie, welcome to this weekend machine learning in AI.
Hi, thanks for having me. Absolutely. So Ajie and I are actually catching up for the second time.
We did have a chance to chat back in December at NIPS, but wanted to get caught up on all of her
latest work, including a paper that she's got accepted to the ICML conference. So Ajie, before
we dive in all that, why don't you talk a little bit about your background and how you got involved
in machine learning research from a statistical perspective?
Yeah. So I started with machine learning pretty early. I did my undergrad in France at Telecom
Paritek, where I specialize in statistical learning theory. They call it a theoretical
advantage statistic. So my background is in a mix of math and CS. After my second year at Telecom,
I had the opportunity to go to Cornell for an exchange program, which I did and worked more
on the staff side there. And after Cornell, I decided that I wanted to find a meaningful
application of statistics. So I went to the World Bank and worked on building models for assessing
market and counterparty risk, with the vision that if I do my job well, then the World Bank is
going to keep it stripper a rating and poor countries will be able to get loans at very low rate
because they don't have access to the market. So I did that for a bit more than a year. And then
I started my PhD at Columbia around 2014, August 2014 to be more precise. And yeah, I've been
working on the 36th department ever since. Okay. Can you talk a little bit more about that work
at the World Bank and the types of models that you were building there?
Yes, there's different ways we were using stats to assess risk. There's models for value
at risk. There's model for potential future exposure. All these models basically tell the World Bank
what are the risk if they enter in a financial agreement with a counterparty. Those counterparty
are, for example, the ones in the financial market. And if they are able to assess the risk in
entering into that financial transaction, then they'll be able to not incur any defaults from
their counterparties. And they will be able to keep their triple a rating, which they are being
evaluated on. I believe every year by standard imports and other like fish and more,
there are different shops that assess rating for these types of institutions. And keeping the
triple a rating is key because then they can get these rates at, they can get these money from the
market at very low rates and also lend money to poor countries at even low rates. So they are
acting like an intermediary between poor countries and the financial market. Okay. So my work was to
assess value at risk and potential future exposure for the World Bank.
What were some of the data sources upon which you were building those types of models?
Those were internal internal data sets. Okay. So yeah, there is a repository where they store every
every transaction they have, either with the poor countries that they lend money to and also to
the transactions they have with the financial market institutions. Okay. Yeah. Interesting. Interesting.
And so then you went over into your PhD program and what's the defining thread that is guiding
your research on the PhD? I like working with probabilistic graphical models and I like also working
with neural networks because I think they are very flexible. And I like applications involving
sequential data because I think there's a lot of challenges in modeling sequential data. You need to
account for the fact that they can be high dimensional. You need to account for all the dependencies
in the data. And I find that interesting from a scientific point of view. So that's mainly what's
guiding my research right now, finding ways to improve learning with sequential data.
And I've looked at things like context representation, regularization, and scalable learning with
variational inference. Okay. And the paper that you have accepted at ICML is focused on one of those
areas regularization in particular. Maybe we can start by having you talk a little bit about
regularization generally and different techniques for doing it and kind of what kind of results you've
seen applying traditional regularization to RNNs. And then we can talk a little bit about this
new technique. Yeah. So, recreational networks are the main family of models for sequential data.
And they tend to be very flexible. They tend to have high capacity because when you have, for
example, texts, you have the recreational network that represent text as using a hidden state.
And basically you project each word in your data into that low dimensional space. And that low
dimensional phase, you also use it to do prediction for the next word that you're going to observe.
And those parameters, those weight matrices that you use to do these projections used to be
very high dimensional. And so you end up easily with models that are that have very high capacity
and that tend to memorize data. And so it becomes important to find ways to regularize those models.
And the paper that I'm going to present at ICML lies in the line of work that used noise injection
as a way to regularize these models. Dropout is one one very famous noise injection
regularization technique. And what we are proposing with noisy is an alternative to dropout that
does the noise injection in a different way. So maybe talk through how dropout works as a
baseline for starting to think about this problem. So in dropout for recreational networks,
you would let's take the LSTN. You would multiply, let's say you have your current observation,
your current word, XT. You would have to multiply that observation with some Bernoulli noise.
And you would also have to multiply your hidden state with some Bernoulli noise. And you will
condition on that noise observation and noise hidden state to compute your new hidden state
before predicting the next word. And then practically what that means is that you're
essentially forgetting or not using some of the weights or zeroing out some of the weights,
is that right? Yes, it's equivalent to basically, like you say, zeroing out some of the weights.
So you are reducing the capacity of the network in doing that, which is essentially what regularization
is. And so what's different about the approach you're proposing in the noise in paper?
In the noise in paper, the motivation was that we want to do regularization while still keeping
the properties of the model we are regularizing intact. In the sense that we want to regularize
an LSTM while not altering the LSTM's properties. And we define that in with the term unbiased
noise injection. And so the way unbiasedness works is that if you take the conditional expectation
of any hidden state in your sequence, in your sequential representation, then you recover
the hidden state of the underlying R and then you are regularizing. And you don't get that
with dropout. And so what way does dropout in what way is it biased or does it not preserve this
unbiased property? It's because of the way you are injecting the noise. So in noise in we compute
the hidden state before doing prediction as usual, but we multiply the finite hidden state with noise.
In dropout, you would multiply the noise with the data and the previous hidden state and you
condition on those to compute your new hidden state, which uses some nonlinearities. So if you do
expectation of that hidden state, you wouldn't recover the previous underlying hidden state because
of the nonlinearities. Whereas in noise in we compute everything, we condition on the previous
observation and the previous hidden state and compute the new hidden state. And before we use
that hidden state for prediction, we multiply it or add some noise to it such that when you take
its expectation, you recover the underlying hidden state. And we found that to be very useful
in regularizing these LSTMs. Is it fair to simplify this as saying that dropout adds a noise
before calculating the hidden state and noise and adds a noise after calculating the hidden state
and doing that, it doesn't bias the network? Yes, that's a good summary of what the difference is.
You talk about in your paper some performance improvements. I'm curious in your use of the term,
you know, biased. Have you identified like more qualitative differences between the way these two
regularization methods perform beyond just the performance? Are there observations you can make
about the way dropout affects the results of a network? Yes, we have not we have not looked at
the qualitative differences. But one thing that was interesting in that paper was that given
under the unbiased noise injection definition, we can consider actually an LSTM that's
regularized with dropout as a new model, as defining a new model class for sequential data.
And we apply the noise in regularization on top of that. And we also found improvements.
We didn't, we didn't unfortunately do any qualitative comparison between dropout and noise
and I think that would be an interesting thing that I should look at next. Could you elaborate on
that last comment you made though? On dropout as defining a model class? It sounds like what you're
saying is that and you hinted at this earlier that dropout and maybe this is comes directly from
changing the expectation of this hidden state, but you can think of LSTM with dropout as almost
its own class of model where as noise in applied to an LSTM, it sounds like you're saying preserve
some fundamental LSTMness or some fundamental thing? Yes, in the sense that the expectation of
your noisy hidden state is the same as the hidden state of the thing you're regularizing
under strong and biasness. Are there other things that you learned about applying regularization
to LSTMs and RNNs in the process of exploring this noise and approach? Yeah, interesting.
Usually when you want to regularize a model, you will have to basically use less parameters.
So one way of doing that in iron and has been to tie the weights of your inputs,
the embedding matrix from the input and the embedding matrix from the output right before you do
prediction. That's an effective way of doing it, but another way is in using noise,
but using noise wouldn't reduce the number of parameters. It would reduce the capacity of your
network, not by reducing the number of parameters, but by reducing the amount that it encodes in the
data using noise. So you have this network that has a very high capacity while also being regularized
because you are injecting noise in the procedures such that the network doesn't try to memorize the
data. No, I'm following you. So one question that occurs to me then is are there implications
on the computational complexity here in applying a noise-based approach as opposed to tying your
inputs and outputs in terms of the training time specifically? I'm responding primarily to the
you saying that you have access to more parameters when you're using a noise-based approach
than with the other approach you described. Yes, what I mean is that you don't have to reduce your
number of parameters. All you have to do is use noise such that your weights will memorize less
of the data than usual. So in terms of training time of course if you have if I give you two
equivalent networks where they both have the same number of parameters but where one uses noise
injection and the other one uses weight time but they both have the same number of parameters then
the training time will will be comparable. Okay. Yeah, the only slight difference will be in the time
you take to multiply a noise with the hidden state. Right. Yeah. No, it's not particularly significant.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, exactly. To test this you tested it against a couple of benchmark data sets. Can
you describe your evaluation process? Yes, we wanted to because it's a regularization method and
because we applied it to language we used two benchmark data sets. In the literature we used
the pantry bank and the week it takes two from Salesforce and so we wanted to assess the method
as being a regularization method. So we compared it to the deterministic unregularized LSTM
and which we so obviously that adding noise helps in regularizing so you get a better performance
as defined by a perplexity but we also compared it to an LSTM regularized with dropout to assess the
importance of having this unbiasedness and we found also that it does better when you ensure that
your regularization method is unbiased and we also built on this unbiasedness notion that
since dropout is biased we can consider it as a new model class for sequences and we also
compared to an LSTM regularized with dropout only as the new model and an LSTM regularized with
dropout augmented with this noise in regularization and we also found that that helps too.
And so just to back up on the testing with these two data sets you basically created an RNN
or trained an RNN on these data sets using these various regularization methods and then
were you giving it a word and asking it to predict the next word and using that to
you know that was your basis for evaluation or is it something else?
Yes, next word prediction.
Next word prediction.
Okay, and then you get the perplexity as a measure of how good your language model is doing.
In the paper you talk about you mentioned earlier Bernoulli noise but you tested this with
a bunch of different noise distributions. Can you talk a little bit about what you saw there?
Yes, what we wanted to assess there was let's not only restrict ourselves to Bernoulli and see
what the effect is when you use any type of noise distributions because there are many and they
all have different properties, some have heavy details and others some are more skewed and others
and things like that so we wanted to assess how that would impact the effectiveness of noise in
but what we found was that the only thing that matters from the noise distribution is its second
moment so the variance and that you can use any noise distribution as long as you use the same
variance you will get the same performance and we show that also theoretically in the paper
by deriving the actual objective function and we found that it depends on yeah the second
moment of the noise. Did you come to any conclusions as to specific either problems or properties
of data sets or other characteristics where you know this performs better than you know say drop
out or some other method or is it does it appear to be broadly applicable to you know whenever
you're using an RNN? Yes actually yes it would be we only looked at text data but it's applicable
to any that's a sequence data and I'm working on extending it on that I'm also working on
extending it to other architectures because ultimately it's not only useful for RNNs because the
procedure is applicable to any type of neural networks so you can use this with convolutional
neural networks or also feed forward neural networks. Okay and how far have you gotten with that?
How how easily does it apply to for example a CNN? There's actually there's actually work on
at nips 2017 the past nips that had something similar to what we were doing in the feed forward
context but there what they were using was this importance waiting procedure and they optimize
the low bound we are not using any of that and and when I say no it is applicable to any type of
neural network it's because what the only thing that it requires is that if you give me a hidden
state which is a low dimensional representation of your data from any neural network then I can
regularize this neural network by just multiplying that hidden state with noise before using it
to do prediction so in CNNs it would be yes do your usual CNN hidden state computation and then
once you hand me that I will regularize with noise in by just multiplying it with noise or adding
it with noise so additive or multiplicative noise injection. Are there any challenges to applying
this approach to any to RNNs in particular or to to any other extending it to other types of
networks? No it's actually very it's actually very simple and we we didn't one thing is that you
have to choose the variance of your noise distribution that's the only thing that it requires and so
you will need to do grid search on that because it depends on that parameter you need to tune the
variance of your distribution according to the data you want to fit and so yes that's what the
one one disadvantage might be that you will need to do grid search on that parameter.
Yeah okay one thing that I also wanted to mention is that it has a an ensemble interpretation
like dropout dropout is usually interpreted as getting predictions from an infinite number of
neural networks we also found that interpretation is the method. Can you explain that elaborate on
that interpretation? Basically when you inject noise and you want to maximize the likelihood you
are basically marginalizing out all the noise you've injected into the network and that marginalization
you can look at it as averaging the prediction of many neural network and that's basically what
ensemble is and it's been known traditionally to actually have regularization effect which is
another explanation explanation for why noise injection does regularization. Right we also talked
about another paper this one you presented at ICLR last year on topic RNNs what was that one about?
It was about combining recurrent networks and topic models for better sequence model in the sense
that you are able to get the right context at each time step when doing prediction. The motivation
for that work was that we found that RNNs and topic models were very complimentary RNNs are very
good at encoding the local dependencies in the sequence so in language that would be syntax so RNNs
are very good at detecting syntax and modeling syntax but they have a problem when you go further
back in the sequence they have problems with long term dependencies because of the usual
vanishing exploding gradients and what we noticed was that actually we don't need to have an RNN
with many time steps because as you go further the dependencies in text are not sequential dependencies
they are semantic dependencies and these words in the document are related semantically with
because they belong to the same team and topic models are known as these probabilistic
probabilistic models that can detect teams in data and so it made sense to use topic models
to get the teams and then condition on those when doing prediction with the RNN.
And so when you say topic models are you referring to things like embedding spaces and word
to veck and the like or something else? I'm referring to something else. So what is a topic model?
A topic model is like a family of graphical model that takes a bunch of documents and tells you
the teams that they discuss. It tells you each document which topics they discuss in which
proportion and it tells you what these topics are. So a topic in the topic model literature is
defined as a distribution of a word of a word and each document is expressed as a distribution
over those topics. And so what you end up with is a distribution of a word that's your topic matrix
at least of distribution of a word and you also end up with a distribution of a topic for each
document. Is your distribution of words is this I guess what comes to mind is LDA is this
something that you might use in LDA to do exactly what it is? There's LDA and there's approximations
to LDA using neural networks. So these are neural topic models and use that version in the topic
ironing paper. We use the neural topic model where you basically represent your document as a
bag of word as in LDA and project that high dimensional bag of word representation using an MLP
to get a distribution to get a document distribution. Now what I do in topic ironing is I represent that
document distribution with a Gaussian and I condition on that in the softmax as an additional
by-ster depending on whether I need to predict the word that needs this topic content or a word
that does not need the topic content. And how do you determine for a given word whether you need
to use the topic content or not? I let the iron and because they are highly flexible I let the
iron and tell me whether the next word should be a quote-unquote stop words. Those are words that
don't need any that don't have any semantic meaning. Okay so based on stop words. Yes. Okay.
So the iron and will tell me whether that the next word needs the topic content or not. Yeah binary
classification. Got it. So this is interesting to me and that it seems like a an NLP type of
application of the idea of I guess this theme that I've seen in other places where hey we've got
these RNN or we've got these neural networks they're great for you know basically approximating
any relationship if we throw enough data at them but you know hey there are also these more
traditionally determined relationships that we've figured out. So for example it strikes me as
analogous to in robotics you know using a strict neural network approach to go from visual input
to motor output you know or an approach that combines the neural network with traditional
like control system modeling or something like that. It seems like it's very much thematically
uh in those kind of along those lines and that's exactly what it is there's this line of work of
planning to combine privacy grabs for modeling and neural networks and and I think that's an
interesting line of work which I'm working on because they're very complimentary like when we are
using ease of these frameworks we are trying to learn from high dimension of data and neural networks
give you a way to design these highly flexible likelihood whereas graphical models allow you to
basically represent the hidden structure you want to learn from data in an interpretable way
so you can combine the two together to benefit from the best of both worlds. Right right and uh
that approach is always um I always find that uh compelling you know but then I I've also talked
to folks that you know we might describe as deep learning purists that say you know it's ultimately
a waste of time the neural networks configure everything out if you throw enough data and compute
at them and I'm just curious how like if you thought about it like that and how you might respond to
that. There are still there's that might be true in some context if you have too much compute and you
have too much data but that's not the case for many people and and there are times where you
actually care about uh these latent variables there are times where you want to look at them
and say oh this uh this is how these things depend together and most of the time when you say
I can just use a neural net and throw compute and data at it and it will give me what I want that's
when you only care about performance about getting the state of the art number but there are times
where you actually use this model to better understand the data you're dealing with to
encode uncertainty to make help people in decision-making understand better their data and
everything and they're just using a neural network to get better performance wouldn't mean much.
So for you the the two counter arguments are limited resource scenarios and
you know broadly speaking explainability and insight that you're able to get from this train
system. Yes exactly. Continuing on in the topic RNN work was there any interesting insights in
the way that you combine the topic models and the RNNs where there are different ways that you
could have done that but you you know went down a specific path or yes there are different ways
you can combine that. Actually the topic RNN worked you can look at it in a more general way and
say that what we are trying to do is at the end of the two model sequence data you need to have
a model to capture the local dependencies so that's that will be your syntactic model and then you
will have a model that will capture the global dependencies and that would be your semantic model
and you have also to decide on how you want to combine them so you have three degrees of freedom
with it you have how to decide on the same tactic how to decide on the semantic how you decide
on combining them. In topic RNN the idea was so cool and motivating to me that I tried
in for any of those three things I tried the simplest thing so for the syntactic model I tried
an RNN which was the main thing that was used for sequences and for the topic model I used the
neural topic model version because those are efficient to learn ways you just project a bag of
what representation for a neural network to get a latent representation of the document distribution
and in combining them I just said let me use the usual software max but add this topic information
as an additional biester but you can actually use all these three things in different ways
and that's what's cool about it because it somehow defines a new class of models for dealing with
these sequences. Did you train these simultaneously or did you train your semantic model and your
syntactic model separately? Yes the cool thing is that you want to define all these three things
in the way you combine them in such a way that you can afford joint training. I always prefer
joint training because then you are letting your model also the ability to decide what
what it want to use from each component so we did joint training from the topic model and the
RNN we trained the two things together because the whole pipeline is fully differentiable.
And how did you evaluate the performance of this approach? The first thing we tried it as a
language model so we say let's see how it improves on existing language models so we did for next
word prediction where we got good results but we also said let's see this as a feature extractor
and we applied it to document classification more specifically we applied it to sentiment analysis
so we use the IMDB dataset which is a bunch of reviews and labels of those reviews whether they
are negative or positive and we use topic RNN to extract features from the reviews and use
those features in a binary classification model and we achieved a very nice results not only
in terms of classification error rate but also in how it managed to discover the features for
the negative reviews and the positive reviews so we had this nice clustering of the features from
the topic RNN of the negative reviews and the positive reviews and that was very exciting.
Interesting and the features in this context would be words like you know stinks horrible
that kind of thing or something else. The features we learned was that we use the because
topic RNN is a generative model for tech for for any sequence data we use the reviews alone
and trained that as a language model as usual and we derived the features by taking the last hidden
state of the RNN component of topic RNN and the document distribution output by the topic model
component of topic RNN and we concatenated them together to say this represents the future for
this document. The last hidden state of the topic model RNN and the so you're trying to get the kind
of your latent state of both your semantic and syntactic models and kind of smush them together
to represent some feature. Yes exactly. Okay. Yeah. Interesting. That turned out to be effective at
telling you where the negative reviews and the positive reviews lie in this data manifold.
I don't know if if this makes sense given like dimensionality and stuff like that but
qualitatively what did those features look like? Did they look like in terms of visualization?
Visualization or like is it a one hot encoded you know an encoded vector of like where negative
words were identified for negative features and positive words were identified for positive
features or something like that or is it something totally different? It's something it's at the
document level not at the word level. Okay. Yeah. It's at the document level when you concatenate
these two things and project them in two dimension then you will see a nice clustering of negative
documents and positive documents together. We don't go at the word level. One thing that's
interesting is that the IMDB has a lot of sarcasm on it so it's actually it's actually very hard
to capture the sentiment just using the review because of that. So this was this was a cool encouraging
result. And so why do you think that this worked better for presumably it did capture some of
that sarcasm? I think the way we use the features, the way we we said let's combine the document
distributions as given by the neural topic model and the final hidden state of the RNN. That final
hidden state usually captures you know how when you when you write a review say oh this movie was
was the actors were great then and then but it sucked because of it. Right. So the whole sentiment is
actually captured in that last part. Okay. So I am guessing that's why it did well because
because you exploit that sarcasm when you actually just look at the most recent information. How do
you see this work being applied? I think it can be used for any we looked on their sentiment
classification. The word prediction thing is not a real task. We were just using it to evaluate
it as a language model. But I think it can be used for any document classification task in
there are many applications to that. Not only sentiment analysis but yeah any document classification
you can use Topikarin and to get to get features it proved to be very effective in the case of
sentiment but you can use it for any document classification task. Say you wanted to classify
documents or like tag documents based on content. Would you have to come up with your own feature
representation or would you use this concatenation that you've described but then do something else
to get at the last mile of how you want to classify? Where does the customization have to take
place in order to apply this to another type of classification problem? The general thing is that
you will have to use both the global representation and the local representation you need both.
And from the local representation side you can decide to use the last hidden state but you can do
anything you want there. You can use an averaging of the different hidden state or you can use a
I don't know like attention. It depends on what you can do. You can build a classifier on top
of Topikarin and I did that actually for medical data and we found again there a nice clustering
of patients according to their diseases. And so yes the customization is in how you use the
hidden state of the RNN part. Okay. Yeah. Well you're working on some really interesting things and
I appreciate you taking the time to share some of them with us. Are there any other things you
wanted to touch on? That would be it. Thank you for taking the time. Thank you for having me.
All right everyone that's our show for today. For more information on Ajay or any of the topics
covered in this episode head on over to twomlai.com slash talk slash 160. If you didn't hit pause
and nominate us for the podcast people's choice awards at the beginning of the show I'd like to
encourage you to jump over to twomlai.com slash nominate right now and send us your love and your vote.
So as always thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.