Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast why interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
For those challenges with promoting the use of machine learning in an organization and
making it more accessible, one key to success is supporting data scientists and machine
learning engineers with modern processes, tooling and platforms.
This is a topic we're super excited to address here on the podcast with the AI Platforms
Podcast series that you're currently listening to, as well as a series of e-books that will
be publishing on the topic.
The first of these books takes a bottoms up look at AI Platforms and is focused on the
open source Kubernetes project, which is used to deliver scalable machine learning infrastructure
at places like Airbnb, booking.com and open AI.
The second book in the series looks at scaling data science and machine learning engineering
from the top down, exploring the internal platforms that companies like Airbnb, Facebook
and Uber have built and what enterprises can learn from them.
If these are topics you're interested in and especially if part of your job involves
making machine learning more accessible, I'd encourage you to visit twimbleai.com slash
AI platforms and sign up to be notified as soon as these books are published.
If you found yourself saying, Cuba, what, Cuba, who, when listening to this intro, this
is the show for you.
In this episode of our AI Platforms series, we're joined by open AI's head of infrastructure,
Christopher Burner.
Chris has played a key role in overhauling open AI's deep learning infrastructure in the
course of his two years with the company.
In our conversation, we discussed the evolution of open AI's deep learning platform, the core
principles which have guided that evolution and its current architecture.
We dig deep into the use of Kubernetes and discuss various ecosystem players and projects
that support running deep learning at scale.
And now on to the show.
All right, everyone.
I am on the line with Christopher Burner.
Chris is the head of infrastructure at open AI.
Chris, welcome to this week in machine learning and AI.
Thanks a lot.
Awesome. So why don't we get started by having you tell us a little bit about your background.
You are coming up on almost two years at open AI now.
How did you get to open AI?
Yeah.
Well, let's see.
So before open AI, I was at Facebook, I worked there for about four and a half years.
And before that, I worked at a couple of startups at Facebook.
I worked on the newsfeed ranking team for about a year.
So it's got just a little bit of introductory experience in machine learning.
And then I worked in the data infrastructure team, worked on a distributed SQL query engine
called Presto, which is open source.
So I have a fair bit of background and big data analytics and data warehousing.
And that has certainly helped me get up to speed with all of the large scale infrastructure
that's required for deep learning these days.
And yeah, I've just been learning all about the infrastructure that you need for machine
learning training and specialized infrastructure there.
And so open AI is certainly doing machine learning at large scale.
Maybe we can start out by having you, you know, we've, I've talked to several people
from open AI on the podcast before, but maybe you can start by providing an overview of
some of the larger projects that kind of stressed the need for a platform for machine learning
at open AI.
Yeah.
Well, certainly our largest project is our data to research project.
And in the past few months, we've announced a bunch of the results with open AI five
there.
And yeah, that's a very large system, trans on hundreds of GPUs and over 100,000 virtual
CPU cores runs in one of our clusters in Google compute engine.
And yeah, that's definitely our largest.
We have several other projects that are also quite large though, our robotics team also
does some very large scale training.
I've actually done a little bit of work on large scale image net training.
And yeah, that's like one or 200 GPUs, I'd say kind of all of our teams have things that
are on the medium to large size, but data is definitely our largest.
Nice.
And I spoke to Christy not too long ago about the data project.
So I'd refer anyone who wants to hear more about that to that interview.
In terms of supporting these types of projects, when you started at open AI, was there much
established or have you kind of had a hand in building it up from scratch?
Yeah, some of both.
So definitely we already had Kubernetes clusters set up when I joined.
They were definitely architected differently than they are today.
And yeah, I've been involved in changing the architecture of them to make them scale
better and also isolate faults better.
So that was in place.
We've also made some changes in terms of our storage technologies and a bunch of the frameworks
that we use for running experiments.
I think that's actually one of the areas that we've seen the largest changes we had.
Two or three different frameworks that existed when I joined and I don't think any of those
are still around.
We've moved on to completely different ones, so yeah, so a mix of things that still exist
and a bunch that has changed.
You mentioned that a big part of the change was driven around scalability and I think it
was reliability.
Those are a couple of things that have driven change, but taking a step back are there when
you think about the characteristics that you're trying to be able to provide to the research
teams from an infrastructure perspective.
Those are the two or most important things or are there a set of things that you think
that they require of you to be able to do their jobs effectively?
Yeah, so those are definitely two very important ones.
There's a couple others that I would add.
One is access to cutting-edge hardware and we run some machines in our own data centers
because we want access to hardware that's not available in the cloud and so yeah, that's
another dimension and then yeah, I guess sort of another aspect, but it's more on the
tooling side is just ease of use that people want to be able to launch their experiments
quickly and interact quickly and so that's another important aspect of infrastructure.
And it sounds like the support for the framework of choice for the researchers is another
one in that you've already kind of gone through a transition on the framework side.
You don't want to lock them into a specific choice there.
Yeah, we try to provide as much flexibility as possible to our researchers.
Like I mentioned, there were some old research tools that I don't think people are using
now because they've invented new ones that are better and similarly we don't want to
be limited to running experiments just in the cloud and that's one of the benefits that
we see from Kubernetes is that it's very easy to port your experiments from the cloud
to our on-premise clusters where we may have access to different hardware and it makes
that transition pretty seamless and the so the frameworks that you mentioned that folks
weren't using that folks that you transition from are those with those internal frameworks
or these all open source frameworks, but you're just using different ones now.
Are we talking about things like TensorFlow and PyTorch or are we talking about internal
tools that have been developed at OpenAI?
Yeah, so those particular ones were internal.
Okay.
It was a few different frameworks for running and managing experiments and visualizing the
results from them and things like that and now I'd say like TensorFlow board is pretty
popular.
That's kind of replaced some of the need for our custom tooling in one particular area.
But yeah, also TensorFlow, I'd say that's definitely our most popular sort of machine learning
framework.
I'd guess that 90% of our code is probably TensorFlow, but there's also starting to be
significant contingent of people who are using PyTorch, so some amount of change in that
area too.
Okay.
Before we dive into kind of an architectural overview of the platform that you've set
up, can you walk us through kind of the level above that, like the workflow or the processes
as you see it, that you're trying to support.
So for example, you mentioned experiment management and how some of the tooling there is shifted
from internal to tensor board.
What are the ways in which you think about the functional requirements of the machine learning
researchers that you're supporting?
Yeah, certainly.
Yeah, I guess at a really high level.
Pretty much everything that we do is research and experimentation and training models.
Which makes us a little bit different than a lot of other companies that are doing machine
learning because they're often then going on to integrate those into a product and deploy
that to all of their users, whereas we're really just focused on the research side of things.
And so we try to optimize our tools for iterating quickly and exploring a lot of different research
directions and providing the flexibility to do experiments in all different areas.
So we've got a number of teams that do reinforcement learning.
But we also have teams doing supervised learning and unsupervised learning.
So a whole bunch of different types of problems that they're trying to solve.
But kind of all of it comes back to training models and collecting the results from them
and then being able to interact quickly on the next version of their research ideas.
Okay.
So whereas in a non-research enterprise, something, some of the front end work of integrating
with data warehouses and things like that isn't so critical for you.
And some of the backend model management tasks where you're trying to manage productionized
models.
It's also not as critical for you or not at all critical for you.
The part in the middle, this experiment management piece is, that has to be done really well
to make sure that the folks who are supporting are able to work most efficiently.
Yeah, exactly.
Because that's pretty much all that we do.
And so that's really where we focus our effort.
And when you think of that job from a quote unquote head of infrastructure perspective,
are you thinking of it?
I guess I have this picture on my head of infrastructure looking down like hardware
and platforms and frameworks and infrastructure looking up like tools that manage that process
of experiment management, for example.
Are you kind of, you know, top to bottom there or are you, you know, just the bottom part
or?
Yeah, I would say that we do kind of a bit of everything, but for the most part, we're
focused on providing the compute clusters.
And yeah, I guess also running like the storage clusters and other things that are related,
but to sort of providing, yeah, the bottom layers of making sure that everyone has access
to the compute and the hardware that they need.
We do also work a bit on the tooling side.
Most of our experimentation management tools have been developed by our research teams,
but we certainly help maintain a few of those and help support them with the new features.
And so I think infrastructure's role has kind of expanded and actually in some ways,
I suppose, contracted to, we used to have other tools that we ran and managed, and now
it's said that those aren't so useful, so we no longer run those.
But kind of the main focus of the team is on providing really big compute clusters, but
then we've also got a lot of other responsibilities on tooling side and other places that we work
on.
One of the things that I found interesting when I look at what you're doing, you've
published OpenAI as published quite a bit on its infrastructure and some of the things
that it's done, and one of the things that I found really interesting is the very strong
commitment to kind of this multi-cloud world.
You've got experiments running on Google, you've got experiments running on Azure, you've
got experiments running on AWS, and of course, on premises.
Can you talk a little bit about the motivation there?
And what's driven the need to support, it's got to be a more complex environment than
just standardizing in one place?
Yeah, for sure.
I guess there's kind of a few different factors.
So one, like I mentioned, is access to kind of a chartware, so we can get whatever we want
in our on-prem clusters, but the cloud also has a lot of benefits, you can quickly scale
things up.
They've got lots of nice APIs and auxiliary services that you can take advantage of, and
so we'd like to have a presence with all of the major cloud providers so that when they
launch a new type of NVIDIA GPU, or when Google announces their new TPUs, we want to be
sure that we have access to those and that we can use them.
And so that's one thing that drives our multi-cloud strategy.
Another part of it is strategic partnerships and economics.
We want to be able to take advantage of whatever cloud we can get the best pricing in, and
so that certainly has advantages to being able to move our workloads between clouds and
our own cluster, of course.
And so you've got these disparate research workloads.
You've got these multiple infrastructure environments, clouds plus your on-premises cluster.
And as we've alluded to, Kubernetes is a part of the platform that ties all this together.
Taking a step back from that, when you describe the platform for machine learning and deep
learning at OpenAI, how do you describe it?
What are the major pieces?
Do you have names for things?
What kind of walk us through the platform?
Yeah, for sure.
Yeah, so Kubernetes is a big piece of it.
We run three different production clusters.
We name all of our production clusters, animals alphabetically.
So the latest one, we're up to J now, which is Jaguar.
So that's our newest one.
We've got two others, Horus and Ibus.
So each of those is a Kubernetes cluster limited to a specific cloud and geographic region
or our on-prem cluster.
And then sort of outside of that, we've got a number of tools.
So the rapid experimentation tool is the one that our data research team developed.
And that does sort of all of their experimentation management and provides a bunch of core building
pieces for building their experiments as well.
And that's one that our robotics team uses as well.
And a couple other teams have experimented with.
So that has really helped us, I'd say, move quickly and be able to launch new research
experiments in the reinforcement learning space because that's what that tool is optimized
for.
Those core building pieces, can you give us some examples of what those are?
Yeah, so they've got an implementation of the PPO algorithm of the what algorithm?
PPO, proximal policy optimization.
Got it.
Okay.
Yeah.
They've got a special implementation for synchronizing multiple GPUs that are spread across
machines to do distributed training, a bunch of infrastructure just kind of for tracking
the experiments, managing optimizers, managing tiers of machines that are running the environment
like the data to game or a physics simulator, streaming that experience back to the optimizer
machines.
So kind of managing the application level distributed system that has to do all the training.
Is that tool used for multiple experiments and what's the I'm curious how customized
that is for a specific application or experiment or if it's, you know, can it can a new experiment
kind of plug into it pretty easily and take advantage of all the different sub components
that it offers?
Yeah.
So it started out quite specialized for the data team and then has expanded into a more
general research tool that we're now using in a number of teams across the company.
So the robotics team was the second team that started using it and they've applied it
to some of their robotic hand experiments and that kind of turned out to be actually a
similar problem.
You replace the data to game with a physics simulator and then a lot of the other components
really fit together nicely.
And now we've got at least one other team that's starting to use it and they also I believe
we're able to get started really quickly, adapt it for their experiments.
So I think a lot of our teams that are doing reinforcement learning are able to just
move their experiments over to it really quickly.
Okay.
Cool.
And so you mentioned you've got these three production clusters and just to clarify,
those are the three clusters on prem and then you've got additional clusters in the
cloud.
Is that right?
Oh no, those are our three Kubernetes clusters.
So one of them is on prem, the other two are on the cloud.
Okay.
And do the three clusters support presumably different research workloads simultaneously
or are they dedicated to a specific research workload at a time?
Yeah.
So it varies a bit.
And because research projects can do the change in scope over time.
And yeah, they kind of ebb and flow in terms of their compute needs.
It changes over time.
Right at the moment, I believe all three clusters are being shared.
I don't think any of them are dedicated to a single team at the moment.
But it tends to be that like two or three teams will share one cluster and that kind of
makes it easier for them to know how much capacity they're going to be able to use.
And it's just kind of easier for the infrastructure team also to know who it is.
It tends to be using each cluster.
But at the moment, we run all three of them, the shared cluster is where anyone is free
to use the capacity.
Taking a step back.
So Kubernetes deals with containerized workloads.
So the training workload, for example, needs to be containerized.
That's not necessarily a skill that the typical data scientist has.
One of the things that I read is that you've built some tooling that kind of does that
for the researchers so they don't have to get into the weeds in terms of containerizing
their workloads.
Can you talk a little bit about that?
Yeah.
So one of the things that we try to do in general is provide a lot of flexibility in terms
of tooling because different teams and different researchers may have a different level of comfort
with different tool sets.
And so yeah, people can use Kubernetes directly and build their Docker containers and there's
a bunch of people who are comfortable with that.
That's what they do.
But then, yeah, there's also a set of people that prefer different types of interfaces
and maybe something but abstracts way all of the container details.
And so another tool that we have called ARCALL, it handles all of the Docker containers
and, in fact, abstracts away sort of all of the Kubernetes details so that you just
have your Python code in a directory and it knows where to find it, uploads it to the
cluster, launches your containers, launches all your experiments, and then you can just
focus on writing your TensorFlow and other Python code and not even need to necessarily
know that it's running inside a Docker container or really that it's a Kubernetes cluster
even.
And are the researchers there typically working with like Git repositories?
So are they checking in code and are you pulling from those Git repos when you're containerizing
or is it all just slurping stuff up from directories on the desktop?
Yeah, we use Git quite extensively here.
And I guess, again, kind of a mix of things depending on the workflow that researchers
and most convenient, yeah, some of them are launching their experiments from code that
they have locally, although that's almost always in a Git repository just from their local
checkout for other ones, yeah, maybe that it's built by a container, a build engine
like QA, and then we're deploying a container from that registry.
Earlier on you mentioned that your use of Kubernetes is kind of evolved from when you started
to today, can you talk a little bit about that journey in general, how your use of Kubernetes
has evolved as Kubernetes has evolved, what some of the big challenges with the different
phases that you've gone through with your architecture has been and how you've overcome
those?
Yeah, it has changed in a number of ways.
Certainly one is the scale, our clusters have gotten way bigger than when I first started
but they've also sort of transitioned in their design.
So when I first joined the design that we had was a single production Kubernetes cluster
and it was a single multi-cloud cluster, so it spanned both AWS and Azure and it sort
of led to some behavior that was difficult to reason about, I don't think for how many
people run Kubernetes clusters where a single cluster is cross-cloud and especially when
we wanted to scale that up significantly to thousands of machines, we switched over
to a model where we have multiple Kubernetes clusters and each one is limited to a specific
physical region, so either are on-prem clusters or availability zone in the cloud.
And that made it a little easier to reason about some of the network aspects of it and
not need to worry about some of the cross-cloud issues that we'd run into.
So that really allowed us to scale more.
Can you give me an example of some of the issues that you ran into that kind of led to that
shift?
What were the kinds of things that you'd see?
Yeah, for sure.
Also because we were needed to run this cross-cloud, we had the control plan in AWS and then we
had a bunch of IP sect tunnels that connected to the other availability zones where the
workers were running in.
So we would have one set of workers running in like Azure's East Coast region and one
West Coast region and all of these would talk back to the Kubernetes control plan over
this IP sect tunnel back in AWS.
But this meant that that IP sect tunnel was kind of a single point of failure if that went
down.
Not necessarily the entire cluster, but a large section of the cluster because that whole
group of workers would now be cut off from the control plan.
So yeah, there was that problem.
Then there was also the problem of if you wanted to use something like Amazon's file system
like in on the name right now, EFS, I think it's called EBS or S3.
Yeah, S3 I guess was a little bit less problematic, but certainly EBS, that's something that you'd
like to use.
But now if some of your workers are in Azure, then you can only use it in half your cluster
and then that's really confusing if you end up with sometimes you can use it and sometimes
you can't and then I guess one of the most difficult to overcome problems was that if you
scheduled your job into the cluster, it was possible for your job to get split so that
half of it was in Azure and half of it was in AWS.
And now if there was any network communication between them, that would just go very, very
poorly.
Right.
So you had to be very careful to specify that your job should only be in one cloud and
not the other.
Okay.
But kind of all of that led to us just changing the model so that one Kubernetes cluster, one
availability is out, then you don't have to worry about any of that.
Right.
Yeah, it's interesting.
I think in the Kubernetes community, certainly there's a lot of talk about hybrid cloud and
multi cloud and even the ability to run a single Kubernetes cluster spanning multiple
clouds.
It's actually document and not necessarily thoroughly, but it's there, but I don't get
the impression that a lot of people do it for reasons like the ones that you're describing.
Yeah.
So some tough problems and we were trying to solve them pretty early in the development
of Kubernetes.
I imagine if we tried to do it now, the experience might be a little smoother, but some of those
are just difficult problems to solve.
And then I guess the other area that our Kubernetes clusters have evolved significantly
since I joined is our on-prem cluster.
So that did not exist when I joined.
And as one that we've been continuing to scale up, just as we have more and more demand
for cutting edge hardware that's not available in the clouds.
And so with that particular motivation, front and center, in particular cutting edge hardware,
for example, you have access to an Nvidia DGX, I'm sure you have access to all the latest
and greatest GPUs.
Are you able to utilize Kubernetes features like labels and things like that to target
workloads to these specific cutting edge hardware or do you just kind of throw them all
into the pool and let them land wherever they land and kind of each incremental hardware
piece just adds what it can bring?
Yeah, so we definitely do a bit of both.
We use labels pretty extensively to provide finer grand control of exactly what hardware
you get scheduled on as much as possible.
We also try to keep our clusters homogeneous or mostly homogeneous so that you don't need
to put too much thought into specifying exactly what you want, but yeah, it's a bit of
both.
Do you find in general that the out of the box Kubernetes scheduler does what you need
for these types of workloads?
Yeah, so we've made some various tweaks to it, although we're still using the upstream
scheduler and I've just made like config changes and then sort of built some services on
top of Kubernetes.
We now have a system that uses the mutating webhooks feature along with a controller
and taints that sort of manage the resources in our cluster so that certain groups of
machines can be dedicated to a certain team.
And then when members of that team submit their pods, those pods will receive a toleration
that allows them to run on those reserved machines.
Is that an alternative to using namespaces or is that something that works in conjunction
with namespaces to provide that feature?
Yeah, so it works in conjunction with namespaces.
So here of every researcher their own namespace and then most teams also get their own namespace
and they can have one if they ask for it, just kind of depends on how they like to structure
their workflow.
And then we integrate all of this back into our directory service so that it knows which
people are on which team and then the pods in those namespaces can then be granted a
toleration to run on capacity that's reserved for that team.
So yeah, that's an area where we consider building all of this into a custom scheduler
but it seemed much easier to support if we just built it as a feature on top of the Kubernetes
APIs that could then interact with the scheduler in the normal way.
And I guess the one significant config change that we've made to the default Kubernetes
scheduler is that the default one prefers to spread out the pods in like a deployment
or a job as much as possible, which is good for fault tolerance.
But for us, we tend to want the opposite, it would actually like as many pods as possible
to be packed into single machines so that it leaves other machines completely empty.
And that's good for two reasons one is that if someone submits a bunch of small pods,
we don't want them to fill up tiny pieces of every machine.
We want them to packed into a few so that their whole machines available for people that
want to use an entire machine.
And then the other thing that it really helps us with is auto scaling.
So in our cloud clusters, we auto scaled them up and down depending on demand.
And so you want to have your machines utilized as heavily as possible so that you can scale
in the unused machines.
What does a small mean in that context is it's based on kind of a real time metric like utilization
or is it something else?
Oh, yeah.
So yeah, in terms of small, I mean like how many resources are being requested.
So I would consider it small if you were requesting only one GPU or maybe you're only requesting
like half a dozen CPU cores, whereas like our bigger pods, those are usually requesting
HGPUs or maybe four GPUs and then they're requesting dozens or maybe even 50 or 60 CPU
cores.
How do you manage if at all the issue of folks submitting jobs, IE pods and reserving
essentially these resources, but the pods not actually, you know, being idle essentially.
Is that something that you actively deal with?
Yeah, so yeah, I guess there's kind of two parts of it.
We just kind of trust all of our researchers to use the clusters resources well.
And so we don't have any like checking of are you using the resources that you requested.
So what we do have is a sort of internal billing system where we monitor how many pods you
had running and how many resources they requested and how long those resources were requested
for.
And then it rolls up your billing every day.
And you can see a report of this is how much money effectively you spent on experiments.
And so yeah, if you were leaving a bunch of pods running the ride, it would show up in
your bill.
And is that something that you had to build or was that a project in the Kubernetes ecosystem
that you were just able to kind of turn on and point to your clusters?
Yeah, it's something that we built, although it's actually very little code will probably
open source it if someone else doesn't open source a better solution that we end up switching
to.
But it's based on Prometheus, so Prometheus already monitors all of the metrics of what
pods were running when were they running for how much did they request.
And so really this is just a pretty simple Python script that query is Prometheus aggregates
all of that data groups it by namespace and then integrates with our directory service
to figure out which team and people's namespace is belong to and that rolls up all the cost
by team.
Okay, cool.
And it sounds like you're running upstream and you mentioned Prometheus, what other tools
are you running or projects in conjunction with your use of Kubernetes?
Yeah, let's see.
So we use the cluster auto-scaler, so we use that for scaling our clusters.
It's Prometheus, we use Heapster, we use a flannel for an Overland network, we've got
some deployments of the cluster, although that's sort of lusterfully related to Kubernetes.
And I guess those are kind of the main ones.
Okay, you mentioned Gluster.
What are the different ways that you deal with storage in the context of these clusters?
Yeah, so that's one of the areas that we're, I feel like we have an OK solution now, but
I'd really like us to have a great solution.
It's a tough problem.
It is a very tough problem.
So we've got Gluster deployed and it's been reasonably good.
We haven't quite gotten the performance that we want out of it, but it's definitely convenient.
And yeah, teams certainly have some data storage in S3 and Google Cloud Store and Azure's
Blob Store.
Yeah, so I spread out over those.
For our Cloud Kubernetes clusters, we use whatever sort of EBS equivalent they have.
Google, that's their persistent volumes, that's really convenient.
For our on-prem cluster, I think what we're going to end up deploying is Saf, possibly through
the REC project, but we haven't started on that yet.
So it's a little bit hard to say what we're going to end up with, but that seems like
it has a lot of promise.
It sounds like then there's a strong inclination towards a distributed storage solution that
kind of runs on the existing compute infrastructure as opposed to some standalone monolithic kind
of NFS type of thing.
Yeah, so I guess what we have found, so I guess Gluster sort of falls more into the single
shared file system like NFS.
And what we've found is that the performance hasn't been quite as good as what we want,
although maybe that could be resolved by tuning some of the configuration settings or adding
more hardware, but the other issue has been fault domains that when one team really starts
hammering the storage, then it causes a disruption in service for everyone.
And so one of the potential benefits that we see of something like Saf is hopefully better
fault isolation where that won't happen because you'll have your separate or weblock devices.
You mentioned a flannel for networking, how has that dealing with the networking been
since you've gone away from the multi-cloud?
Is that kind of addressed all your issues or is it still a challenge for you?
Yeah, I'd say that that really simplified things and these days I don't worry too much
about our networking.
So flannel has worked out nicely, we have integrated all of our clusters together via VPN so the
researchers can connect all of them very easily and that's worked out well.
And with our on-prem cluster we've kind of figured out some of the performance aspects originally
when we had deployed flannel, we had been deployed it in a way that wasn't as performant
but when we switched over to, so we're now using their direct routing feature.
And that really resolved the performance problems that we were seeing there.
So yeah, it's pretty much been a non-issue since we made some re-architectures to our clusters.
And one of the advantages of the single Kubernetes cluster as opposed to a federated would
be that the researchers don't need to think about where a particular workload goes.
Have you found another way to abstract that or do they just have to, you know, do they
target a specific cluster when they're deploying workloads?
Yeah, for sure.
So our experimentation tools handle a little bit of that of trying to abstract it away so
that the researchers don't need to worry about it so much.
Longer term I've been sort of loosely following the upstream work that's being done in federated
Kubernetes and how that all is going to work.
I think at some point in the future, we're really hoping to switch over to a model like
that where there is a federated control plane that can then handle a schedule length that
looks like a single cluster, but yeah, not there yet.
Right, right, right.
Speaking of which, what's been your experience with Kubernetes as it evolves?
How have changes on the Kubernetes side changed the way you use it?
Maybe starting, was there any, did you run into any hurdles early on that you had to
maybe develop around or hack or hound that Kubernetes eventually caught up with what
your needs were, whether it's in terms of its operation or scalability or reliability
or things like that, or how's that whole experience been for you?
Yeah, definitely.
So I'd say in general, super positive.
The direction that Kubernetes has been going in has really just continued to address more
and more of the pain points that we've seen.
So yeah, I guess a few specific ones, and we were probably one of the first people using
Kubernetes to schedule GPU devices, and so we were using the alpha feature that added support
for that, I believe as soon as it was released, and so we did have to build up some additional
tooling for handling that and making it work seamlessly, like in particular, the device
drivers need to be mounted into your container.
And so we had kind of a whole way of managing that with Simbling so that people could do
it.
Now that Nvidia has released their device plugin, that's kind of all been automated for
us, and so we switched over to that in all of our clusters, and it has simplified all
of the management of the GPU devices there, and also like on the scalability side, I think
Kubernetes now officially has been tested up to like 5,000 nodes in the past.
That was not as true, and we had to do something to work around various scalability issues,
but now a lot of that has just been handled by upstream where they have optimized things.
You mentioned in terms of things that you're looking forward to, you mentioned some of the
work around federated Kubernetes, are there other things that you see on the horizon
for Kubernetes or more broadly that ecosystem that you're excited about?
Yeah, definitely federated Kubernetes.
Yeah, earlier I mentioned the Ruck project, and that's definitely one that I've been
following and have quite a bit of an interest in.
It looks like it might make it really easy to run Seth at our on-prem clusters, so that
would be really exciting for us.
So I'm hoping that that project continues to get more traction.
And beyond that, one of the things that we're looking at next is on the network side.
We're planning to enable Rocky, the RDMA over-converged Ethernet protocol in our on-prem
clusters, and so this is one of the things that we can't get in the cloud, that's why
we have our on-prem cluster.
So I'm not familiar with that one, you said Rocky, and RDMA would be for remote memory
access.
Yeah, exactly.
Are you familiar with Infiniband?
Oh, yeah, sure.
Yeah, okay, so Rocky is basically the same thing as Infiniband, but it goes over Ethernet
instead of the custom Infiniband protocol.
Oh, cool.
Yeah, so it's really cool, because then you can have all of your normal Ethernet workloads
that are doing TCP or UDP or whatever.
And then you can also have your RDMA applications that are going over exactly the same links.
And yeah, so we're pretty excited about that.
I think that's really going to improve both throughput that we can get, and also really
cut down on latency.
And Infiniband has become pretty standard for some of these high performance computing workloads,
because of its performance.
Are you able to, how close do you get to that?
And this is over 100G Ethernet?
Yeah, so we've done some testing on 100G Ethernet, and I believe have seen up to like
97% like utilization, so.
Oh, wow.
Pretty awesome.
If I remember correctly, on the Infiniband side, correct me if I'm mischaracterizing this,
my impression is that it's been limited to kind of these niche use cases like HPC, because
it requires that the applications need to be modified to take advantage of this memory
access.
Is that true?
And will the same thing need to happen with Rocky?
Yeah, so it is true.
And yes, the same thing will need to happen.
But at least you don't need a whole separate network infrastructure.
Right.
At least you don't need to buy completely new network cards and new switches and everything.
So then it can just happen at the application level.
And really, what I'm hoping will happen is that we can handle all of it in the framework.
And then you'll just have like a, you know, op that you plug into your TensorFlow graph,
which is the, you know, all reduce over our DMA operation.
And then people that are doing research won't have to worry about any of that, but that's
still to be seen how that works out and how all of this is going to integrate into the
Kubernetes ecosystem.
Nice.
And you mentioned something that made me realize that one area that we skipped was how
you're doing distributed training.
Can you talk a little bit about that?
There's a number of solutions for TensorFlow, for example, there's out of the box, there's
porovod, there are some others like how have you approached distributed training?
Yeah.
So that's one where we have a number of different approaches.
So we're definitely using porovod.
I've used it a bit.
I know a bunch of other teams are using it.
It's worked out quite well for us.
We have some people that are just like directly using MPI for Pi.
I think that has also worked well.
I believe there's at least one custom implementation of all reduce, and one of our teams has written.
So yeah, kind of a few different solutions haven't converged on anything particular.
And the idea is, in part, because everything is containerized, they just containerized
those components of their distributed training, deploy them out via Kubernetes, and it all
kind of works like anything else.
Exactly.
Cool.
Well, any thoughts or words of wisdom for folks that are interested in Kubernetes as a platform
for ML and DL and just getting started?
Yeah.
I'd say that the portability aspect of it and just the use of running it and scaling it is
something that has really benefited us a lot.
Especially if those are important factors that are recommended.
And in terms of ease of running it, sometimes Kubernetes or at least early on Kubernetes had
this reputation for not being particularly easy.
What's the support burden on your team for supporting the cluster bin like or the clusters?
Granted that you're already had a pretty tremendous scale.
Yeah, well, and I would say that that early reputation did reflect our experience too.
When I joined, we had a lot of problems that we were resulting.
And there was a pretty non-trivial support burden.
But both as Kubernetes has evolved and as we have evolved our way of managing it and
understood some of the aspects they need to pay attention to, like EtsyD in particular,
really want to make sure that you've provisioned enough IOPS and everything for that.
Now we've gotten to a point where I would say there's a very, very little maintenance burden.
We have an on-call rotation, of course, but in terms of critical issues, I'd say it's
rare that we have even one problem a month.
Oh, wow.
So let me re-ask that last question about words of wisdom and light of all of the kind of
revealed wisdom over the past coming up on two years now that's gone into allowing
it to be easy to maintain.
You mentioned, make sure you provision enough IOPS to your EtsyD.
What are some of the other things that folks need to do in order to have a good experience
managing Kubernetes for these kinds of workloads?
Yeah.
So we actually published a whole blog post back in January or February that talks about some
of the top ones.
So yeah, definitely, EtsyD is one of those.
And most of these, there are really issues that you're only going to hit once you go
beyond a few hundred machines.
So you can run it at a pretty good scale and not have to worry about much of it.
But yeah, once you get into the thousand or multiple thousands of machines, there's a bunch
of stuff to be aware of.
So, yeah, EtsyD was one of them ran into some funny network issues.
I spent a good couple of days learning all about ARP caches and how those work.
And it was predical that I had learned about back in college and figured out never needs
to know about again.
But very important to make sure that the ARP cache is big enough.
The combination of using flannel means that you need a significant amount of space in
your ARP cache.
If you've got thousands of containers that are talking to each other or talking to a single
one, like the CUBE DNS service.
So there's a few other issues that we enumerated in that blog post, but it's really not stuff
that you're going to hit until you've got many hundreds of machines.
Well, we'll link to that in the show notes for sure.
Chris, thanks so much for taking the time to chat with me about this super interesting
stuff.
Likewise, yeah, thanks so much for having me.
Alright everyone, that's our show for today.
For more information on Christopher or any of the topics covered in this episode, head
on over to twimmelai.com slash talk slash 199.
To learn more about our AI platform series or to get our e-books, visit twimmelai.com slash
AI platforms.
As always, thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.