Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast why interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington to close out 2018 and open the new year we're excited
to present to you our first ever AI rewind series.
In this series I interview friends of the show for their perspectives on the key developments
of 2018 as well as a look ahead at the year to come.
We'll cover a few key categories this year, namely computer vision, natural language
processing, deep learning, machine learning and reinforcement learning.
Of course we realize that there are many more possible categories than these, that there's
a ton of overlap between these topics and that no single interview could hope to cover
everything important in any of these areas.
Nonetheless we're pleased to present these talks and invite you to share your own perspectives
by commenting on the series page at twimbleai.com slash rewind 18.
In this episode of our AI rewind series, we're bringing back one of your favorite guests
of the year, Jeremy Howard, founder and researcher at fast.ai to discuss trends in deep learning
in 2018 and beyond.
We cover many of the papers, tools and techniques that have contributed to making deep learning
more accessible than ever to so many developers and data scientists.
Enjoy.
Alright everyone, I am here in Montreal with Jeremy Howard and I'm speaking with Jeremy
as part of a special series of shows we're doing about reflection of the machine learning
in deep learning world for 2018 and some thoughts on predictions for 2019.
Jeremy, welcome back to the show.
Thanks Sam, nice to be here, I'm worried I'm not nearly cool enough to be able to tell
you much about trends and whatnot but I'll do what I can.
I am sure we're going to have a wonderful conversation.
So this is the first of these that I'm doing and I expect that the format will shift
a little bit as I do them but maybe we can kind of start by just getting your off the
top of the head kind of reflections on 2018 before we focus on some of the things in particular
around deep learning research that you found most interesting.
Well, I guess it's easiest for me to talk about the year and the stuff that I care about
which is increasing accessibility of deep learning for normal people to solve normal problems.
So I guess our main work towards that this year has been trying to make it faster and
easier and less expensive to train neural nets across more different areas.
So there's a lot of people who have been doing work in that area as well which I could
touch on.
One is that when you look at the Stanford competition called Don Bench, it kind of kicked off
increased interest in an area which had been really underappreciated before which is
can you train accurate, large models quickly and cheaply.
So there's a competition to measure those two things and so before the competition it
took a few days generally to train image net to a reasonable accuracy, particularly if
you're using kind of commodity hardware like stuff you would rent from AWS.
And at the end of it we had gotten to first place on the leaderboard with 18 minutes, $40
being nothing but Amazon AWS and then there's been other related work from other researchers
who have got it down not on AWS commodity equipment but on more specialized equipment
down to seven minutes.
And so the kind of stuff that's allowed that to happen has been things like fantastic work
from Leslie Smith on achieving superconvergence so using much higher learning rates, particularly
a approach to learning rate scheduling called one cycle scheduling which we use as the default
all the time now and makes life much faster and easier.
I remember in the course and I believe our last conversation talking about cyclical learning
rates is one cycle.
Yeah, this is the next stage.
So last year I guess Leslie did the CLI paper, cyclical learning rates.
One cycle is just what it sounds like which is to spend about half of your epochs gradually
increasing the learning rate, about half gradually decreasing it.
But there's a few really important insights you have to combine with that.
One in Leslie's paper is that as you increase the learning rate you should decrease momentum.
So you have these two things happening at the same time.
So if you use the first AI library that will happen for you automatically.
And so it means that as you get to those really high learning rates, because the momentum
is a lot lower, you're much less likely to kind of accelerate further than the model
can handle.
Something not quite related to Leslie's work, but stuff from Frank Hudders lab around being
able to handle weight decay properly when you're using dynamic learning rates.
So the momentum and Adam, so their techniques called Adam W, turns out to be super important
as well for this.
Was that Adam W this year?
I can't quite remember, in the last 12 months or not, it may be slightly more, I don't
know.
But the combination I guess of all these things has been very much this year.
So, and we combine those two together along with progressive resizing.
So basically, I don't know if we were the first to do it.
There was a lot of people that kind of did it all about the same time, but basically this
idea of like, why don't you do most of your training on small images and then gradually
resize, because modern convolutional neural nets are all, don't care what size your input
is.
And what's the advantage of doing that?
Well, it's just super fast, you know.
So two things, super fast, you do most of your training at 64 by 64, so you're decreasing
your compute by more than 10x.
But then the nice thing is you can do the last one or two epochs at a larger size than
most people.
So most people do 224 by 224 the whole time.
So we'll go through to 288 or even bigger.
So the intuition there being that you can teach the network, the basic things that it wants
to learn about edges and textures and stuff.
Well, you know, what does the cat look like?
Yeah.
And what a cat looks like at 64 by 64 is basically the same as 288 by 288.
So the last couple of epochs, it's really just learning a few little tweaks around
like, okay, this breed of cat has a, you know, this color of nose and this breed of cat
has this slightly longer hair or whatever.
So it can do most of its learning.
And actually, that's been a real focus for us throughout the year is like this kind of
and same with Leslie Smith, doing a lot more stuff dynamically, changing things during
training.
So for example, something we're going to release next week is doing the same thing for
the GANs. So we've now got GANs training quickly and easily and reliably for the first
time.
And the trick again was basically to pre-train the critic and pre-train the generator using
kind of simpler, fast approaches and small images and then at the very end, you kind of
GANify it.
Okay.
So, you know, that's kind of been a common theme, I think.
And so that all, and so a lot of that ties in then to kind of transfer learning because
all these things of like gradually increasing the image size is kind of just a type of
transfer learning.
It's kind of transfer learning you're doing within the training learning.
Yeah.
So for our GANs, you know, we kind of do a similar thing of this kind of transfer learning
as part of the process of training again.
And so in general, transfer learning lets you generalize better, lets you train faster,
generally lets you use less data.
So we had a particular focus, as you know, on NLP for that.
And so we show it with NLP, you can use like 100 times less data and still get state
at the art results, sentiment classification.
And so that's all about transfer learning.
And then Alec Radford, at OpenAI, you know, built on top of that, replacing our LSTM with
a transformer, and then Google built on top of that, making some tweaks, but mainly just
doing it for longer with more data and, you know, we're now at a point where we know,
I guess we know kind of every time people try and do transfer learning anywhere.
Yeah.
It tends to either let you get way better results on small datasets than people thought
were possible or if you use big datasets like Google did with, but you know, it's kind
of smashed the state at the art of what people thought was possible.
So still really underappreciated area, frankly, still most people don't know how to do it
properly.
Had an interesting conversation here at NURPS, someone approached me and was, we were just
kind of exchanging thoughts on what was interesting at the conference and they said they didn't
see a lot of transfer learning like did that go away.
And I haven't seen any.
I both haven't seen it, but it's also, it's kind of, you know, being baked into a lot
of things.
It's kind of different.
But also like, NURPS is very tainted by its history and culture.
So the papers here, like, very tend to over-represent either things which are very mathematically
intensive or also things that follow certain trends.
So NURPS every second paper is either adversarial, blah or reinforcement learning, blah, you
know.
So like, yeah, it's not necessarily a conference you expect to see the most practically
impactful stuff, unless some of the workshops are a little bit different.
But I think that's been another feature of 2018 is like, people are putting adversarial
into everything and putting RL into everything and not generally for good reasons, especially
adversarial.
This is huge literature now around avoiding adversarial attacks and I've yet to find
anybody who's, and I've asked many researchers in the field, you know, directly, can you
show me a actual practical example of where you would need to use this thing, you know,
whatever they built?
Right.
No one's managed to get.
What about on the generative side of you as bearish on the generative, on the GANS?
So yeah, so I spent two weeks figuring out how to train GANS properly and finally, we
now have something in first AI where you can train them in an hour on a single GPU reliably.
And I'm very proud that we got to that point and we have this really flexible API that
allows researchers to plug in things in ways they couldn't before, but at the same time
I was also researching how to avoid GANS and I've figured out the generative stuff who
actually get GAN level performance without using GANS, so I'm not sure.
Is this stuff that you've written about or published somewhere?
It's coming up.
Okay.
So we're particularly doing some work in microscopy, in collaboration with the SOC institute
at the moment.
Okay.
Through analytic or through the fast idea.
No, no, I haven't had anything to do with endotic for years.
Okay.
This is through a few things, but it's particularly through a new medical and life science
research lab that I've just helped start, and I'm now the chair of, called RAMRI, with
low AI and medical research institute, and it's at USF University of San Francisco.
And we basically invite medical researchers and life science folks to partner with us
and we'll help with the deep learning stuff and they'll help with the domain specific
stuff.
Yeah, so through that collaboration, one of the things we've been working on is helping
the SOC institute to get better results from their microscopy because they're world leaders
in this area and it turns out that if you can get really high resolution microscopy,
then you can literally learn they have been publishing papers showing breakthrough understanding
of how proteins fold and how they actually impact cells and stuff like that.
So yeah, so initially we were kind of looking at GANs and getting pretty good results and
particularly one of our previous students, Jason Antich, has created this awesome thing
called de-oldify, which takes old black and white low resolution photos and turns them
into beautiful color pictures.
And so he's been helping us with some of this work of like getting GANs to work reliably
because he does better practical work with GANs than anybody else that's seen.
And how would GANs plan to this SOC institute use case?
Well, you've got these microscopy results, you want to get the highest resolution outputs
you can from whatever input comes out of your microscope.
And so there's actually been some very high impact work in microscopy recently on using
super res for that purpose, but it turns out not surprisingly that that research was not
at all using kind of modern, deep learning methods, so it's clear we can do a lot better.
But then, you know, as I say, then it turns out we've kind of realized that there are certain
loss functions we can use which avoid the need for GANs entirely.
So I'm now wondering if I wasted all that time.
But I'm very interested in generative models, you know, and to see the stuff that's happening
in the world of life sciences, you know, through better using whatever signal they can get
from their microscopes, it's really exciting, you know.
And you really need domain specialists and deep learning specialists working very closely
together because like there's all these cool things that they can do that I wouldn't
have otherwise known about in vice versa.
So for example, they can like, while they're kind of taking the picture, they can like
change the wavelength of light they're using, they can change the focal length they're using,
they can change the angle that they're using kind of then they can kind of end up with
this like long exposure almost like a video, and so we can then get this whole extra dimension
and this is kind of sub-pixel resolution embedded in that.
I mean this is what, this is exactly what we hope for, honestly, when we start a trust
AI is that kind of domain experts would be able to use deep learning to do a better job
of whatever it is they're doing, so it's nice to see that really happening.
Have you seen any applications of GANs outside of the image domain, I kind of wonder
conceptually you should be able to apply this to text and maybe do some of the things
that people are using RNNs and LSTMs to do?
Yeah, well like I say I feel like people are putting adversarial in everything and I'm
not convinced it's helpful, I think often it's a bit of a lazy shortcut to like actually
thinking about what your loss function should be.
Yeah, I mean you mentioned text, it's a good question, there's, I think the more general
question in text is what kind of like augmentation and stuff can we do in text to be able to use
less data and get better results and I've kind of seen some sign of trying to use adversarial
approaches there which I don't think is necessary, like there was a recent paper in the last
few weeks which was basically, I don't know if you're familiar with the cutout paper,
so you've got dropout which I think everybody knows which is like removing activations
around them and then the cutout paper in vision specifically removed a whole contiguous
sections of an image so kind of cut squares out of it and use that as regularization and
then there's been a more recent paper in the last couple of weeks which is kind of basically
done cut out at every layer of the neural net so it's basically dropout but instead of
removing activations at random, you remove activations at the next to each other, stuff
like that almost certainly will work equally well in text and don't require any of this
kind of adversarial stuff.
So yeah so I think my view is probably cans are a little overhyped and adversarial attacks
are a little overhyped and it's certainly a great way to get published in Europe and you
feel the same way about RL, have you also experimented with RL?
Well, kind of I spent 10 years kind of studying optimization more generally and I never felt
like these standard differentiation based approaches when you've got this kind of long-term
credit assignment issue necessarily make a lot of sense and I still feel like there's
a lot of the optimization literature that's being ignored by the RL community.
You've seen a little bit of like evolutionary algorithms get touched on here and there
like I think everybody's in work there but when I think back to like all the stuff that
was going on in the early 90s, people just started to rediscover some of it.
So for example, in the early 90s combining evolutionary algorithms together with kind
of gradient-based methods was really common and I just saw a paper literally reinventing
it like two weeks ago.
The problem RL is trying to solve is great which is like hey let's not just try to predict
things but let's actually try to figure out what action to take but I feel like currently
the RL community is not quite treating it as enough as differently enough as it should
be.
When I spent a long time on optimization it became clear over time that it's a good idea
to kind of recognize the differences between prediction tasks and more general optimization
tasks.
This is interesting because I had a chance to chat with Sergei Levine last night and
we were talking about generally what he's found interesting over the past year in RL in
particular.
This was informal.
But one of the things that he mentioned was a paper, TD3 paper, Twin Delay, Deterministic
Policy Gradient which sounded like just the kind of hack that you would love.
Like it's a tweak to the way they do the policy that he didn't even go into the details
because it was such a knit but it gave him two X better training times.
So if fast AI was doing RL it would be just the kind of thing that you bake into the library.
Yeah, but I mean we only work on stuff which clearly works in practice for the kinds of
problems most people have and Levine's one of the very few people who's using RL in
very appropriate and useful ways at the moment.
So for stuff involving robotics there's a lot more you can do with RL because any time
you've got some physical system that you can actually model with physics pretty accurately
you can kind of pull it apart and add appropriate constraints and an appropriate kind of
auxiliary losses and there's a lot more that you can do.
So I think the stuff he's doing is interesting and useful but a lot of people are using
RL for stuff I don't know.
I just went to the start of the health workshop here in Europe and there's all these people
tackling various medical problems using RL which just seemed like slightly ridiculous
in my opinion.
Interesting, interesting.
So there's been, we were chatting before we got started and you mentioned some of the
work that's been happening to try to better understand the way some of our tweaks we've
been doing like batch norm and other things are working.
Can you elaborate on some of that work?
Oh yeah, I'd love to.
I feel like that's something where there's been some great progress this year and particularly
in the last couple of months.
There's a fantastic poster here at Europe that's been an archive for a while called Visualizing
the Lost Landscape of Neural Nets and what they basically showed is it's something I've
been talking about for ages but never actually did anything about it which is this idea that
you can have this idea of sharp parts of the lost surface where if you're in a sharp
part of the lost surface then the idea is it probably won't generalize very well because
if you change anything a little bit now you're not in that kind of nice low area anymore
and it's kind of overreaction to what I thought was a kind of obvious and kind of mathematical
issue which is how you can like reparameterize the weights to make anything arbitrarily sharp
which to me like if any time you read can reparameterize something why don't you just normalize
out that reparameterization.
So this Visualizing the Lost Landscape actually did that so they actually did the normalization
and then they did this you know they built some beautiful software and some beautiful visualizations
to show what happens and they found some really interesting things.
One of the most interesting was they found that when you look at the actual trajectory
as you train your own app for example if you take the PCA space of the weights there's basically
only two dimensions you can basically that plot the entire or they said 40 to 90% of the variation
in the direction of the gradient updates lies in just two PCA directions independent of the
dimensionality of your well this was on image net so I mean this is obviously super high-dimensional
so yeah over a hundred million weights and so you know that and you know one of the nice things
that means is you can kind of plot exactly what pretty close to exactly what's going on which
they did and you can also plot the Lance Lost Landscape that's being navigated and so one thing
that they found was if you as soon as you add skip connections so Resnets versus the exact same net
without the identity shortcuts Resnets basically make the whole surface incredibly smooth
and dense nets make it even smoother by the way so when you see their pictures it just
immediately makes you realize like okay you know this is why we've been loving Resnets so much
and so you can kind of see similar stuff with normalization so one of the really interesting papers
to come out in the last couple of months so there's been two papers coming out very similar times
which both both both basically said hey you know how batch norm was meant to help with covariate
shift where it turns out it doesn't help with covariate shift and it's got nothing to do with
covariate shift and actually what it does is it makes the loss surface smoother which actually
if you think about it makes perfect sense you know if your if your current activation is scaled
really poorly then if you don't have batch norm the only way to fix that is to modify all of your
weights on that layer where else if you do have batch norm you only have to modify the batch norm
weights to fix the scaling so just makes the loss surface a lot smoother so then there's been other
very nice kind of follow-ups to that well exactly follow-ups coming out at similar times to that
saying hey here are some different ways of doing normalization which don't focus on the covariate
shift but focus on the scaling so spectral norm and weight norm in particular which are now both
built into pie torch and when you create a conflare in fast AI you can literally
pick from an enum of what norm type you want and yeah they they they help a lot actually with
against stabilizing training so yeah all these all these kind of insights into what's going on
and so the neural network is helping lead to better ways to train the neural networks which means
less hyper parameters less you know more resilient higher learning rates it's all making life
easier in practice which is great so last year the big controversy at least one of them was
Ali Rahimi's kind of call for greater rigor do you feel like a lot of this work is a response to
that or no I never quite figured out what Ali meant and even though I had quite a few private
chats with him I never quite figured out what he meant I tried to dig into it I think yeah so
so I you know since I don't quite know what he was saying and haven't figured it out I can't quite
I mean he's a great speaker and so a lot of people would like I really speak to that talk
when I ask them like what exactly did he mean by rigor and exactly what are you going to do about it
no one had a good answer to that question so for me you know as a kind of an experimentalist I think
rigor is about ablation studies you know so if you look at the your LEMFIT paper that Sebastian and I
did we spend a lot of time doing ablation studies so we said like what if you did this with more
data versus less data what if you removed this training thing from this training thing from this
training thing what if you tried this versus that data set and so we just had lots of tables and
pictures saying here's you know here's the thing showing you which bits help and how much they help
and what they help with so to me that's you know when when people don't have that I don't find
their papers terribly useful because I don't know what's what's actually helping and often the
things they thought were helping weren't helping even worse for me is when people don't use a
strong baseline so they'll have some really crappy model and they'll say like oh look at our technique
X improves that crappy model but when you look at it it's you know their technique X is just a
crappy way of doing what the normal baselines would have done anyway so I think like to me in terms
of experimental work strong baselines and good ablation studies is is what it's about but you know
for the New York's crowd rigor often means great letters you know they want to see like
you know convexity proofs and error bound proofs and all this stuff which I've just
never seen useful like the only thing I've seen those kind of proofs do is to totally mislead people
so like we had what I call the SDS pretty strong it's true we that what I call the SVM winter for
like 15 20 years which is basically you know that Nick did this really to some people compelling
papers it's just kind of like hey all you need is SVMs here's the mathematical proof and
it you know when you actually look at it it's it's it's it's the the things that people took out
of that are rubbish like it's the difference between like in theory here's what ought to work
versus in practice here's what actually it works so it's it's it's nice this year
leonbertos I can't remember the co-author but leonbertos work won a test of time award his 22 2007
paper which basically I mean it's it's it's ridiculous that it was necessary for this paper to
even happen but he basically said look or you people who were spending all this time on like
fancy optimizers for SVMs actually SGD works better and and and like and then here's all the
Greek symbols you need you know like here's all the proof and math and whatever else so like
there's already plenty of experimental evidence to say like it works better which
most of the community ignored and so it really took somebody to come along and like say it in
their own words and to like prove it so to me I'm kind of like I don't like similar thing with
like going back further minskie right minskie like proving that neural nets are a waste of time
because they can't like solve the x-all problem and so the thing is all these mathematical proofs
they're always of oversimplified versions of the problems we're actually trying to solve because
the problems we're actually trying to solve are not amenable to that kind of analytic approach
so you know took 20 years really for somebody to come along and say well we're not just using
one layer you know we actually have a hidden layer if you have a hidden layer then we can solve
any arbitrary problem to arbitrarily close given enough parameters so again like these kind of AI
winters we had were really kicked off by people taking theoretical results far further than they
should have ever been taken and ignoring all of the empirical evidence of like I don't know like
guys like Jan LeCouin who's like saying like hey I've actually written this thing on that five
that actually reads numbers you know it works it's this thing called a convolutional neural network
and you know people like that just weren't getting published because you know because the theory
had already proven that we should be using these other approaches so yeah I think that's um
that's a concern I have about our field in general it also is a real problem for diversity
and inclusion because there's lots more people in the world who know how to code or you don't know
how to do some engineering but won't know how to prove error bounds on something or whatever
and also like we'll be much more focused on like hey I want to actually solve this problem in
in medicine or in you know disaster resilience or whatever and so they'll want to be
publishing papers saying his thing A that works for thing B and the current focus in our field is
yeah very unfriendly to that kind of stuff interesting yeah yeah um I'm curious having launched the new
fast.ai course this year the deep learning course any you know specific 2018 learnings
about deep learning education or what's required you know what's you know what's needed to kind
of broaden the fold of folks that can do deep learning. I think I've been surprised by how far
people have gone on the back of the fast.ai course like a lot of presenters at nureps have come up
to me and said they got into deep learning through fast.ai and if you would ask me three years ago
if our students are going to go on to be researchers presenting at nureps I would have been like
that sounds like me I feel like we're just trying to get people to be reasonable practitioners so I
think I think that's been a pleasant surprise um it's also been I must have been a bit surprised
at how quickly the software has taken off um like for me that's kind of my focus now is like I would
love for software to be as standalone as possible and not really require people to do the course
because there's a lot of investment in time to do the course and yeah I'm increasingly running
into particularly researchers now who have come from backgrounds in TensorFlow or pure pie
torch or China or whatever and kind of saying like oh I started using the software and
my research is going faster than it was before so that's been nice um but I think overall
you know it's we've kept on finding the same things we've found in previous years it's just
accelerating like I went to the black and ii dinner last night and the black and ii workshop which
I saw you there as well um and uh yeah I mean it's just so great how many people came up to me and
said like you know hey I'm from the ivory coast or I'm from Tanzania or whatever and
I had no way to learn deep learning until your course came along and now I've done it and now
I'm here at nureps presenting at this workshop and uh and they're always like kind of inspiring
stories because often that you know they're telling me last night about the steps they had to go
through to get a visa often having to go to other countries and contacting the console general or
you know like as they're they're forging paths no one's ever forged before and now they're
finding communities so like um it's so cool the way like three years ago and we did our first
course we had one student from legos and he was like asking on the forum like hey anybody else
from legos here anybody else from africa here you know tonight you're like can we have a community
no nothing you know and and now uh legos is a second biggest faster your community
long outside of the u.s so a bungalow is still the biggest bangalow that legos is huge so like
it's been really cool to see how just a little bit of um and I know it's certainly not all
thanks to fast ai there's lots of people doing great work here but I know like plenty of the people
involved have got there thanks to fast ai so for example one of the um people presenting at the
black and ai dinner last night uh judy jichoya she's a um a radiologist who got into deep learning
through fast ai and now she's like a incredibly kick ass leader both in the radiology world and
in the deep learning world in the black and ai world so um yeah I feel like there's now enough
momentum going on that these uh underrepresented groups are not going to be underrepresented
too much longer mm-hmm mm-hmm yeah I thought the I forget his full name but one of the presentations
was kareem karen those an interesting uh slide where one of the speakers uh from tenizha
kind of asserted that ai is both this incredible both uh existential threat for africa in some ways
and and an awesome opportunity and kind of uh you know for for him it was a rallying cry to
you know get more people engaged in the process i thought those were really interesting yeah
I mean that's kind of why Rachel and I started this or it's exactly why Rachel and I started
this is we both thought like this has the potential to massively increase inequality that's that
is exactly what will happen if there's just a status quo right because all the people you know
before we started fast ai all the people pretty much studying and working in deep learning were
you know western white men who very very few of whom had any kind of domain expertise background
so they were using deep learning to solve kind of bullshit problems um so we thought okay if
nothing changes that's going to get worse and worse because those people keep getting money thrown
at them and and they keep hiring more of the same people and investing education in the same
places and but at the same time you know um it's deep learning is not at heart and it can be used
to help so many areas with so many problems so if we could get kind of get this the the skills out
there um then maybe uh people who otherwise would not be able to will be able to like make a big
impact so i mean jute is a good example i think she's from Kenya uh and uh you know uh i'm
sure she would have been a great radiologist regardless right but i feel like now you know we have
somebody in the kind of senior thought leader community amongst radiologists who is black and who
is a woman and who is you know both bringing ai to radiology and radiology to ai you know it's
exactly the kind of perspective which yeah hope you know i think can create opportunities but
they didn't exist before um let's talk a little bit about the the tools landscape obviously one
of the big developments in 2018 was the launch of the 1.0 versions of both the fast that ai library
and and uh pie torch is it too early to to talk about kind of momentum from the pie torch launch
or it's not too early because one of the really interesting things is paying to see TensorFlow's
reaction which is they've really got off their ass and doing good stuff you know they made some
tough choices like getting rid of tf.contrib making tfo a much more community given exercise i think
they realized that you know the the direction you know you talk to almost any Google TensorFlow
engineer off the record at least and they'll tell you they all hate that code based you know it's
full of technical debt and it's just not well put together um and it's not focused on the kind
of the developer experience um it's really focused on using as many tp users possible so so tf2 is
looking like a huge step forward in terms of the developer experience and um you know uh just
kind of a piece of software that people will enjoy using breath of the news because they have to
so and i really think that's been i mean i know it's been very heavily a reaction to pie torch
which is not to say pie torch invented this approach uh it's i mean China certainly did it before
pie torch and i don't quite know the history before that but um i think yeah realizing that
the the tools need to be written for developers uh is just a really important insight so i think
that's been so i think the impact on the on the TensorFlow gorilla has been important and interesting
but then um yeah people just using pie torch uh particularly in the research community
you're definitely seeing things you know more innovation as a result you're seeing faster innovation
and then yeah you know the impact of fast ai is probably a little early to really know but um
we're seeing that for a whole nother level for the you know quite a few researchers who are picked up
fast ai um and you know fast ai kind of has two different user groups in mind there's the
you know very much the research user group so that's all about the kind of
lower level of abstractions where so for example with our gans you know we've made it so you can
easily do research around like if you want some dynamic approach to switching between training
the critic and the generator you know you you can just plug in your own gans which are class or if
you want to pre-train a different kind of critic you can plug in a different pre-train critic class
whatever and then of course there's the user group of people who just want to um get something
working at their company so for example one person who came up to me at europe's last night said
oh my company has three million documents um it's a pretty big international company and we've
been using faster ai and urlm fit to basically tag all three million documents and they have a
full-time taxonomist who sits there and classifies documents and then that gets fed off to urlm fit
through fast ai and then they put the results and find you in the model and um so they're not
doing research level customization or whatever they're just getting stuff done so I think yeah I
think both of those groups so uh you know I think previously they would have been using
keras if you wanted to do something like that but keras just doesn't really give you easy
supportive things like nlp and things like that so um I think that yeah maybe that's one of the main
impacts of fast ai in that area is easy deep learning isn't just in computer vision anymore
it's also nlp and tabular and collaborative filtering
any other interesting things on the tool side that you've that have caught your eye
um yeah there's plenty of stuff going on I wish I had more time to dig into them than I did
I mean you know in the pie-torch community well I mean obviously one big thing in pie-torch
version one release which just came out yesterday is the just in time compiler so you can add a
jet decorated to your code and get you know fused you know fast inference version of it so
um it's quite a bit of that stuff going on there's another much less known library for pie-torch
which is the galsion processes library and um so me it's not so much interesting because of the
galsion processes but be interesting because they have to encode a lazy tensor which kind of
takes the jet to a whole nother level which is you can as you basically say these are all the
mathematical operations I want to do on my tensor it it's just storing the computation graph it's
not doing the actual calculation at all until later on when you just say you know compute and then
it compiles a kind of a fused version and then much faster handles kind of stuff like sparsity
and stuff much better and they also have some kind of nice linear algebra identities which they
use to you know just use arithmeticly much better choices when they know that you know you had
these different shape matrices and you did these particular operations to them and you know
this linear algebra identities so therefore we can replace that set of operations with this
single faster one um at least with the lazy tensor is this an example of kind of pie-torch moving
towards tensor flow while tensor flow is moving towards pie-torch I think so um I think so yeah exactly
so the kind of the the the jet in pie-torch is starting to feel a bit like XLA I guess in tensor
flow but with less technical depth yeah and they're kind of a lazy tensor stuff is starting to
look a bit like the um uh kind of static graph approach but without all the horrible boilerplate
the tensor flow so um I mean what we're I'm really excited though is what TNG chain is doing with
TVM like hopefully that stuff with TVM where there you'll have right on that what's TVM
our TVM is is something that's basically at a lot of level which is that you um take a it's
basically a compiler for tensor expressions that will create an an optimized version of your
tensor expression and um because at the moment one of the things I hate I as I hate it when I say
to a student like okay let's dig into this code which calls this which calls this which calls this
and let's understand all the stuff that's going on and they get to a point where it's like oh and
this calls n videos kudian and library so at that point okay after that it's magic um so one of
the cool things TVM does is it um kind of lets you see you know um it doesn't suddenly stop at
kudian and it's now here's the TVM code you know okay and then um TVM ends up believe it or not
faster than kudian and even although TVM is automatically creating that optimized kuda kernel
so is it replacement or is it compiling down to kuda or something i mean it still has to
compile down to what i'm not necessarily kuda but maybe ptx um so it's still you know so it's not
business not just for Nvidia it can also target you know um or you know um various mobile devices
or cpu um so i'm kind of like excited about this because i think it might mean that um particularly
for stuff like swift for TensorFlow which is a project i'm really excited about you know
you know hopefully we can see things where we can write everything we're doing in our kind of
host language and um i was gonna ask are you excited about that because you're excited about
Swift the language or because you want to see deep learning accessible via all the languages
um there's a number of reasons i'm excited about it one is that i hate Python so great to you know
get rid of it um it's just it's just incredibly frustrating to have to write in a language which
has so many klachi things like with global interpreter lock and just so incredibly slow every
time you actually do something in python and um so you know it's it's very very frustrating to
to to work with it's fine if you're doing a web app or something but for numerical programming
you spend all of your time trying to figure out how to have everything not being done in python
you know you're basically always calling to see your kuda or whatever libraries um partly it's
because Chris Latina everything he touches is awesome so it's just nice when somebody like that
comes into your field and um i just can't you know i just love seeing what he's doing
partly because Swift is just you know it's a good language um it's uh you know there's a few good
languages in the world like i think f-sharp and julia and swift uh all examples of just good
languages um but the thing about Swift uh and julia and f-sharp is they can all um you can write
fast code in them and so like and so Chris's approach with with the swift potential flow team is
that you'll be able to write all of your kuda kernels and stuff in swift you know and so be
you know and and because like he's the llvm guy you know you know he's got the compiler chops to
make sure that those swift kernels are not going to be any slower than the c kernels for me
so also from a teaching point of view it'll be really nice to be able to show people every layer
and from a research point of view it'll be really nice because we're we're able to
swap out this lstm cell with our own lstm cell and not have to yeah worry about
you know switching into c++ and comparing an extension and then dealing with a whole different
debugging framework and all that how far along is it um not terribly far along um yeah it's not
some of our students have tried to kind of play with it and it's not really usable yeah
but i'm sure it'll get there okay and similar stuff going on in julia by the way julia also
has similarly exciting stuff going on around writing kernels in julia and all that okay
uh so maybe switching gears to 2019 and things you're excited about uh opportunities
what what do you what are you looking forward to um well what do you think is going to happen if
i don't know if you're one for kind of dusting off of crystal ball but
no i don't know what i'm doing i'm doing another people i mean we're just keep doing what we're
doing i guess um so i'm going to be doing a deep dive into um speech recognition kind of next year
we're going to write a book about faster i and patorch kind of the book version of the course
i guess early in the year with uh silvenko gogo who has been helping us with pretty much
everything this year um you know i i hopefully will keep lowering the bar around um and we hopefully
will start getting to the point sometime soon i don't know if it'll be in the next year where we can
do useful stuff without any code that's that's really the the main bar that i want to get to is
doing useful stuff without any code what does that mean for you so this is a startup i'm involved
in called platform ai where we're trying to do exactly this for one particular sub domain which
is image classification so you can uh don't even need labels you can import some some photos and we
try and provide a uh kind of intuitive representation of what the model is learning to help a domain
expert interact with it in an entirely visual way um so for me it's all about like people using
stuff like that to solve scientific problems or to optimize their logistics or whatever it is
they're trying to do you know like um it's all about recognizing that machine learning is
computers learning from examples and so that should be all about getting rid of code we shouldn't
need for loops and conditionals and stuff you should just be able to say here are my examples
and the computer said here is what i'm learning and then you should say well here is some
feedback about which ones are right and wrong so that's where we want to get to so yeah so we've
uh already got the startup doing that for computer vision and i hope to do similar things in speech
and nlp as well um as long as we rely on people knowing how to code we're missing out on something like
99.9% of local population right right so maybe you know not kind of being so strict about
2019 just you know looking ahead to the near future what um you know where you think the
opportunities for us uh liar or are there specific um ideas you know or even some of the ideas
that we've talked about in terms of you know better understanding of the way some of the training
techniques are working or so the the big opportunity right now is nlp so um you know this year
we and others showed that transfer for learning for nlp works specifically it works with that
requiring an email labeling um um other than your target task and even then doesn't require
much labels um we're gonna see i'm pretty sure similar things being shown for um generative models
for text um so unfortunately that means one of the big opportunities will be that um spammers
and trolls and people interested in disinformation will be able to use this technology to
cause much more mayhem than they've been able to cause before um so i would say that's probably
gonna happen in the next 12 months so i would not be surprised to see massive scale
bots of generative text which are both appropriate enough to the thing it's responding to to seem
reasonable and kind of reasonably believable stylistically that large numbers of people will
be fooled by them large amounts of the time and they will not be easily automatically blocked or
even analyzed to know the scope of them the way that things are now so i think the technology
to fight that is harder than the technology to create it or is it just a will no it's much harder
okay i i i i feel very confident that i you know if i had the reason or motivation to build such a
bot now i feel very confident i could create one at scale which would you know be devastating to
any social media platform uh and i think lots of people i mean not lots lots but you know
anybody involved in the modern nlp kind of uh transfer learning stuff could um i would have
know if somebody said to me like hey Jeremy Sebastian Root has just become an evil genius so this
has written a twitter bot to spread russian disinformation can you go and help block it that'd be
like no probably not you know i don't know that sounds really really really hard uh and that's
often been the problem in these kind of areas is it's normally easier to create mayhem than to
block it um and also when you're trying to block it you're always kind of being reactive
particularly where we're not using more heuristic approaches to do the generative modeling but
using kind of smarter approaches so yeah i think that's going to be a really big problem and one of
the challenges is that the best way to fight that would would be to write your own generative
text bots and you know use them to fight the disinformation but the kinds of people that would
want to fix the problem would be much less likely to be the kinds of people who would be prepared to
launch their own generative text box so i think that'll be difficult um but i then i think you
know there's a lot of opportunities to uh you know in industry for for companies to be able to use
text as a valuable resource i think it can certainly happen in medicine as well um like
one of the challenges and radiology is that the the labels are all buried in radiology reports
right and when you look at stuff like the data sets that the NIH should have provided for medical
imaging the labels they've created have been using classic rules based NLP approaches and they're
just terrible so having um that labeling done with these kind of modern transfer learning
approaches will be awesome so yeah i think that's hopefully going to be one of the big at least
the positive side of it will be one of the big things in 2019 um i think we're going to see
these different approaches to normalization um probably start to take over from batch norm um i mean
it's kind of unfortunate that we don't have a real image net competition anymore because like
image net you know has plenty of flaws so i'm not saying we need image netback but the fact that
there was our competition that quite a few of the more serious researchers decided to invest
significant time in meant that each year you would see you know this year we've got
measured three by three comms this year we've got resonance this year we've got you know
Andrew Howard's data augmentation methods like they were like it made people who would otherwise
be focusing on mathematically pure whatever's like actually focus on solving a problem properly
mm-hmm so i i do worry that you know and also those solutions got published not just as papers but
as you know um pre-trained models so we can download so i do worry a bit that we might continue
to use pre-trained image net models with older architectures and older normalization approaches
and stuff just because we don't quite have an image net competition anymore so i don't know
what the fix to that is i mean there is like tf hub and now there's a torch hub which trans you
know actually provide pre-trained models but people need to start realizing i think yeah that
the image net models are increasingly out of date and then you know skip connections
are still interesting the the unit paper is now the most highly cited mick i medical
image and conference paper of all time resinat obviously is still kind of all powerful
so two really important skip connection stuff so i think hopefully people will keep finding ways
to better utilize skip connections mm-hmm and those two things skip connections and normalization
yeah really help make models easier to train quickly and accurately mm-hmm
the i think the rate at which new data sets are coming online is uh been uh increasing there
have been a ton of these and like various domains in 2018 any do you think we see um or need for
that matter like a kind of a better image net or a monster you know kind of the image data set
to and all image data sets or do you think the domain specific direction is more that one better
yeah yeah you know um so google to their credit just yesterday maybe it's this morning released a
much more diverse version of open images um and that's really fantastic because the the previously
the open images and image net data sets were incredibly biased in terms of they're basically all
came from white western countries and so on that very very difficult to train models that could
recognize Hindu weddings versus Christian weddings for example um so yeah i think we have a great
photo object classification data sets um but we don't have great
my cross-copy you know histopathology data sets we don't have great radiology data sets
um on the text side and lp side uh on both yeah um particularly thinking of vision um yeah on the
text side i mean it's ridiculous the it's there are almost no publicly available label text data sets
that normal people can use as they wish um most of them are locked behind this thing called the
linguistic data consortium which is part of you pen and um i'm sure originally when it was
created it had every good plan to help research whatever but today it's basically this um
thing that is increasing the exclusivity of the field so like it's my students can't replicate
results in papers because so many of the data sets in an lp are locked behind all kinds of
licensing agreements and like under the most popular ones the voters corpus you have to like
download print sign with your organizational affiliation of form and send it to the to the
government for approval you know you can't have a hundred thousand fast day ice students doing
that so i can't use those data sets because they just aren't the like they were created in a time
when people just didn't occur to them that like maybe there's more than just this like little
research community of people who go to my little workshop but there's actually a there's a
whole world of people out there who are wanting to do work right you know so that's a huge problem
so i think um you know i think something else i would really like to see is in areas like
medical imaging where data sharing is difficult um i want to see more model sharing
so like there's lots of pre-trained image net models like more than we need
so where's all the pre-trained histopathology models and the pre-trained
CT models and the pre-trained MRI models like those are actually much more useful because you know
if stanford releases their pre-trained prostate MRI model and then Boston picks it up and fine
tunes it a bit and publishes those weights and then Harvard picks it up and fine tunes out a bit
and then publishes those weights and then stanford can come back and fine tune that back in the
circle right end up something better than they started with like it's actually it's been shown
that you end up with just as good a model as you would have if you actually shared the data
hmm but more you actually have to do is share weights so i would love to see people
releasing pre-trained domain specific networks so another thing we saw quite a bit of this
year was proposals for data sheets for data sets model cards you know different
representations of the idea that we need to document the biases and and lineage in some cases
of data sets and models do you see that stuff taking off? I don't see it taking off no I mean
I think it's really cool the work that Jim Nick Gepparoo and all those folks did with the data
data sheets for data sets work and it's a really interesting examples of other industries where
that's happened so I've done some work with electronics and certainly I'm used to as they
describe in the paper that every electronics component comes with a data sheet and a fairly
consistent format and you rely on it having said that we're still suffering in the deep learning
world from people not publishing the data at all or not publishing their code at all so I also
worry about like if we say like well you can't publish your data set unless you create this data
sheet maybe there'll be even less people publishing their data I do think that all the conferences
need to say if you have experiments you need to publish the code and the data okay people claim
that we have this great peer review system but when you actually look at it it doesn't really work
like reviewers don't recreate the papers right the code to recreate the papers ever on the other
hand where people put stuff up an archive there'll be many of our students all at the same time
trying to replicate it and if they can they'll get up on GitHub and post issues and say what's
going on which has happened just a couple of weeks ago it turned out that a widely cited paper
as students went to replicate it and found they couldn't and discovered that the researchers
had accidentally used the test the test set as part of the training data you know so like I don't
at all agree with this idea that we have to keep this pure exclusive peer review system what we
instead need is to be able to publish their code and publish their data and then get it out there
so that the rest of us can can try it out and I think the academic community still doesn't realize
how many of us do do that replication like every single algorithm that fast AI teaches or
implements in our software we always re-implement from scratch and test from scratch for example and
we're definitely not the only ones so I think like people are lots of people going to start
publishing the data sheets for data sets let's first of all have the published data sets at all
it would be great if they you know and I guess it's up to the kind of conference and venues
and journals and stuff to start saying you know first yes you have to publish your code and data
and then maybe once that's happening okay you actually have to also publish a data sheet to go
with it we could at least encourage through the review process in the meantime to like if you've
got a new data set to kind of say like can you you know reviewers could ask for information about
how it was collected and you know what the diversity of people involved in was and stuff like that
it certainly does seem like a good bar in a time when you've got 4,000 submissions to
nerfs and a thousand papers being published to require that folks that are doing experimental work
publish the code as well it does yeah well Jeremy it's been so great to chat with you once again
great to see you here and thanks for taking the time thank you Sam
all right everyone that's our show for today for more information on Jeremy or any of the topics
covering in this episode visit twimmalei.com slash talk slash 214 you can also follow along with
our AI rewind 2018 series at twimmalei.com slash rewind 18 as always thanks so much for listening
and catch you next time happy holidays