Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast why interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
While at this past NURBS, I attended the second annual Black NAI workshop, which gathered
participants from all over the world to showcase their research, share experiences and support
one another.
This week, we continue our Black NAI series with interviews with some of the great presenters
from the workshop.
Today I'm joined by Justice Ammo, a PhD student at Dartmouth, Thayer School of Engineering.
Justice presented his work on an optimized recurrent unit for ultra low power acoustic
event detection.
In our conversation, we discuss his goal of bringing low cost, high efficiency wearables
to market for monitoring asthma.
We explore the many challenges of using classical machine learning models on microcontrollers,
and how he went about developing models optimized for constrained hardware environments.
We'd also like to wish Justice the best of luck as he should be defending his PhD any day
now.
Enjoy.
Alright everyone, I am on the line with Justice Ammo.
Justice is a PhD student at the Thayer School of Engineering at Dartmouth.
Justice, welcome to this week in machine learning and AI.
Thank you Sam, I'm happy to talk to you today about my wake.
Fantastic, so to kind of lead us into what you're up to, I would love if you share a little
bit about how you got started working in machine learning and AI.
Yes, I'm happy to share a bit about my background.
So I was born and raised in Ghana and came to Dartmouth for undergrad.
So this was in like 2009, I mean, undergrad when I was coming in, I always wanted to do
electronics.
So that's where I started.
Pretty much embedded system tried.
How do you build devices that was always fascinating to me?
So I finished undergrad becoming sort of good at building devices for embedded systems.
And then when I stayed a year after undergrad to do research, one of my mentors in undergrad
was he had this research project and he was like, hey, I think you really do good on
this.
He was interested in building a wearable monitor for monitoring asthma, like monitoring
the lungs, right?
Like if you can listen to what is going on in the lungs, then maybe you can better advise.
So he asked me to come on board and I was excited to come on board and just explore that project
for a year.
And it really came down to two things.
One was how do you build the hardware that can really listen to, you know, can acquire
the sound really well, right?
And then the second phase is once you have that hardware in place, right?
How do you detect these sounds well enough?
How do you detect sounds and symptoms like coughing, whizzing or even when someone is
panting?
How do you detect them and do that very well?
And so that one year I did, we came pretty far on, like, device in a good hardware.
And so I started looking at, you know, how do we do detection?
What are the algorithms that exist in for detection?
That's what brought me to classifiers and machine learning and looking at that.
And so after that one one year, we're all excited about the work as I say, hey, let's
explore this as a PAD work and I start going to work on it.
And it was mainly from the standpoint of your, okay, how do I, now that I have some hardware,
how do I make the signal really great?
And then how do I really detect these sounds very well?
So started from traditional classifiers, like, you know, decision trees, hidden macaw models
because those were the things that people were doing around that time.
And then all the way meeting to, you know, deep learning, looking at, like, convenants
and then more recently into recurrent.
So that's kind of been the very broad journey, yeah, of mine.
One thing that jumps out at me hearing the story is that you started with the hardware
and then went on to think about the software, is that it stretched me as the opposite of
the way that won my purchase, is that like an academic thing or was there something novel
about the way you were approaching the hardware that you thought was the right thing for this
application?
Yeah, actually, it's interesting you point that out because like, I really started out
interested in hardware, right?
How do I build really good hardware?
And the point wasn't just, you know, build whatever hardware, like, you know, build the
best hardware, I was really constrained for very efficient but affordable hardware.
The initial boost, where, like I mentioned, I'm from Ghana, so our initial boost, where
how do we build devices that can be used in, you know, and the resource communities,
communities where, you know, they cannot afford to buy really expensive devices, right?
In areas that you can have doctors to do diagnosis, can use some of these tools to, you know,
better do diagnose.
So that was really the real motivation.
And so when I was building hardware, even in building the hardware, I realized that,
you know, hardware is expensive, software is cheap, right?
So there is this trade off you can do, right?
You can build a just okay hardware and do more of the signal processing and machine learning
so that you don't have to use, you know, the best sense.
So you can have really cheap hardware and then software is much cheaper, so, you know,
you can duplicate it, right?
So that's where it really, like I followed that trajectory, where I built a hardware
that was like, you know what, this hardware is good enough, I could spend more time making
the best hardware that would be very expensive, but I think this is affordable.
And so now, how do I use software to bridge that gap to go the extra mile, right?
And so that's where it came in and machine learning became a really good answer to that,
right?
And if you have data that is not like 100% like, you know, clean, you can still use advanced
patent recognition tools to extract information from that and make really reasonable inferences
of that.
So it was like that practical approach that brought me into machine learning.
And so before we jump into the machine learning elements, can you give us an overview
of the hardware and the various components? It sounds like acoustics, maybe some microphones
or something like that.
And, you know, what is the processing capability?
What are the various components of the hardware system?
So as I said, I'm interested in this application, we're interested in basically escortating
sounds from the body.
So that's like what a status group does, right?
And so you want an acoustic sensor that you can collect sound from the body.
You could use really advanced microphones, like MEMS, but then those are really, they
can be more expensive.
But also, when you think of collecting data from the body, you can, and you can use pz
electric transducers that have contact sensors, right?
And so when you have that compared to a microphone, it would only pick up sounds that is coming
from the patient.
So already you start off eliminating a lot of the external background sounds, right?
So a huge part of the hardware system is a contact pz electric transducer, also a pz
electric transducer can generate power.
And so it's not that power hungry.
You don't have to, it's going to be really good for low power applications, right?
And so from there, from the pz electric transducer to your raw sensor, you have some analog
front end secretary to condition the signal, right?
You're looking for things like cove sounds and we sounds.
But a person is going to be wearing this most of the time, right?
And people speak all the time.
So you want to make sure that you're actually filtering out a lot of this, you know, the
speech sounds and all of the other possible background sounds.
So that's what a lot of the analog front end does.
So these are things like low pass, high pass, notch filters, that kind of thing?
Exactly, exactly.
So you have, you know, a couple of stages of, you know, classical analog filters where
you are really in the, in the kind of the range that we are interested in, you're looking
for sounds between 100 heads and two kilohertz, right?
So you're attenuating anything outside of that band, that band and sort of really amplifying
the signal there.
Because in that way, you can capture the re sounds, the cove sounds and the things that
are of interest, right?
Yeah.
So once you condition that signal, then now you come to, you know, you need a microprocessor
to sample the, to sample the analog signal and then, you know, maybe preprocess and identify
what events actually okay, right?
And so there you have a lot of options for microcontrollers.
But if you think of something that is going to be wearable for, you know, there's something
that someone will wear for maybe a whole day, that leaves you with only ultra low power
microcontrollers, right?
You cannot think of some of the fancy, you know, and for even M7, you have to go to something
that is really, really low power.
So the huge specification of this was to go for the lowest power microcontroller.
So we are using an ARM M0, right?
It's like the lowest power, the most energy efficient ARM microcontrollers are out there,
right?
So once you go there, that's where all the constraints begin to happen because you don't
have, you don't have floating point operations, you don't have DSP instructions.
So you are really constrained, right?
And you still have to be able to get inference and working at that level.
That's, I guess, pretty much sort of the set up for the hardware.
And so that led you down the path of trying to figure out how to get the various types
of software that you wanted to have working on this hardware, you had to work within kind
of these constraints.
You've got some constraints that are set up by the choice of microcontroller.
Are you also thinking about power envelope and that kind of thing, or is that all inferred
by the microcontroller choice?
So actually, the ultimate and fundamental constraint is power, right?
Power is always, right?
Exactly.
So you start out with power.
And if you really look at the power range, you are talking about, right?
To put it in perspective.
So I like smartphones around the thousand milliwatts, even some of these fun embedded systems
are around hundreds of milliwatts, but we are talking of tens of milliwatts.
So that already really constrains you.
And when you look at all the microprocesses available within that low, ultra-low power
range, right?
You realize they have so many things in common, like they don't have, you know, they don't
have floating point operations, the clocks are normally much lower.
We are looking at things less than 48 megahertz.
And so the constraints become very apparent for that range.
I guess what I was curious about was, you know, certainly within a given power constraint,
you choose your microcontroller.
But I guess I was envisioning a scenario where you want to do things at the software level
to even further manage the power consumption given a specific microcontroller.
Are you having to deal with that kind of thing or did you just constrain the power by choosing
the microcontroller and then you can go hog while you're with?
No.
So that's a perfect question actually, because even with the microcontroller, you have
in place, if you just run it all the time, you're not going to make your power budget.
So you have to do this, you know, event pre-event detection task that can, you know, your
microcontroller is mostly in a very low power state.
And you wake it up when you think that the events you are seeing correspond to, you need
to make an inference on it.
So you have all of those like low levels sort of software already implemented.
It's kind of like the very first layer of your entire detection pipeline, right?
This wake up webbit has an sound event okay and at all, right?
Before you wake up, other things to be processing.
So you have that block link.
It sounds like a low level version of like the wake word for an Alexa type of device.
Exactly, exactly, exactly.
Yeah.
But putting like the whole pipeline is very, very interesting because you have to get all
these blocks in place in order to make all your specifications.
And so you have the hardware in place, I'm imagining that the traditional way of solving
this problem is using kind of time-tested digital signal processing algorithms.
Is that the direction that you'd first go with this or is there something else?
Yeah, yeah.
So when I started my research very early on, right, the traditional way was, you know what
you get your signal and you do like a smart signal processing as you can.
So you're doing things like, you know, what is the best feature extraction that you can
do, right?
So people have come up with so many sort of kind of fifth features that once you extract
those features, it makes it so easy to fail your event, right?
So I'm imagining things like FFTs would come into play here.
Exactly, exactly, exactly.
So FFTs being fast for your transform form is a way to kind of extract the frequency
components of an incoming signal.
Exactly, exactly.
So doing something like that and even other sort of steps on top of the FFTs, so get
something like the spectrails, centroid, the fundamental frequency and all of these things
make it much, much easier so that now you can just use a very simple, say, like, you
know, thresholding to detect when an event has happened, right?
So that was kind of like the assistant work, right?
How do you extract the salient features from this so that classification becomes so,
so much easier, right?
Okay.
But of course, the handicap of that is, what is the best feature, right?
So FFTs spend so many years sort of identifying the best features for say, curve detection
for whiz detection.
And I started out with looking at all of that.
And that's when the promise of deep learning became really exciting because in deep learning
now, you don't have to hunt engineer features, right?
You can do the learning of both the features and the classifier jointly.
So that's actually what pushed me into that direction that, hey, what I'm sitting here
trying to hand crab the best feature sets, but it can actually be automated as part of
the process.
So how about we look at that and see how that compares?
And so as a, you know, someone who's equally excited about deep learning, I kind of get
that as a direction, but I wonder if you've got, you know, a very well defined kind of body
of work for that's, you know, there's already handing you the features, kind of telling
you the way to do it.
What's the real advantage that deep learning is giving you?
Yeah.
So one of the key things to start realizing was these models with that, these kind
of like handcrafted features were there, but one of the areas that they really struggled
to do with was how do you handle, you know, the temporal nature of the data, right?
Okay.
That means it's pretty key.
So a typical part actually has very key characteristics.
You have about three phases.
So there's a phase phase that is sort of the explosive phase.
You literally have like these three phases that are very distinctive to the core, right?
And the properties in any of these three states are very different, right?
But then most of the previous methods were all sort of pretty much like think of them as
a static way of approaching and not really taking advantage of the temporal properties.
So they could only do so well, right?
And people had now started using things like hidden Markov models to try to model those
temporal patterns and those were sort of like working very well, but then hidden Markov
models are pretty, you know, basically algorithms to start dealing with, right?
And so a good segue was, hey, and I started out also like implementing HMMs for this application.
And at that level, you've already gone into the complexity that, you know, you can now
use some of that even deep learning models that these days much easier than, you know,
a full blown hidden Markov model, right?
So you quickly run into the area where you realize that this traditional approach was
not doing the work quite right.
And congestion becomes even much more complex when you start thinking of different patients,
or main patient to patient variability, so the sounds, the cough sounds sound very different
from different patients.
And when they have different conditions, it makes it sound like, you know, very different.
So you quickly run into the issue where you just feel like, no, I need better models
to really capture this.
How far down the path of the traditional models did you go?
Did you try?
Did you have a working HMM that you could later compare to deep learning?
Yeah.
So that was actually one of my very first papers.
I did a whole survey on all of these traditional algorithms that folks have been using.
They had decision trees, you had your SVM, you had the HMM with like, you know, Gaussian
make some model observations.
And then you had like the, you know, the early neural networks I started working on.
So the first one I started being was to use convolutional neural networks.
And they compared very well, they compare like, you know, much better than the HMM, right?
Which was very, very impressive.
And at that time, I was using the convolutional neural net on top of the spectrogram, right?
I was using, yeah, on top of the spectrogram.
So it was being able to learn both the, you know, the temporal and spatial in terms of
the frequency components of the sound and helping you make decisions, like make good inferences
based off on that.
So I started off actually validating that, hey, actually, these deep learning approaches
work much better than the traditional, you know, approaches, those are some of my
anyways, okay, before jumping or into it, okay.
So I'm imagining the early work into CNN's, you, you validated all this, but you were
doing this on desktop computers and then you had to figure out, okay, how do I get this
thing to actually run on the devices?
Exactly, exactly, exactly.
Before we dig into into that, I just remember a question I had from your earlier description
of the hardware.
You mentioned that you were using traditional analog stages to condition the signal.
One of the great things, and you mentioned this about deep learning is that you don't
have to do a lot of feature engineering and often you find that by giving the network,
you know, as much data and not doing as much pre-processing as you might otherwise do,
you can find patterns that haven't traditionally been used, like maybe a cough has like these
really high frequency components that no one really thought about, but that can be predictive.
Did you explore that angle at all?
Yeah, so I did, I did with sort of the first combination, right?
So this was around, I started this week, around 2014, 2015 using the combination, and
so I was using like piano at that time, and I started visualizing the features it was
learning, right?
Of course, some of them were, there were some that looked really interesting, so if you
look at the spectrogram, normally in speech, you have these harmonics, right?
Where you would have these kind of distinct fine lines in the spectrum, but cough is just
a burst of energy, right?
So it's quite over the entire place, right?
It's like the whole place is just full of energy.
And you could see that what the network was actually doing was for the cough.
It was really activated by like a broad range across the spectrum.
For us, like for the speech, it was mostly activated by these sort of lines, right?
And in that space, I thought I was discriminating between cough and speech.
So you could definitely see that it was learning this notion, and was being activated by the
fact that in cough, you have a burst of energy spread across a wide range of frequency,
and it would highlight those.
Given that, why is it still important to do the conditioning?
Oh, so the reason why it's actually important to do the conditioning is because of the sense
that we are using, right?
So like I mentioned, I'm using this piezoelectric transducer, which is, it's not like you
know, your best microphone is actually a good, it's used for like guitar pickups.
So the sense is not great to begin with.
So your signal is actually really bad to start out with.
So the conditioning that we do on there is one to sort of make sure that hey, your signal
is at least clean enough that it's even audible when you hear that, you know, a person
can discern something because without that conditioning, you can even hear the different
events that okay, but yeah, but I think what was really critical is you do have a point
because we could have done more conditioning on there to get a really great signal, right?
But that would have defeated the point.
And so because you could have added more stages, just like really good operational amplifiers,
but we really did the minimal.
So we have like a one stage filter, for instance, right?
A minimum processing so that you can use the rest of the deep learning pipeline to take
advantage of that, right?
So we do sort of really use the benefit of the not having to clean up the signal too much,
except we do do a little cleaning.
Got it, got it.
Yeah, that was the intuition that I was trying to explore.
Yeah.
Awesome.
So for your latest paper, which you presented at NURP set the the black and AI workshop,
which is all about an optimized recurrent unit for ultra low power acoustic event detection.
Tell us about that paper and the key challenges you're trying to solve there.
Yeah.
So that's great.
And I think it follows very well, we kind of like what we've been discussing up on
to now.
So like I mentioned, I started with convolutional neural nets and the comments are great,
right?
We all love them.
They do awesome.
And even these days there is an argument that hey, recurrent neural nets are no longer
necessary, because if you see some of Google's work with on like wave net, you see these
direct solutions are doing great for speech recognition and like speech synthesis.
So why do we care about recurrent net at all?
And the motivation for that was first recurrent net when you're thinking of like really
constrained sort of applications where you don't have a lot of time for you can't admit
a lot of late things, right?
In combination, if you think about it, you literally have to buffer up the entire event
so you can apply the confidence, and you have to apply windows, but recurrent net have
this natural nature where they can process data one time step at a time, right?
So that's really great.
It's great for application because it's just like a digital filter.
You can implement it in such a way that a sample comes in, you process it, the next sample
comes in, you process it, and you have really, really low latency, right?
So that was one of the big promises for starting this, right?
But then once we started, okay, we have this recurrent net.
We can train them and they can do very well on the task.
How do we put them on the device?
Then it's like, wow, we open a whole box of challenges because it's interesting.
And there are a lot of people working on deploying deep learning to the edge.
And you know, you have, you know, really great hardware systems, like the Nvidia drive.
You have like Jetson, which is like this small embedded system board by Nvidia that you can
true, you know, neural nets on there and they run just fine, right?
But when you look at all of these hardware, you are just above our power budget, right?
We are running at either tens of thousands of milliwatts or thousands, and we are literally
looking for something that's within, you know, tens of milliwatts, right?
Something that looked very promising was this library, it's called, like, new tensor or
micro tensor.
It's supposed to be a really lightweight tensor tool like we that can run on certain embedded
boards.
But then when you look at that, it's still above the power range of these really, really
ultra-low power, like, you know, microcontrollers, right?
And so the challenges, can we take the classical models and put them on these microcontrollers?
And the first thing realized that no, if you look at the specifications on the, you
are thinking of, you know, memory of, you're thinking of memory of like less than 32 kilobytes,
you don't have floating point operations, that's like a no, no, right?
So the real challenges was, well, how do we look at the, you know, some of these recurring
neural networks?
I was looking at particularly the gated recurring unit, now can I optimize it all the way down
so that it can run on my target device, right?
So that was the motivation, right?
But when you look at the current systems, they are limited precisely in terms of power,
right?
And if we can come up with a way of optimizing them, such that you can run on this unit,
then that would be great, right?
So once that problem was formulated, I run into the, you know, the main areas in which
I can start optimizing them, yeah.
Okay.
And just to get a sense of the scope of this, you said you're trying to optimize this gated
recurrent unit all the way down, does that mean you're like writing it in assembly and,
you know, and writing it to, you know, to run on this physical device at the instruction
level?
Like how far down are we going here?
Oh, okay.
So I'm writing it to run just at C level, right?
Okay.
So it's just, yeah, see, not assembly, I think with me, but just at C, right?
But that means, you cannot just, you know, grab your TensorFlow model and just run it on
TensorFlow Lite, right?
That means you're going to have to write everything from scratch in a very optimized way.
And so this, how did you approach this process of writing the, of kind of writing it to run
on the device?
Was it, and we, you talked a little bit about challenges, but was it was, was it just
kind of work or were there's particular problems that you ran into that you had to overcome?
Yeah.
So there were, there were actually like three main areas I identified that, you know,
of like optimization that could really make this feasible.
So just sort of stat, and a lot of these had been, you know, already resets and explored,
right?
In isolation, but they had been done.
That's one of the great things about the deep learning community.
There are so many researchers working on incredible things.
And so just taking the time to look at all the work you would see that a lot of people
have worked on, how do you really quantize which, right?
So there was a lot of work there.
And how do you make which run on, run, how do you see, maybe build new networks without
even using a lot of multiplication?
So there were a lot of these, you know, research out there.
And when I really sat down and started like, you know, thinking of implementing, I did
this in steps by the four main areas that I did was, the first was sort of in the gated
recurring unit.
So if you think of the gated recurring units, actually an optimized form of the LSTM unit,
right?
Where, you know, in LSTM, you have a lot of gates.
In the gated recurring unit, you just have two gates.
You have your reset gate and your data gate.
So I was like, wait, if we can optimize LSTM to goo, then we can optimize goo even down,
right?
What happens if we just use one gate, right?
And there's a lot of, there were some, there are some, a few weights out there actually
from 2017, 2017, 2018, there were a few researchers who had just woken on this idea of, hey, what
if we true out one of the gates, particularly the reset gate?
So two main papers stood out, there was, there's one paper from Banger's Group, which said
in speech recognition applications, you can actually omit the reset gate.
And because speech doesn't change so much, it doesn't change too quickly, like you don't
have these sudden discontinuities, it tends to work just as okay as having a group.
And so I took that and sort of tried to apply that to my case of like, okay, maybe I can
get rid of the reset gate.
And when I, in my first simulations, when I did it, I realized that for my application,
it actually tends to work well.
And yes, conditection is different from speech because you do have, you know, sudden changes
when the event happens, but then I validated that you can actually omit the reset gate
and get it to work as much, right?
The next, once I was able to do that, so you cut down one gate and get that expensive
by the way, because it gets means you need weights, you need a lot of weights you need,
you need a lot of computations to do the dot product, like do the weight and the activation
function.
So just by removing one gate, it's like you cut down the network by 33% in terms of memory
and, you know, computation.
Like, so once I got rid of the gates, the next, the main area that everyone thinks of
when you're thinking of, you know, making optimizing neural net is quantization, right?
So I have to do quantization.
But what was popular out there was 8-bit quantization.
I think even today you can use TensorFlow or even PyTorch and you can get 8-bit weights equivalent
of whatever network you train, right?
But I knew 8-bit wasn't going to cut it for my publication, so we have to go all the
way down to just three bits, right?
Three-bit quantization for the network.
So I also did a lot of experiments and simulations to ensure that with three weights, I can still
sort of train the network and have it run, well, and the trick there was to do what people
have done in the past, which is during training, you apply the quantization as kind of like
functions within your computational graph so that you are simulating the quantization process
while you are training.
And the next trick is learning about it and shifting the weights to the right place.
Something else too with the quantization was rather than just quantizing to three-bit
weights, you could quantize them such that they are just, you know, integer exponents of
two or like, you know, the inverse of integer exponents of two.
And if you did it that way, then you don't need multiplications anymore because you can
replace all multiplications with, you know, with base shifts, right?
So to recap the two main areas, one was true, I will show a way one of the gates and then
you know, cut down the network computation and memory by 33% do this kind of exponential
with quantization all the way down to three-bit and that saves you a lot of memory, but also
enables you to just do base shifts and no multiplications, which you can do on the
ultra-loop power microcontroller, right?
And then the other main area of optimization was we don't have, we don't have two team
points units on the microcontroller.
So to get rid of every floating point of operation and replace that with integer operations, right?
So the whole network on the microcontroller has to be implemented in such a way that you
are just using integer operations, right?
So all the activation functions, all the, you know, the linear transformations, the
weak multiplication and the dot product, they all have to be done in such a way that
you're operating within integer, you know, framework, I was using like 16-bit integers and
then you are applying all the necessary collecting so you don't overflow, right?
So those were the main sort of key areas of quantization, the integer arithmetic throughout,
train out the single gate, like, train out the reset gate, and then also using fast activation
because those are ourselves, right?
Using what was that last one?
Fast activations?
Yeah, I have to, like, you know, so in the traditional, you know, recurring unit or
updated recurring unit, you have the sigmoid and a time each and those are expensive on
the microcontroller.
Whenever you have to do an exponential on the microcontroller, if you are thinking all
child do power, they become very painful.
And so what I did was to use soft sign function instead, you can have like, soft sign variance
of the time each and a soft sign and it works just as well, right?
So these are the four main areas I had to, I had to bring together in order to really
pull this off.
One of the things that occurs to me here is a lot of times when we're trying to get networks
to converge, we're doing things like drop out and other things that are like adding noise
which kind of helps with regularization, but your process is inherently adding noise.
So does that change the way you do regularization or eliminate the need to do regularization
when you're trying to train the network?
Yeah, so I don't do any additional regularization apart from these methods that I'm talking
about.
And almost every one of them you can actually think of as a regularization and you see
that effect.
So if I train on a really big network, it actually trains, you are able to convey to
about the same or even it's slightly better than what you would with like a full precision
network, right, but then when you go like really when you are training a very, very small
network, the full precision will, you know, do better, but yes, you do see the regularization
effect of these and you don't need to do any additional external regularization.
I think one thing also that I have to point out is you see the whole simulation, the quantization
but also the fixed point in the gyrismatic, it pretty much means you are sort of clipping
how high the outputs of certain nodes can go, right?
So nothing can go above the highest number in say 16 bit into the presentation.
So it's almost like you're doing with clipping, right?
You're doing all of these things that you traditionally do with regularization.
In fact, really strict regularization.
So it ends up training very well and then you're able to get a network that function.
So you made a comment about how for large networks, it works as well or better than,
than non, you know, networks where you're not doing these four things.
How broadly does that generalize, is that, you know, just for this specific problem?
Or, I mean, we always care about, you know, compute and usually care about power.
Like could you just take this and apply it to something totally, you know, a totally
different kind of problem?
And do you think it would work or there are specific things about your problem that
allows you to make these compromises?
So actually in my paper, in the work that I presented in the paper, I actually wrote
a paper on this that would be coming out for you become, like maybe later this year.
What we realized was we tried on two additional like tasks, right?
One was recognizing spoken digits, right?
And you see that it still waits, right?
In like, when you're trying to Google has this speech command dataset, it pretty much has
like one second audio recording of sounds like on or, and you have 20,000 flat examples,
right?
And the way it's just as well, where you begin to see it hurting is when you look at the
test as we consider this was called like a band sounds where you have really, really long
recordings.
You have recordings that are about four seconds long, right?
And sequences that are about 100 plus, you know, instances that you begin to see it hurting.
I think one of the reason why it begins hurting is because when you don't have the reset
gate, you are pretty much now like you're limiting the long-term memory of the network, right?
Like the very advantage of the group and then LSTM, like your handicrafting, the network
is that because it can't really remember for too long, right?
So I think these optimizations make it very suitable for applications like, you know,
keywords, potten, or where you are, literally detection sounds that are very short, you
know, or not very short, but relatively short.
So, you know, anything one second, two second and below, then it becomes really promising.
And then once you are looking at really long sequences, like you would in speech recognition,
then it would not be ideal, right?
And so you mentioned two additional tasks was one the digits and the other was the speech
commands or were those one?
Yeah, those were one the speech commands has the spoken digits.
The test was this a band sounds.
If the data says it's available online and they have, it's actually a really difficult
task.
You have like recordings of environments, you have things like child playing, car honking,
and you know, you're supposed to identify these classes.
You have about 20 classes or 10 classes, 10 to 20 classes, one of those.
And sometimes it's really even hard for a person to discriminate between them because
you know, the sounds are long and then the context is also very broad, right?
So those, that was a very difficult task for our model.
So we're performing maybe 10 to 15% ways than using a full precision, like, you know,
green network.
Okay.
What was that data set called again?
Abans sounds data set.
So I think if I remember correctly, it's from, yeah, they have two.
There's the Abans sound 8K and then like a more Abans sound like with even longer recordings
and we have a paper out there on it.
I think it's a data set in taxonomy for Abans sound research was published in an ACM conference
on multimedia.
So it's a data set that has been out there since 2015.
I'm sorry.
Yeah.
All right.
So you've developed this GRU kind of all the way down.
You have demonstrated that it works for your task and reasonably well for other tasks.
Are you done then or is there more work that you had to do here?
Yeah.
So I think right now for, and I actually had deployed it to the device and have it like,
you know, run on examples in the data set and get like the decent results.
I think one key area to was late, right?
You need this to not just fit, but be fast enough.
And that also we were meeting the right spec actually where I'm going about 60 to 70 times
faster than if you were to just manually put a GRU onto any of these devices.
And so while they all work and everything is like great, you've been able to embed
the model.
The entire pipeline that I talked about, right, also needs to be in place, right?
So right now, it means, you know, our our GRU, our optimized recovery unit can, when
you train it, they can't really detect these sounds.
But then once you put it, once you start thinking, you know, okay, I have a whole streaming
input, right?
How do I ensure that I'm telling off my microprocessor, like at the right time, I'm waking up quickly
enough so that I don't miss the events.
And then my, you know, recurring neural network is also like, it's also processing the incoming
sequence.
And and finally also, how do I, so you get some outputs from your recovery net, right?
But how do you smoothen over those posterior probabilities and actually record the event
at what time?
So those are that sort of additional work, that's what I've been working on, sort of completing
that whole pipeline, right?
Because I don't see the, the RNA is one block in that whole pipeline and you want to get
the whole pipeline working, so this can be used in real time, right?
So that's kind of like the work that I'm finishing on right now.
Nice.
And you're finishing up your PhD, what's next for for you in this project?
Yeah.
I'm very excited, I'm hopefully going to be defending in a month.
Oh wow.
And yeah, so very exciting things.
But actually, my advice and I have found that a company called Clewis to commercialize
these, this Asma monitoring device that I've been talking about, this world would device
for monitoring the lungs, right?
And the company is called Clewis and we are very excited about it.
We just, I was just awarded an SBIR grant to sort of see that too.
So I think for the next year, that's what I'll be, that's what I'll be fully dedicated
to trying to bring the technology out of the lab and into the hospitals to actually use
in patients on patients.
Nice, nice.
And so I imagine that this will have to go through the, kind of the FDA approvals, is this
subject to like clinical trials and all of those kinds of things?
Yes.
So, eventually, it's going to go to FDA.
We've actually been sort of prepping on the right materials and sort of lining up the
right studies we have to do.
I have done some preliminary studies at the hospital on patients' population of even
up to 30, actually testing on patients, but we have to do like a really full-blown study.
But for the next year, we are hoping to work with some medical companies who are already,
you know, doing clinical trials for their respiratory therapeutics, and they need data, they need
data on, you know, have these patients responding to particular drugs, right?
And often, the available data is just subjective reports from patients, oh, I think these
recalls COVID-19, but if they could have something that's more objective, huh?
They were within X, RS throughout this week, and that reduced by 10% the next week, or
their cough went down by this, they'll be really, really, you know, actionable for them
and really valuable to them.
So we are talking with some pharmaceuticals about, you know, the need and positioning the
device in such a way that it can fulfill that need.
Awesome.
And will you also be getting into physical manufacturer of the devices themselves?
Yes.
So, for some of the studies that I did, I had to do like batch sort of manufacturing of
these processes of these devices, because, you know, you're running a small study where
you have maybe 50 subjects, you still have to have a lot of, you know, devices, and you
have to have like packaging down how they're going to arrive at the hospital, how do you
get the information in and out, and so I have had to do that, and I anticipate I'm going
to have to do much more of that, like in this year, once I finished school.
Wow.
So, yeah.
It's exciting.
It sounds like a really exciting project, and you will certainly have your hands full
over the coming months.
I really appreciate you taking the time to share it with us.
Oh, thank you.
Well, this was fun.
It's taking a while.
Fantastic.
Thank you.
All right, everyone, that's our show for today.
For more information on justice or any of the topics covered in this show, visit twimlai.com
slash talks slash 2 3 0.
For more information on our Black and AI series, visit twimlai.com slash Black and AI 19.
As always, thanks so much for listening, and catch you next time.