Welcome to the Twimal AI Podcast.
I'm your host, Sam Charrington.
Alright everyone, I am on the line with David Duveno, David is an assistant professor
at the University of Toronto.
David, welcome back to the Twimal AI Podcast, thank you Sam, it's nice to be back.
It is great to catch up with you, I'm really looking forward to this.
You have been super busy since the last time we spoke, which was back in January of 2018.
So just about two years ago, or at least that's when we published the show, we might have
actually caught up a little bit before then, but that show was on composing graphical
models with neural networks and you've been quite prolific since then and we will hopefully
get a chance to talk about a bunch of what you've been up to.
Our fur folks back to that show for your full background and how you got started in machine
learning, but why don't we start out by having you share a little bit about your current
research interests.
So yeah, obviously one big thing that's happened since two years ago is that we started
working on differential equations a lot.
And we had the first paper, you know, at the neural ODE's paper and we've just actually
released it.
And I'll just interrupt you to say that was a huge paper last year.
Yeah, it was, yeah, it was a, this was Neurf's 2018 where that paper was presented and
you've been on my list.
We actually did try to catch up around that time, but you were, you were super busy and
we'll talk about it this time.
Okay, great, great, great.
There's a lot of, I think, pretty interesting follow ups.
I'm trying to not let that take over all the research that happens here, or at least
among my students, but we just published a follow up which I'm really happy about where
we figured out how to train stochastic differential equations in a scalable way.
And that was actually really surprising that it hadn't been worked up before.
It was one of these things where I thought, oh, you know, when we looked at ordinary differential
equations, the basic math for how to efficiently do backprop through them was already no one
in the numeric community.
So I assumed that, you know, SDEs have been around almost as long and it would have been
worked out.
But actually, it hadn't.
And there was sort of a few, there was things called like backwards SDEs and a few other
approaches for trying to build the same sorts of algorithms for doing a grading based training
of SDEs.
But none of them were scalable.
And I think it's one of these things where the differential equations community typically
hasn't been focused on computational efficiency.
So the idea is that, you know, showing that there exists these dynamics is, that had
been worked out with the dynamics where, but how to do these things efficiently hadn't
been.
So I teamed up with a probableist here at University Toronto, Leonard Wong, an amazing
undergrad who's now a Google Brain resident, Joy Chen Lee.
And we worked out all the details and, you know, they're the ones who really did the mathematical
heavily lifting.
And I just sort of convinced them that there had to exist a simple algorithm or rather
an efficient algorithm because for everything else that people have looked at, there's always
one.
Backpropagation always has the same asymptotic time complexity as the forward pass.
And this was one area where people sort of thought, oh, maybe it's not the case that there
is such a efficient reverse algorithm and we eventually worked out what it was.
So I'm really happy about that.
I feel like we're just diving into the neural ODE stuff and we'll circle back to maybe
how all of the different things your lab works on kind of connect together.
But for the neural ODE stuff, let's just start from the beginning.
I am sure there are folks that are listening that don't really understand what a differential
equation is.
So.
Yeah.
And the only thing is that I actually never learned these in undergrad.
Like I never took one of these courses on ODE's.
Oh, really?
Yeah.
I just kind of picked it up, you know, from talking to people who knew about them and
reading about them.
It's almost good.
So if you take a course on ODE's, at least the ones that I've looked at, most of the material
is based around solving them exactly for special cases.
So if you have like linear ODE or some sort of structure in a second order ODE, there
is this special case is where the answer is like sign or cosine or X or something like
that.
And most of I think most often, at least when I encountered them in undergrad, it was
the context that were was provided was typically like physical systems, like physics or, you
know, the relationships between things in the physical world or, you know, often governed
by these differential equations.
Yeah.
That's where they typically come from.
And that's actually another big difference is that the numeric community is used to looking
at differential equations that are given by nature.
And they have to work out how am I going to solve these equations?
I can't choose which ones I want to solve.
I have to see all the ones that are there.
And one thing I want to kind of talk about a bit later is that when we use neural networks
to specify these differential equations, it's actually a pretty different game because
we think that there's many different sets of dynamics that will encode the same or
that will roughly solve the problem.
So we can maybe try to choose dynamics that are easy to solve that give almost the same
answer as like the very best dynamics that might be really hard to solve.
How was frame out the problem that you're trying to solve with this line of work?
Is it solving a differential equation?
Like you have a given differential equation and you're trying to, what exactly are you
trying to do?
Sure.
So that's a great question because there is some work on trying to use neural networks
to solve differential equations.
And we're not really doing that.
Although I do want to mention that one place where I did learn a lot about these was actually
when I visited Philip Henning, who's an amazing researcher at the Max Planck Institute.
When I was a PhD student, I did an internship with him in Germany for one summer and we worked
on a project where we were trying to, well, where he had worked out this correspondence
between the standard ODE solvers called like Runga Kuda methods and probabilistic models
that like, well, the ocean processes that would extrapolate what these functions would
do in the future given observations about their gradients in the present.
So basically people had come up with Runga Kuda algorithms by asking how could we extrapolate
in such a way that all these errors cancel out and then he realized that actually you
can drive these automatically by just putting a Gaussian process prior on these functions.
And then if you ask what the predictive posterior looks like, it actually gives you these
Runga Kuda algorithms for free.
Anyway, but the point is that all this work on neural adhesives is not actually focused
on building better solvers.
We're saying let's inherit all these amazing solvers that the numeric community has built
and just try to repurpose them to train even bigger models than people normally have before.
And from a technical point of view, all the tricks in the neural adhes paper were already
existed in the numeric literature, we just put them all together in one place.
And so when you say train even bigger models, meaning you're trying to come up with algorithms
that are either alternatives to gradient descent or enhancements to gradient descent
that facilitate converging on different weights for neural networks that the networks themselves
are solving arbitrary problems that don't necessarily have to do with differential
equations.
Oh, that's a great question.
So what I mean specifically is let's find efficient ways to compute gradients of predictive
loss or some sort of training lots with respect to all the parameters of some differential equations.
And then use standard training algorithms like Adam or whatever in the standard ways on
the standard losses.
And so when we think of a gradient, the way that that's typically described is it's a slope
which is a differential equation in a sense.
And so you're applying these methods to identify these gradients more quickly.
Well, yeah.
So it's pretty good for me to be specifying because almost every question you ask about
could we use ODE's to compute gradients or gradients to solve ODE's like the answer is
always yes.
So there's a lot of different ways that these tools combine and different people are working
on different aspects of the problem.
So to be precise, we're saying people have often like parameterized differential equations
based on some few parameters and like simple functions to maybe specify like, you know,
how planets evolve or how chemical concentrations change.
And then they call ODE solvers to run these forward and find what the trajectories of these
systems look like.
And sometimes they want to fit those systems to data, which requires computing the gradient
of the training loss like the mismatch between the predictions of your model and the data
back through these ODE solutions to the parameters that specify them.
So those were the in the neural ODE paper, we basically imported all the tricks from
the numerical community into one algorithm and said, oh, this is a scalable way to compute
gradients where we can use the like fanciest ODE solvers that also the numeric community
developed.
So it was really, it was really kind of just showcasing a bunch of things that the numeric
community knew and putting them all together in such a way that it would scale to very
large systems.
Got it.
And so what I heard you just say was that you kind of people have in the numeric community
have, you know, long studied, you know, how to kind of do the, you know, forward projection
of differential equations to trajectories of physical things.
And then they want to do kind of the backwards reconciliation so that they can determine how
accurate their predictions are.
And there were a bunch of different techniques or are a bunch of different techniques for
doing that.
And what's the relationship between, you know, all of that and neural networks?
Did you then pull those into like a deep learning or neural network framework or doing this
backward gradient calculation?
Yeah.
So there's a few different ways we can use these tools.
And one of them is to fit these physical systems that people have been doing.
But what was I think most exciting to the whole deep learning community was to say, oh,
there's also a potential that this sort of network, this sort of ODE network could replace
some of the backbone of the neural networks that we used to train today.
So in particular, residual networks is like the standard way you build a very deep network.
And it's just adding together the contributions of a whole bunch of small neural network
layers.
And so the connection that we talked about in the neural ODE paper, which had been made
before, was, oh, well, if you ask, if you look at how one of these ODE solvers solves
or like confused one of these long trajectories, it also adds up many different calls to these
smaller functions, the only thing that we really did knew was to sort of take this really
seriously and say, OK, let's actually then use ODE solvers to solve or to compute the
answer of our neural network.
And then it can decide, you know, how many function evaluations to make and where.
And yeah, so that was the new part.
And so this has a few advantages.
It's kind of a different way of formulating the problem, instead of saying, here's the
algorithm for computing my residual network, which is like, you know, train together 100
times.
We say, here's the dynamics of this trajectory, ODE solver, it's your job to figure out how
many times and we need to evaluate this function and where to tell me what the exact or to approximate
what the exact trajectory would be.
So the cool thing is that if the problem is easy, it might only need a few calls to the
function and if it's hard, it might need a lot.
But this is something that's sort of being determined adaptively on the fly, instead
of at training time, where normally right now people have to just sort of try different
steps.
They say, oh, I tried into their neural network with, you know, 10 layers.
It didn't do as good as one with 20.
I, you know, it started doing better and better than where I added, but then everything
was too expensive.
So I had to cap it.
The hope is that we can now say, oh, let's at training time, let the, like, just tell
our optimizer, here's my tradeoff between accuracy and speed.
It's up to you to figure out how to, like, trade these things off.
So that was something we sort of said you might be able to do, or rather this idea of at
training time, trading off accuracy and speed is something that we, you know, thought we
could do, but we didn't really work out how to do it.
And, but this is one of the papers that it was up late last night working on for somebody
to ICML was me and my, since then, me and my student, Jesse Pettincourt also working with
an undergrad, Jacob Kelly and my friend at Google, Matt Johnson, we were saying, oh, well,
maybe we can add some sort of term, some sort of regularizing term to the loss that makes
the dynamics easy to solve.
And so we got that to work.
And now we can see, oh, there's this tradeoff that we can explore between having, having
training a ODE network that exactly minimizes our training loss versus one that is cheap
to solve and sort of requires fewer layers.
And so now, you know, if depending on your compute budget, you can just move along this
pre-do front and trade these things off however you want.
Nice.
And that was the neural networks with, no, that's not the neural networks with cheap,
this is unpublished stuff.
This is an unpublished paper that was just submitted February 7th in the, we hours
of the morning for the upcoming ICML conference.
Exactly.
It doesn't get any harder off the press than that, yeah.
Nice.
And is it already up on archive or?
No, it's not an archive.
Although Jesse gave a talk about it at the program transformation workshop at NRIPS, although
it wasn't working at that point, we were just sort of saying, here's the math that we're
going to try to implement.
And so is this related to the cheap differential operator's paper?
Sort of.
So the cheap differential operator's paper, again, that was actually Ricky's idea.
He just sort of came to me and said, hey, I think we can actually constrain the dynamics
of our neural networks such that these quantities that we need to compute are cheap.
So the motivation from that was there was a follow up to the neural ODE's paper called
Fjord.
Or the name of the method was Fjord, and it basically said, we can build normalizing
flows out of a continuous time using ordinary differential equations.
So normalizing flows are a family of density estimators, which just means, you know, a generic
way to model any data in an unsupervised way that work by taking a simple density like
a Gaussian and somehow warping it into some non-Gaussian complicated parametric density.
And so one of the nice follow-ups from the neural ODE's stuff, we're saying, oh, it turns
out that if you think of this transformation happening continuously, then the math that
you need to compute the change in density is a little bit nicer.
So it goes from having to compute the determinant of the Jacobian of the dynamics to just the
trace of the Jacobian of the dynamics, and that's actually a lot easier to approximate.
So it's still expensive, though, and it's still kind of a downside of this method.
So Ricky worked out that actually if we constrain the architecture of these dynamics networks,
we can give them exact trace, we can compute their traces exactly.
And this is, I kind of like it, so I want to talk about engineering neural network architectures.
So there's a lot of work that has been totally foundational to the field where people sort
of do trial and error and they say, oh, what if I add more layers here?
Or if I change the non-linearities of my network, what if I add noise here or there?
And sometimes these are well-motivated theoretically, sometimes or not, sometimes it's just sort
of the trial and error that we need to get any technology to work.
Right.
I think in the first year of my podcast, there was this period where many of my conversations
were asking, okay, how is this done?
How are people doing?
And the answer that I finally came to understand was that it was just trial and error, and
graduate student descent was the term thrown around, and a lot of the great models that
we use to solve problems then and now, like came out of this just iterative exploratory
process.
Yeah.
And there's nothing wrong with that.
But it's more satisfying when we can say, oh, I want to have a network that's going
to learn functions with this property.
Therefore, I know that I need that my network has this architecture or that, or saying,
if it has architecture, it'll definitely be able to learn functions that enforce this
property, like maybe some sort of invariance.
So there was some really nice work on this called deep sets, which said, what if I want
to have a network that takes in a set of things and gives me an answer that doesn't depend
on the order of the things in that set, because that's sort of what makes it a set is that
the order shouldn't matter.
But on a computer, you do have to give things in a particular order.
So sometimes people just budget and they randomize the order, but these guys worked out the
math to say, oh, here's the family of architectures that will always be invariant to the order
of things in a set.
So I really liked that work.
And then I liked Ricky's idea because it was the same sort of thing saying, okay, well,
we know we want our networks to have this property.
Here is the general way.
Here's the general trade-off where we can say we have to make this sacrifice, but then
we will achieve this nice property.
And we can actually interpolate between networks that are, let's say, very restricted, but
we give you exact traces or ones that are less restricted, but then you have to approximate
the trace.
And the trace corresponds only to the cost of determining the weight source, the trace,
more fundamental or have broader implications.
Yeah, which we had a way forward, but when I say trace, I mean, the sum of the diagonal
terms in the Jacobian of these networks, and the Jacobian is just the matrix that says,
what is the gradient of all the outputs of the network with respect to all of its inputs?
Yeah.
So it's just one quantity that we sometimes need to evaluate, but it's actually quite expensive
to evaluate it exactly from first standard neural networks.
So you're able to, by fixing the network architecture, fixing the trace to be easier to compute,
does, is characterizing the trace in that way?
Is it just an issue of computational complexity, or does the trace have other implications
on the network or its performance or its characteristics?
It's an issue of computational complexity.
Yeah, that's a great question.
So I think one very valid question that people asked is basically saying, okay, how does
the trade-off look empirically like where along this curve should I go?
What does this restriction actually mean in practice?
And in this initial paper, all we basically did was lay out the trick and show that it
worked in a bunch of settings.
But I think that's a great question.
We know that this restriction hurts the expressive capacity of these networks, but we haven't
characterized them exactly what way.
So that's a great question, and I wish I knew the answer.
All right, cool.
And then another paper that you presented at or that your team worked on at this last
nerve was the latent ODEs for a regularly sampled time series, how does that one tie into this
body of work?
Well, that one was kind of satisfying because the original motivation for looking at ODEs
in the first place was Yulia, who's the first author of that paper and the, well, second
but co-first author of the neural ODE's paper was working on some medical applications
where we had some gene assays of people's tumors that were evaluated at like a week apart
and then a month apart and then maybe another week apart and then a year apart.
And it's not quite clear how to fit that sort of data into a standard recurrent neural
network or something like that.
So that made us look at these continuous time models in the first place.
But then we wrote the neural ODEs paper, which didn't, it just had proof of concept.
It just said, oh, here's something you can do, we look, we explore it on toy data.
So I think academics, including myself, have a bad habit of taking an applied problem,
saying, oh, if we did solve this theoretical thing, we could tackle this applied problem,
write a paper about solving the theoretical thing and never go back to the problem.
So we still haven't applied it to the original data set that Yulia was looking at, but
we did apply it in that paper to a standard medical records data set where it's like people
in the intensive care unit and there's also different measurements being made of them
from different people at different times, like what is their temperature or their blood
pressure or whatever, and being able to combine this all into one model is something that's
not very natural for the discrete time models we normally use.
So we sort of showcase that, yeah, once you have continuous time, here's a set of architectures
you can explore in the advantages and yeah, it worked, it was satisfying paper to write.
What is the role that this continuous time versus these regularly sample time series played
in the original paper, was it a big motivator or just a side note, given this machinery,
we can probably tackle this continuous time problem differently.
Yeah, so it was the original thing that maybe started to revisit these models,
but then in the paper it ended up being secondary.
I think in most people's eyes who are just interested in supervised learning,
right, like the bread and butter of the machine learning community is like I want to train a
giant classifier or something, and so we put that front and center because we knew that would
be a lot of broader interest, but the thing is that until we make noise faster or at least
as fast as standard architectures, I don't think people are going to, I don't think people should
use them, and so that's why that motivated the work with Jesse on regularizing them,
regularizing them to be fast.
We're still at the proof of concept stage there, we just got to working in some standard
endless sort of things, but right now I am really excited about the time series setting
for two reasons, so one is that it's really, right now, one of the main areas where you definitely
do need a continuous time model, or rather you definitely need differential equations, if you
start talking about continuous time, you're basically already said you're using differential
equations, like I don't want to go and shoehorn differential equations in where they don't
actually make sense empirically or practically just because it's like a cool thing, and so the other
thing is that I think the...
What is it about continuous time models or problems that necessitates differential equations?
Oh, well you need to be able to say how the system changes for any arbitrarily small amount of time,
and so once you've done that, the only way to do that is to basically describe the derivatives
of the state. Like maybe you don't like discrete time, the relationship is between something
happening at time n and something happening at time n plus one, whereas with continuous time,
you need a continuous function to relate things happening at different times, and if that's the case,
you hope that it's differentiable.
Yeah, or rather, if it is a continuous function that says how the thing changes, then that meets the
definition of a differential equation as far as like my turn. Like maybe there could be some...
Yeah, I got it.
But, and the funny thing is that I think the business community and like the medical community haven't,
I think kind of hilariously underserved by the machine learning community in the sense that almost
all the data sets that they... Like when I talk to the sponsors of vector or people at like
big companies, they say, okay, so my data looks like I have a bunch of interactions with my
customer that happen over years, and they're irregularly sampled and they're different types of
observations, and I want to be able to predict... I'm going to be able to model this data and deal
with the fact that it's like all missing... or almost all missing almost all the time.
How do I do this? And I say, well, I mean, I guess you could kind of shoehorn it into an R&N maybe,
like vending data. There's some nice work on deep common filters by David Santag and some other
people at NYU and MIT that said, okay, if you move things to discrete time, here's how to deal with
missing data. But it's really just like the bread and butter of like most of industry doesn't,
like their data sets just don't fit with what's coming out of most machine learning labs,
who are more focused on things like video or audio or text, where you really can't say that
there's an observation at every time step. Well, a lot of times don't we just throw away the
sequential nature of the problem and just treat each individual sample as, you know, unrelated
training data drawn from a distribution? Oh, yeah, that's one of the ways that you can force the
data to match your model. And I guess I'll just see, you know... But the point being that you,
yeah, if actually there's some sequence there, you're throwing away information. And what this
is doing is proposing a way to take advantage of that information yet still be tractable. Yeah,
exactly. We want to meet the data where it lives. I think in the future, like statisticians
should take some sort of Hippocratic oath where they swear not to just like destroy data.
I mean, I mean, you know, a lot of data is not particularly valuable, but the point is I see
oftentimes, including, you know, in my own work, if we don't have the tools, then you just say,
okay, well, we have to throw away a bunch of data and we're already crippling our ability to make
good predictions when you do that step. So that's kind of how I view, like maybe not just my recent
research, but how the field moves in general is how do we get closer and closer to the raw sensors
and put more and more of the modeling problem into the hands of one giant model that's jointly
looking at everything instead of a sequence of people who are each looking at their little piece
and throwing away what they think isn't necessary. So we've talked about the cheap differential
operator's paper. We've talked about the irregularly sample time series paper. There's a paper
residual flows for invertible generative modeling. Is that the residual flows paper that we talked
about or is that a different residual flows paper? Yes, that's confusing. So that's a different
residual flows paper. And it's kind of funny because so we had this follow up to the neural
ods paper called fjord, which was the continuous time version. And the cool thing about that was
that it let you use totally unrestricted neural network architectures. So I was talking before
about how sometimes you can restrict the architecture to allow you to have some nice property. So
that's what the normalizing flows community did from about 2015 to 2019. There's like real NDP,
slow, all these big models where they said, oh, if we restrict our architecture, we can compute the
change in density cheaply. But then it's kind of hard to figure out how to make these restrictions
without requiring a whole bunch of layers. And these models end up being very deep and
very expensive train. And so we said, oh, if you go to continuous time, you can just use any
network architecture. And it's fine. But then a couple years ago, Yorne Jacobson and Jens
Bareman came to the vector institute. And we're thinking about the same problems. And they said,
okay, well, fjord is great. But you know, people don't like to have an odsolver inside of their
model. And I think that's the reason of all thing to not want. Because now you have to fiddle,
you have to worry about some numeric issues. You have to choose an error tolerance.
There are similar issues with like floating point, but not as bad. Anyway, and they worked out,
they said, okay, well, what if we use the same math, but for discrete time, could we come up with
some version of fjord that actually used standard neural network architectures and fixed
number of layers and the sort of standard way of setting things up that we that everyone's comfortable
with, but inherited some of the nice mathematical properties. And then they did work it out and
found and basically worked out over the course of these two papers. Another way to get an unbiased
estimate of the change in density, but for finite time discrete flows. So it's kind of funny
because it's like this detour into continuous time led to a better discrete time model.
And that's the invertible generative modeling paper. Yeah, well, there's two. One of them,
it was called the newer one was called residual flows. And then the first one was called invertible
resonance. And maybe we were polluting the the namespace with all these like minor variations.
I mean, Miss, that what is the review the invertible characteristic for me?
Oh, well, so one thing. What is that saying?
Yeah, so what that means is that if I have two different possible inputs to my network,
they won't ever map to the same output. So if you want to use the change of variables formula,
you need to make sure that you never take the original density and somehow like
tear it or squish it into a point. All of these things cause sort of infinities in the in the
likelihood. It makes me think of like a some kind of hash relationship. Is there anything interesting
there? Yeah, maybe you could say we want to avoid we want to write a hash function that avoids
collisions. I mean, the thing is we don't necessarily want to scramble our density.
But yeah, we definitely do want to control when we lose information in these networks.
Because if we ever lose this right information, then we can't use this this change of variable
formula. And are you also saying that networks that are thus characterized if given a prediction,
you can go back to the original inputs? Is it that invertible? Yeah, yeah. So it's the same,
when we say an invertible function, it's the same like in one dimensional, like I say, for
instance, f of x equals x. Okay, that's a silly example. Okay, f of x equals three times x square
root and square, for example. Yeah, so square is not invertible. Well, that's not square
invertible because of the signs. Right, right. But okay, square root is invertible on the positive
reals square is not invertible because you can square the positive number or the negative number
and get the same answer. Right, right. It's a little bit getting into the weeds, but basically
the residual networks mean that we can use any architecture we want to train normalizing flows.
And this is in contrast to the previous methods like glow and real MVP that had to restrict the
architecture. And so the remaining of the four papers that you had at NURBS is efficient graph
generation with graph for current attention networks. Yeah. Is that also related to this ODE thread
or is that off on its own? No, and that was really, you know, one of the papers that,
well, it was driven mainly by the first author, Renji Lau, who's amazing. And there's been a sort of
race once people said, oh, you know, we could build generative models over graphs to try to make
them scale. And again, it's related to this question of how do we enforce some invariance? So
people are always trying to say, well, the funny thing about a graph is that the order of the
nodes doesn't matter. And this is sort of the central, this makes a lot of things hard because
if we like graph isomorphism is a standard sort of known to be harder than polynomial time. Oh,
I think it might have just been recently shown to be in some sort of like quasi polynomial time.
Anyway, it was thought to be hard for a long time. I forget the exact complexity classes in
which is given to graphs like a list of nodes and edges determined whether the same graph that's
that's not trivial. So we want to make sure that our models of graphs also don't care about the
ordering. And so we were building up some work recently that said, oh, well, there was a lot of progress
being made sort of by just ignoring the problem to some extent and saying, well, let's just choose
unordering. And as long as we can assign high likelihood to like one of the many orderings that
matches the data, that's probably good enough. And so people like Will Hamilton now at McGill was
using recurrent neural networks to gradually iteratively add one node to the graph as we generate
them. And he was sort of using recurrent networks both at each node addition. And then
within each iteration of node addition, he went over the existing nodes in the graph and it fixed
order with another RNN. So it was kind of like an RNN within an RNN. So completely breaking this
order and variance like like twice over. And then we did that paper says, oh, we actually only
have to bring it once. We have to choose an order. If we use graph neural networks, the great
thing about graph neural networks is that their answer doesn't depend on the order of the nodes in
the graph. Those were the papers that you had at Nureps more broadly. This neural ODE thing is
just kind of one of many things that you're focused on in your lab. I've got a list of those here.
Automatic chemical design using generative models. That is sounds more applied than anything that
we've talked about thus far. Yeah, maybe that's a little old. I mean, that was stuff that I did mostly
in my postdoc at Harvard. Oh, really? Working with the alumnus for music, who he's really
taking the mantle on that one. And now he actually moved to Toronto. Yeah. Well, maybe I should just
abandon this list and let you pop it up a level and tell us what are some of the other cool things
you're excited about? Yeah. Where did you publish on everything you were excited about at Nureps?
Oh, no, no. Yeah, still got. So we got lots of stuff. And the pipeline lots of stuff I still
don't even understand well enough to publish on. But one thing I'm kind of starting to appreciate
now as an academic in my like fourth year of being a professor is that once you're known for one
thing, the incentive to just double down on that one thing are enormous. And it's kind of you know,
like when a band like releases an album, but it has a different sound than the old one, everyone's
like, well, wait, I thought you were going to talk about that other line of work. But I'm really
trying to resist the incentives to pigeonhole myself just because in the really long run, you know,
things change. We have to keep it up in mind. So the general area that I've been excited about
for a few years, but it's really hard to make progress on is let's say learning to search.
So I just thought a grad topic course on this last term. As a way, grad topic courses are a great
way to get a feel for an area and several other recent papers and get some students to start projects.
And it totally worked out. So actually, and a lot of people at DeepMind have been working on
and are publishing similar ideas along this theme. It sounds like a kind of mash up between
meta learning and neural architecture search. Is that kind of the direction? Yeah, maybe those
are related things. I mean, the basic idea is that we have algorithms like Monte Carlo
research that now we're starting to understand how to embed in other hard machine learning problems
in particular inference and planning. So the idea is that most of what reinforcement learning has
done or meta learning just says, oh, yeah, I'll just sort of brute sort brute force try to learn
a policy that does the right thing in every situation. It has a giant lookup table of when you're
in this situation, you should take this action. And that works if you can train the policy, but it's
really expensive and it requires it puts a lot of strain on this one neural network, this policy.
And, you know, I think most people agree that what humans do is they have this hybrid approach
where they say, well, I know roughly what to do, but whenever I realize I'm in a tough or novel
situation, I'm going to stop and plan and I'm going to think imagine a few steps ahead.
What would happen if I did this, what would happen if I do that and then evaluate what I like
that outcome. And so doing a little bit of search on the day when you need to make a decision in
your mind takes a lot of pressure off the policy and makes you a much more powerful agent without
having to in your head prepare for every possible contingency ahead of time. And so like nothing
I'm saying is like new or groundbreaking. I'm just saying that now we finally have the tools
to build such systems. And there's been a lot of work coming out of deep mind in this way.
One paper that I feel like is waiting to be written is about intrinsic motivation or curiosity.
So there's all these papers talking about, oh, you know, how is it that people somehow know not
to not just pursue their goal directly, but also try to learn and do some exploration or stuff.
Maybe something of something evolution, something something like the value of randomness.
And it kind of so I think these papers are making sensible technical suggestions, but the
philosophical sort of speculation about why is this curiosity necessary and making it sound
like some serious thing bugs me because if you just say I am going to have to solve a task,
but I don't know exactly what it is yet or I don't know exactly what the dynamics of my environment
are, then the optimal plan will include doing some exploration, some learning, practicing skills.
So in particular, if we formalize this as a Palm D.P. partially observable Markov decision
process, this is like the bread and butter of reinforcement learning since like the 70s.
We can't solve these because it's too expensive, but if we could, all these behaviors would
emerge automatically. And it's not clear to me how much other people agree with me about this,
because for a long time I thought I was the only one who thought this. But then when I started
to talk to some other, and I thought that probably because the motivations of these curiosity papers
didn't seem to understand this point. But then when I talk to some of the serious RL people that I
know, they're like, oh yeah, of course, yes, that's I totally agree. So you know, it's that's
reassuring. It's also kind of sad because you want to be the one guy with the idea that no one
else realizes, right? So yeah, so right now we can't scale up these amortized planning algorithms
to do effective exploration in really tricky domains. Like what you'd like is if you put your agent
in a gym and you said, you know, you're going to have to play a game tomorrow. I'm not going to
tell you what it would, you know, learn to dribble a basketball or like, you know, pick up the soccer
ball and learn to kick it or, you know, just invent games that it might have to play and then
invent practice drills for itself to learn the dynamics of how it could, how it should play them.
And I think that's there's no remaining foundational problems there, but there's just a lot of
engineering problems for which we have now promising tools to tackle those.
Yeah, as a researcher, how do you approach engineering problems? And do you approach them differently
than an engineer might or, you know, is it about framing them?
Yeah, that's a great question. I mean, I would say the one of the blessings in the
curse of this job that really feels like a blessing most of the time is that I don't spend a lot
of time engineering. And I really like getting my hands dirty and coating up to the point of a
proof of concept, but it is a bit of a slog to get these things to work. And my students are
amazing at that. It's been said of my student, Will Graftwell, that he can get a potato to get
state of the arts on C-Far 100 if he has to. I mean, and of course, you don't want the engineering
skill to be the determiner of which method ends up looking best in your paper. You know, we take
that seriously. I'm just saying, the students here are really amazing at finding, diagnosing
these problems and getting them to work. It's still really fiddly. I feel like, you know,
we're still in the dark ages of understanding what's happening when we're training or on that
works or building models, even in, yeah. Is that something that you're focused on from our research
perspective? Yeah. So actually, one of the other ICML submissions we published yesterday,
or we didn't publish, we submitted yesterday, was a collaboration with Philip Henning trying
to automate the step size selection during training. And the idea is that we said, oh, well,
right now when we run stochastic gradient descent, we just, we, you know, if we'd have a
momentum or we do atom, we kind of have a little bit of averaging of the previous gradients.
But we actually know how to combine noisy observations of different things in, like,
perfectly well on principle with common filters. And this is just like a simple,
latent variable linear ocean model. And so Phil and his student Lucas were saying, oh, yeah,
and one cool thing that we can do now that we couldn't do, at least for modern autodip systems,
is get cheap hash and vector products and get them for every example in a mini batch.
Anyway, I'm getting into the weeds here, but the point is we can look at all the statistics of
the gradients within a mini batch that we're observing, put that in a really cheap and scalable model.
And now when we're trying to choose which direction to go and how far to go, we have a lot more
information available than normal. So our step size can trade off. You can say, okay, well,
I know I'm this certain about the gradients. But I also think there's curvature in this direction.
I also think there's, you know, I'm uncertain about the curvature. I think my future gradient
observations are going to have this much noise. You can trade off all those things to ask, like, what
direction and how far would give me the greatest expected improvement or probability of improvement
or whatever else you want. So we kind of hope that is it fair to characterize this as using
using a model within the machine learning training process in a place that you would otherwise
kind of hard code, hard code a parameter like step size or do like cyclical step sizes or
something like that. You got it exactly. And we just took a lot of care to make sure that there
was no inner training leap. Like we don't have to train this model. All the updates are closed
for them. So the algorithm looks like something like Adam where such a bunch of
vectorized operations that don't have any training leaps. Yeah. And then the hope is that
using this session information or this information that was always available, but we don't really
use it, we can design optimizers that at least always make progress. Maybe they, you know,
some fancy tuned hyper parameter schedule will be able to do better in principle. But if you could
say I'm just going to run my optimizer for a really long time and it's never going to stop
because the learning rate was stuck at being too high or too low. I hope we, you know,
we hope that that will make this sort of engineering struggle that every deep learning student
faces all day every day at least have one less hyper parameter. And you know, and it's a pretty
important hyper parameter. Is there a way to combine this with other methods that have been worked out
that, you know, it sounds like what you are fundamentally trying to solve or at least the result
you presented is that you're less likely to get stuck in some kind of local optima. Is it also
possible to to combine this with, you know, some kind of, you know, acceleration or momentum or
something like that so that you can both converge faster and not get stuck in a optima?
Yeah, that's a great question. And that's sort of where we left the research or that's how far
we've gotten so far is that we got this method to work. We got the step size to work. But
finding the enough, we've kind of found that it converges a little too well or rather that
so we have this one experiment where if we just want our automatic step size selection,
it makes a lot of progress really early and it ends up getting in stuck in a local optimum,
which is normally not really okay. I thought that's what I thought that was the
the opposite of what it was doing by the way you described it, you know, what it really does
as well is, you know, eventually converge. Yeah, well, exactly. Well, when we say converge,
though, you know, we can only talk, we only can guarantee local convergence. So these heuristics
for saying, oh, what maximizes my probability of improvement or expected improvement, that only
looks one step ahead. Yeah, in principle, we do need to somehow look ahead like multiple steps
ahead, but in practice, that's just always going to be really hard. It's like as hard as actually
solving the original problem. So, you know, we had some reason to believe that this might or to
expect that this might be a problem. There's like Roger Gross, my colleague here has some nice work
on the short horizon bias basically saying, if you optimize to do one, well, one step ahead, you won't
make good long term progress. So the thing is that there's also reason to believe that this wouldn't
be a problem because we think that the local optimum that we in training deep nets isn't such a big
problem. So, you know, we're not totally sure if these are actually local optimum or just places where
the optimizer can't make progress. But we did find that if we run for a fixed step size for a while
and then switch to our adaptive step size, that works the best. So it's one of these things where
we did get this thing to work better, but because it's myopic, like it only looks a few steps ahead,
if you have a really long computational budget, just using fixed step sizes for a while and then
switching works best. And so that's an unsatisfying answer. So I think that's the remaining question
to get this to be really practical is it could be that if we just run this adaptive thing for
long enough, it will be able to escape these local optimum. We haven't really looked into this
in depth yet. But anyway, I mean, I'm impressed that you identified the the weakness in this whole
story and just guessing it. Yeah, maybe taking a step back, you know, there's kind of a lot of
contemporary debate around, you know, the role that deep learning plays in artificial intelligence,
moving us to AGI. What kind of motivates you and where do you see this all going?
Right. So as I said, I think from a practical point of view in the short term, just being able to
meet the data where it is and deal with the actual huge piles of real problems and data sets that
can't even really be touched by standard deep learning or at least supervised deep learning or
discrete times here's models. That's like huge area of low hanging fruit. And there's a ton of
people who are just saying, oh, you know, I was promised that AI would revolutionize my industry,
but it's still kind of very bespoke and only can be applied here there. And then, but yeah,
that's sort of partly why I'm also spending a lot of time thinking more about these
amortized search and planning algorithms. Because I do think also that we are about to have a big
improvement in the sort of general reasoning abilities of machines. And I think this is still
going to be like mostly toy demos for a few years. And do you think that that mostly comes from a
reinforcement learning type of problem formulation? Well, the thing is that reinforcement learning is
such a vague word. And I guess I'll say model three reinforcement learning, you know, has it's like
now no one's excited about it. And everyone was super hyped about it like, you know, three or four
or even two years ago. I guess I would say right, like model-based planning or model-based control
is really starting to become practical now for the first time. I think a lot of people have said,
you know, been leaving in this for 40 years. There's this amazing book by Britsikis Neural
Linguistic Programming that basically outlines most of the methods that people are excited about
today. And I think it's from like the 80s. Yeah, but it's just that we now have a pile of
or a set of tools that we have an idea of how to combine. We're starting to understand how they can
be scaled up. So what I hear you saying is that you're mostly not placing bets on this kind of,
you know, what's going to get us to AGI kind of question and you're focused on like, you know,
how we can use this technology to solve current problems. Well, no, I guess I would say
working backwards from what gets us AGI is a really fun research agenda, right? And I love all
the papers of the Google machine. There's a recent work on logical inductors that try to sort of
sketch out what these would look like. And then they always have a part where it's like, and now
you do a search over all possible programs or something like that, which we don't know how to do.
But I love the idea of working backwards in there. And I guess I'll just say we also have a huge
amount of low-hanging fruit, like strong gradients saying, oh, if we combine these two tools that
we have, we can figure out how to do that. We know we'll have a big step towards more general
reasoning capabilities. So I think we don't even have to, we shouldn't think of you thinking hard,
but for the near future, I think we can make a bunch of progress without even thinking that hard
about the long term. Well, David, thanks so much for taking the time to update me on what you're
up to and, you know, generally share with all of us what you're working on at your lab and with
your students looking forward to catching your ICML papers. Oh, it's been a pleasure. Thank you, Sam.
All right, everyone. That's our show for today. For more information on today's show,
visit twomolai.com slash shows. As always, thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.