Welcome to the Twimmel AI Podcast.
Alright everyone, I am on the line with Andreas Madsen.
Andreas is an independent researcher based out of Copenhagen, Denmark.
Andreas, welcome to the Twimmel AI Podcast.
Thank you. It's great to be here.
It's great to chat with you.
I first came across your name as a result of a medium post that you wrote about your experience
becoming an independent researcher in the machine learning in AI field and ultimately getting published in ICLR
with a spotlight paper and we're going to dig into all of that here.
But let's get started with you sharing a little bit about your background and what motivated your interests in ML and AI.
That's a long time ago, probably like nine years ago I think.
I was reading a book called Programming Collective Intelligence, like all the way back in high school you would call it.
That's the O'Reilly book that talks about collaborative filtering and stuff.
Yeah, exactly. And I was reading this and at the time I wasn't really sure about what I would do for university.
But after reading that, I mean I read it again and I was really sure this was the direction I wanted to go in.
And so this was all the way before like machine learning really became like a popular subject.
Uh-huh. And particularly at that point interested in how he did natural language processing.
Okay. Yeah.
They used non-negative matrix factorization.
You did that now that will be a really old fashion.
But nevertheless that was like how I started and then I did like apply mathematics at university and I just took all the machine learning courses.
I could. And so you kind of pursued machine learning independently and in your blog post you you recommend that people avoid pursuing machine learning as independent researchers elaborate a little bit on your experience and why you make that recommendation.
I mean if you just want to develop machine learning like in the industry and you don't necessarily want to do anything novel as we call it.
Right. You can do that independently. I think that's totally fine.
But if you want to do research, if you want to like develop new methods, then this is a really hard field to do it in because you need like huge computational resources that you're not going to have.
And you probably also need to like collaborate with others who are really experts and who can stay up to date and like at least 300 papers a year as opposed.
And you're not going to have like conversation with those kind of people because you really you're just kind of alone right.
And also research in itself is just a very frustrating experience for everybody and also sort of to go through that alone without having like PST colleagues or such.
I think it's not that healthy like mentally just to be kind.
And mentally taxing just because of the isolation. Exactly. Like it's not that I don't have friends that I talk to right but they're not in the research business right.
So maybe they cannot really emphasize with how it feels to get rejected after seven years or seven months of writing a paper on your own funding right.
And so when you started to do this when you set out as an independent researcher was that coming right out of university or graduate school or did you leave a job to do this where were you coming from.
Right. I think it's like two and a half years ago and right after that I started as kind of like a freelancer at this company called near form that basically just do like open source JavaScript.
They're really good at that. And at the time it was kind of like fit up with academia.
And I didn't want to do a PST at that point. I think it's my master just for context.
Yeah. And I had this opportunity that was like very perfect for me in terms of my skills. And in that sense I could get paid quite a lot.
And I didn't quite know what I wanted to do next. So doing this for like three or six months was kind of perfect for me.
And JavaScript JavaScript freelancing. Yeah, exactly. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So like you're talking about creating like a profiling tool for programs or JavaScript programs.
So it's not like your typical kind of JavaScript is. And then after that they were like, okay, like this party is great.
If you want to do another six months sort of focusing on machine learning projects that are sort of minor and then I did that for six months and that was then the end of it.
Because it didn't really materialize into them getting a client there and an outsourcing company just to give some context.
And that was sort of also what I expected. So during that time I had already been working on this paper here called
Visualizing Memorization in the colonial networks. There was also one of the projects I did for them.
I just proposed this just by the paper as like marketing effort.
And so it's been like one month from that with them. And then I just finished it on my own time. After that.
Yeah. And so then I thought after that, I got published in the still with this paper here. I thought like I would have a chance at getting like a research software engineer position where you kind of do both engineering and machine research.
Because I thought like I was a good mix of both. But that turned out to be really difficult. Then I look into getting PST positions into PST programs because that's sort of the unwritten requirement.
And this was where I was told like this publication you have right now is not enough. You need to have like at least one top tier publication right or publication in like a top venue conference.
Right. This was someone telling you that you needed the publication and the top tier conference to answer.
They get a top advisor, right? No, not necessarily a top advisor. What was the context for that statement? I talked to like five different professors from different universities and they were like, yeah, it's like really competitive.
It's not that you're going to be more qualified. Like your abilities will be that much greater because you had this publication is just, you know, that is the field that they use because they get like a thousand.
Applications. And so that's really just the host reality.
And so in spite of being a little fed up with with academia, you embarked on, you know, what is in many ways an academic pursuit to pursue research independently, push your paper and your your ideas a little bit further.
How did you get from the mapping or visualizing paper to the neural arithmetic unit idea?
To an assistant researcher at the same community University of Denmark here that I live quite close to. It was like at an opening for a foundation, I think, and he was just talking like if you're interested in doing some kind of research, maybe we can collaborate on that.
And so I worked with him and we just talked about different kind of projects. And I felt this project here was kind of like in my.
Wheelhouse because I had already done quite a lot of optimization work, not research, but done a lot of study in that field.
Well, some of the comments that you got suggest that, you know, it's not necessarily not necessarily easy to find the willing collaborator if you don't have that credential.
So you kind of locked out there, maybe I mean, he's not a professor. He's not even a PC program, right?
Okay.
He's just sort of assisting students with the master thesis and stuff like that, right? Got it.
And during a course they were running, they were trying to reproduce this paper here that we will probably talk about Nellow neural arithmetic, lot of units. And they were really struggling to that and like nobody could reproduce it consistently.
And so he thought that might be an interesting research subject.
So I think like yes, I did log out a bit, but not that much, I think.
Okay. So what, you know, before we kind of jump into the topic of the paper, you know, you kind of suggest that this is a hard way to go the kind of independent researcher life, but you were able to successfully get your paper written and accepted at ICLR.
You know, what works for you? What, you know, someone else wants to, you know, disavow your advice, not to pursue this path, but, you know, is open to your advice on what to do if you do decide to go down this road, you know, what would that advice be?
I mean, you definitely need to, to collaborate because you're not going to go out of university and be an expert at Chris, criticizing your own work. Even the ones that been in the academia for like 10 years, I don't think are experts at that, right?
Just inherently resistant to criticizing your own work. I think it's a fundamental property of being human. And so you need to collaborate with somebody who can do that. This not necessarily has to be a professor, I think.
Like anybody who has experienced reading machine learning papers and criticize them, I think we'll suit just fine. And then I think like also have reasonable expectations, like if you're going in with the expectation that there's like an eight percent change of success, like you're delusional.
Like, sorry, like the success rate in these conferences is like 20 percent, right? And you're probably going to have like less of a chance than that, because you don't have the resources everybody else have.
And so you should expect to get rejected from your first summation, I think. And I was rejected.
First, I proposed this paper here to to no lips, right? I got rejected from that. And then I could use that peer review to improve the paper and then submit for for I clear. And then we then got accepted.
And even that, I think it's not not a guarantee, right? I mean, could also been rejected there could also have been less lucky with the peer reviewers.
We're very fortunate to have actually the same one of the same peer viewers that have from new lips who are very constructive and could see that we had made like really good progress.
And I think also they themselves had also had like a few months to actually think about this work and also be able to think a bit more critical about the competing paper.
This was also an open review, so he was sort of like comment on other people's reviews, those are really helpful.
So there's like almost once in a lifetime, you get that kind of really constructive people, you're like again, like loggy there, I think.
So tell us a little bit about the paper. What's the motivation for the research?
Right. And so it really comes down to very abstract weapon that is neural networks are really good at interpolating. They can create very complex approximations.
But they're not very good at extrapolating, right? It's a classic example with for example image recognition, you put in like a white pixel somewhere and suddenly it goes from being a separate to being a couch.
And that really comes down to neural networks and are very good at extrapolating.
And what specifically do you mean by that? Because in a lot of ways extrapolating is what we expect machine learning to do, like make predictions based on data that it's seen. That's kind of extrapolation.
It's probably interpolation, right? Well, you're seeing pictures of of separas before, but there never been like a dead pixel in any of these pictures here.
So it's not it's filler with the concept of of separas, but it's not familiar with the concept of a dead pixel.
Right. And that's really where you go from interpolation, like this is just another picture of a separate that is never seen before this interpolation. But as soon as you add like a dead pixel, then you're now into a new realm of extrapolation.
And it's not an easy concept, I think, to understand when do you go from interpolation to extrapolation.
But mathematically, at least there's no reason to expect the neural network to perform well or an extrapolation tasks.
And so the research was on what measuring networks ability to do extrapolation or coming up with methods that help them to do extrapolation.
Right. So, so what is the deep mind paper here by Andrew Tresky, the nano paper, and proposes to look at like a subset of problems where the underlying problem has some fundamental arithmetic to it.
So some combination of addition and multiplication, let's say. And that you will have example in physical models in financial models or some question answering models.
Like what is three times five. And given that assumption, can you then develop a null unit similar to, for example, LSM.
But in this case for like a rhythmic extrapolation that given this training data can actually work on a numerical values that is outside of the training distribution.
And so that's the central problem here. And then there's the deep mind paper now that they propose one solution, we then find that this does not converge very consistently.
So it does work sometimes, but if you're training like 100 different seats, then it might only work on 10 or one of those seats.
And what we are doing is then to improve that consistency, such that it works on almost all the seats, like 99 or 100.
How did you go about doing that?
Right.
I think like the, the Nell papers was a very, it is a very empirical paper. It just proposes the small here doesn't really give any kind of explanation behind why it looks exactly like this.
And then it evaluates that on seven different tasks. And so a lot of the typical mathematical analysis you might put into proposing a new unit wasn't really done.
So even simple things like how do you initialize the weights was a question that was not answered and probably not analyzed.
And so what we looked at this example in the station as I mentioned also gradients.
You can also just plot like the law space.
If there's some odd behavior here, in this case, we found like big area of singularities around global minimus.
That's a really give you an indication that something going wrong also redundant parameters can also be a problem when optimizing.
Like if you can somehow simplify this units while still achieving the same things.
Maybe that's an easier to optimize.
And so these are all the properties we looked at just analyze them one by one and then we sort of OK identified that these are problematic areas.
And that's really the easy part. Then the hard part is then to come up with a new unit that doesn't have these issues.
There's there was different components to this Nellow unit here. So there's like a part they can do additions, part they can do modifications.
And then they have like a gaining unit that can switch between these two parts here.
And what we also did was we for example could say OK let's just say it's a multiplication problem which fix the gaining to always choose modification.
How well does that improve anything.
And so this is what you probably call like an emblaziness study where you remove some of the complexity and then you'll see if it still works or if it works better.
And they are there also for example find that the gate mechanism that they're using really doesn't work as it should.
It more or less just chooses other addition or multiplication randomly independent of what the actual problem is.
That doesn't sound like what you wanted to do.
No, no, of course. Things to convert dependent on your data.
And so you develop this unit with kind of a different arrangement of gates.
Is that the general idea?
We actually skipped the gating problem so this is still on salt right to me if you want to solve it.
And then we just focused on getting multiplication to work more consistently because that only converts like 30% of the times.
That I will say our primary contribution.
So does that mean you you punted on arithmetic problem or did you do that independently but the network didn't have to choose which one I was doing.
Like we said OK you have to do multiplication or you have to do addition it didn't like understand that itself.
Yeah OK got it.
It turns out to be hard enough problem itself.
Yeah, like what was happening before was really just it chose like randomly and then you know if you turn a train on enough different seats then one of the times it's going to hit the right thing.
Yeah and and our idea here was essentially to make it more linear linear functions or at least partial linear functions are typically more easy to optimize than very not linear function.
So the narrow function is essentially a exponential function so it has like X to the power of your weight stop you.
And then if W zero then it's not selected and if W is one then you multiply.
And where in our case we we placed that concept with essentially gaining mechanism between one and X.
And so this is easier to optimize because it's a little more linear.
And so did you also apply this to a variety of different benchmark tasks or were you strictly evaluating performance on kind of this mathematical operation.
Right so the the number of people who posted I think six or seven different tasks and I mean I'll just be honest here if most of those tasks are not relevant to what they're actually solving.
Because they do not they do not test extrapolation and they do not test multiplication only one of those seven tasks actually test extrapolation on multiplication.
And so that is a task we benchmarked on and that is quite a simple task so we also took one of the other tasks they had.
And then we modified that a bit so it would also test multiplication instead of only addition.
And so how are these tasks set up is pretty simple you have like one part that is like you have a hundred different inputs and then you take two subsets of this input here and then you sum that together.
Now you have two numbers and then you multiply those two numbers and that's your target.
And then this is pretty easy to test extrapolation on because then you just sample your input from a different range than you trained on.
And then we have a more complex task because well you can show that this works really well but what if you had this in the context of a more complex neural network then maybe it wouldn't converge.
And so what we did was also looked at endless numbers where we take like a sequence of endless numbers for example and then we try and add them together or multiply them together.
And then of course you need like a convolution neural network to translate the image to a number and then you have our unit to then translate those numbers or multiply those numbers.
Presumably the problems are set up as supervised problems so you're training on you said in the case of the first task a different range of the inputs and then you're running your testing against a range at the.
Yeah, this is supervised to regression problems. Yeah, how do you ultimately perform on the various tests? I mean we perform quite a bit better so what's the right way to even measure performance on these kinds of tasks.
Right. That I think is a very good and central question because there's not been a lot of work in extrapolation and we actually did two papers in this a workshop paper neural lips and where we actually just discussed how do you evaluate this and then our I clear people where we improve the model.
And I think the fundamental idea you need to have so the never paper is they just evaluated on one seat and they just show the mean squared error and mean squared errors are great for comparing is this model better than this model but that is not really was interesting here because if you truly can extrapolate that means you found the perfect solution you're complete a solid problem.
And you should have a mean square error that is very close to zero whatever error that is left is really just due to like computer precision if you follow the problem. Yeah, exactly.
What the NL people does did was they compare this to a random all and as you can imagine a random all can have quite a big error especially if you multiply different numbers can the target becomes like a million and then you have a random all that produces something that's a million of that and then you square that and not something you have a like a really big.
And so comparing really relative to this random model doesn't really make sense. So what we didn't status compare to a nearly perfect model so we simply just like develop the perfect model and then we add like a little epsilon to the weights and then we use that as a threshold for what the means squared error should be.
And that's all about success criteria and once you have the success criteria then you can just do this a hundred times on a hundred different seats and then you can measure the success rate.
Okay, I'm not sure I'm following the process here so you said you are comparing to a nearly perfect model. I mean the nearly perfect model is what you're trying to figure out in the first place.
And you have you know that you know the absolute answer for multiplying the numbers where does this nearly perfect model come from.
Well, it's really just the absolute value as you call it from multiplying the numbers like plus an epsilon.
Got it. So you're you're taking the result that you know to be true and adding some noise to it and you're training against that.
Exactly now this epsilon here you of course need to adjust to reflect the number of operations equivalently to perform this calculation.
And why do you add the noise in the first place? Well, how does that help your model converge presumably that's why.
No, it's not it's not added to the problem itself.
It's added to the criteria. Okay, or the top like what do you actually like you get some mean squared error.
And that's very close to to zero.
And like let's say.
But is this you you're not adding this in your or are you adding this in like your loss function or is it just after you train a model in the way you present the results.
It's just a way of evaluating like the results like you need need to compare the mean squared error to something you cannot compare to zero because it's never going to be zero right.
And so you need to compare to some epsilon and in order to compute that epsilon you essentially just run a perfect model on the problem.
Except it's not a perfect model. It has like a really tiny error and then you get a really tiny mean squared error and that's what you compare against.
Besides the the Nallu paper there are other results that were out there to compare against or was that the kind of state of the art in this space.
It's a very new feel so that is the state of the art.
There are other papers that are sort of also doing a written text or for example neural GPU is kind of a popular paper.
That paper they're trying to learn algorithms. That's a bit different.
And also they don't focus on extrapolation, I believe.
But that's like the most similar.
And but really it is just that paper.
Yeah, that's also part that they made a attractive for me to research because they didn't need to spend like half a year just understanding the background.
Yeah, yeah. What are kind of your next steps beyond this paper?
Right now I'm just focused on trying to get into more permanent situation, a PSD program or a job or something similar.
That's sort of my focus right now. Then I'm doing a collaboration with one from DeepMind.
Unlike what will probably be a small workshop paper, but not Andrew Trask.
Not Andrew Trask, no.
Who have interviewed before on the podcast incidentally, it was at NURBS a couple of years ago, I think.
Okay.
But we talked about his privacy stuff and open mind and not any of this.
Yeah, he really been public on that this year, I think.
More into interpretability, I think that's a really important problem.
We're creating all these very complex models here, but we how do we can we rely on them actually working.
And so this sort of already is around what I'm already working on like I did the visualization of memorization.
That is an empowered interpretability and also my work here relating to NALO is also about extrapolation,
which is essentially about like can you trust that this model is also going to work once I see this data that it has not seen before.
And this is something I wanted to do for a long time, but I was always discouraged from pursuing it when I was at university
because they didn't really feel like you could publish in the big conferences and that subject.
But Dennis was at NURBS 2019 because I did a workshop publication and saw this talk here by being came from Google.
And I think she really like illustrated for me that it is possible to do like high quality research in this area here and get published at conferences that are used for your career.
And so that is really what I kind of want to pursue.
But preferably with with an organization, you know, whether academic or industry as opposed to independent.
Yeah, probably.
So you did it, you wouldn't recommend it and you're taking your own advice.
Exactly. Well, Andreas, thanks so much for taking the time to share a little bit about your journey and research.
Yeah, thank you.
All right, everyone, that's our show for today. For more information on today's show, visit twomolai.com slash shows.
As always, thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.