Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimal Talk, the podcast where I interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
This week we continue our industrial AI series with Sergei Levine, an assistant professor
at UC Berkeley, whose research focus is deep robotic learning.
Sergei is part of the same research team as a couple of our previous guests in the series,
Chelsea Finn and Peter Rebel, and if the response we've seen to those shows is any indication,
you're going to love this episode.
Sergei's research interests and our discussion focus in on how robotic learning techniques
can be used to allow machines to autonomously acquire complex behavioral skills.
We really dig into some of the details of how this is done, and I found that my conversation
with Sergei filled in a lot of gaps for me from the interviews with Peter and Chelsea.
By the way, this is definitely a nerd alert episode.
Before we jump into the show, I'd like to thank everyone who's taken the time to enter
our AI conference giveaway.
You all know that one of my favorite things to do is to give away free stuff to listeners,
and we've been fortunate to be able to give away tickets to the O'Reilly AI conference,
to lucky Twomo listeners since the very first event in the series last year.
Well, we've got a couple of exciting updates for those of you who want in on this opportunity.
First, we're making it even easier to enter our ticket giveaway for the San Francisco event,
and second, we're giving away two tickets now, not just one.
To enter the contest in 30 seconds or less, just hit pause right now, and visit TwomoAI.com
slash AISF right from your phone.
Finally, a quick thank you to our sponsors for the Industrial AI series, Banzai, and
Wise.io at GE Digital.
By now, you know a bit about Banzai, right?
You've heard me mention their AI platform, which lets enterprises build and deploy intelligent
systems.
Well I actually spent some time in the Banzai offices in Berkeley last week learning more
about that platform and recording an interview with their co-founder and CEO Mark Hammond.
It was a great conversation and I'm really looking forward to getting it up on the
podcast in a few weeks.
In the meantime, I'll reiterate that if you're trying to build AI-powered applications
focused on optimizing and controlling the physical systems in your enterprise, whether robots,
or HVAC systems, or supply chains, you should take a look at what they're up to.
They've got a unique approach to building AI models that lets you model the real world
concepts in your application, automatically generate, train, and evaluate low level
models for your project using technologies like reinforcement learning, and easily integrate
those models into your applications and systems using APIs.
You can check them out at Banz.ai slash TwomoAI, and definitely let them know you appreciate
their support of the podcast and this series.
Last week, I announced wise.io at GE Digital as a sponsor for this series as well.
Wise.io was among the first companies I began following in what I call the machine learning
platform space back in 2012-2013.
I've since interviewed co-founder Josh Bloom here on the show and mentioned the company's
subsequent acquisition by GE Digital.
At GE Digital, the wise.io team is focused on creating technology and solutions that enable
advanced capabilities for the industrial internet of things, making infrastructure more intelligent
and advancing the industry's critical to the world we live in.
I want to give a hearty thanks and shout out to the team at wise.io at GE Digital for
supporting my industrial AI research and this podcast series.
Of course, you can check them out at wise.io.
And now onto the show.
Hey everyone, I am on the line with Sergei Levine.
Sergei is an assistant professor at UC Berkeley in the EECS department and I'm super excited
to have him on the show.
Hi Sergei.
Hello.
How are you doing?
I'm doing well.
Wonderful.
How about we start by having you introduce yourself and talk a little bit about your background
and how you got interested in your current area of research and what that is?
Sure.
So I actually started off in graduate school working on computer graphics and particularly
in computer graphics.
I was really interested in simulating virtual humans, simulating virtual characters.
And the trouble is that if you want to simulate very realistic virtual humans, one of the
things you have to do is you have to simulate intelligence because humans are intelligent
and machines by default aren't.
So a lot of my work turned out to be essentially artificial intelligence work in computer graphics
to get these virtual characters to behave in ways that look plausible.
So from there, I decided that, well, if I have some methods that work reasonably well
in computer graphics, I can create some plausibly realistic virtual humans, perhaps those are methods
that are also applicable, for example, to robotics.
So I did a postdoc after that in robotics, turns out that a lot of the stuff works well
for robots as well.
And a lot of that led to my current work in reinforcement learning and deep learning.
Fantastic.
I noticed on your website that you've got a paper, except that you're speaking at a computer
animation conference, are you still fairly active in the video domain?
Not as much in recent years.
So I think my last paper there was in 2012.
I am giving a guess lecture this summer actually at SCA, that's a symposium on computer
animation to talk about some of the recent progress in deep reinforcement learning.
So actually, since I moved to robotics, actually, a lot of this technology has made actually
a big impact in graphics, and that's really right about now and this past year that's
been registering a lot.
So they invited me to come give a talk to them about how some of this stuff is going.
Fantastic.
So as you know, we recently had on the show Peter Rebel and Chelsea Finn, who are your
colleagues there at Berkeley, and the conversations I had with those guys were really, really interesting.
And let's maybe take a minute to talk about the research that you're doing in a little
bit more detail and we can dive in deeper.
Sure.
So the area that I work in can be broadly categorized as robotic learning.
So I'm interested in developing algorithms and models that can allow robots to autonomous
who learn very large and complex repertoire of behaviors so that they can take on more
and more of the functionality that we associate with intelligent human beings so that they
can do all the things that are dangerous and pleasant or for other reasons undesirable
for people to do themselves.
And to me, this problem is not just a problem that has a lot of interesting practical implications,
it's also something that I think can serve as a really valuable lens and artificial
intelligence because in the end, we have only one proof of existence of true intelligence
of human beings and human beings are embodied.
So we don't just exist sort of in the ether thinking abstract thoughts, we actually have
a body we interact with the world and the nature of that interaction is very central to
shaping who we are and how and how we reason about things.
So I think that dealing with systems that are embodied systems like robots gives us a very
valuable perspective in understanding how we might be able to construct artificial intelligence.
So more so than some of the non-physical applications of machine learning in AI, including other
deep learning applications like gameplay.
Well, so the thing about other applications of AI is that oftentimes, especially in
things like computer vision, speech recognition, so on, we work with just the perception
half the equation.
So we think about how we can take in data and produce a particular answer.
But the nature of intelligence is much more complex than that.
It's about taking in information, reasoning about it, making decisions, thinking about
the outcomes of those decisions and so on and so on.
Now you mentioned game playing, which has some elements of this.
But one thing that game playing won't let you do is it won't let you tackle the full
complexity and diversity of the real world because the real world is characterized not
just by sequential nature, but also by its diversity, by the sheer number of unexpected
things that might happen in a natural interaction, which computer vision has dealt with for decades,
but without handling the decision making and the game playing handles the decision making
but without handling so much of diversity.
So to what degree is your research and robotic learning kind of integrative across all
these different fields?
Are you specifically focused on pulling together some of the state of the art research from
these various fields or is your domain within robotic learning kind of established and you're
heading down a path that way?
I don't know if that question makes any sense, but if you kind of get a sense from where
I'm going.
I think I see where you're going.
This is actually a very good question and something that for robotics has been sort of
one of these big tensions over the years is that it's often been very tempting for researchers
to think of robotics as fundamentally a systems or integration exercise.
So if you have, let's say, a very effective computer vision system and you have a very
effective, let's say, planning system, well, maybe building an intelligent robot is just
a matter of welding those species together, connecting up the wires and seeing it work.
And a lot of people have hoped for exactly this that by making progress independently in
different domains, we'll get closer and closer to intelligent robots.
Unfortunately, reality hasn't quite panned out that way.
And a lot of robotics will actually lament that if they take sort of the latest image
net train model and put it on their robot and try to use it for object detection in the
wild, it'll actually do a pretty terrible job because the biases that are present in
the kind of data sets that those models are trained on don't really reflect what a robot
will see from its cameras in natural environments.
So I actually think that in order to really get this right, we need to draw on the lessons
in the state of the art models in, you know, game playing, vision and so on.
But at some point, we have to kind of do a lot of that ourselves.
We have to take the lessons, but not necessarily the technical components themselves.
And for that reason, I've actually been a really big advocate of end to end training for
robotic learning where we set up models that include both perception and control and
act to train together to perform the particular task the robot needs to handle instead of relying
on integration of existing components.
In taking a look at your research, I came across a really interesting example of the
effect you're describing, the particular research was where you were training a robot arm.
I think it was a backster robot to tie knots in a rope.
And some of the comments associated with the research on the, I think there was a
get-hud page about it was that, hey, we trained this system on a, I think it was a red
rope.
And, you know, we're working hard to make it work with a white rope also that's a little
bit stiffer.
And we trained it on a background that was a green background and, you know, that doesn't,
we found that that doesn't generalize to other backgrounds.
This is a conversation point that came up with Peter as well, this notion of mastery versus
generalization.
Can you talk a little bit about that and how your research is taking that issue on?
Yeah, absolutely.
So, the backster paper that you're referring to there, what we did is we actually had a robot
practice tying knots, but of course, it was one robot and it was practicing tying knots
in one particular rope.
So the resulting system could do really well at tying knots in that rope, it could kind
of tie knots in ropes that looked a little similar and it pretty much broke down if you
gave it something, you know, a rope that was too thick or too thin or something like that.
But here's the thing that in robotics, there's like oftentimes when we run experiments,
the experiment is the entirety of the data collection process.
So if you imagine an experiment in computer vision, you take all of ImageNet, you train
your model on it and you show its performance.
In robotics, an experiment basically amounts to generating an entire new data set, training
your model on it and then observing its performance.
So of course, if you're generating an entire data set every time, if you have one robot,
just a little bit of time, it's not going to generalize very far.
We did actually try to study at one point what would happen is if we scaled up the style
of technique, we did this actually in partnership with Google, which has quite a
bit more resources as far as deploying large numbers of robots.
And we tried to see actually, like if we run data collection at the scale of something
like ImageNet, can we actually get robotic skills that generalize effectively?
So what we did there is we set up, we called this the ARM farm by analogy to server farm.
We set up a cluster of about 14 robots and we had them basically working day and night
to practice grasping objects.
So we chose grasping because it's something they can do to pretty much any object and
it's also very important for a lot of other robotic manipulation tasks.
And we had them running day and night like this and they collected about 800,000 grasps,
each grasped had maybe five to ten images.
So the total size of the data set was about on the same order of magnitude as ImageNet.
And there we did find that actually the resulting networks that you train on that really large
data set, they do actually generalize effectively to new objects that are completely different
than what they've seen before.
In fact, when you do learning at this larger scale, you can observe some really interesting
or emergent behavior.
One of the things that we were thinking as we did this work as well, grasping is a very
geometric behavior.
So probably the first thing that these systems will learn about is the geometry of objects
in the world still learn that you need to put the finger on one side, put the finger on
the other side and so on.
What we saw, which surprised us a little bit, is that in the earlier stages of training,
when you have maybe 100,000 grasps before we collected the full data set of a million,
in the early stages of training, the network actually didn't pay as much attention to geometry,
but what it did do is it paid a lot of attention to material properties.
It recognized right away that if something was really soft, then it could pinch it and
pick it up really easily.
But if something was rigid, then it couldn't do that.
And this is completely different from how conventional, manually designed grasping systems
tend to work because when you manually design a grasping system, you're going to use
some sort of geometric motion planning and you're going to completely ignore the material
properties.
It's really interesting to us and that's sort of underscored, I think, the value that
you get from using learning through trial and error because you actually learn about
the patterns that are really present in the world rather than the ones that your analytic
model thinks are important.
Are there any other emergent behaviors that you observed in that set of experiments?
Let me see.
So that was the only one that we could pin down in the sense that we could actually measure
it, like we could actually put different objects in front of it and quantify that, yes,
it was really employing the strategy.
And formally, there were a few things that it did tend to do pretty consistently that
I can kind of speculate a little bit about.
I just don't have the hard numbers for it.
Intended to figure out, for example, that if you have something like a brush that you
should pick up the brush by the stiff part rather than the flexible bristles, which is
nice, it tended to figure out that center of masses of objects really matter, especially
for awkwardly shaped objects.
So those were some of the things that it picked up on.
There were also a few mistakes that actually made that we're kind of amusing.
So it just so happened that a lot of the soft things in our training objects were brightly
colored because we bought, you know, we wanted to buy small items of clothing and small items
of clothing, our children's clothing.
And children's clothing.
So we brightly colored.
So it had this association of things that were brightly colored were soft.
And in our test set of objects, we had a pink stapler.
And that pink stapler was just impossible for it to pick up because it was just convinced
that this pink stapler was a soft fuzzy thing and it could just pinch it.
So that's a good example, actually, of the kind of funny data set biases that you can
get that will actually affect you even in real world tasks like this.
Interesting.
When I hear you describe the examples, an example like the pink stapler, it makes me wonder,
you know, to what extent is it possible to layer the traditional object recognition types
of technologies into a model like this, like, should it be able to recognize the stapler
first and then have some higher level abstraction that we're also training on in addition to
just the raw pixels?
Is that something you look at?
Yeah, that's a very good question.
That's actually something that we've thought about a lot here.
So one of the big things that you get out of traditional approaches to dog detection,
it's not actually the models themselves.
It's the data.
There's very large and extremely diverse data sets, label data sets of objects with bounding
boxes, segmentation, and so on.
And it would be really nice to try to use that.
But at the same time, you want to avoid losing the benefit of end-to-end training.
So if you simply run a bounding box detector on what the robot is seeing and then ask
it to pick things up, well, it's not just the bounding box that matters for the grasp,
it has to also understand something about what's in that bounding box.
So you don't want to lose the benefit of the end-to-end training, but at the same time,
you want to somehow get more out of all these auxiliary sources of information.
One of the things that we've been working on a little bit, and this isn't out yet,
but this will be released in probably a couple of weeks, is some work on semi-supervised
learning of robotic skills, where we combine experience from the robot's point of view that
includes the actions that it took and the observations that it saw with kind of a weekly
labeled image data set.
And weekly labeled in the sense that that data set just tells you, does the image contain
the object that the robot needs to use?
If the robot is learning, for example, how to put a cap on a bottle, the weekly labels
might say, does this image contain a bottle or not?
And the idea is that the robot itself, when it's interacting with the world, maybe it
only gets to interact with a few instances of those objects.
So it can use those few instances to understand the physics of the behavior, but it's not
really enough for it to really generalize to understand what the entire class of objects
of this type looks like.
So the weekly labeled data is there to basically show it, what can this skill be applied to?
And the important thing when incorporating this weekly label data is not to lose the benefit
of the intent training.
So in this technique that we develop, we're actually including the weekly label data and
the robot's own experience at the same time in a joint training procedure, rather than
actually splitting things up into components and then trying to wire them up together as
in the more kind of conventional systems approach.
And that turns out to work very well.
Under the hood, the method has kind of an intentional flavor to it, so it basically
learns what kind of objects to pay attention to from the weekly label data and then uses
that attentional mechanism to perform the task at test time.
How do you express weakness in this model?
Well, when I say weekly labeled, I just mean that the images have a label that only tells
you whether the object you care about is present or not.
So you can think of this as a person telling the robot, here are the things that you can
execute this skill on.
So here, lots of pictures of the thing that you can do this task too, and here are all
the pictures of things that you cannot do this task too.
Right.
And is there a general approach to incorporating in kind of higher level abstractions, higher
level abstractions into models like this, meaning, you know, in the case of a, and going
back to the stapler example, you know, we could do the object detection and determine that,
hey, this is a stapler, but there's also, you know, there are other neural nets that or
other examples that can do geometry detection and things like that and orientation detection.
And I guess the question that I'm trying to get at is it sounds like the general approach
to applying deep learning in this model is, you know, let's just collect a bunch of data
and, you know, throw it at and train on a bunch of data.
And if there are important features, you know, the model will figure it out, the network
will figure it out.
And what I'm curious about is, is that do you, hey, I guess what are the, you know, what's
the, is there an analytical foundation to that assertion?
And if not, are there other ways that folks are looking at incorporating in abstractions
or features into, you know, these models to help them, you know, both generalize and train faster?
So I think there's perhaps a little more to it than that.
So it used to be that when we thought about kind of the, the previous generation, generational
machine learning models, the way that we would imagine using them is exactly when you describe
that we say, okay, we have some edge detector, we have a pose detector, we have some kind
of thing that will analyze local geometry, we'll plug that into the downstream module and
so on and so on.
The thing about deep learning is that the model itself, you know, it's good for making
predictions, but there's nothing kind of unique or special about it.
You can actually have the same model perform multiple tasks.
And that's often not actually that much harder than stapling together two models that each
perform those tasks. So if you want a model that can, you know, segment an image and detect
poses of objects, you could train two separate models and then combine their outputs or
it can just train one model that does both of those tasks.
And the latter is often not actually that much harder, but it has a substantial benefit
which is when you train a single model to perform multiple tasks, it can actually learn
internal representations that share the knowledge that's contained in those two tasks.
So if you were to ask me how I would consider combining, let's say, a object pose detector
and a grasping system, I would much rather train a single model that predicts both pose
and grasp than to take a pose predictor and feed its output into a grasp predictor.
And the reason for that is that the data already has all the information.
There's nothing, you know, magical that's contained in the model that's not already contained
in the data and it's possible to train these joint models.
So I might as well take both data sets and train one model that'll benefit from the shared
structure in both of those tasks, then train two completely destroyed models and then
try to stable them together afterwards.
Right.
Have you run into situations where there's there are pre-existing models trained on inaccessible
data?
I guess I'm maybe I'm kind of chasing the chasing the tail of the scenario a little bit,
but it sounds like, you know, there may be some corner case where it makes sense to do
that if you don't have access to the data, but you do have access to the model.
But I get the point that in general, the data is the data and if you can train one model
that can build these internal representations, it's much more efficient than trying to
engineer one model that can solve part of the problem and another model that uses that
to solve the thing that you're actually trying to do.
Yeah.
Basically, it's a lot easier for us to compose data sets than it is to compose models.
Right.
So, one of the challenges that comes up that you've spent some time looking at is the
efficiency of training these deep learning models.
Sample efficiency in particular is one of the ways you talk about that.
Can you talk a little bit about that problem and the things you've done there?
Right.
So, I assume you're referring specifically to sample efficiency for deep reinforcement
learning algorithms.
That's correct.
So, deep reinforcement learning algorithms are kind of a funny creature.
Deep learning, like standard deep learning with gradient descent, it's a common perception
that it's inefficient.
And in some sense, it is like we can build very good object detectors, but we need maybe
millions of images to train them, which might seem like a lot, but if you consider what
that model is really doing, it's reasoning about pixels, edges, everything from those pixels
and edges all the way to complex higher level concepts, that's actually pretty sophisticated.
With deep reinforcement learning, though, things get a lot worse.
So, if you look at the kind of sample complexity for learning to play, let's say, a simple
video game like Pong, and there you're going to be looking at millions or even tens of
millions of images for a task with visual diversity that's nowhere near where we see
in conventional, let's say, computer vision data sets.
So, visually it's very simple, physically it's very simple, but you need a lot of samples
to learn that task, and those samples involve actively interacting with an environment.
How it happens to be a simulated environment, so you can run it much faster than real
time on a server, but still something here seems a little out of whack.
Something here is a lot worse than perhaps it should be.
And what's the intuition for why that is the case?
There are a couple of reasons for it.
The short version is that we don't fully understand, but the long version is that there are
a few things that are being done that could perhaps be done differently.
Now, if I knew exactly the answer to this, then of course, I would have a much more efficient
algorithm to give you, but it's possible to guess a few things here.
One of the things is that reinforcement learning provides a much weaker signal than supervised
learning.
So in reinforcement learning, even though it's gradient-based optimization, you don't
really have gradients of the thing that you really care about.
You're sort of estimating them in this very peculiar way, depending on the reinforcement
learning algorithm that you use, so you essentially get a lot less information from every gradient
step.
A lot of reinforcement learning algorithms also tightly couple the collection of data in
the environment and the updating of the model, which is very different from supervised
learning.
So in supervised learning, you first collect a large data set, and then you take many, many
gradient steps on that large data set.
In reinforcement learning, you often interleave collection of data and updating the model
because you need to collect data that agrees with your model.
So if you're learning a policy, you'd like to collect the kind of experience that that
policy will actually see, and you want to do this iteratively.
So that means that you're often throwing out lots of data from old policies that you
can no longer use because your policy has changed, and that prevents you from reusing
old data.
So that can be very harmful for sample efficiency.
In fact, some of the most inefficient methods, methods like policy gradient, that are very
convenient to use in simulation, they're often the most inefficient in the real world
because they can't reuse data.
So we need to look at methods that can reuse old data, these are sometimes called off-policy
algorithms.
Before we go there, can you elaborate on the throwing out of the data?
Is this something that the algorithm is doing as part of the way it's constructed, or
is this something that we're doing manually to tell us a little bit more about what we
mean by that?
Oh, so that's just how a lot of on-policy, policy gradient algorithms work.
So these algorithms will operate as following, they will collect experience from the current
policy, they will compute a gradient descent direction on that experience, they will take
that gradient step, update the policy, and now they need more data from the latest policy,
which has not been updated.
So they have to throw out all the old data and collect a new batch of data.
So if you want a mental picture of what this looks like, if you have a robot that lets
say it's learning to walk, it'll try to walk a couple of times, update its behavior, try
to walk a couple more times, and so on and so on, and that's the reinforcement learning
process.
But you have to remember that each time it changes the behavior like that, it has to
basically collect new experience because you need to understand how well its current
policy is really doing.
Right.
So that can get really, really expensive in terms of the amount of time it needs to spend
collecting experience.
So if you're running stuff in a simulator on a server farm somewhere, then it's okay
you can paralyze all that and everything is reasonable.
But if that's a real physical system that's actually executing those trials, that can
get extremely tight consuming.
Mm-hmm.
Okay, and you're about to talk about some of the ways we can get beyond this.
Right.
So one of the things we can do is we can look at off-policy algorithms.
So these are algorithms that can supplement their training with data from other policies.
So what can you learn from other policies?
Well, intuitively, one of the things that you can learn is you can learn about predicting
future events because the rules of physics and so on, they will hold true regardless
of which policy you're executing.
And the kind of future events that you can predict can range all the way from very detailed
where you're actually predicting, let's say, the entirety of your future observations.
And this is sometimes called model-based reinforcement learning.
Or all the way to something fairly abstract, like the future rewards that you will see.
And this is actually a type of model-free reinforcement learning that's sometimes referred
to as value function estimation or Q-learning that also falls up this category.
But they're all kind of prediction-style methods.
So on the one extreme, you're predicting the entirety of your future sensory observations
and on the other extreme, you're predicting something very abstract, like rewards that
you will see in the future.
And that tends to be more efficient because that allows you to incorporate data from other
policies, including your own past policies.
Hmm. And so, can you talk a little bit about those policies and how they differ from
one another?
Yeah.
So I can talk a little bit about the model-based reinforcement learning because I feel
like this is something that perhaps hasn't gotten quite as much attention in the research
community in recent years because there's been a lot of excitement about model-free reinforcement
learning.
The model-based reinforcement learning, it's perhaps not as far along because the prediction
problem that is trying to solve is a lot harder, but it has a lot of problems for dramatically
improving sample efficiency for two reasons.
The first reason is the one I mentioned that you can use data from other policies.
But the second reason, which is perhaps a little more subtle, is that a model-based reinforcement
learning, every sample has a lot more bits of supervision.
So if you imagine what you're doing when you're, let's say, predicting a value function,
you're predicting one scalar value that's a function of your current observation or state.
When you're predicting everything that will happen in the future, maybe you're predicting
future images that you will see, there are many more bits of supervision in that prediction
problem.
So every single sample actually carries a lot more bits of supervision, and that means
that your model can learn a lot more from each of those samples.
Now the flip side of the coin is that your model is now trying to solve a much harder problem.
It doesn't have to predict just a single scalar value, just a predict an entire image.
So it's sort of a little bit unclear how that shakes out, but potentially the benefit
in sample complexity can actually be quite substantial there.
We've done a little bit of work on model-based reinforcement learning for vision-based tasks,
section on real physical robots, and this is some work that we did that also involved
actually paralyzing data collection across multiple robots, but at a much smaller scale.
So with the grasping, I mentioned that we needed about 800,000 grasped attempts.
For the model-based reinforcement learning, we actually trained a video prediction model
for pushing objects around on a table with about 50,000 pushes.
And that was actually effective for generalizing to new objects and pushing them in new directions
and so on.
Simply by predicting what the robot will see in the future, and then taking the actions
for which that model predicts the kind of outcomes that you want.
So that was already a lot more efficient and it ran on real physical systems.
Now the downside is that because the prediction problem there is so hard, the predictions
were very short range.
So the robot could only execute behaviors maybe with a horizon of two to three seconds.
So these weren't complex behaviors.
And that's because the prediction problem is so hard, but hopefully as we get better
and better video prediction models, which is a very active area of research right now,
these methods will get better and better.
Is that the inverse reinforcement learning problem?
No, this is the model-based reinforcement learning problem.
So when I looked at the, again going back to the backster robot video, it talked a little
bit about this inverse RL where you are, it sounded like you're doing the same thing.
You've got your rope in one state, you have the human move it to another state, and then
you're looking at the action, the robot action that it would take to get it from one state
to another and producing the inverse of that.
Or that becomes the action that the robot takes to move the rope into the rope to a position
that's required to imitate what the human did.
So that's the inverse RL, how are what you just described sounded very similar to that.
So I think what you mean is actually inverse dynamics.
Inverse dynamics.
Okay.
So when you have a model-based reinforcement learning problem, there's actually different
ways that you can represent your predictive model.
The most common way is to build what's called a forward dynamics model.
So forward dynamics means that you're predicting from the present to the future.
So you're looking at your current observation, your current action, and you're predicting
what the next observation will look like.
Inverse dynamics means you're predicting from the future to the action.
So that means that you're looking at your current observation, your future observation,
and you're predicting what action will get you from one to the other.
Right.
So I've got the rope in position A, I've got the rope in position B, what's the action
that's required to get it from A to B?
Exactly.
So it's just another kind of predictive model and they have different pros and cons.
So with a forward model, you can run it forward many steps because you can basically
recursively apply it to its own predictions, but you have to work a little harder to get
the action.
With the inverse model, the action comes right out of the model, but it's difficult to
chain it together because you don't know what the following observation will be because
the model has some predictive observations and predictive actions.
So inverse models are perhaps a little easier to use, they're a little easier to train,
but they're a little harder to use for longer term planning.
Okay.
So in the discussion about sample efficiency, one of the things that I came across was
mirror descent, guided policy search, can you talk a little bit about that and where
that fits in?
Sure.
So mirror descent, guided policy search is a technique for optimizing a very complex policies
like deep neural network policies by only using supervised learning to train the policy
itself.
And that sounds a little bit funny because if we're doing reinforcement learning, well,
that's not supervised learning.
So mirror descent, guided policy search sort of plays this game where it tries to figure
out what is the supervision that I can give to a supervised learning algorithm such that
when it trains some complex policy, that policy will do the right thing.
So it's like if you know that you're that only supervised learning is ever allowed to
touch the neural net, what can you give to the supervised learning algorithm so that it
does the right thing for solving a reinforcement learning problem?
And the way that the algorithm works is something like this that you're going to basically
have a model based teacher that's going to generate training data for your supervised
learning algorithm, so that model based teacher is, it's a kind of model based URL method,
but it's not a deep model based URL method.
It's just a, you can think of it almost like a, like a non-parametric algorithm.
So it'll look at a few different trajectories that you took, figure out how to improve each
of those individual trajectories by themselves without reasoning about any policies.
And then that will generate training data so that your neural network can be trained
with supervised learning to do better.
So instead of reinforcement learning, which looks at you at the parameters of your model
and says, how do I change these parameters to be better, in this mirror to send guided
policy search, it actually looks at the trajectories that you executed, fit some model figures
out how those trajectories should be improved, and then as those improvements as training
data for regular supervised learning.
That way the neural net is only ever trained with supervised learning and standard back
problem.
Okay.
But at a very high level, the reason that this procedure is efficient has a lot to do with
why model based our algorithms are efficient, because it really is a kind of model based
on real algorithms, it's just one that, under the hood, uses standard supervised learning
to train the policy neural network.
So there's another interesting paper I came across, and that was the one on policy sketches.
Can you talk a little bit about that work and what the goals are and what the results
were?
Yeah, I'd be happy to talk about that.
So that was worked by a student named Jacob Andreas, together with Professor Dan Klein,
who's another professor here at UC Berkeley, Jacob and Dan, they both worked on natural
language processing.
So the premise in that paper is that we'd like to see how symbolic descriptions of tasks,
you can think of these as very, very simplified natural language, how symbolic descriptions
of tasks can be used to improve learning.
And the key ingredient there is that we'd like to basically see how symbolic descriptions
can improve learning without assuming that those symbolic descriptions are grounded.
So without assuming that the agent already understands what the symbols mean.
So if you, let's say go to a foreign country, let's say you don't speak French and you go
to France, and someone tells you, in French, how to, let's say, make a piece of furniture
out of wood.
And then they tell her how to make another piece of furniture out of wood, and then they
tell you how to make a bench out of wood.
Well, listening to those descriptions, you'll probably notice some common patterns.
You'll probably notice that some words repeat, and if you hear enough of these descriptions
and you actually perform those tasks and you kind of understand physically what it means,
you'll find those patterns, even if you don't actually speak the language, and eventually
when you hear a new phrase describing new items that you can construct out of wood, for
example, you might be able to put the pieces together and figure that out more quickly.
So that was kind of the idea that we were working with.
So what Jacob did is he constructed this sort of simplified version of a Minecraft video
game.
So it's like a little crafting video game.
It was simplified because we didn't want to deal with vision, we just wanted to deal
with kind of simple kind of top-down navigation problems.
And it had these tasks that were like, you know, pick up the wood, or chop it on the
tree, pick up the wood, make the chest, for example, chop it on the tree, get the wood,
make a boat, or, you know, grab the coal, put it in the oven, and so on.
And there was a long list of these different tasks that the agent could perform that were
constructed out of these symbolic verbs, essentially.
And the agent would be given a set of these tasks, it would learn them.
And the symbolic descriptions would just be given as an additional input.
So they would result in some decomposition of the neural net, but there's actually
different ways you could do that.
But essentially they would be provided as an input to the agent without telling it what
those symbols really mean.
And just by learning the different tasks with the different symbolic descriptions, it
could actually figure out how to then use new symbolic descriptions to solve new tasks
more quickly.
Interesting.
It's funny when we talk about learning objects, object detection, and images, you know,
the amount of data that is required to train a neural network to figure out what an object
represents seems so large compared to our ability as humans to do it.
This is an example where I would need at least a million examples of the French sentence.
So not knowing if I didn't know French, you know, I can imagine needing a ton of examples
of training examples for myself to be able to figure out the language and then how to
put that together to make some furniture.
But you know, if you spoke Spanish, you'd probably figure it out much more quickly.
And that's true.
Ah, this is true.
And I think that actually there's something to that as far as how the learning-based systems
can work better.
I talked before about multitask learning.
And one of the things that distinguishes humans from these learned models that humans
are actually always doing multitask learning, we're always doing multiple things at once.
We're looking for things in our environment, doing something, we're worrying about we're
going to have for dinner, we're worrying about some other stuff, we're observing some
interesting, you know, car that we see on the road over there, we're always doing many,
many things.
And perhaps a lot of our efficiencies actually down to this fact that we're never learning
anything truly from scratch.
Because we're learning so many things all at once, any new thing that we have to do,
we get a broad basis of knowledge in which to draw to figure out that new thing.
So in a sense, perhaps what we're doing is we're actually extremely broad kind of multitask
learners.
And maybe that's a big part of how we get that efficiency.
And what's the relationship between multitask and transfer learning?
Well, monthly task learning is one of the ways to get transfer learning.
Right, so in multitask learning, we're learning multiple things in parallel.
And in transfer learning, we are transfer learning is a broader idea that includes taking
pre-trained models and using them, applying them to other things.
I guess the direction that, you know, the curiosity that has been peaked is like, how do
we combine all of these things to, you know, make our ability to train these models even
faster?
Right, well, so one of the things we've been looking at quite a bit actually is how we
can use past experience to accelerate future learning so that we've worked on this in the
context of reinforcement learning, supervised learning, and so on.
There are a number of ways you can approach that problem, but they all sort of boil down
to some version of looking at your past experience, breaking it up into, you know, little
pieces of training data, little pieces of validation data, trying to build your model
such that when it sees that little training data, it'll do well in that little validation
data and do this many, many, many times so that you get a model that's basically good at
quickly adapting to small training sets.
There are different ways that you can construct these types of models that, you know, many
other groups and end us have looked at, but that's sort of the big picture setup.
These are sometimes called metal learning algorithms.
I think that's actually an extremely promising direction for the future to really take deep
learning methods beyond this regime of always relying on really gigantic data sets.
And I think it goes hand in hand with multitask learning that basically that the way that we
can get to the kind of efficiency that we've seen humans is by solving many tasks, solving
those tasks in a metal learning context so that we're using the our past experience of
solving old tasks to accelerate the solving of new tasks.
And then when we encounter new tasks that we hadn't seen before, we'll generalize and
quickly adapt to them.
And does multitask learning necessarily imply a single network across all of the tasks or
are there variations there?
There are definitely variations.
So one of the things that we've studied actually as well as several other groups is how we
can construct actually modular networks.
So networks that will have some components that are shared and some components that are
distinct between tasks.
And the nice thing when you build modular networks, actually the policy sketches paper you
mentioned is an instance of this that also had modular networks.
And you have modular networks.
One of the things that you can observe is that there will actually be kind of interfaces
that emerge naturally between different modules.
So in a robotic context, let's say you might have a module for perception and maybe you
have one module for a color camera and a different module for LiDAR.
And then you have a module for actuation for a robot with four links and a different module
for actuation for robot with three links.
And you can mix and match any combination of these.
You can say, OK, here's a LiDAR robot with four links.
Here's a RGB camera robot with three links.
Train different combinations of these modules.
And then you can actually find that you might get generalization to new combinations of
sensors and robots.
And you can figure out that bottleneck between the two modules actually constitutes a kind
of a learned interface.
Because different modules, they have to basically adopt the common interface because they don't
know who's going to be downstream from them or who's going to be upstream.
And at the systems level, what are the implications of that?
Is it then easy to take one of these modules and drop it into another system or does it
not quite work like that?
Well, I think that's part of the hope.
So I think we haven't seen that yet.
But in the long run, that's, I think, one of the really interesting things about modular
network designs is that perhaps it could actually be possible to use this as a way to combine
the benefit of intent learning with the benefit of modularity to be able to actually train
up some component, let's say, if you're doing autonomous driving, you train up a particular
vision component on one car, maybe supplement it with image net data, and then you just drop
it into a different car.
But then that different car has its own modules for, let's say, controlling the acceleration
or something like that.
So I think that that's part of the hope we're not quite there yet.
This work is still in fairly early stages, but I think that's definitely a really exciting
place that this kind of stuff could go.
The scenarios you just described were all end-to-end trained, at least in the initial system,
they're end-to-end trained as opposed to training module at a time, is that, right?
Right.
So that's actually the, that's the nice thing about modular neural networks as opposed
to modular anything else is that neural networks can be composed.
So if you have a modular neural network, you can still train the whole thing, a combination
of multiple modules end-to-end.
Now when I say end-to-end, there could be different ends, so end-to-end could mean that your
vision system is simultaneously trained on image net recognition and feeding the right
visual representation to a downstream control module to perform some task.
Yeah, it's interesting.
So the general question that I want to get out here is, I think the basis that you've
laid out for end-to-end robotic learning makes a ton of sense.
At the same time, when I talk to folks in industry about how they're using neural networks
in deep learning, and I present this vision of, hey, we're just going to have this one
uber neural network that can figure everything out, invariably, I get back some reaction
that's like, no, no, no, we don't do it like that at all.
It doesn't work.
It's too hard.
How do you account for the gap there?
Do you see similar things, I guess, for one, and how do you account for that gap?
Well, I think one way to look at it is it's a little bit like the difference between gasoline
cars and electric cars.
So it's very difficult to, right now, or maybe even like five years ago, to make the case
that, well, everybody should have electric cars because gasoline cars are really good.
We've been designing them and improving them for almost a century.
So of course, you build the first electric car that's not going to be as nice as a gasoline
car that's benefiting from all those decades of engineering, but I think the technology
is progressing.
So I think the reason that you hear, especially, you know, it's certainly in robotics that
we get this a lot, that you'd like to be able to use something like a manually designed
motion planner on top of your learned computer vision system because that motion planner is
really good, like it's benefited from decades of development.
So that's, I think, maybe the explanation.
Now, the solution, I'm not sure.
I think there are a couple of possible solutions.
One solution is that, well, maybe we should see what makes that really nice, manually designed
component work so well.
Can we incorporate that into a learning system or can we use it as part of an intent system?
So can we use that manually designed, let's say, controller, differentiate through it,
compute gradients and use those to improve our vision system?
Or maybe we just need to make a little more progress in reinforcement learning to the
point where we can replace that component without a loss of capability.
Right.
Great.
Any other things that you wanted to cover?
No, I think that's everything on my hand.
Fantastic.
Well, what's the best way for folks to catch up with you to learn more about what you're
up to?
I know you've got a webpage on the Berkeley site that will include a link to in the show
notes.
Are there any other ways for folks that you'd like folks to get in touch with you?
I think my website is a good place to start.
Also for anybody who is interested in learning about deep reinforcement learning, we do have
a course that I and Chelsea and our colleague John Showman taught at UC Berkeley, and that
all that material is online.
So if you search for Berkeley deep reinforcement learning course, you can find all those
lectures.
That can also be a good resource.
But yeah, for getting in touch with me, definitely my website will be a place to start.
Fantastic.
Well, I'll make sure I include the link to the course in the show notes as well.
And thank you so much for being on the show.
Thank you.
Thanks, sir.
All right, everyone.
That's our show for today.
Thanks so much for listening and for your continued feedback and support.
For the notes for this episode, to ask any questions or to let us know how you like the
show, leave a comment on the show notes page at twomolai.com slash talk slash 37.
For more information on industrial AI, my report on the topic or the industrial AI podcast
series, visit twomolai.com slash industrial AI.
The report is complete and it's beautiful.
And I'll be notifying folks who sign up at that page.
How they can receive a copy of it shortly.
Once you're done with this show, take 30 seconds to head over to twomolai.com slash AISF
to enter our giveaway for a free ticket to the AI conference in San Francisco in September.
You could be one of two lucky winners.
Thanks again for listening and catch you next time.