Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimal Talk, the podcast where I interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host, Sam Charrington.
This is the second show in our series of podcasts from the recent Wrangle Conference.
As you might know, a few weeks ago I was in San Francisco for Wrangle, which is a great
little conference brought to you by our friends over at Claudeira.
Wrangle is such a fun event each year.
It brings an interesting and diverse community of data scientists to an intimate and informal
setting for great talks on real data science projects and issues, not to mention Cowboy
Hatson BBQ.
If you haven't caught the first episode in our Wrangle series, Twimal Talk No. 39 with
Drew Conway.
You'll want to be sure to check that out.
It's a great interview and the intro includes important announcements about this series
as well as our latest ticket giveaway, our online research paper discussion group, and
my email newsletter.
The show you're listening to now features my interview with Sharath Rao.
I reached out to Sharath about being on the show and was blown away when he replied that
not only had he heard about the show, but that he was a fan and an avid listener.
My conversation with him digs into some of the practical lessons and patterns he's learned
by building production ready, web scale data products based on machine learning models,
including the search and recommendation systems at Instacart.
A quick note before we dive in, as is the case with my other field recordings, there's
a bit of unavoidable background noise in this interview.
Sorry about that, and now on to the show.
All right everyone, I am here with Sharath Rao.
He's an engineering manager at Instacart, and we are on location at the Wrangle conference,
and Sharath has a talk later on, and I'm fortunate enough to have him here to tell us a little
bit about what he's going to tell the Wrangle audience about.
So Sharath, welcome to the show, it's great to have you.
Great, thanks for having me Sam, I'm a big fan of the show from having heard earlier episodes.
Nice, nice, well I really appreciate that.
As you know, one of the places I like to get started then is to have folks introduce
themselves, tell us a little bit about what you're up to, and how you got there.
Yeah, yeah definitely.
So I'm at Instacart, I've been here for a couple of years, Instacart is an on-demand grocery
delivery service, and my role here is, I started off as the data scientist or machine learning
engineer focused on search personalization and recommendations, and now I do that, but
also lead a team that is working on that effort.
So prior to this, I've spent time at a couple of companies doing search, advertising,
and auctions, that sort of stuff over the last 10 years.
And even going back further, grad school, I worked on speech recognition and speech translation
before it was practically useful in the field.
That's part of the reason why I started working on other things after grad school.
So yeah, so that's probably captures the range of things.
Awesome, awesome.
I hear a lot of stories from folks who, you know, I was working on this stuff in grad school
and it just wasn't ready, or we were in the middle of the AI winter, and it kind of went
into hibernation.
And now that we're all so focused on doing this stuff, it's like time to dust off those
skills.
Absolutely.
Yeah.
So in your description, you said data science, slash machine learning engineering, how
evolved is the distinction between the two of those at Instacart, and do you consider
yourself as spanning both?
Yeah, let me take the first one first.
I think at Instacart, well, or was industry, I think we are moving better, you know, towards
understanding these two roles.
And so at least we are sort of settling around maybe three roles, actually data analysts,
data scientists, and data engineers.
Even if they're slightly called separately, I think maybe their companies like maybe LinkedIn
or maybe NB where probably have data scientists and machine learning engineers and data engineers.
But broadly, the difference is around, you know, people working on data products, building
systems and algorithms, essentially things that are consumed by other algorithms and systems
who might be like machine learning engineers, people working on things, the output of which
is used for, you know, decision making, you know, by the team that they serve or the executive
leadership.
We call them data analysts at Instacart, but data scientists elsewhere, and then finally
data engineers who are working on like platform infrastructure typically comes in, you know,
maybe later in the company stage.
Right.
I think it's a lot of progress we've made from just a few years ago, and, you know, data
scientists was this unicorn that no one could really hire because we've defined it in
such a way that, you know, it requires these disparate skills that, you know, aren't traditionally
paired.
Yeah, I remember back in maybe 2012, 2013, the term of unicorn data scientist was probably
one that captures what he just described, but I don't hear that too often.
There's more like specialization and people understand that over time, most professions
end up specializing, although I'd imagine, in depends on the context of the companies,
I would imagine say startups, if they're hiring their first data scientist, they probably
want somebody who can also do like the other two things that are reasonable level of competence.
Overall, in a macro view, I think, the roles have sort of specialized over time.
Yeah.
And I remember back in that same time period, 2012, I think as a community, we thought
that it would take way longer for us to reach this level of maturity, because like you'd
see these stats that say, you know, we're going to have, you know, we're going to be under
resource in terms of the number of data scientists until like the year 2050 or something like
that.
I think this specialization has been part of the key for alleviating that stress, although
we're far from having enough, you know, people with data competencies to meet all the
demand.
Right.
I think every speaker at an event like this gets up and says, oh, and by the way, we're hiring.
Yes.
Right.
Yeah.
So I've heard that and also more recently I've heard about and maybe even seen it in
the field where there's, you know, with, you know, obviously the market has responded to
at least a perceived lack of, you know, strong talent.
And so we have quick, like smaller one of your masters or bootcamps that have served the
need.
So as a result, I think in maybe in some part of the market, they might, maybe at like
optimum or even oversupply of, you know, data scientists at arguably at starting level.
Really?
Well, that's happening quickly.
Maybe I mean, just generally that I guess everything is moving faster and now even for
example, with newer areas around, say, deep learning and AI, there is, you know, there
are more research institutes, there are more, again, training, you know, workshops and
so on that people respond faster to needs than maybe they used to.
Mm-hmm.
Interesting.
All right.
So you talk.
Yes.
You've got to talk in an hour.
Yeah.
What's your talk about?
Sure.
So my talk is title lessons from integrating data, machine learning models into data products.
So initially I had a two part talk, but you know, today I'm talking about like the part
one of that.
But really the, the genesis of that comes from having worked at first of all, you know,
relatively a smaller company as opposed to some of the bigger companies that were in
we have, there is a product per se and there are machine learning models that are integrated
into various parts of the product that are making different decisions for the customers.
So there's that and then there is aspects about like data scientists building models, model
prototypes and even productionizing them, but also interfacing with product engineers
within a single team.
And the fact that what I call like all model, all model prototypes look familiar, but every
model and production is unique in its own way.
So I'm trying to understand, try to frame a conversation about what does it mean to have
a model and production?
You know, what are the questions to ask yourself and how do we communicate as data scientists
with in a product managers and product engineers about what this model does, what are its requirements,
what are the constraints?
And so that's, that's what I'll be talking about.
Okay, so how do you, how do you structure walking people through that?
Yeah, I try to keep it, try to find, you know, going back to conversations within the
team, for example, each time we, we have one team that has, you know, three or four product
engineers, you know, a couple of data scientists in a designer and a PM, right?
And largely most of the work happens, you know, within the team.
And each time we work on an experiment or a feature that that data's data scientists build,
we have this conversation about how will this go into production?
And typically the conversations, you know, if you think about it like the process of building
a model, thinking about a problem, building a model prototype, largely happens, you know,
within the domain of data science and maybe, you know, with some interaction at the PM.
But the moment it goes into production, it's now touching like so many different parts
of the system.
And, you know, a couple of things come in like, how much time do we have to make, make
a decision in terms of like the model, you know, running in production, you know, many
if you're serving up pages live to the web, you know, you've got to serve, yeah, serving
latency, for example, yeah, address right?
Yeah, so there's a constraint that very often gets dictated by the product itself and
rightly so.
And then there's this question of, you know, for the model to be successful, how much information
does it need?
And how can I get that information?
By information, I mean like, for example, let's say you're trying to recommend a product.
Maybe you definitely need to know if you want to, you know, it's a personalized recommendation,
you need to know the user, you know, user identity of their past data, you probably need
to know like what page they're on and so on.
But do you really need to know their recent searches and, you know, recent activity, like
that certainly is like short-term context.
So how much context do we need, does the model need rather to operate successfully?
Both of these sort of give you a way to think about, can I cash my recommendations?
You know, what can I cash versus what needs to be served in real time?
If it's real time, can I do a reasonably well if, you know, let's say, let's say I'm making
a decision about what product to show based on things that you've added to the cart recently.
So think of a model that is continuously producing a, you know, prediction of what, what part
is a good recommendation?
But it doesn't necessarily surface that.
It's always, you know, continuing to score and maintain a best estimate of a recommendation
in the background.
But, you know, at any point it's available with a best effort response.
So this is an example where you don't, you know, you have a good response whenever there's
a need for it.
We can wait until the last moment to actually serve that recommendation.
So those things that happen in the background.
Are you describing a system that is doing like online learning or active learning, which
is where you're updating your model kind of in place?
Well, yeah.
So the model could be static, model need not be updated, but the model predictions could
be happening continuously in the background based on, based on whatever data it sees.
It doesn't need to score in immediately reporting, it can keep scoring as it gets more data
and then always be ready to serve a recommendation when necessary.
Okay.
So that gives us like, you know, so we have this, you know, four quadrant because I'm considering
latency and context sensitivity of the model behavior.
And we get these four quadrants where, you know, you obviously have like high latency is
okay, but you have context sensitive and the other, basically, the other four possibilities,
other three possibilities.
And so it's part of what you've observed, then, you know, are we at the point of maturity
and thinking about this that, you know, for each of these quadrants, we've got like design
patterns or best practices that teams, you know, either at InstaCard or in the industry
are following?
Certainly, InstaCard, we try to place ourselves and don't like, where does this model sort
of lie, you know, just mentally and internally.
And that's sort of all, given that we've built a few experiences, few models over the past
a couple of years, we have patterns, you know, we know, we sort of know 90% of, you know,
the way the model is integrated in the rest of the product, when we are thinking about
the model, we don't have to like start from scratch each time.
So for example, search, search ranking, you know, we latency needs to be really low.
And context sensitivity, we can start off with, you know, low context sensitivity, I mean,
let's say you're simply matching the search query and the bunch of products without like
recent context.
If you could start there, then as we, the way to improve the model would be to, well,
continue to have latency requirement being low, but make it more context sensitive, obviously
there's a lot of work that might involve a model that is ranking, re-ranking products
based on, you know, recent activity.
So that's one example.
So with search, we start, I call it we start from quadrant four and go to quadrant one.
Sort of will be clear from the slides, I guess, but with the recommendations, it's almost
always the case that you start with, you know, in start in quadrant three, where you cache
as much as possible, you score them, you know, in batch mode, you cache them and then you
serve.
So that keeps, that gives you, you know, you can use as much information as you want,
and you know, gives you the latitude to use more data and have like recommendations.
The way to improve that would be to go from quadrant four to, or quadrant three to two,
I guess, where, you know, you still, you know, latency is still not a consideration.
You're re-ranking your products, your, you know, candidate products, and, you know,
in the background, be very, very, to serve.
And then finally, you might have like, you know, contextual recommendations wherein you
have to recommend something, you know, immediately, and so that becomes like a real-time recommendation,
which is, you know, a model that, you know, re-ranks a set of products that you've cached,
you know, based on the context.
So the set of products you've cached may be personalized or maybe not personalized, but
then when you serve, you re-rank it based on user activity and make it personalized.
Yeah.
So how much of this machine learning engineering is machine learning and how much is engineering,
meaning a lot of what we're talking about is, you know, system level, scalability, like,
you know, just hardcore software engineering that, you know, in a lot of ways is orthogonal
to the machine learning.
Well, I guess the model stuff isn't, but in a lot of ways it seems orthogonal.
There are principles at least that seem orthogonal to the thing that you're scaling, right?
It's, it's web-scale engineering, yeah, applied to M-O.
So like fine tune that statement, how much of it, you know, a specific is domain specific
and where are those points that it gets super domain specific?
That's a really good question.
And I think the point at which it gets domain specific is that, as a data scientist,
you understand the model, its assumptions, its requirements.
At what point, you know, it'll fail to perform.
What does it absolutely need?
What is table stakes versus, you know, what is a cherry on the top?
You understand that and you, well, you need to understand that and then articulate it
to, you know, product engineers and to others on the team.
Obviously, you don't want to do that right at the end when you've already built the model
but you want to do it right at the beginning so that you can know up front if there are
any constraints on the engineering side.
Right.
So it is sort of good mix of machine learning, you know, and software engineering.
And even product design, frankly, you know, I'd imagine we've one of one of the things
you found, for example, is we may have some latitude in how we change the product experience
for a user based on some of the constraints on the engineering and machine learning
side.
For example, if you want to buy yourself time to be able to score, what would that interface?
What will we do with the customer at that time?
How do we design the product experience?
Yeah.
Interesting, I've been, I've talked to a few people about this, like, I think there's
an evolving field of like, I always call it intelligent design but that's like way over
loaded but there needs to be, and I think there will be, you know, some, you know, thought
best practices for lack of a better term, like just a way of thinking about designing
kind of in light of machine learning and intelligence and things like that, that, you know, I don't
see a lot of people talking about that kind of stuff yet.
And it's not necessarily exactly what you're describing here, what you're describing is
even, you know, kind of going back to the previous question, it's really more the interaction
between, you know, design and product engineering and like performance engineering and things
like that, like how does our, how does the system, how does a user experience change because
of the limitations, you know, in, you know, performance and product engineering and stuff
like that?
Yeah, I definitely think it's definitely controversial to suggest that we have to change user experiences
to work with the limitations of, you know, engineering or machine learning, right?
And it may not be common to do that but I wish I had like more examples where it's
possible to do maybe, maybe it's not something that we generally talk about, if indeed it happens
in the field.
And that's the other thing, which is like, it's hard to talk like about machine learning
models and production, widely, simply because there are a lot of details that are probably
very specific to the product and, you know, one just assumes that it's not interesting
to somebody else or that these details don't really generalize.
So there is no, there are definitely basic principles, you know, software engineering,
but beyond that are there other principles that are specific or that are more important
when it comes to like software engineering with like machine learning systems or data products.
So I called out a couple of examples of some work in the community like recently, maybe
about early this year, there was a document from one of the machine learning engineers
at Google about, I think it's called rules of machine learning or so.
It talks about a really nice, what I think is it quite reading for data scientists building
data products.
And what are the different things, what are the different trade-offs, what are different
stages of building a data product?
And talks a lot about the engineering aspects, the training, the data management, metrics,
the interface between like metrics and our model formulations and so on.
It's kind of like, you know, it's a four-page PDF with such a density of knowledge.
Like, at Instacard, we had like a reading group session, we spent like, I let a group
with like two hours of going through that and they're talking through like salient ideas
from that paper.
Okay.
Well, I have to make sure I get a link for that one and post it up in the show.
Definitely, yeah.
There's one more people that are like, quickly, which from Pinterest, where they talk about
the evolution of the recommendation systems over three years.
And this is, it's a really good one, I think.
It talks about, incidentally, it talks about how they started it off with a simple system
that was like caching recommendations of the Quadrant 3 world.
And then from the how they progress from that to, you know, Quadrant 1, where they use
what you get, what you cash, and then you re-rank it with a model.
It's helpful to have this, you know, view of how this really massive, you know, at-scale
recommendation system evolved so that, you know, people who haven't done that before
don't need to believe that we need to start with what Pinterest has in production after
three years of work.
Right.
So, it's sort of underappreciated part of literature, I think.
Yeah.
So, this is maybe a little bit of a tangent, but I don't know if you've heard on some
recent podcasts I've mentioned that I'm going to be starting a, like, an online paper
reading group of podcast listeners.
I mentioned it randomly in a podcast, and like, there were a bunch of people who expressed
interest in it.
So, I'm going to be getting that kicked off, but since you mentioned that you are involved
in one at Instacart, any tips for running a paper reading group?
Great.
So, yeah, let me see.
We have, like, two different sessions where all the data scientists come together, you
know, sort of alternate weeks, and one of them is, or the one that I was talking about,
we call that lunch and learn, we have, we do it over lunch every Tuesday.
And the bar, in a sense, is that, you know, I had a time we talk about, like, what paper
we are, what somebody is going to lead a discussion.
That person doesn't need to have completely understood, but it's helpful for them to be
able to know enough to drive the discussion.
It's obviously optional for, you know, people who want to attend, because, you know, we
have, we touch different domains in Instacart so somebody may not be particularly, you know,
keen on a paper.
And, but then it helps to have, like, discussion, you know, if you come in, make sure you've
skimmed the paper and come in for discussion.
We talk about what the paper, some of the, you know, what it takes away from the paper,
and also, like, how that immediately might apply to what we're working on, you know, in
our regular work.
How long did they turn around?
It's a one-hour, and we typically have anything from, like, eight to twelve people and
odd, you know, group, you know, I would say maybe, like, four to five of them will live,
like, let's put the paper a little bit.
Yeah.
But I think these are opportunities for people to not just learn, but also lead a discussion
and people get better at it as they go.
Yeah.
Okay.
Well, I'm really looking forward to it.
And, like I said, a lot of people, a lot of other people seem to be looking forward to
it as well.
Yeah.
Also, have you joined us and then walk us to a paper over here of your choice?
Really, yeah, definitely.
Yeah, I think it's very common in, like, grad school and, like, research labs to be,
like, doing this, like, reading the paper is an art and understanding, like, what is
the next, what are the assumptions, what are the achieved, what are the opportunities
from here, like, how can we build on that, what is relevant to us, how hard is it to reproduce,
you know, in our environment, right, that, you know, what are the generalizable lessons,
so to speak.
Yeah.
Those are sort of the questions we are thinking about.
So, kind of going back to your presentation, what are the generalizable lessons from your
presentation?
Sure.
So, one of them is to think deeply about how the model integrates into your product.
Have the discussion ahead of time with people outside, you know, your own group, like, off
data scientists, maybe, you know, product managers, product engineers, like, the kickoff
meetings should probably talk about that.
And at what level are you having that conversation, because there's integration from a perspective
of data, there's integration from a perspective of data sources, APIs.
Yeah.
Generally, at the level of APIs.
Okay.
And it's also a way to sort of get a buy-in from product engineers, build that relationship
so that, you know, think shouldn't look like you're just throwing things or the fence
to the engineer and asking them to, like, productionize it.
I think, for them to understand it in a way that is at a level that they can even provide
an input to and, you know, contribute to improve the design, like, the technical implementation
would be helpful.
And I picked out, like, two different aspects of, like, latency and context sensitivity.
There might be others.
I mean, I picked up two and I got a four quadrant hub.
Yeah.
We can pick, look at, you know, more aspects of it that are generalizable across models.
And, yeah, this, I hope it sort of evolves into a discussion about how we can, you know,
we have ways to talk about model prototypes, you know, how a problem is set up and how
training data is generated, you know, at someone, you know, the model is fit and we persist
the model we have, you know, abstractions about what happens, you know, in training phases.
But abstractions that help us understand how a model is, you know, being served or the
model predictions are being served and, you know, how it's actually executed and implemented
might be helpful.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah, I keep coming back to this idea of design patterns, like, you know, you may be familiar
with the gang of four design patterns book where there's, you know, they've cataloged,
I don't remember the year, but, you know, cataloged a lot of, I've been oriented design
principles.
Like, are we there yet with machine learning or?
Great question.
And I think I probably had a, I tweeted this question a few, maybe, maybe a year ago,
like, what sort of abstractions do we have for, you know, serving machine learning models
in production?
Right.
I don't know if any that is, that substantially builds on, like, you know, software engineering
patterns, like, or I don't know if anything that the community has agreed on.
I'm sure there are a lot of things that in people's heads.
Yeah.
And a little bit of that I'm talking about today will be about, like, what I, you know,
we've seen and working in our team.
But going back to the Google doc, I think that, again, although it talks about more than
just serving, I think we need more of that in the community, yeah.
To mention that there isn't enough generalizable because things are just too coupled with the,
with the product is probably not, not true.
Hmm.
Yeah, you made an interesting comment early in the conversation about how you have a lot
of these machine learning models in production, but they, you know, at some level, they all
seem like snowflakes, I guess, is what I took from that.
And that, you know, it's been, it's been an effort and a challenge to kind of extract
the general principles from across these different environments, is that kind of what you
were getting at?
Yeah.
Insofar as we're talking about, like, implementation.
Right.
Yeah.
That's all in different problems, but there might be, like, in terms of, like, software
engineering patterns, they share, like, some of these aspects that they then, in one
of these quadrants.
And are there common implementation slash architectural patterns that, you know, that are kind
of assumptions for you guys that, you know, you're doing across all, at least all new
efforts.
Like, for example, microservices, are you doing microservices, containers, are you doing
containers?
Like, does any of that, where does the kind of evolution of the state of the art and, you
know, software engineering for non-ML stuff intersect with ML stuff?
Good question.
And, well, at the early point, yeah, we have services that are, well, we can call them
microservices, I guess, but, yeah, we have, you know, engineers, product engineers and
mission engineers agree on, you know, certain contracts.
And so that is, like, table stakes.
There are questions about, like, what can we cache, what can we not cache?
There are questions about, well, yeah, how long can we cache something, you know, what
sort of, what sort of data stores we might use, and what is configurable, what is not, what
is, yeah, what is an experiment versus what is not.
Most things are experiments, how much do we expect to iterate on this feature before,
you know, we think we're done for a while, which is, I think, for a company like Instacart,
where there are a lot of different places we can invest in.
It might be, like, quite a few months before we come back to, you know, we too of something
that we built.
Yeah.
Because, you know, we're still exploring the space of areas where machine learning can
help, and, you know, where help the most, I guess, yeah.
But do you, to a point about, like, beyond software editing, what is new, yeah, I don't
think I have an answer right now.
Okay.
To follow up on your last comment on just the opportunity prioritization, at Instacart
are you generally taking an approach of, like, trying to take on, you know, big moonshot
types of problems and, you know, make a few small big bets to kind of, you know, ensure
that your resources are focused on, you know, these things that could have outsized
an impact, or is it more, you know, we're going to try to, you know, we're going to try
to touch, you know, broadly, you know, in, you know, high impact, but more concentrated
ways to kind of spread that impact around, you know, the systems in the various business
teams and processes.
Yeah.
I think there's probably the, there's a top down and bottom up in terms of what sort of
projects get worked on and explored, you know, within, you know, within, say, data
science for, just to stay in data science for a moment.
So we have company goals about, like, what are we, quarterly goals, long-term goals,
translate the company goals, which typically talk, you know, are aligned to some metrics,
and, you know, different teams should know how they can move certain metrics.
And, you know, there is, and then we think about, like, what sort of a data science effort
could serve that metric.
So there's that.
What I call the bottom up is, well, you know, in the end, we are still, we are e-commerce,
but also last mile, you know, logistics operation.
So naturally with that domain, some problems just are there.
Like if you have e-commerce operation, you have a search engine, and if you have a search
engine, you're probably working on, like, you know, spell correction and autocomplete
and, you know, search ranking, matching, business understanding, the queries better,
and recommendation systems and so on.
So we already know, given the kind of data we have, and we collect, what sort of problems
have been addressed, like, what sort of product features have been useful, in that sense.
So between the top down and bottom up, I think we generally find, you know, tactically projects
to work on, you know, given, you know, current goals, yeah.
And oftentimes, you know, we hit, like, dimension utilities, soon enough for plateau,
soon enough, maybe in the first version, we might wait for, like, a while before we come
back to it.
Okay.
Interesting.
Well, I think you've got a presentation to get ready for, but I really appreciate
you taking the time to chat with us, and I'm looking forward to your talk.
Sure.
Thank you, Sam.
Thanks, sure.
All right, everyone, that's our show for today.
Thanks so much for listening, and for your continued support of this podcast.
For the notes for this episode, to ask any questions, or to let us know how you like
the show, leave a comment on the show notes page at twimmelai.com slash talk slash 39.
Thanks again to our sponsor for the Wrangle Conference series, Cloud era, to learn more
about Cloud era and the company's data science workbench family of products, visit them at
cloudera.com, and be sure to let them know how much you appreciate their support of the
podcast by tweeting to them at at cloud era.
If you're interested in joining our first Twimmel online meetup, where we'll discuss
Apple's recent research paper on generative adversarial networks, you can register for
that at twimmelai.com slash meetup.
And don't forget to sign up for our email newsletter at twimmelai.com slash newsletter.
Thanks again for listening, and catch you next time.