Alright everyone, I am here with Yenshwai Tsau. Yenshwai is a senior research team lead at
Borealis AI. Yenshwai, welcome to the Twomol AI podcast.
Thank you for having me, Sam.
Awesome. I am really looking forward to digging into our conversation. We'll be talking
about Turing, which is a recent project that you've been working on that does text to
SQL. But to get us started, I'd love to have you share a little bit about your background
and how you came to work in machine learning.
Alright, so I did my undergrad at the University of Toronto in Computer Science and Math and
stats and I took a number of AI courses during undergrad and that gave me the opportunity
to work in the computer vision lab run by David Fleet at U of T. And so I did two summer
research projects there and afterward went down to do my PhD with David, close device
by her husband and did my PhD in actually in Gaussian processes, not in computer vision.
And so Gaussian processes is this class of Bayesian and parametric models that learn
very quickly from small number of data points and my work was focusing on scaling the
compute aspect of GP. And on the side, I also worked a little bit on adversarial robustness
of models. So this was the time when people just found out that you can actually apply
this imperceptible perturbation to images and then change the class labels. So we thought
that a, you know, can you change more than just a class label, can actually change the
features to make the features like, you know, another image completely, not just a change
label. And surprisingly, in terms of actually, you can, you can actually take a picture
of me and then apply a perturbation change the feature of me to look like a feature of
a car, for example, not just any car, but a particular car of particular color in that
pose, et cetera. And so that was very surprising at the time, but without, you know, this
adversarial robustness issue is going to be solved very quickly, but turns out to help
me more further from truth, things still consult the problem.
Do you still follow that space?
Not super closely, but it still motivates a lot of things that I do, especially later,
after I joined Borealas, you know, I look at that literature and people found out that
not only can do this on vision, you can do this on an LP as well. And obviously, there
the perturbation is not imperceptible, you know, change to pixels, but you add some extra
text. And also, you can do this in the physical world, apply some patches to images that
are not, you know, changing pixels, but some patterns that people don't pay attention
to. And so, and they're actually very hard to get rid of. So, so what that tells is this
old, you know, theoretical approach of studying and understanding this adversarial tax, we're
not actually capturing what really under the hood, like these people were considering
adversarial tax with like some sort of perturbation with in a ball centered at the image and then
look at the robustness model that way, but that clearly doesn't capture all the other
ones. And fundamentally what it looks like is what the model, how the model represent the
data, represent the word is different from human, you know, from people's representation
and they're not aligned. And it looks like their models are picking up on sort of a short
cause or a speed of correlations or other type of, you know, associations that, you know,
we don't use. And fundamentally, it looks like that's the problem. And, and it looks like,
you know, one has to really, you know, go beyond pattern matching to really, to be able
to get to the root of this problem. So, to look at, you know, model that can reason that
can try to discover the, you know, the type of relationship that people use in recognizing
understanding and reasoning. So, that was, that was my thought at the time. And I think
it was also, you know, thinking share by, you know, lots of people in the field. And so
that led me to work on an LP, because an LP is a lot closer to reasoning, I felt, because
language is already a model of the word. And, yeah, also because, for us, it's part of
a robot Canada. There's a lot of potential application of text of an LP inside a bank.
Tell us a little bit about touring and the motivation for it. How did the project get
started?
Right. So, touring is, is this natural language database interface? It's a demo of a natural
language database interface that we built. And it's really just putting a lot of our work
on semantic parsing this space together in this academic demo. So, natural language database
interface, the, from an application perspective, the, the potential users to allow non-technical
users to interact with structured data set, because there's a lot of insight in there.
And, you know, we want to give it opportunity for non-technical users to get those insights.
And, from a research perspective, it's a very challenging natural language processing
problem, because the underlying problem is you have to parse, question us in English
or any other natural language and, and convert to SQL. And, we all know natural language
is ambiguous. Machine language is all ambiguous. So, you have to resolve all the ambiguity
in order to parse correctly. Furthermore, what's different from something like convert to
Python or other program language is the mapping from patterns to SQL is underspecified if
you don't know the schema. It really depends on, you know, what is the structure of schema.
And so, so model has to really learn how to reason using it, and in order to resolve
all the ambiguity and correctly predict the SQL. And lastly, you know, this, you train
the model on some domain, you don't want to just work on this domain, you want to work
on domains and databases that you've never seen before. So, that's the cross domain,
cross database part of it. And that is a very, very challenging, because it's a completely
different distribution once you move to a different domain.
So we're talking about touring, you know, shortly after the release of OpenAI's Codex.
And so I imagine as you're talking to people about it now, that's a correlation that
folks make, because that project is also focused on code generation. I'm curious, you know,
if you might compare and contrast the different projects and, you know, maybe the complexity
of the challenge or, you know, different aspects that would help us understand how they,
you know, might be similar or not.
Right. So, first of all, Codex, I saw the demos, and the demos are really amazing and
impressive. I think if you look at the where it's applied, it's focusing on product language,
like Python, JavaScript, and all this language where you can find a lot of public, available
training data, like, you know, on GitHub and other sources. I think there are training
on code from GitHub. And so, the availability of data is a one major difference. When you
try to do SQL, as I said earlier, you really have to know the schema, right? There's not
a lot of training data for SQL, public, available, like, people don't post their schema online
generally. So, the amount of data is very, very small that can be used for, you know, even
for, like, modeling will SQL, you can't find a ton of it for training purpose. And so,
so that is, I would say, like, one major difference. So, that's also why Turing is a academic
demo that we built, where it's Codex, obviously, with the, you know, all more data, the model
is, it is, you know, fairly good, and you can build a product of it.
Okay. You mentioned earlier that one of the elements of this project is kind of reasoning
and reasoning on text, and that that's a fundamental aspect that allows you to transform
natural language to SQL. Can you talk a little bit more about the role of reasoning in
this problem? Right. So, so one of the aspects is what I mentioned earlier, like, it's
underspecified. And it's underspecified due to, you know, you have to, you know, really
leverage schema. And the other part is you have to really have common sense. A lot of times,
for example, if I say, you know, which cities have the most number of employees under 30,
under 30 that refers to age of employee. I assume that I have a scheme, a table with
age column. It's never mentioned explicitly. But, you know, the model has to learn to,
that under 30 refers to age and have to make that association. So, that's common sense.
And learning, you know, reasoning using schema, an example is, if there's textual evidence
for two of the tables, but these two tables are, you know, unrelated to each other, and
there's no foreign key links. And the model really has to look at how the schemas link
together, you know, the relationship of elements in order to infer that, hey, maybe there's
a third table that I need to bring in in order to produce the correct SQL. So, all of
this is an example where something is missing, causing it to be ambiguous. And the reasoning
feeling in this missing information allow the model to deconfond the relationship. Otherwise,
you know, if the information is not there, and the model can just pick up, you know, on
spherical correlations, shortcuts that makes learning possible during training, which
of course doesn't generalize, especially on a task like this, where you try to generalize
to a new domain, a new schema, and with very small amount of data.
And how is reasoning implemented in the model? Is it, it is something that's primarily
done at training time, and at inference time, it's a single step, a single step inference,
or is it more something that's done at inference time, where you're, you know, going through
multiple steps to try to reason about a particular query?
Right. So, there's few elements in the model that can, you know, that express some structural
prior about the problem that performs some form of reasoning. One is, you know, it's
overall, it's encoder decoder type of architecture, architecture on the decoder side. The decoder
actually knows the grammar of C-pole, and it's baked into the, you know, the decoder
knows has some sort of knowledge that we designed into the, into the model, and it leveraged
the grammar of C-pole to, to figure out at this step, what are the legal things that can
be produced, and that allows us to prune search space during inference, and during training
and, and it learns what are the things that are likely. And on the encoder side, it's,
the model is, is basically a transformer, but, you know, a special type of transformer,
uh, called a relational way of transformers, and can consider the different religions
of schema elements, and, uh, as well as, you know, association between the, the question
tokens with, with, with the, um, elements in the schema, like a table name, column name,
and you can give something, uh, prior knowledge about this, uh, foreign key relationship,
and, uh, some initial evidence about, uh, which token, the question is likely to be linked
to which column, uh, and, and then during training, uh, the model learns to basically clean
up the sort of relationship, and in, uh, during inference, it can basically, uh, starting
from an initial guess, and then try to refine, uh, the potential link, and then, uh, remove
some ambiguities. It's, uh, it's still some, I'll say it's still, um, rough form of, uh,
reasoning, it's, uh, obviously it doesn't capture all the different type of things that
we wanted to, to continue to do, but, uh, it already, uh, make a big, big difference.
Okay. Um, you, you talked about how you're part of what makes the model work, is that
you're providing information to the transformer during training. Can you talk about how
the, the data is prepared and generated to train the model? Uh, right. So, um, during training,
um, basically the model considers both questions and schema, and, uh, so, uh, the, uh, the, uh,
the model is actually a, uh, consists of a pre-trained, uh, deep transformer, like a Roberta,
and on top of it, it has some extra fresh layer of, uh, relational wear transformer
layers, and, uh, the relational wear transformer layers encode, uh, some prior knowledge, um,
between elements of, uh, you know, columns, relations, and, uh, words, and, you know, uh,
words in the questions, and, uh, words in the, uh, the column, uh, in the table, for
example, if, for instance, if we see a column, uh, in the questions, um, if we see a mention
of, uh, you know, a column of the, uh, name in the questions, it, it provides some initial
evidence, and so it has a link there, and, uh, during training, um, basically the model
tried to maximize the, uh, the, the correct, uh, prediction, and, uh, during that process,
it can learn to adjust the weight and, uh, uh, remove some of the, the noisy, initial
links. Um, so, so the relational layers aren't trained, those are, um, you know, built,
as priors, and then added to the transformer. Uh, the, they, they are trained. So everything
is okay. Okay. And, uh, the relational layers, um, they are able to take, um, so maybe
let me take a step back. But are they trained separately from the rest of the transformer?
Okay. Everything is trained together into end. Um, so maybe let me take a step back. So,
the transformer is generally like, they can encode, uh, basically, they encode the fully
connected graph, right? It, it looks, uh, if we ignore the position in bedding, it looks
like it considers the full sentence as, uh, as a fully connected graph, it's every word,
it's, it's, it's every word. And if you take a schema and, uh, say that you flatten the
schema, uh, into, like, uh, just a long stream, like, uh, question and put it together with
the, uh, with, with the, uh, with the, with the question and it looks, consider everything
as a fully connected graph. Um, what relational wear transformer does is, it, uh, as, you know,
some additional prior information saying that beside this, uh, fully connected, uh, knowledge
about, you know, everything could potentially be related to everything else. Uh, you know,
we have this knowledge of special links, like foreign, foreign key relations. And, uh, if
we see, you know, mention of, uh, car in the passion and, uh, there's a column, uh, called
a car type, uh, it's more likely that these two are related. So it, uh, makes this, uh,
as this additional inducted bias into the model. And later on during training, it can
refine what, uh, the initial given, uh, evidence into, uh, the, you know, try to infer what
is truly there. Okay. Uh, I think that, I think that's consistent with what I thought,
but I'm still not clear on the, you know, where does the initial inductive bias come from?
Is that trained, you know, separately or is that, uh, you know, baked in as kind of an engineering
process? Um, so the foreign key relations that's known from the schema and the initial, uh, link
that's, uh, given by some heuristics. So, so that there's some, uh, a little bit of engineering
there. Okay. But even if the schema link can miss some of the initial relations, it's able
to, uh, to, to, to, uh, pick those up and training. Yeah. Okay. Okay. Um, interesting. And so
then the, the entire model is kind of trained and to end, uh, you know, starting with those
biases and what are, and the training data, the training data set consists of, uh, set of
questions that are, um, appended, can catnated with schema information? Uh, yes. Uh, in a way,
there's more information, uh, like there's, uh, information about, uh, the, the, uh, the, uh,
the type of, uh, columns, uh, that can be used in there. Um, but, uh, uh, conceptually,
you can think of this as just a graph that, uh, the model looks at. So there's, uh, essentially
question, uh, natural language queries, plus, um, some features related to the, the database
essentially. Yeah. Is that right? Um, and the, um, um, there's a, uh, kind of a label that
is the query that you want returned. Is it the query, is it the query that you want to execute
or the results of the query, uh, against the database? It's the, uh, query that you want to ask
you. Okay. Okay. Um, there's, uh, so, so, um, uh, this system, we, we trended on this, uh,
public benchmark dataset called spider. Uh, it's, it's a very, uh, small dataset, uh, you know,
for, uh, from deep learning, you know, standpoint, it, uh, but because collecting data for this
generally is pretty hard. Spider is the de facto, you know, uh, benchmark dataset for this problem.
Mm-hmm. It has, uh, uh, 200 different databases, but overall, just, uh, a little bit over 5,000
queries. So it's, uh, it's a very small, uh, data problem. Uh, yet you have to learn to
generalize to complete new, uh, developments. Mm-hmm. And would it be practical? Would you think to train,
not on the query that you want, but on the resulting data so that, you know, you can get the same
data with many different queries and the database, some will be more optimal than others. Um, you know,
there's, you might want to let the network figure that out. Yeah. So, so there are other works, um,
uh, in this base that actually looks at, uh, use execution result. Okay. So, uh, it's, it's possible,
though you have to, um, either change how your model works. So, so your model still has to produce
these discrete objects that, uh, execute. Uh, and so you either have to change that to, to some sort
of, uh, differentiable structure, uh, or you have to, you know, use, uh, reinforcement learning or
other related, uh, uh, techniques to be able to do credit assignments through that. Um, um, so,
yeah, so, so it's possible other people have explored, um, on this problem, um, it doesn't, uh,
work super well, um, generally, um, but we are, we, we have explored, uh, combining with our
techniques and the denotation, the execution result to help, uh, perform data augmentation
afterward and that improves performance. So, in a way, yes, we are, uh, we have additional step that,
that, uh, can leverage the execution results. Okay. You mentioned, uh, a couple of things, one,
that the, the data set is, you know, fundamentally a small data set, uh, you just mentioned data
augmentation is one possible way to address that. Are there other things that you have done, uh, in,
in this project to kind of optimize the transformer model around the small data set problem?
Yeah. So, so, um, actually one of the, the key, um, difference that, uh, in our approach, uh,
so a lot of things that I mentioned, uh, previously was techniques that were already invented in,
in the field. So, so, relational wear transformer, we didn't invite, invent that, um, but we're,
you know, we, we found out is, uh, if you put a very deep relational transformer, um, you can train
it very well. Um, the models, uh, you know, even if it has ability to perform sounds or,
form of reasoning, if you can train it, then it's no use. So, so we found a way to, uh,
train deep transformers, uh, in the very small data set in the stable fashion. And, uh, so,
this is, um, very, um, you know, counter to what people used to believe, like, uh, you have,
you know, you, you, you train deep transformers, you have to have large data set,
um, yeah. With, with this technique that we, we came out, it's published that ACR this year,
uh, it's possible to train it in a stable fashion or small data set.
And so, what are the key elements of doing that? Right. So, um, it's, uh, in the nutshell,
it's, uh, it's a better way to initialize these models. Okay. And, uh, it also builds on
prior works that, uh, looks at, you know, initializing deep transformers models. And, uh, we're,
we're, you know, we make a big difference here is, uh, we make it possible to actually add
these layers on top of pre-trend and then train everything together. So, previous techniques that,
uh, improve stability of this transformers, they were only considering training from scratch.
But when you print on, on a small data set, you want to leverage pre-trend. You don't want to train
transformer, you know, a fresh transformer from scratch completely. But the previous techniques
just doesn't work when you have, you know, put the new layers on top of a, uh, pre-trend bird or
Roberta. And, uh, in, in, in the nutshell, well, you know, the, how this works is, um, it turns out
the problem with deep transformer, with transformer training generally is the layer norm, uh, layer.
And, uh, previous work have found out that, you know, if, if you can remove that somehow and, uh,
still make training stable, the performance is much better. And training transformer generally
require you to, like, have layer norm large batch size and learning rate warm up. It turns out
you want to remove layer norm, uh, don't do warm up. And here, you know, on small data set,
you have to use small batch size. So we make all, you know, these three possible.
And when you say you make all those three possible, how do you, how do you do that?
Right. So, um, the, um, basically in the nutshell, the idea is, um, you want to, there are
certain parameters that are, uh, in the transformer, either read vanilla transformer or relational
wire transformers, uh, you want to, during initialization, you want to scale them by a factor that's
proportional to the depth. And in the paper, we have, uh, some derivation show exactly what that
scale factor is. Uh, in turns out, when you do this on top of a pre-trained model, that scale
factor, uh, needs to be data dependent. And so, so our matter is called the DT fix up,
um, data dependent transformer fixed update initialization. So when you do that, uh, the,
the, the, the model is initialized to, uh, basically, uh, in a stable regime, uh, for
optimization with, uh, Adam, and, uh, it doesn't also lead, which is the typical problem with, uh,
that learning rate, warm up, and later on, try to fix, but, uh, uh, fail set, uh, doing. So,
when you do all of this together, uh, you know, training is stable since the beginning, and you can
train your deep transformer, uh, we can, you know, the maximum we train was 48 layers on this small
dataset, um, with very small batch size. Uh, the overall dataset is, is just, uh, you know,
5,000 less than, you know, for training is less than 5,000 queries. So you can't use large,
very large batch size. So instead of the learning rate warm up and the layer norm and the large
batch size, you kind of substitute that with, uh, data aware initialization that sounds like it
does a pass on the data and then scales the parameters and set your initial weights and then
you get a stable result from the, uh, your training. Yeah. And, um, what's amazing is, um, once you
are able to train, uh, this in a stable fashion, the transformer plus relational wear transformer
can already perform a lot of the, you know, the, the reasoning it, the improvement on this hard cases
is, it's, uh, it's huge. So it turns out, it's, so, so what's, uh, the learning here is,
it's already, you know, this model can already do, uh, some form of reasoning like this,
it's just we're not able to trend them, uh, on this, uh, in a stable fashion.
Mm-hmm. And with the initialization approach, uh, and its data dependencies, is it, um,
did you find that it was broadly applicable to, uh, a variety of data sets or is it very specific
to the, you know, the benchmark data sets that you use or, you know, other, um, characteristics
of the data set? Right. So we, uh, we also tried this, um, a completely different, uh, problem,
but that also requires, uh, uh, reasoning. So, so a problem for logical reading comprehension.
Mm-hmm. So, so we actually did this after, you know, we made all this working, uh, on, on the
semantic parsing problem and we took that data set and, uh, it's also very small and very hard
problem and we just, uh, applied the technique and got, uh, very, very good results like, uh,
without any special engineering on the, on that task, we thought, uh, near state of art on that
problem as well. So generally, yeah, it, uh, it looks like it's, um, uh, obviously if, if your
data set is already huge and then you can use large batch size and, uh, that, that, that makes training,
you know, much more stable, but when you have small data set, you can't, you can't do that.
And we're the, uh, the data sets, the, the benchmark data set that you use, was that, um,
was that a multilingual data set or is it monolingual and, um, you know, what kind of support for
multilingual do you have? Uh, these, these problems are, are just, uh, English like the reading comprehension
and, uh, semantic parsing. But, but, uh, yeah, that, um, there, yeah, we, for, for semantic parsing,
there is, uh, another data set, but, but there, um, but, but there's no, uh, cross language.
At least in the, the, the popular ones for cross database and semantic parsing, there's not
simultaneous cross database and cross language. Mm-hmm. Is multilingual something that you're
looking at or interested in? Uh, yeah, I think it's, it's very challenging problem.
Um, uh, at the moment, we're not studying this, this problem, uh, is there, there are other like,
unresolved, uh, calendars.
Uh, let's talk a little bit about those. What are the kind of the big challenges are next steps
with this work? Right. So, so generally, um, you know, data, if you want to continue to improve
the accuracy, um, data is a problem. How to perform data augmentation in this space. Um, I think
that's, uh, that's a fundamental, uh, blocker. And we are looking at, uh, how to, uh, how to do that.
In fact, it sounds like you did a bit of data augmentation already, right? Uh, yes. Um, actually,
we, we, um, so for the non, uh, academic research part of this project, we actually done a lot of
data augmentation to make something like this work. Um, but it's, it's challenging. Um, so other people
who have done this, their, their technique is, um, to basically engineer some sort of a grammar
that can simultaneously produce, uh, seagull query and, uh, natural language, natural language.
But it's, it's very, very tedious hard task to do. And we, we actually also tried it. And that
was also, uh, our first intuition when it comes to do data augmentation in this, um, but to actually
engineer this grammar to produce questions that are very natural. It's, uh, it's very, very tough.
So, so how to do data augmentation without, uh, you know, going through
and engineer a, a generative model for this, basically. It's, uh, yeah. It's something that we're
looking into. And we have some working progress. It's not yet released that, uh, that allows us to
leverage, um, uh, you know, knowledge from pre-trained model to actually improve, uh, the,
effect, effectiveness of data augmentation. Um, and before we go to the, the next challenge, um,
the, the data augmentation conversation kind of sparked a question around the complexity of
the questions and the queries. Can you, uh, can you kind of speak to that and characterize the,
the level of complexity that the, that turns able to, um, to deal with?
Yeah. So, so in terms of query that can produce, it can produce, um, you know, queries that involve
joints, uh, multiple joints, uh, subperies. Um, so sometimes you have questions that are,
in English, very benign, very simple, like, um, this is not an example that our own shell spider,
but, but, you know, say, like, what's the average return of all the stocks that performed above
market average? So, so there's compositionality there. And, uh, market average referred to, like,
you know, actually, well, depending on the structural schema, well, will require you to first compute
that number by doing some sort of, uh, averaging, abbreviation, and the plug it into, you know,
the, the top level query. And, uh, turning is able to, to do things like, like this. And, uh,
also, obviously, it's also able to handle some of the other extreme, like, if you write questions in,
you know, very verbosely, you know, with lots of different conditions, uh, and, uh, you know,
it can, you know, handle a lot of that as well. Um, now, obviously, you know, it will have,
you know, mistakes, uh, it definitely is not, uh, yet a system that, uh, is quite a level of accuracy,
it's, you know, useful, uh, directly as, uh, you know, if you want to just trust the result,
extreme result, 100%, it, it's not quite there yet. That, that's also why, like, for the Turing
demo, uh, we built in some, you know, system, uh, in presenting the end result, we help user, um,
you know, really makes sense of the result and try to judge for themselves whether it's what they want.
So, so what do we do is, um, uh, Turing is able to produce multiple hypotheses,
uh, during its generation, and we explain the hypotheses back to the user in natural language,
um, and we highlight the difference across the different hypotheses, and then they can see for
themselves, okay, the difference between these three is, you know, instead of this column,
we mentioned that column, and here instead of this value, it's using some other value,
or maybe the overall just structure law is completely different, and, uh, then they can see
for themselves, which one corresponds to their, uh, intention originally, and can choose that.
Now that, that explainability model sounds like its own research project. Is that something you
worked on internally, or is that kind of an off-the-shelf technique that you're able to go by?
It's, uh, our, our own work. Okay. So, so that part is, um, so, so we had a number of different
publications at ACL this year, um, so the work on optimizing deeper transformers, that's one, uh,
paper, and the Turing demo paper actually consists of the core semantic parser, the component that,
you know, uh, tries to fill in the value after you get to the SQL sketch, and as well as the
explanation module, and the explanation module here, um, it's kind of different from normal
natural language generation, where you, you know, for, at least for research, there's a lot of, uh,
neural language generation. Here we actually don't, explicitly don't want neural language generation,
because we want, uh, you know, the difference across the hypothesis to be only due to the hypothesis
themselves, not that the natural language generation part. So we have a, a, a, a very, you know,
computer linguistics type of, uh, grammar-based model that can take the SQL and compositionally
produce the, the natural language explanation step by step, and the only difference there is due
to the difference in the SQL. Mm-hmm. And just to make sure I understand that, so you're the,
um, the, um, the explainer is explaining the result, not the process for obtaining the result.
All right. That interesting nuance. Um, um, it, uh, it doesn't sound quite like, you know,
not wanting to do generation, but it, it, it sounds like I'm wondering if, you know, there's
something, you know, missing in not trying to explain the process that won't capture, you know,
for the end user, what the model may have done to get to the result. But I don't, you know,
does it even matter? Uh, well, we think it doesn't, we think, because, um, normally, you know,
user just care about the final answer, right? So you, you can think of SQL as just some sort of,
uh, um, some sort of, uh, intermediate representation. Um, but this is an intermediate
representation that actually, you know, could potentially be aligned with how humans think about
the problem. This goes back to what I mentioned, you know, at the beginning, like, uh, you know,
the machines representation of the data of the domain of the world, how can we make that
align with people's representation? So there's a lot of intricacy of about how the neural net maps
the questions and the reason and maps to the final. But, uh, that details might not be interesting
to end user. Sort of like when you and I, we speak, I don't know, everything that goes on inside
the neurons of your brain, like you don't have shared language. And that description allows us to,
to have a shared understanding. Yeah. Maybe another way to put it, the, the problem that you're
trying to solve is that the machine is going to spit out SQL that the, the, the user didn't write.
And so the user may have some difficulty understanding what's actually happening. If you can explain
to the user what the SQL is doing, they can more easily determine if it's what they expected or
what they need. And it doesn't really matter what the network did to, uh, it's, that's not the
explainability problem that you're trying to solve. You're just trying to explain the end result.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. The intermediate result, not really the end result. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Um,
and you mentioned to some other challenges that you're looking forward to solving?
Uh, yeah. So, um, in terms of, uh, you know, how to, um, just, uh, so, so there's some,
some problems that, uh, in the field that people identify like, uh, you know, the cross-domain
generalization. So, despite our benchmark, uh, looks at, uh, cross-domain generalization already,
but it turns out when you're, uh, if you try to generalize to a different data set that are
collected different, under a different, um, policy like, uh, for data collection,
um, uh, the accuracy drop is, is pretty big as we all expect from engineering systems. Yeah.
Like, um, so, so how to, you know, um, you know, make a model more robust, you know, not, uh,
just, uh, across-domain, across, uh, database that are, you know, sort of more or less collect
under the same data collection protocol, but to, you know, things that are very different, uh,
in the wild, uh, that's still a big open problem. Mm-hmm. Possibly relating back to the data
augmentation problem as well, right? Yeah. Uh, yeah, that's, that's definitely a big part of it.
Awesome. Awesome. Well, Yenshwai, uh, thanks so much for taking the time to share a bit about
what you've been working on. It's very full-stop. Take our exercise and we're having it. Thank you.