All right, everyone. I am here with Michael McCourt. Michael is the head of engineering at Sigopt.
Michael, welcome to the Twomo AI podcast. Thank you, Sam. It's a great pleasure to be here today.
I'm really looking forward to our chat. We, of course, have chatted and met multiple times in person,
typically, but we haven't had the opportunity to get you on the show yet. That is changing now
to get us started. I'd love to have you introduce yourself to our audience.
Absolutely. How would your story, how'd you get started in the field?
You know, I've been very fortunate. I'm very fortunate to be here today because when I started out,
I was actually not doing ML at all. I was doing mathematics and I did undergrad and graduate
degree in mathematics undergrad at the Illinois Institute of Technology in Chicago grad school
at Cornell. And then as part of my graduate program, I actually had an opportunity to work
at Argonne National Labs, which is where I really got started doing a lot of high performance
computing, some heavy-duty writing software, which was a great opportunity to learn how to write
software as part of a big project. A project that a lot of people are contributing to and most
of it has been written before you even got there, which has been great prep for the work that I'm
doing now. After I finished a postdoc, also still doing mathematics, a friend of mine, Scott Clark,
who founded the company, Sigopt, reached out and said, Mike, started a company and we're working
on the same topic that you've been doing research on for a while. Now, I didn't appreciate that
at the time because I had just been doing in what in my mind was sort of pure mathematics or applied
mathematics. I often referred myself as a theoretically applied mathematician in the sense that I hope
somebody applies it, but it's not going to be me. And then I had the opportunity really to take it
and put it to use here, as part of my time at Sigopt, where we've been using some of the kernel
methods and Gaussian processes work that I had been working on for more of the mathematics and
the computational statistics side. And now I'm seeing it also put to work in the ML perspective
and having this new technology available to our customers so that they can have sort of as
good an experience as possible. So my own journey is a sort of a weird one, but I'm so so so so
fortunate to be here and be able to work with such amazing people and meet outstanding people in
the ML community, such as yourself, Sam. Awesome. Awesome. So Mike, one of the conversation topics that
I wanted to jump in with you is this broad topic of optimization. You spent a lot of time working
on that as the Sigopt broadly. And one of the questions that maybe a place to start is,
you know, how do you think about optimization relative to machine learning? Optimization
is obviously a part of machine learning, but it's also a standalone technique. How do you think about
the differences between these techniques and when and where they're applied?
Very, very intricate there. I think there's a lot of interplay between a lot of different elements.
At its core, I think some people might argue that machine learning is a
branchary, segment of statistical learning theory in sort of its core genesis. I think you can
also argue that nowadays machine learning also has obviously this very strong engineering
element to it. We're talking about the flow of data, data structures, the ability to deal with
not just noisy data, but somehow data which is beyond the scope of the core assumptions
in statistical learning theory. So as a result, I think there are a variety of even different ways
to just talk about machine learning as its own entity. And then in addition to that, you throw
in the topic of optimization, I think on one hand, there was a famous paper, if I recall correctly,
learning to learn by gradient descent. And that sort of was a cute play on words, but was a
fundamental point of discussion there. A lot of the time when we talk about many of these machine
learning methods, not all of them, but many of them, we ask ourselves, can we learn this not just
with the model, but with gradient descent. So when we talk about learning at all, in a sense,
what we are talking about is gradient descenting our way sometimes down to an answer. Now that's not
necessarily required. Of course, we could look at, let's say, linear or logistic regression,
there may be a closed form solution to that in a classical sense. I don't know if anybody would
still use that in a very large data setting, but that definitely exists. When we talk about support
vector machines, we might talk about quadratic programming. Quadratic programming is optimization,
but it's not necessarily gradient descent, or maybe there's gradient descent mechanism
for solving a quadratic program, but usually there's another mechanism for it. So there are,
I think, a variety of ways just to talk about optimization in as much as it supports the process
of learning. And then to push that a step further, of course, when I talk about optimization in
the context of sigopt, that's even another step beyond mathematical programming, beyond gradient
based optimization strategies. What we're thinking about inside sigopt, when we say the words
optimization or sample efficient optimization, what we're talking about really are problems where
we have no knowledge of the structure of the problem to do mathematical programming. You have to
have a solid knowledge of the structure, maybe that it's quadratic, or that the constraints
fit a specific format in a gradient based setting. You need that gradient information, at least
an approximation to it. Whereas when we're thinking about optimization here, it's more of an
aspiration. We're sort of saying, I aspire to find the optimum, but I don't actually have any
delusions of finding the optimum in any sort of finite or reasonable amount of time.
The goal for us when we do optimization is to try and identify as higher performing outcome as
possible, in as rapid a fashion as possible. But without necessarily any real guarantees of
performance. Now, there are some great articles that are talking about performance guarantees
or regret minimization for Bayesian optimization. There's some fantastic papers. I think the ICML
2020 test to time paper, 2021 test to time paper this year was the article talking about
defining regret in a Bayesian optimization setting through the banded literature. So I think
that there is an opportunity to do that, but from a practical circumstance. When we talk about
optimization for what we are doing, we're not talking about optimization for the purposes of
learning an ML model. What we're usually talking about is optimization, maybe for this tuning
process. And in addition to that, optimization that uses learning itself to power the optimization
process. I mean, internally inside of a Bayesian optimization algorithm, you probably have a Gaussian
processes at play or maybe a neural network that you're using your modeling on. Obviously,
these need to be learned. There's information theory, perhaps that's powering the acquisition
function element of your Bayesian optimization. But in reality, what I sort of think of this as
is more just an intelligent search process, an intelligent learning process learning about the
optimum. So yeah, it definitely is doing learning. But when we talk about optimization, it is very
different than this gradient-based optimization that I think many people in the community would think
of when they first think of optimization. You aren't lying when you said there was an intricate
relationship between those. We've got optimization, which is used in the context of machine learning as
part of the process of learning. We've got optimization, which is separate from machine learning in the
sense of we're trying to identify an optimal solution to some problem that we don't have as much
information about as we might if we were doing applying machine learning. And then we've got
machine learning embedded into the optimization process to try to optimize it in a sense.
I mean, very realistically, yeah, that's what's happening. I guess it's no surprise than that it
is a bit confusing in that at least this word optimization is overloaded in a lot of different
ways. You mentioned in there one aspect of optimization that Seagop does spend a lot of time on
and that's, you know, specifically, it's applied to the hyper parameters in a machine learning problem.
But you also are increasingly doing other types of optimization like in a, you know,
HPC style. Is that and what are those and those types of problems are I think one that I've
talked about previously with Gustavo on your team. An example of that is like identifying the best
materials. It was a it was a piece of glass. It was trying to come up with the right materials
with which to additively manufacture a special type of glass. And I think it's for solar like for
solar power. Exactly right. These these optoelectronic devices. It doesn't have to be solar. Your cell
phone theoretically is using this as well. But yeah, you're exactly right. Got it, got it. And so,
yeah, maybe from kind of a, you know, optimization 101 perspective when we're, you know, we've got
you know, a problem and we can contextualize it in the context of this materials problem or if
you've got a kind of a simpler context conceptual problem for us to start with.
You know, how how how do folks typically start when they're thinking about an optimization problem
and kind of what's the path of, you know, maybe increasing complexity like what's the simplest
approach and then, you know, where do you go from there to try to do a better job? I think
it starts with a initial formulation of what it is that's trying to be addressed. And when I say
that, I mean that it's actually maybe two different parts of the formulation. There's the initial
formulation, which is the the physical world, the physical manifestation, whatever it is you're
working on, whether it is manufacturing something like a like a coffee cup or whether it is designing
an ML algorithm that you're going to put into production to give recommendations. Both of these
require an initial statement of what is it that we're trying to accomplish? And what is it that
we're willing to do in order to accomplish that? If if we were willing to have some brilliant
artisan come in and design this mug and spend hours crafting each one, that's very different
than hey, I need to get 10 million of these manufactured in any given time. The same thing is
true realistically of an ML algorithm as well. If you're willing to spend years and years and years
building these up, that's very different than hey, we need this to get out in three weeks and we
need it not just to get out, we need to be in production and be stable and be monitored and
feel confident that we're not really hurting our business here. So I think that that's sort of
the first side of stating this this formulation and explaining the world in which you're willing
to live. And then the second step is the actual to some degree phrasing of the problem as an
optimization problem. What metric or potentially metrics is that you're interested in considering
in this situation? What domain? How is it that you can parameterize this space of decisions
that you're willing to make? And to some degree also, what is your your budget here? When I say
budget, it could be a financial budget, it could be a time budget, it could be a experts time budget.
So so both of these elements are I think key to to progressing the problem forward. And once that
initial discussion has taken place with not just the person who's being assigned or people who
are being assigned to do the modeling, but also whoever the stakeholders are in this, whoever
we're going to make the final decision, yeah, this can this can be a winner or no, it can't be a winner.
They all need to agree and ideally that all kind of happens at the start because if you wait until
the end, you might have wasted three weeks, three months, three years trying to build something that
people actually decide isn't acceptable. And so you've got this problem formulation. And
when I hear the way you describe that, I'm thinking like English, you know, or a natural language
more properly and like in a document as opposed to a mathematical formulation of the problem,
is that what you're describing? I think that's the split there between the two formulas. I think
on one hand, you need to have an agreement and maybe formulation is honestly probably the wrong
word, which again, I think even the optimization community sometimes uses optimization too broadly.
I'm probably using formulation too broadly here, but yeah, on one hand, you need the English
language document. You need a bunch of people who aren't going to be need deep in the project to
still agree with the goals of the project and allocate the necessary resources, but then you also do
need to some degree this rigorous mathematical formulation. You need to be able to compute things.
If you have things you can't compute, if you have things you can't measure, it's going to be very
hard to optimize though, not necessarily impossible. We can talk about that a little bit later, but
I think it's an ill-defined situation if you go forward and try to not have very explicit
statement of these are the metrics I'm studying at the very least studying. If you can't state that,
it's going to be very hard to feel confident that you're doing things successful.
And so in the case of the the glass or the mug, do you you've got some property that you want to
optimize and you've got some set of parameters that influence that property. I don't imagine that
you always have a straight line mathematical equation between those parameters and the ultimate
property that you're trying to optimize. Very rarely, very rarely. And when you do,
you probably have some very nice clean way to try and do the optimization.
I'll say that there's a few different sets of circumstances that can pop up here.
The relationship between these parameters, these choices you can make and the resulting
metrics of interest to you is in some sense always defined by a physical outcome. I build the mug,
I drop the mug on the ground, I watch whether it cracks or not. Much more often,
you're going to see people using some sort of computational simulation to help accelerate the
process because presumably running something on the computer is going to be faster than actually
manufacturing, fabricating whatever device or tool or object that it is. Not always,
but usually. And that's why, of course, people are buying more and more computers and moving more
and more of their testing process into the computational world. As far as understanding this relationship
between choices you can make and resulting metrics, it's sometimes you have a great insight
into this as an expert, somebody's been working in the field for 20, 30 years. Sometimes you don't.
And sometimes even if you do, you want to get beyond your intuition, because your intuition
got you to where you are now. If you're trying to do something new, somehow you need to get beyond
where you would initially, naturally be guided to act and the decisions you'd naturally be guided
to make. And I think that that's a key element of what the sort of mathematical and statistical
formulation of optimization brings to the table is you can leverage your prior beliefs, your prior
sense of the world if you want to. But you also can drown that out. The computer doesn't have to
have any prior beliefs about things. So the computer, the optimization algorithm, will figure out
whatever it can figure out. And that can expose you to some new ideas, some new strategies,
which are, I think, what everybody's really trying to go after when they're building a new model
when they're designing a new coffee mug or the glass, for example. And really, I think one of the
interesting things about that project was it wasn't to one metric problem. It wasn't one objective.
We were interested in there were actually a lot of objectives of interest. And the relationship
between the parameters and the metrics were complicated. And then the metrics themselves,
of course, competed with each other. One of the key metrics we were interested in studying there,
we need the glass to be low haze light has to pass through and not get scattered, which obviously
if the light gets scattered you're not going to be able to see what's on the other side of the glass.
So light that's coming in from the sun might not actually be as efficient in the solar panel
or you're not going to be able to see what your phone is trying to show you. But on the other side
of that, you want the glass to be very easy to clean, which was this term super omnipobic glass.
We don't want oil or sand in the case of solar panels, oil in the case of your fingerprints on
your computer screen. You don't want that stick into the glass. And if it does touch the glass,
you want it to be wiped right off very quickly, not to need some very harshest stringent to get it
off of the solar panels. But these things are at odds. I mean, when you think to yourself,
what sort of thing does oil not stick to? Gee, a cooking pan. Could I make my phone out of a
cooking pan? Teflon? No, obviously you can't do that. So when you try to maximize one metric,
you're hurting the other metric. And that sort of balance that understanding the exploration
of how the decisions you make demand these trade-offs in your resulting models or your resulting
solar panels or whatever. That's a really key part of what I'd call the modern optimization
process or maybe the modern intelligent experimentation process. So you formulated your problem
identified the things you care about and your constraints. You've identified the
relationship as best you can between the knobs and dials you have and the quantities
that you care about. And then I'm imagining the next step is some type of optimization approach.
And maybe the easiest one is like, hey, we'll just try every value of every knob and write down
what the outputs are and see where we get, but that is quite expensive. And so then we can get
more sophisticated approach. That's the crux of the problem. There it is. No, but I think you've
hit the nail squarely on the head. At the end of the day, if you want to find out what works best,
try a bunch of things, whichever works the best is the winner. And realistically, that will work.
That absolutely will work and every day of the week people do this all the time. How do you
pick the toothpaste you like the best? I don't know about you. I try this toothpaste. I try this
toothpaste. I try this eventually one of them I like and I'm like, okay, I'll take that toothpaste.
That's fine. I think that that strategy is a perfectly reasonable strategy in certain circumstances.
But as we get to these more complicated decision spaces, as we get to a point where we're trying
to design coffee mug. Now we're talking about not just the shape, but we're also talking about maybe
the material. We're talking about how hot it's put into the fire for. We're talking about the color
on the outside. You're talking about increasingly complicated space. You just can't try them all.
You absolutely cannot try them all. So you need some intelligent strategy to search the space.
And in particular, the way that strategy is going to be intelligent is by figuring out
whatever relationships exist between the parameters you're studying and the metric that you're
interested in optimizing. And that's really the difficult point. You mentioned earlier, could somebody
go through and define this relationship? Absolutely. Maybe that is possible. But in most circumstances,
that's not going to be possible for all sorts of reasons. Most of these objectives are very noisy.
In most of these problems, you have some limited amount of precision with which you can set these
parameters. In reality, the metric you're trying to optimize is probably not the metric that you
are doing the optimization on. If I run a computer simulation for something, I'm doing pretty well
as far as approximating the real world, but it's not the real world. When I go through to actually
manufacture or when I go through to actually put my model in production tomorrow or the day after,
tomorrow and the day after are going to act differently than today. So even if I have the best
data possible, it's just not going to be possible to actually optimize the thing that I'm trying to
study. So as a result, we're going to need to move as quickly as we can in our optimization process
so that we can figure out the best thing for today and then retune in the future as new information
pops up, as new strategies pop up, as I want to design something different because it turns out
customer taste of change. All of these things are key elements in what is going to be a successful
optimization process. And what we do internally in what many of these Bayesian optimization methods
use is some sort of modeling strategies we talked about basically ML on the inside to come up with
what this relationship between parameters and metrics are. The better we can understand that
relationship, the more quickly we can point ourselves towards where the high performing outcomes are.
I want to maybe take a digress for a second kind of returning back to the earlier
conversation around machine learning versus optimization as approaches to solving a particular
problem. Is optimization something that you might apply when you haven't collected as much
historical data relative to machine learning? Or does that not have anything to do with it?
Ultimately, when you're trying to build the mug that has the strength that you want given
whatever your constraints, there's some parameters that you're trying to figure out that optimize
the strength and whatever other targets you have. What is it that says that you shouldn't try to
machine learn those parameters? Rather, you should optimize and find those parameters that way.
It is very much this desire for sample efficiency. And you could absolutely test one design,
the next design, the next design, the next design. You could try and do this for 4,000 times,
8,000 times, 50,000 times. However many times it would take to learn your whatever it is,
XGBoost model, neural network, whatever. And then, of course, once you have an XGBoost model,
neural network, optimizing that, finding the optimal value for that, it's very, very cheap because
evaluating an XGBoost model, neural network, support vector, and evaluating that's very cheap.
The key here is that the cost of each piece of data is so high.
So it's the same thing. It's the same thing. You know, as with machine learning, you need a label
data set. Oh, very true. These are your inputs. Yes. This is your strength. You know, this is
your whatever. Those are your out your labels. Yes. And for the types of physical world problems
that we're talking about, primarily, you just don't have that. Exactly. Or if you do, it's very small.
It's a very small set. And you don't have the amount of time required to make a very large data set.
Yeah. Exactly right. Forgive me. That should have been obvious, but it wasn't falling.
No, no, no, no, no, no. That's a great point. And let me tie that in with a small branch of
machine, I shouldn't say a small branch, but a branch of machine learning called active learning.
Active learning is very much a key driving force behind Bayesian optimization.
Right. In an active learning setting, you are trying to do machine learning on this relationship
between parameters and metrics, but you're doing it in such a way that you acquire each piece of
data sort of in a sequential fashion or maybe in batches, but you don't have all the data at the
start. You're trying to accumulate more data. The goal there, though, is to exactly as you're
talking about learn this model. The goal in Bayesian optimization is to sequentially accumulate data,
but not to learn the model only to learn about the optimum or high performing outcomes.
Even if our internal models are very bad, it doesn't matter as long as they're pointing us
in the right direction, as long as they're identifying high performing outcomes, the model itself
could actually be garbage, just totally terrible, totally useless, not predictive in any fashion,
as long as it points you in the right direction. And that's, I think, the key benefit of applying
Bayesian optimization, as opposed to, let's say, active learning, is that you have a different
goal. If your goal is a simpler goal, find the optimum, that's simpler than learn the whole
function over the whole domain. And you can do it in a more sample efficient fashion because of that.
That was super helpful. I'm remembering back to my conversation with Gustavo. I don't remember
if it was, if this was part of the published interview or a prior pre-call. But I remember not
really understanding the connection with active learning and thinking that it was a bit of a
stretch, like, yeah, or just not like, is that kind of a marketing association? Or like, what's the
relationship between optimization and active learning? But what you said just help kind of frame
that for me with, in both cases, you're kind of doing sequential optimization, estimate, you're
trying to go from your inputs to your outputs sequentially and evaluating how close you got to
where you're trying to go and feeding them back to help you determine where to go next. And in
the active learning case, your goal is to create a model that you can then take and apply independent
of this incremental process in your optimization case. You just want the values at the end that tell
you what to go try in the real world. Exactly right. No, you've nailed it. And these aren't,
I think they're very closely related communities. I think the people who are doing active learning
are very closely related to people who are doing optimization. I think there's a minor offshoot
of active learning, this active search topic that Roman Garnett has been working on for a little
bit, which is like optimization, except that your metric is not numerical, it's a zero one metric.
So all you're trying to find is the highest number of successes possible. You might hear people
talk about every once in a while active differential inference. I need to be able to understand the
state of the world in as sample a fashion, a sample efficient fashion as possible. In particular,
this pops up sometimes in medical diagnostics. If you're running a test on somebody,
especially let's say a test that has some sort of radiological element to it, you want to do so
in as sample efficient a fashion as possible. You can use these active differential inference
methods for this. There's a field called Bayesian quadrature that's the active estimation of
integrals through exactly the same way. Let me accumulate some data. Let me do so in a way,
which gets me the most accurate integral, the most accurate understanding of the world as fast
as possible. The only question is what's your goal? Is it learning? Is it optimization? Is it
inference? Is it quadrature? Is it search? These are all parts of, in my mind, the same spoke.
Now, could you say that this is all strongly related to sequential decision making and in particular
the topic is sequential is going to make it maybe in the real world? I would argue, yes,
some people in sequential decision making community may argue no reinforcement learning is a different
thing. I think that in reality, I think that many of these things are closely related,
but they do have practical enough differences, perhaps, that they're certainly worthy of studying
in and of themselves. I don't think there's any need to merge all of these topics, but I do think
that knowing about the literature in each of these fields has helped each of these fields progress
faster than they would if they were just coistered off on their own.
So we're starting to get to, where I hope we get to, which is kind of like the, we've defined
optimization kind of framed it relative to machine learning and we're starting to talk about
like what's the research frontier in optimization? What are the open questions? I mean, optimization is
way older than machine learning, right? And so it's a much more mature field
beyond kind of mentioning, you know, some adjacent areas like you did, is there a way for you to
characterize like what's almost taxonomized kind of the, you know, the research frontiers of
optimization, like how and how are folks thinking about what are the interesting open questions
in optimization? What I'd say is I think that there is a division of the optimization community,
and for the record, it lives also within a lot of different communities. I think that a large chunk
of people who would say they do optimization and do research on optimization live purely within
mathematics departments, they're thinking about what I would call sort of the classical mathematical
optimization. And you're right, that predates machine learning, that predates statistics, that
predates, well, they're statistics, the concept, but at least the field of statistics starting,
let's say 1910 or something like that. So yeah, there are people who have been thinking about
optimization since forever Newton's method is optimization. So I think that you can, you can look
at that and say that there is a massive field, a huge bunch of literature, continuing research,
thinking about different implications of smoothness, quasi-convexity, various different things.
I think that you've got another branch of the community that is optimization, but thinks of it
in terms of what's called mathematical programming. And those people may live in a math department,
they may live in operations research groups, they many different places can be thinking about linear
programming, dynamic programming, stochastic programming, all those. And quadratic programming,
exactly right, mixed integer nonlinear programming. And in many cases, those people are sometimes
addressing problems that may be very close to some of these problems that we might address with
sample efficient methods, but the goal may be different. In the case of doing mixed integer nonlinear
programming, the goal may be prove that I have the answer. I have the answer with a perfect guarantee
or I have a answer which is within blank of the true answer with some guarantee or something like
that. I think that both of those are sets of optimization. And then I think there's this topic,
maybe that we're working on now, which is more of the the quote-unquote black box optimization
community, which is a bunch of evolutionary algorithms. And of course, those evolutionary
algorithms are, I think, often very poorly represented at ML communities, but are a massive
bunch of literature and there's some outstanding work going on there right now in the evolutionary
field. And then you've got these statistically motivated sample efficient optimization methods,
which are probably the most common ones you'll see talked about by myself and in some of the
context of the literature that I'm referring to. I think obviously you're still seeing a huge
amount of gradient descent literature in the NURPS community. So that's sort of the taxonomy
that I'd split it on. Are you doing something that's yet in this in this group here that is
gradient descent? Are you doing mathematical programming? Are you doing something evolutionary
or are you doing something in one of these sample efficient categories, the Bayesian optimization
category? Got it, got it. And you mentioned NURPS, are you kind of up to date on some of the
optimization conversations that are happening at NURPS? What does that look like?
Yeah, and I think that in particular, I can characterize how I'm thinking about it, especially
a lot with the workshops. See, there's a workshop that is on optimization in ML. It's literally
the name of the workshop. They've been having it for a long time, a lot of great research going
on there, but that is more focused on either many of these gradient descent style methods or
elements of mathematical programming. There are some articles in there that are on more of these
sample efficient methods. In particular, I think National University of Singapore had an article
or someone from, I shouldn't say the University, someone from National University of Singapore
had an article on BIO for a simulation, catlibrating simulation models. That's what it was.
So there is some amount in there, but in reality, that workshop I definitely would say is more focused
on the gradient, the SCASTIC gradient descent methodologies. I think that you're seeing, though,
a widespread of workshops right now, which are trying to take AI out of AI's community and get
it out into other segments of the community. There's the ML for physical sciences or ML and the
physical sciences workshop. There's the one tackling climate change with machine learning, one of
this obviously, not just three timely, but I think is a really exciting opportunity to get out of
the AI world and immediately be helping things and have an positive impact. There's the AI for
the sciences, or maybe it's called AI for science, workshops as well, which you said, it sounds like,
okay, ML for physical sciences, AI for science. What's the difference? I mean, in reality,
I think this is just a sort of embarrassment of riches here. There's so many people doing so
much great work that we have a lot of different workshops that are on close topics. And I think
this is giving us a chance to really encourage participation, not just by the people who have been
doing this for a long time, but anybody wants to get in the game. Anybody wants to be taking AI and
putting a convolutional known networks or maybe reinforcement learning and put them out in the
world there, or people who want to be doing sample efficient stuff, the Bayesian optimization
stuff. There's some great papers in some of these workshops on BO. I think there's one from some
authors at Shanghai Tiao Tong at the ML and the physical sciences workshop trying to talk about
thermal photovoltaics, I think. There was a Carrie Ann Bergen at the AI for sciences workshop.
She's part of a panel, but I mean, she's been doing good work recently, especially trying to say,
hey, how we're using ML to deal with earthquakes. And as somebody who lives in Hawaii, something I'm
very concerned about. I really want to make sure that we're dealing with earthquakes. Well,
so I just, I love to see it. It's really exciting for me. And it's exciting to see people out there
taking advantage of ML in the sciences, but also specifically, yeah, the sample efficient
optimization in the sciences out in the real world, making big things happen. I'm excited.
And so a pattern, the, you know, clear pattern here is that when you're trying to apply
machine learning in ways that kind of interface with the physical world, optimization,
does, would you, is it too strong to say the optimization plays a bigger role or is more important
than, you know, when you're optimizing, you know, ad revenue or something that's, you know, purely
physical, I'm sorry, digital based. I think, I think everybody's led to have their own opinions
about what's the most important thing, the most exciting thing. I know I personally find it
incredibly exciting. And as I mentioned before, I didn't grow up in the ML community. I grew up
doing theoretically applied mathematics. And what we worked on back in the day was a few different
things in particular, some magneto hydrodynamics. And we're seeing, we're seeing even now,
nuclear fusion trying to, trying to bubble up, trying to be a little exciting right now.
ML is playing a little bit of a role in that. I'm excited by that because, you know, it's,
it's a, it's a moment right now. There's a moment where ML is starting to mature and it's
starting to see its capabilities expand beyond. Sure, yeah, let's say recommender systems.
Now, the people working at whoever using these recommender systems, I am, I guarantee they're
excited to make that money. They should be. That is, that is their job. I personally find it
incredibly exciting to say, hey, let's get out there and deal with drug discovery, a place where
sample efficient optimization, active search in particular has been really exciting so far.
I love the idea of dealing with construction and how to make construction more environmentally
friendly. There are versions of that problem that can be addressed with sample efficient
optimization. And in particular, as we see more and more fields moving away from maybe the,
the classical way of doing business where it's just an expert tells you this is what you do and
then you do it. And saying, now let's use a data driven approach. And in particular,
let's explore the space of possible options. We have to find the one that works the best.
That's where sample efficient methodologies is going to play a big role. That's where things
like basic optimization are going to play a really, really, really big role because when you're
talking about new strategies for construction or new, new flows for a canal or how to deal with
displacement of wildlife or any number of different things. We talked about solar panels before.
How to best design solar panels or as energy efficient as possible. These are problems that can take,
I mean, for some of these things, you're talking about days, weeks, months to test some of these
hypotheses. You need to do as much as possible in the computer at first. And even those simulations,
those numerical simulations can be on the order of hours or days to run these climate simulations
that are being run at NCAR right now. You're talking about months for some of these simulations
to try and predict the impact of additional rainfall in certain parts of the world or something
like that. So you really need the sample efficient methodology. So as to help guide what is going
to be put into production in the eventual real version world, what we're actually going to go out
and test because you only have so many shots of that. You only, if each of those tests that you're
going to run is going to take a year, three years, five years or something like that, you really need
to have the right guidance to put that in play. And that's, for me, that's where the optimization,
the Bayesian optimization, the active learning, the sample efficient methodologies are just going
to play a massive role. And you're already seeing it at the workshops right now. You're starting
to see it, especially in these application journals. In each of these fields, you're seeing articles
being published, Bayesian optimization, intelligent ML, sample efficient ML, a surrogate assisted
optimization for construction, for manufacturing, for safety for vehicles. You're seeing it all
over the place. And it's just, it's a great time. It's a great time to be in the field. I think
we have a chance to do some really cool stuff. And I'm lucky to be a part of a company that wants
to be a part of that. I think I ran into that name collision overloading of optimization again
and asking that question. What I was trying to point at is there's this application of sample
efficiency. You've got some machine learning problem. You want to optimize that problem.
You know, hyperparameter optimization is a way to do that. You want to do that as efficiently
as possible. There's an element of sample efficiency there. And that's applicable whether you're
dealing with, you know, the ad optimization problem, you know, pure digital or not. Then there's
this other type of problem that the, again, for lack of a clearer way to articulate this,
seems to be highly correlated with real world and expensive experimentation. And I'm thinking of
my recent interview with Kim Branson, who's the global head of AI at GlaxoSmithCline. And he,
you know, the thing he's most excited about them having built is this data driven experimentation
process because they can't just run all the experiments. It's too expensive. So they have to
use data to guide the way, you know, to guide their scientists, you know, work in the lab. And
and that's a, it's a different, it's still sample efficiency, but it's a different kind of
sample efficiency. It's, you know, it's kind of this, you know, intelligent experimentation is
one way to to think about it. It's in a sense, it's, yeah, I'm wanting to like, think about it
in terms of the relationship between, I want to think about it like on this side, maybe ML is
the front end and optimization is the backend and here optimization is the front end and ML is
the backend. I don't know if that is what I would say is. And in this case, maybe there is a bit
of a backend front end relationship. Obviously, I have no idea what the outstanding researchers at
GlaxoSmithCline are working on internally right now, but I'm going to, you know, not dissimilar
from the materials problem. I think exactly right. I think exactly right. And I think that
there's, there's not a, there's not a massive sort of disconnect here between how this ML model
is being built and optimization. The question is, how is this ML model then sort of being used?
And let's say you have some sort of ML model talking about different design methodologies or,
and I think for many of these sort of traditional engineering fields, what you have is not an ML model,
what you have is probably a PDE simulation, a differential equation simulation, some sort of
computational simulation, which for them is maybe taking taking the place of this ML model that
somebody else may have to construct in the absence of any of these abinitio principles that guide
the development of a PDE model or some maybe some sort of stochastic simulation. So in both of those
circumstances though, the question is how do you use that model to tell your, your people in the
wet lab, your people out there going the construction, hey, why don't you try this next? What is the next
best thing to try? What is the, what is the best possible thing to try? So, so you are still using
maybe an ML model which is meant to predict how two chemicals are going to interact with each other,
or you're using your numerical simulation to predict, hey, I've designed this airplane wing,
this is how much turbulence it's going to generate or something like that. And you use this,
and you, you conduct your, I think, Bayesian optimization on the outcome of these ML models to say,
hey, here is what the, the next best thing to go out and actually build is. Here's, here's the,
the one or three or five things to spend the next year manufacturing and testing under the hope
that one of them is going to end up being the winner. So maybe to some degree, there's a,
a bit of a multi-scale element here. You've got your ML model, that takes time to build,
but then predictions from it can come quickly. Same thing with the numerical simulation,
predictions from that can come quickly or at least faster than the actual manufacturing process.
So you run your optimization, I think, oftentimes on the, the outcome of the ML model or on the
outcome of your numerical simulation, and that guides you to, hey, this is what you should spend
the next year do. Awesome, awesome. Very cool stuff. Very, very cool stuff and helped me kind of
think through maybe, I don't know, this interview may be more than, than some others is kind of me
trying to reconcile a lot of conversations I've had recently and I appreciate you participating
in that with me. Sure, it's my pleasure. And, you know, I absolutely love talking about this topic
and I especially love being able to talk with you about this topic. Hey, thanks so much.
And I appreciate you coming on the show and sharing with us. Absolutely. Thank you.