All right, everyone. Welcome to another episode of the Twomol AI podcast. I am your host Sam
Charrington. And today I'm joined by Basi Filiman. Basi is vice president and general manager
of machine learning and AI at Amazon. Before we get going, be sure to take a moment to hit that
subscribe button wherever you're listening to today's show. Basi, welcome to the podcast.
Thanks for having me, Sam. I'm super excited for this discussion for those who, well, you don't
know yet, but you're about to know this is a very special interview because it is the first in person
interview I've done since NURBS in Vancouver in 2019. I happen to be in New York for some meetings
with AWS as was Basi. And here we are. And we're going to spend some time today talking about
the recently announced Amazon code whisperer coding companion. And as a bonus,
Basi will be doing a demo for me that you'll be able to catch on YouTube towards the end of
our interview. Basi, let's get started with some background. Tell us a little bit about your role
at AWS. Yeah, so I'm vice president at AWS and I'm responsible for AI services. My background is
machine learning. Back in the 90s, I did a PhD in computer science from the University of Maryland.
And I chose to do it in machine learning. It wasn't a common thing to do at that time. A lot of
my friends were asking me what, what, what the heck is machine learning? Like, why are you doing
machine learning? You should be doing databases or you should be doing operating systems.
But I'm, I have to say that I'm the one with the last laugh. I'm kind of glad that I did it
at that time. It's serving me really well right now. And your role at AWS, your, what,
what aspects of ML and AI are you responsible for? Yeah, I'm responsible for a lot of the services
that we have at the top layer of the stack. Are you familiar, Sam, with the, with the three layers
of the stack, the way we think about machine learning? Absolutely. Yeah. So, but we can, we can
recap that infrastructure at the bottom developer or data sciences, focus tools in the middle. Right.
And cognitive services for lack of a better order. AI services at the top. Right. Right.
And I'm responsible with the top layer there. Okay. AI services layer. It's not just cognitive.
There's a set of cognitive language services at the top layer. There's also a bunch of
industrial services. So, there's a whole variety of services at the top layer of the stack,
the whole, the difference though with the middle layer is that the top layer is more managed
experience and people using those services don't have to be experts in machine learning.
All they need to know is, here's my application and here's how it's going, I'm going to make it
smarter. And I need this capability that I could just plug into my application to make it smarter.
And then they can just go and use it just like they do today. They, they access a web service for
compute or the access of web service for storage. They can now access an AI service in the same
exact way. And they can insert it into their own applications and make their applications faster.
Mm-hmm. So, let's dig in a little bit into the distinction between cognitive and industry.
So, the non-cognitive services would be things like, I know AWS has, for example,
medical transcription. Would you consider that non-cognitive or are you thinking like the call
center AI or? Okay, okay. Let me describe that to you in more detail. When we started out,
the first few services we launched, I would call them like foundational to any machine learning
business or a unit. And they're foundational in the sense that they capture a lot of the cognitive
things that humans are able to do. So, to give you an example, we started with Lex Lexes,
sort of the guts of Alexa. Essentially, it's the two A's removed from Alexa. And what's inside
is Lex. Not many people know that, but now they do. It all makes sense. Right. Right. And Lexes are
conversational AI platform. And what people can do with it is they could build their own Alexa's
if they wanted to or they could build a chatbot and insert it into their website. And so,
that Lexes something that would understand both text input as well as speech input. So,
they build a bot just once and then they can insert it into a call center conversation so that
it can take the call and maybe take care of the customer that's calling. So, that's Lex,
which is a conversational part. And that's definitely a cognitive service. We call it a language
service. I think Gartner calls it a language service too. So, we also have Polly. Polly is our
text-to-speech service. Alexa's voice is actually a Polly voice. But customers now have the
capability to have their own voices. They can pick from one of the many languages that we support
and the different kinds of voices we may have for each of the languages. And then they could just
use it for various applications. And a common one they use it for is they just put this thing on
a web page. And so, when people are driving their cars, they can just listen to what's on the web
page and Polly is going to narrate it for you. Right. So, that's another cognitive service.
Then we've got Translate, Amazon Translate, which is a document translation. You can go from
one language to another. And we've gotten to very high quality these days in terms of translation.
So, you could do a lot of cool things with that. Then we've got Transcribe, which is a speech-to-text.
We talked about text-to-speech before with Polly. But this one is a speech-to-text. And so,
this is useful for you to understand what's being said in a conversation. So, that is another
cognitive service. And then we've got yet another one called Comprehend, which is a natural language
processing service. And it's got all kinds of things you could do with it, like sentiment.
Given a piece of unstructured text, it'll tell you what the sentiment is. Is it a negative sentiment?
Is it a positive sentiment? So, customers often they use it for reviews. Like, the capture
reviews and then they run it through Comprehend. And they understand, like, are people excited about
what whatever it is that the review was for or are they unhappy about it? And we've got things
like targeted sentiment. So, you know, in the same sentence, you could say that the food was great,
but the service was lousy. And so, that's that's multiple sentiments within the same sentence.
That's the kind of stuff you could do with Comprehend. You could also do things with Comprehend where
you can extract entities of interest from unstructured text. Like, let's say you see
there's an article on one company acquiring another company. You could now just look at that
news article and you can extract things like which was the company that was acquired,
who was the CEO of that company? What was the transaction value? All of those kinds of things
can be extracted. So, that's kind of what Comprehend does. It helps you understand unstructured text.
Right? So, these are sort of the language or the cognitive services that we have. And that's what
we started with at the beginning. These are the basic foundational blocks you would need to build
anything else. And then, more recently, we've added domain specific services. Like, let me take one
industrial service, for example. Monitoron is an example of it. And this is an AWS service that's,
it includes a piece of hardware that comes with it. The hardware is essentially a temperature
and vibration sensor. And it's meant for shop floor technicians that want to monitor
their equipment on this factory floor. And they want to do predictive maintenance. So, they
buy this piece of hardware from us and they attach it to some portion of the machine that they
want to monitor. And what we do is we learn the behavior of that part of the machine in terms
of vibration and temperature, which is what the sensors are in that unit. And so, over time,
we'll be able to tell the person, the user, the customer, if there's a deviation in behavior.
And because vibration is something that it predicts, it's something that it'll tell you
before things are going to fail. It has that predictive nature. So, we're able to actually
detect issues way before they actually happen. So, for example, our fulfillment centers,
we have conveyor belts in our fulfillment centers to move the products around. And so,
it's very important for those belts to keep running. And there's a lot of rotating parts there.
And we use these, we use Monitoron there to monitor the health, the whole conveyor system.
And we've been able to catch failures like two weeks before they actually happened.
So, this essentially allows customers to plan the maintenance, rather than, you know,
react in a, it's going to be chaos if it just happens and they are not prepared for it. So,
that's a very clear, that's, it's not cognitive. It's something that is specific to the domain.
And it's a large enough segment there. And lots of customers have moving parts.
And they have equipment that they can't afford to fail. And so, that's a place where things
like Monitoron is being used. And to come back to your question on the medical transcription thing,
that's just an extension of the transcription that we have. It just applies to the medical domain.
So, I would say that that is a cognitive service because it has to do with, you know,
the speech and it has to do with understanding speech. So, those are the kinds of things we have.
We have also other kinds of services up there at the top layer at the stack. We've got
things like contact lens for Amazon Connect. And what contact lens does is it's a higher level
abstraction. It uses transcribe underneath the scenes. It uses comprehend underneath the scenes.
But it was built for the call center. And if you're a call center customer,
what you're interested in is you just want to know why are customers calling me, right? You want
to know that. You want to know how every call is going. Is it going? And by the way, you want to
know this real time as it's happening, but you may also want to do it post call, which is called
post call analytics. You want to know how your agents are doing. How are they responding? Are they
actually helping the customer? Are they saying the right things at the right time, right?
So, you could do all of those things. And that's what contact lens does. It actually
implements the actual, it takes the business problem and just implements it using a combination
of these foundational services that I talked about. So, we've also got some of those at the top
layer at the stack. And then I've got one more thing. And it's called Amazon Kendra.
And that's about search. It's about enterprise search where you've got, if you're an enterprise,
you've got a lot of documents within your enterprise. And these documents are typically siloed.
They're not, they're not like the documents on the web where everything's linked to each other.
And you know, you can figure out what people are clicking on and keep track of which documents
are more interesting. Instead here, they're all siloed. They're sitting in different systems.
Like they're sitting in SharePoint maybe or they're sitting on your wiki pages or
they're sitting inside Salesforce. And so, it's always a much harder problem for employees to find
things that they actually want to find within an enterprise. If you've, if you've ever tried
the search systems that are at enterprises, they are pretty horrible. And the one that we used to
have inside Amazon wasn't very good either before Kendra. So, and-
This is a space that I know fairly well. Having worked at a startup that tried to solve this
problem 20 something years ago. Okay, okay, all right. But it's like you're giving the
pitch that we used to give back then. It's one of these problems that just, you know, hasn't been
solved and probably won't ever be solved in the enterprise. Okay. Because it's such a difficult
problem. Absolutely. It's a difficult problem. But I think our tech, the technology is there where
we were able to solve it in a very good way. And I'll tell you the kinds of things you can do with
Kendra. So Kendra is again, another higher level abstraction where it just focuses on the business
problem, which is search, right? You need to be able to help people find what they're looking for
and documents are sitting in different places. So, you can't use all the usual techniques.
So, what Kendra does number one is it allows you to suck in all of the data from all of these systems.
There's connectors, managed connectors. All you have to do is to provide credentials and it's
going to suck in all of the data and also keep the access rights along with it so that you're not
going to show up, they're not going to show up in search results for people that are not authorized
to see certain kinds of documents. So it keeps, it not only sucks the data from these different
systems, but it also keeps all the permissions intact so that it knows what to show and what not to
show. The second thing Kendra does is it understands all of the documents like a human would after
reading it. So now, anyone can ask a question and I'm not talking about keyword search. I'm talking
about semantic search here. So I could actually say, where is the IT help desk at this Amazon building,
right? I can just ask that question. And the answer is not going to be like a hundred links where
I need to click on every single document and then hope I find this information in there. It's
Kendra is actually going to tell me it's the fourth floor, right? Right up there. And of course,
it's going to have all the links as well. The documents below like you're used to in a traditional
search, but you don't have to go digging for the answer. If it's confident, it'll show you the
answer right up there. And also in terms of relevance in the document, the documents being the
right documents, even we can't use a lot of signals that are available on the web. We use a lot of
clever techniques there. It's pre-trained on various domains. So it's going to perform really
well out of the box. So there's a lot of our customers that love the ease of setting this up.
We've also made it very easy to set up. You can ingest all of your documents with these
connectors and immediately you've got to search application that you can just go in and try it out.
And then of course, you can embed that into your own websites and things like that.
So that's what can, and underneath the scenes, if you're interested in kind of underneath the
scenes, there's a whole bunch of NLP models. That's what makes it happen. You said it was a hard
problem and that's rightfully so. Yeah, we were using Verity and I think we started looking at
autonomy. These are all text search engines and the problem that you described if a user getting
back tons of links that match, but relevance was the difficult problem. And we were nowhere near
at that time, summarization and some of the things that you described. Absolutely. And underneath
the scenes, there's a whole bunch of models. There's a document ranking model. There's an FAQ model.
There's a question answering model and all of these models sort of work together and all of the
complexities is not, I mean, the user doesn't have to deal with all of our complexity and putting
all of this together. We make sure that these things work seamlessly together. And of course,
Kendra has like learning, like continuous learning. It gets better as more people use it.
There's explicit feedback. There's a thumbs up, thumbs down on the search results. If somebody
does click it, we'll keep track of it. It gets better for the enterprise or implicitly we can track,
okay, they are clicking on this document in from the results. So maybe it wasn't the first one.
It was the third one. And so those kinds of things make sure that it gets better over time,
which is another thing. It's continuous learning. So that's another thing that's made it possible
for customers to find information that they actually want to find and make their employees more
productive. So that's sort of the top, the top layer of the stack is essentially a whole bunch
of AI services. There's some foundational ones, like I said, and then there's some that are
specific to domains like healthcare and industrial manufacturing domains. And then there's a lot
of applications, sort of things, things that solve business problems directly.
So you've described this pretty broad set of services. We want to jump into talking about
code whisperer. Code whisperer is not the first AWS service that's dealing with code,
right? There was code guru and then possibly others. Yes.
Talk a little bit about what AWS has been doing with code and kind of how code whisperer came about.
Yeah. So we've always known that AIML is going to, it's going to help a whole variety of
different areas. It's going to find its way into many different areas and it's going to make
things easier in those areas. I remember I think Werner Vogels, who's our CTO, he wrote a blog
article on how AIML has the potential to completely change the way developers do their every day go
about their every day work that they do. So the journey actually started in 2019. And if you look at,
I think I should start with what is a developer's workflow look like? That's a great place to start,
and then I can sort of tell you how we went about tackling all of those different pieces.
So what a developer first does, of course, he writes code. That's the first sort of stuff he writes
code. And then the next thing that they do is get the code reviewed by peers and some people may
even use some automated systems to kind of scan the code and help find things. So that piece,
you get it reviewed. And once you've reviewed the code, you deploy it, you deploy the whole thing,
and then you monitor it as the application is serving the customers that it's meant to serve.
And at that time, you're monitoring your applications for cost and performance, and then you'll
maybe find opportunities to make those better. So those are sort of key pieces of a workflow,
developer's workflow. When we started in 2019, we launched our very first service with
that is related to developers and writing code. And the one we decided to launch at that time,
it was CodeGuru in 2019. And what CodeGuru does is it helps you find bugs in your code,
and it helps you find lines of code that are very expensive, expensive in terms of the amount
to compute it would need. So that's the kind of stuff that CodeGuru helped. And so you could think
of CodeGuru then as taking care of the quality of the code, the reviewing part, it helps in that
part of the workflow. And is it considered an ML service or an AI service? Yeah, it is considered
an AI service. So in the AI service groups at the top layer of the stack, we also have a developer
focused set of services. CodeGuru was the first one, which we launched in 2019. The second one we
launched was a year later, and that's DevOps guru. And this is to tackle the monitoring the
application once you've deployed it, and you're monitoring it, and you're up, then you're trying
to find places to optimize it, right? And so that's what DevOps guru does, and we launched that in
2020. And we finally, we've now tackled the writing code part, which is what Code Whisperer is
all about. And let me set up the problem a little bit more. I mean, writing code is majority
of what a developer would do. And I'm still, I'm a, I've always been a very passionate developer,
and I still write code, not as much as I like to, but I still write a lot of code. And so
the best way to set up this problem is, is to talk through my own experience here. Like,
so what I tend to do with the limited amount of time that I can get these days, I may pick a pet
project that I'm either that I want to automate. And I'm doing it mainly to learn, because I know
that there's new frameworks all the time. And so when I hear about something, I want to,
so many new frameworks. That's right. That's right. That's right. So I just want to learn. I want to
be in touch with the technology, because then, you know, I can interact better with my people,
because that's what they do all day long. So, so what I tried to do, this was about, this was
maybe a year and a half or a year and a half ago. I was hearing a lot about React as a framework
for front-end development. And the last time I've done any, any front-end programming was back in,
I mean, the 2011, 2012 timeframe when, you know, there were, there was this, you know,
Microsoft had this Windows presentation foundation. There was this concept of XAML, which would separate
design from, from actual implementation, the design of how the user interface would look like,
from the actual implementation of what would happen when you actually trigger those, those buttons
and those dropdowns, right? And so that was the last time I'd done any kind of front-end programming.
But then I've heard, I heard so much about React, everybody talk about it. So I said, okay,
I need to learn this too. I need to see what it, what it is. And so I picked a project that I wanted
to just implement. I thought it was going to just be a weekend project. And so I learned about
React. I knew Java, but JavaScript, I've not done a lot of JavaScript or TypeScript, but it was
close enough. And so the first issue was, of course, programming language and the syntax and
how things are. They're all different. There's so many programming languages these days.
And new ones coming up all the time. And each one has its own area where it shines and other
areas where it's not so great. So that's the first place. There's a difference. If you're,
it's a different language that's used there. But then the framework itself, the concepts behind
React and how do you use it for doing front-end. That was another thing. But it wasn't enough for
me to just learn about React. The moment I, once I finished learning about React, I needed to
learn about React Router, which is the thing that would route incoming calls. But that wasn't
enough. I needed to learn about React Redux. And even that wasn't enough because I like to test
my code. I like to, I shouldn't even say test. I'd like to specify the behavior of the code first
and then actually go and implement the code. So I needed to have some testing frameworks. So
just, I needed to learn about just. And that was also not enough because there's another testing
framework for React called Enzyme, which is very popular. So by the, there were all these different
frameworks. And by the time I had gone, I just spent a whole bunch of weekends learning a lot of
these things. And I still haven't written anything meaningful. I've not made any progress
on what I wanted to build, right? And so, so that's, that's a big problem that there's just so
many different things that developer needs to know. And now if you take this to the cloud world,
you know, with AWS, we've have 250 plus services, I think, today on AWS. That's about
10,000 plus APIs, right? And by the time we finish this conversation, there'll be a few more.
So, so what is a, how, what is a developer, how does he do this, right? And typically what people
do is they go to stack overflow. Yeah, okay. And then you're going to look for snippets of code
that you can copy paste, right? So that's the, that's the life of a developer. And it's, it's,
it's, it's gotten harder. And so that's kind of where code whisperer comes in. And what code whisperer
is is it's an ML powered coding companion, a pair programming companion, if you will, that just helps
developers be more productive. And it doesn't matter where you are in your journey as a developer.
What what code whisperer helps you accomplish, it helps you magnify your impact no matter where
you are in the journey, right? And so I think that's the core, that's the core reason why we built it.
Yeah, I've got to ask my, my suspicion is that, you know, most folks listening to this podcast,
if not all, have heard of co-pilot, which is kind of collaboration between OpenAI and GitHub,
which preceded code whisperer by sometimes six months maybe. Did they scoop you or
no, I mean, so you actually helped me set this up really nicely by with your previous question,
right? Like, so you, I talked to you about the journey we were on, developer tools. We started
in 2019 with code group, right? So for me, this is a continuation of that of that whole journey.
So you can argue who came first with that story in place, right? But let me tell you about
things that we're doing differently with code whisperer. We did a few things very differently
with code whisperer. The first thing we did differently, if you look at things, the other tools
that are out there that do things that are similar, often you'll see headlines like a lot of the
code, about 40% of the code that's generated has security problems, security issues. Security and
licensing are the things that come up quite a bit. So I'm going to tackle security first,
but then I'll come to licensing. So you're hitting all the sweet spots right now. So yeah, so it's
on security. So what we do is as part of code whisperer, which by the way, it's part of the AWS
toolkit. And the toolkit is a plug-in to all the major IDs. So it's, we've got plugs into
which was studio code. It also plugs into all the JetBrains IDs. So it's, I think, PyCharm for Python
and IntelliJ for Java and WebStorm. And primarily to do completion for APIs and that kind of thing.
Yes. And it's, or initially, if not, yeah, we're not talking about completion, like, you know,
like the way IntelliSense used to be. We're talking about like 20 lines of code and 25 lines of
code. So when we get to the demo at the end, you'll see that I was speaking more generally about
the IDE toolkit that preceded code whisperer. Correct. Or is that? Oh, the AWS toolkit has been
there for a long time. Right. And that was primarily created to make those IDs aware of the AWS
API. Exactly. Exactly. Or completion and things like that. Exactly. Okay. Now it's just like
completion at another level. That's right. You will show us. Absolutely. Absolutely. Yeah.
That's true. So and what people just need to do is just download the AWS toolkit and they have
it as part of these IDs. We also integrated code whisperer into our Lambda console. So Lambda is
our serverless service. So it's where you just type in code and there's no servers to manage.
Your code just runs and gives you the results. Right. And so there's a lot of code that's being
written on the Lambda console. So it's plugged in there. It's also built in a cloud nine yet.
Yes, it is. Okay. It comes with integration into cloud nine as well. That's our web web based
ID. So we were on a topic and I dig dig rest and went into this one. Yeah, the differentiators.
Right. So this the first one is this the security security thing. Like for us at AWS
security is like job zero. I'm sure you've heard a lot about how seriously we take security.
And we think we need to help because security is a very specialized skill. Most companies have
you know a separate group of experts that are just there for you know for this topic in general.
And so we have what's called a security scan that's built into code whisperer. So
you can you could write code and then you could you could accept a lot of the code whisperer
suggestions. And you can also edit it further. But at the very end we've got the security scan
thing that you can hit. And it's going to tell you if there are any security issues in the code
that that it's scanned. So that's the first thing that we've done differently. We want to make
sure that the code we generated the code that ends up coming out at the other end. We want to
help in as many ways as we can to make sure that it has the it doesn't have any security issues.
And presumably that security scan is also an ML model that's trained and recognized
potential security issues. Absolutely. Yeah. Yeah.
Code guru had this capability when we launched it in 2019. And so we're we're using a lot of
that here as well. Okay. So that's the first area where it's different. And the second area where
it's different is in terms of the code it generates. I'm sure you've heard of like AI systems like
with games like chess and go. These they come up with new moves that they've never seen before or
new strategies they've never seen before. And to a large extent that's what happens when code
whisperer is generating code. It's generating code it's not seen before. But there may be instances
where the code that it generates is close enough to something that it's seen before. And
code whisperer of course is trained on billions of lines more than billions of lines of code from
public repositories from Amazon repositories code repositories from documentation and forums
public forums. And that's it's trained on a lot of stuff. So it may have seen something similar
before. And then what code whisperer will do is it provides what we call a reference tracker
where it lists the license under which that other similar piece of code was provided. So this
way developers know that the code that is there could potentially have that license so they can
decide whether they want to include that piece of code or they want to accept that suggestion or
they don't want to it depends on you know what the what the company rules are and it depends on
things like that. So that's the second thing that we're doing differently. And the third thing that
we're doing differently is like we talked about the the number of AWS services. And so first class
support for AWS APIs. We know what the most common patterns are in terms of application developers and
how they use the cloud. And now you can you can without having to learn about the 10,000 plus APIs
without having to worry about any of that your intent you just express your intent as you will see
later you express your intent either in the form of a good name for the function or in the form of a
comment. And we're just going to give you the best pieces of code that would make the most sense
and that point. So those are some of the differences. We're also pretty we do some aggressive
filtering on on potential harmful stuff. And so we're also we've taken a lot of effort to
minimize any issues there as well. So these are all the differences for code whisperer at this point
in time. You talked about the sources of code that the code whisperer was trained on. You spoke
about them broadly is GitHub included in that that set of repositories anything that's public and
has the right license. That's what we use. And are there specific licenses or types of licenses
that you filtered on? Definitely the the pieces of code that are public and are available for
consumption. Those are part of the training corbis as well as all of the Amazon code internally that
we've had from over many years. That's part of the that's part of it as well. And anything that's
public and like documentation that's public. Those are all pieces of code that goes into the training.
I'm imagining that if you're scouring the web crawling the web looking for code
that even the you know identifying code identifying the licenses associated with that code presents
interesting machine learning problems. Absolutely absolutely yeah. There's a lot of classification
problems right there right. A whole class of classification problems just on figuring out
which are the ones that you want to use and which are the ones you don't want to use. And of
course we've we've used every every technique that we've already have. I've talked about many of our
AI services at the top layer of the stack. Comprehend for example has a document classification API.
Essentially what you do there is that you decide what you're what you want to call your category and
you give it examples of a certain document that belong to the category. Some number of documents
that belong to the category define a category two. Another set of documents that belong to that
category and then you could define a third category called other where you give it a whole bunch of
documents that have no particular category. And then Comprehend will train a custom model for you
and you're not an ML you don't have to be an ML export for it. It's just not accessible through
the APIs and then you have now an endpoint where you can send it new documents and it's going to
tell you is it class one or class two or class three and so we we have a lot of these techniques
already in place and we've used that a lot for these kinds of things. Okay. Okay. Presumably this
is based on a large language model like other implementations of code generation
in the text textual context of LLM's one of the big conversations is around bias and
kind of responsible use of those. Yeah. Did those same kinds of issues surface when we're talking
about code and if so how? Yeah. So if you if you look at a lot of the transform models
they've got you know they're built on top of each other so there's various checkpoints.
Typically you would have a large language model that's trained on just text and then you
would that would be a checkpoint and then you would take that and then now train it on code.
Right. So if if there's issues with that core based model they're probably going to linger on
and so we've got if you go to amazon.science it's a it's a it's a one of the websites and
you'll see that we published just in the last year alone we published about 400 papers on
responsibly I that deals with all of these topics which we take very seriously things like bias
and fairness. We have in in my team we've got we've got the person that wrote the book on algorithmic
bias. He's a professor at UPEN his name is Michael Kerns he'll meet him later today and so
we've got all of those experts helping us avoid the pitfalls as much as possible. Now this is of
course an emerging it's a it's a thing that's still progressing it's not like we know exactly
what we need to do here but we've got the best minds looking at these topics and helping us
figure out how best to deal with those situations. I didn't mention some very aggressive filtering
that we're doing to prevent those kinds of situations those kinds of things were implemented
with the guidance of folks like Michael. I'm imagining the kind of classic profanity in comments
is one example is example but are there other yeah I was kind of trying to get some examples of the
way bias types of issues might surface in a code code specific context are there examples that
come to mind of that. Yeah generally if you're let's say you're writing a function that takes
an agenda and makes a decision based on the gender there could be areas where bias can creep in
and so you've got to explicitly look for situations like that and make sure you don't generate
codes along those paths and that's one another one is of course keys right like so we're talking
about APIs in the cloud a common thing that I see happen a lot is just keys where your secret keys
and your and developers tend to sometimes just put it into the source file including the ones
checked into GitHub right there's a lot of your keys are in there right right and now if you're
learning from all of that and let's say you do want to generate you do want to generate that
line it could up like you could leak potential key right and so we've taken a lot of care to prevent
those kinds of situations and I'll probably be able to show you that as well when when we actually
get to the demo in the end. Awesome awesome well this may be a great segue to the demo before we do
any any additional thoughts you want to share before we jump into the demo. No I just think that
I told you that I was like I'm a very passionate developer and a developer and still am
I really think that this is just the beginning of what we can we're going to be able to do
and this is going to make developers lives a lot more easier and I think they can focus most
developers that I know they want to focus on the the higher value problem they're less interested
in the boilerplate you know things that a framework may dictate and that's that's the that's
the bad part of writing code it's the the the real cool part is the is the business logic the
that's the cool parts that you want to actually write and so I think this is going to be this is
going to be in a space to watch going forward there's going to be a lot of innovation coming
on this topic and I just I'm very excited for what's to come in this area. No just to probe into
that a little bit do you do you have a gut feel for where you think the innovation will come first
or kind of what the you know what the path looks like. We've got some ideas on where the path looks
like and I'm sure you know that like 90% of what we do it it it it is driven by our customers it's
what they're asking us for and about 10% of the time we think on their behalf and and we do
something right based on that the obvious next steps will just be support for the more popular
languages I think we're currently support TypeScript JavaScript Java Python is what we support
so obviously there's going to be an element of supporting some of the key languages that's
definitely going to be one that's going to be there but I think it's just going to get better
and better in terms of in terms of the actual code that's generated today developers can accept
you know they can accept there's going to be options so when when code whisperer generates
generates code it gives you it gives you x number of options you can actually scroll through it
and see which one sort of fit your style and and what do you want to include those those suggestions
will get better over time and I think it just make people's lives a lot easier and best practices
you know we can capture best practices I mentioned already we kind of know the patterns of how
AWS APIs are accessed for application development and if you use there's best practices in terms of
how you put them together how you do error checking and things like that and so those things can
come more and more out of the box and this will this will make it easier for even you know developers
that are earlier in their journey to generate pieces of code that are pretty robust so that's
pretty much what I can share at this point in time awesome awesome well let's let's jump into the
demo okay all right what are we looking at here Vassie all right you're looking at
uh jet rains pie charm and I think this one because python is not a language that I like but
that that's exactly why why you know code whisperer is very useful um so let me let me just alienate it
I know I know I know I know I know I just don't like be able to redeem yourself by saying you love
Julian okay all right all right um anyway um so I'm gonna be doing a series of demos and each one
sort of takes it up a notch a little bit that's what I'm gonna try and do here um so the first one
it's it's kind of going to be a utility kind of thing that I think most developers want to do what's
they end up doing at some point um right so um code whisperer is enabled and the AWS toolkit has
been installed you guys can see it on the left side of the screen um so I'm gonna just start by saying
um a function to convert a JSON file to and I you see code whisperer just popped up
even my comment all right um so I'm just gonna accept that and um I want to specify a few more
things like I want to say things like um the keys of the JSON file are the column names again
you see that code whisperer popped that up I'm gonna accept that as well and then I don't care
about the values much um and now let's see let's see what code whisperer does it just generates
the function name um I'm just gonna accept it um and there is a set of code a bunch of code that
it just popped up um and then you can see this little thing at the bottom and that those are the
choices it says one of four and so I could probably go through the various options it's given me
um and and try and pick the one that I like the most and I'm probably gonna pick this one um it's
you can see what it's doing here it's taking the keys it's writing the header with the keys just
like we said and then it's writing all the rows so I'm just gonna pick that um and so I guess
that's kind of done I don't want to print anything and then let's if we just go in here to an empty
area and then see what else it's going to you can see that what it did here is now it's it's saying
a function to convert a CSV file to a JSON file so it's the opposite of what we just did which is a
common thing that most developers do like they um they write a transformation from one side to the
other and it's very likely you want the transformation from the other side as well so um we can
continue doing that and we'll see what happens here I don't I don't want that thing so
and there's the function name CSV to JSON I accept it and then I keep going
and again I've got a bunch of options here um you can see it uses a dict reader on on the CSV data
and then it's dumping it into the JSON file I could just accept that and I'd be done with it so
that's sort of the first little demo that I wanted to start with so that you get used to the
interface you kind of see what happens yeah um what I'll do next is um I'll I'll go to a more
obscure API um and I say obscure because most most developers that use AWS they've used the s3
they want the typical examples are upload a file to s3 or um they're doing some EC2 stuff right and
so um transcribe is one of my services the speech to text service um unless you are an AI developer
or unless you're a developer that wants AI in your app you probably won't know about it and
it's and so this is a situation exactly like that um so what I'll start with and because we're
going to be demonstrating use of an AWS API here um I'll start with uh you know variables for
AWS credentials right um and you can see there's the access key but you also see that it's not
giving me the key itself and even though it may have seen some keys in the training data um there's
a secret key probably a region and I guess I don't care anymore um then the next thing I'll do is
um write a function to transcribe uh I have to type right transcribe a German you put it popped up
audio file but I want to say a German audio file to text and you can see it popped that as well right
so it's giving me the name of the function I accepted it and this is going to be some elaborate
it's going to just going to be more elaborate so we just wait for it um you can see a lot of stuff
happening here um the bottom client is created with the transcribe thing that's typically how you
can see that the access keys and the secret keys in the region from above that variables are being
used to generate that that um that variable and then you can see the cool thing here it understands
the locale uh it's d-d and so it's there's uh you don't have to look up the documentation there's a
transcribe start transcription job right and then here it returns the job um right and so um there's
probably more options um there's probably more options down there um but I'm just going to
know if you yeah speaking of options if you knew a little bit about transcribe and say previously yeah
define the variable with the channel type which is one of those parameters that transcribe will take
yeah yeah uh would it have inserted that in the right place?
yes absolutely so the way it what code whisperer works is it gets context in the call and the
context for it is depends on where the cursor is it's code code around that cursor um and it could
even be code in other files in the project and so it uses that to figure out what's the best way
to do it and some of the options may include it some of the options may not include it all right
so that's kind of how it works um so let me let me accept this and maybe what I rather than
returning the the transcribe job maybe what I could do is um you know just delete this thing here
um and see what what it would generate maybe it would generate the same thing um but
okay wait for the transcription to complete um okay while true
and let's see what happens yeah okay so it's it's actually parsing the thing
going into it multiple levels to figure out the status sleeping for a while and and so on and so
forth and um so you could keep going uh with this and it's discoverability of these APIs it's
it's now a lot easier you don't have to go to stack overflow and look for the snippet the snippets
right there on the ID all right so that's the second demo that I wanted to show and I wanted to
show how it would work on a on an AWS API that's not very common for people to know about um then
the last thing that I probably would do and this is where we let's actually create something that
we actually run and see if it works right and so um and what I'm gonna try and do is um write a
function to plot sign of sign of x and let's say two star cosine of x come on with red and blue dashes
for the range minus pi to pi all right that's a lot of stuff yeah we always have to
pray to the demo gods so to speak and yeah uh but you would think that that given the the nature
of what's happening it'd be fairly robust uh typos is that what you find in general um I in general
I'm when I'm writing code I'm writing it for the next person that's going to be looking at it more
than anything else so I there's this whole philosophy and I can talk about it for hours
um a good code base is is one where um let's say you have a new developer in the team that person
can add a new feature in the shortest amount of time and I think that's possible only if your
code base is self-explanatory it's decoupled isolated things responsibilities are isolated um so yeah
I I even if I you could say okay why can't we correct the typos maybe that would be a future
thing that we do it should be possible to do I don't see a reason um why that won't work but in
general the context is a lot of stuff and so if let's say there's a spelling error in fact you know
what what I'm going to do right now um let me actually take this let me actually mess around with
it I don't want that argument um right so it generated that I'm actually going to change that
and now let's see what it does it just generated all that stuff right and you can see it's using
minus pi to pi and it's got the red dashes on red dash on sign and the the blue on the
let me just accept it and then if I go here um yeah so it's calling that function so
now if I just run this thing let's see what happens if it's even correct and there it is all right
so you see you see the um the program actually running so that's kind of the the last thing
that I wanted to show that um it can do things that are pretty elaborate and um in the end though
the the developer is responsible for the code and I think the person needs to know
what to accept you know with the options um how does he want to take this further so that's why
we call it a uh it's more of a companion than it's not the thing leading the way it's the thing
that's helping you not have to go look look things up in multiple places yeah um so that's your
typo not right right but I think that's definitely something that we should be able to handle um
so you've just given me a good idea for our roadmap
cool um that's all I had um to show well Vasi uh great conversation and great demo thanks so much
for uh taking the time to share with us a bit about code whisperer and more broadly the
AI services portfolio and the way you think about all those things it was a pleasure thanks for
having me sir my pleasure thank you all right bye bye