Hello everyone and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast where I interview
interesting people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
So I'm recording this intro in New York City where I've been attending the O'Reilly
AI and Stratocomferences.
I did a ton of great interviews here at the events and I'm really looking forward to getting
these posted over the next few weeks.
Today though, I've got to show that I know you're going to really enjoy.
My guess this time is Angie Hugeback, who is Principal Data Scientist at Spare 5.
A company focused on helping its customers generate the high quality training datasets that
are so so crucial to developing accurate machine learning models.
In this show, Angie and I cover a bunch of the real world practicalities of generating
training datasets.
We talk through the challenges faced by folks that need to label training data and how
to develop a cohesive system for performing the various labeling tasks that you're likely
to encounter.
We discuss some of the ways that bias can creep into your training data and how to avoid it.
And we explore some of the popular third-party options that companies look at for scaling
training data production and how they differ.
Before we dive into the interview though, I really want to take a moment to acknowledge
Spare 5, who stepped up to sponsor this episode of the show.
Now, I'm not going to spend time talking about their service here because Angie and I do
cover that in the course of the interview, but I will say these three things.
First, what Spare 5 is doing is really cool.
And if you have a training data problem and you know who you are if you do, you should
definitely take a look at what they've got to offer as you explore your options.
Second, they've put together a great offer for 25 lucky twimble talk listeners, which
you'll hear towards the end of the interview.
And third, I'm just very grateful to Spare 5 for helping to make this podcast possible
for all of you.
And I want to really encourage you all to show them some love.
So please, hit them up on Twitter.
They're at Spare 5, S-P-A-R-E, the number 5.
And just thank them, visit their website, sign up for a demo, all of these things let
them know how much you appreciate this podcast and their support for it.
As always, I'll be linking to Angie and the various things we mentioned on the show in
the show notes, which you'll be able to find at twimbleai.com slash talk slash six.
And now onto the interview.
So hey everybody, welcome to another episode of twimble talk.
I've got Angie Hugeback, the principal data scientist at Spare 5 on the line Angie, why
don't you say hi?
Hi everyone, hi Sam.
Hey, so happy to have you on here today.
Yeah, excited to be here.
All right, yeah, I'm really looking forward to digging into some good stuff.
Awesome, awesome.
So why don't we get started by having you give us a little bit about your background
and how you got started in machine learning?
Yeah, sure.
So I started out as a math major in college and I took a stats class.
I was at the University of Minnesota Duluth and I really fell in love with the idea that
you know, it was math, but it was applied and you could learn about the world around you
through math.
So I got really interested in statistics.
I ended up getting my masters in PhD in statistics.
I got my PhD at the University of Chicago and when I came out of school, so I had worked
with my PhD advisor was really big on teaching me how to creatively solve a problem, do creative
algorithm development, just start from the basics.
What are you trying to do and construct from there?
When I was really interested in doing that, I had a strong interest in machine learning
types of topics.
So when I came out of school, I had this idea that I want to work in machine learning,
but I want to do creative algorithm development and trying to find that.
And at the time, you know, the term data scientist didn't exist yet, but that's essentially
what I was interested in doing.
So it just took me some time from there to kind of blend between the traditional definition
of statistician and sort of the engineering end of machine learning and find a good balance
and this is where I landed.
Awesome.
Now, what were some other kinds of problems that you were interested in in grad school as
a statistician, statistician looking into machine learning?
Yeah, sure.
There was, when I was doing my master's degree at a master's thesis problem that was really
fun.
I was, you know, there's the game mastermind where you have the little colored pegs
and someone has a code, which is an ordering of colored pegs and you're trying to guess
through making proposals of, you know, what you think the code might be and getting
some feedback.
Right.
And so I had a lot of fun playing around with.
I ended up building like a metropolis hastings, important sampling style algorithm to solve
the game mastermind in a very limited number of steps.
And, you know, the game is, you know, fairly straightforward when you're dealing with
six pegs in the traditional sense.
But then I was taking it up, you know, well, what if it's 14 pegs or 50 pegs and the space
of the problem becomes incredibly complex?
And I was really interested in, you know, the metropolis hastings algorithm is kind of
like a simulated annealing algorithm where you're able to explore a really high dimensional
space very quickly and kind of rapidly move around in this space and figure out where
you're making progress and work toward an optimal point.
So that was fun.
I also worked on a lot of problems in astronomy.
So astronomy was something I'd always been interested in but never had a chance to learn
in school.
So my advisor was awesome, Mark Clorum.
He invited me to, you know, come on over into the astronomy department at the University
of Chicago and talk to the professors there and figure out what kinds of problems they
were working on where I might be able to help out.
So I did some work with quasars.
I got to do some work on some solar science research, got to do so.
I had an internship at NASA working on some solar research to continue to do some consulting
with them for a while.
And then the last project that always sticks out out in my mind wasn't really part of
my thesis work but when I was in my PhD program, Netflix announced their Netflix prize competition
which was, it was a competition on predictive modeling to do movie ratings, right?
So they released this publicly available data set and it was all these pairs of movie
ID and a user ID and then a rating.
And then you were supposed to be able to predict how certain users would write certain
movies.
And I played around with that problem for about six months.
It came up with a great solution that was competitive in the contest.
But then through that, I actually came to a different understanding of what worked better
in terms of actually making recommendations.
So I built a movie recommender out of that and headed up on the web actually up until
about six months ago.
I was still using it to recommend movies for myself and some of my friends are still
using it.
And so those kinds of problems were the things that I was generally interested in.
Wow.
I was going through school.
So does that mean it takes you less time to pick a movie to watch than it takes the rest
of us?
Yeah, typically it actually works pretty well.
I got to get it up and running good.
Yeah, the best feature was being able to combine two movies.
So you say, I want to see something that's like, I want to watch a movie that's like
Flut loose meets fatal attraction or something like that, and then it would come up with some
great recommendations crossing between those two.
That was really fun.
Oh nice.
You mentioned a whole bunch of really interesting stuff in there.
I want to mention since you mentioned astronomy, I don't know if you've had a chance to hear
the last tumultalk episode that I just posted is with Joshua, Joshua Bloom, who's an astronomy
professor at Berkeley and also the CTO of a company that uses machine learning.
I think you'll find it super interesting.
Oh, yeah.
Thanks.
I'll check it out.
Oh, absolutely.
Thanks.
I mean, you've given us an entree to go deep kind of quickly here.
Metropolis hastings and portance.
Yeah.
What is that all about?
Is that an L or stats or a good question?
I think it's, you know, it was sort of sitting in between the two fields and probably a little
bit more in ML.
Yeah.
So metropolis hastings is one thing important sampling is another.
Okay.
Yeah.
And so, yeah.
So metropolis hastings, it's really just an optimization technique, you know, for, you
know, maximizing a function in a high dimensional space where rather than say, you know, following
the derivative or doing something more mathematical in that sense, you use a random component.
So you say, you start with a space in the high dimensional field, you say, okay, this
is my initial starting point.
And then you propose a point around there that you may go to next.
And so you, you come up with a proposal function.
So you say, okay, maybe my proposal is I pick one of my dimensions at random.
And then I perturb that, that value a little bit with some random, you know, in some random
distance and in some directions, something like that.
And you say, okay, that's my proposed point.
And then you compare your function on that proposed point to the function on the initial
value.
And if you're in a better place and you say, oh, yeah, this is a better place to go to,
you know, you'll always move there.
But if you're, if it looks a little bit worse than your initial position, you'll still
move there with some small probability.
And so what that allows you to do is it allows you to move away from, you know, local minima
and things like that that you might get stuck in.
Yeah.
And it just, yeah, in many, many problems, it provides a kind of a rapid way to search
through a very high dimensional space.
Would it be fair to say that if your proposal function was, was your slope in the end-dimensional
space that it metropolis Hastings, we've kind of approximate gradient descent?
Um, not exactly, no, the proposal is always another, it's, it's basically a sampling.
You're going to sample from the collection of all possible points that you might evaluate.
Okay.
So, um, I mean, I suppose, I suppose you could create a proposal function that says I
always select a point that follows, you know, the slope, but, you know, that's the
thing I suppose you come up with that.
But typically, you, yeah, your proposal is supposed to have a random component and then
there's the additional random component that you may choose it, even if it moves in the
wrong direction.
Okay.
Oh, nice. Uh, so, uh, that, that raises a question for me coming from, uh, strong stats
background, you know, what, how does, how do you feel like this, uh, guide your perspective
as a data scientist?
Data science has come to me in a whole ton of things.
Uh, for many, it's, you know, heavy programming for others, it's heavy data engineering.
You obviously, it's heavy stats, um, heavy, do you have kind of a philosophy on data science
and kind of what that all means to you?
Yeah.
I mean, yeah, definitely, definitely data science is a, is a big umbrella covering a lot
of different things.
And, you know, I think the field, the whole field is, is evolving, right?
And, you know, and there's, there's more and more applications in this area, many more
people going into this field.
Yeah.
So, um, I'd say now there are a lot more people coming out of a computer science background
going into this type of work, um, you know, whereas back, you know, when I was coming out
of school, I, you know, it was almost 50, 50, it was like machine learning was really
sitting in between, um, statistics and computer science, at least that's the way that it
was at, at University of Chicago.
Okay.
Um, yeah, and I do feel like I think I have, um, I, I tend to approach problems more from
the predictive modeling, uh, viewpoint.
I, um, I do a lot with just, um, constructing probabilities, um, likelihood estimation, things
like that that maybe wouldn't be as commonly used coming straight from a, more computer
science engineering machine learning perspective where, where it may be more about, um, deep
learning and, you know, specific types of, of algorithms.
Um, so, so I guess I see a little bit of a difference there, um, but I, you know, and
I have background in more traditional statistics, you know, with just doing, you know, I don't
also, you know, experimental design and, um, doing, um, I, you know, more, more just classic
kinds of testing issues and, um, distribution comparisons and things like that.
But I would say that's a small part of my daily work.
It's one of those, you know, yeah, we do IB testing, we do things like that and I'll participate
in assisting with those kinds of, um, experimental analysis, um, but typically I'm doing more, um,
um, yeah, just constructing from probabilities, from likelihoods, um, you know, uh, working
with predictive modeling, things like that to, you know, to solve our product goals.
That's it.
That.
Are there things that you see commonly in the industry that you think, uh, would be
different, uh, or approaches that folks take that, uh, they might take differently if more
people had, uh, uh, a stats background?
Yeah, I mean, well, I'm, I'm biased, but yeah, I mean, I tend to think, uh, yeah, I don't
know, I, I see them, I see them blending and I see, you know, in people today that are
coming out of, you know, strong computer science programs with machine learning background,
really, there, there's quite a bit of overlap in terms of, you know, the materials that's
been taught and the skills that are there, so, um, yeah, so I'm not sure, not sure.
Okay.
Uh, and so what are you up to now?
Yeah, so right, so now I'm here at spare five, um, yeah, and, uh, yeah, so what we do here
at spare five, we do, um, we collect training data for computer vision and natural language
models.
So other companies that are building out AI, building out their own machine learning
models and computer vision and natural language, um, types of problems need really good labeled
training data in order to power, you know, the algorithms that they're trying to build.
And so that's what we do.
So, um, I got really interested in this space because at my, at my prior company, we started,
um, we were building out to natural language models there and, um, we had some really
good stuff.
It was working really well, but we wanted to push it to the next level and the thing that
was preventing us was just getting that really good labeled data.
Um, and so I was thinking a lot about that problem.
And then I heard that, um, Darren, who's our CTO here, I heard that he was at spare five
when I heard about what they were doing.
And I just saw a huge opportunity in terms of, I was like, you know, AI is getting really
big, machine learning is getting really big.
You know, it's no longer kind of a fringe thing that a few companies are trying out.
It's, you know, it's like to be in the, in the space, you know, to be competitive companies
need to be building, building these things out.
And as far as I can see, the real bottleneck is in the training data.
So, you know, that was where I was excited to jump in and be a part of that, be a part
of that business.
Nice.
I think there's growing recognition that the availability of training data is one of
the biggest issues that new entrants to, you know, folks that are trying to apply machine
learning to various problems take on.
And, you know, for a lot of people, they look at it and say, and I've heard this, you know,
I've heard this coming from several different angles, but, you know, something along the
lines of, you know, soon, if not now, it'll be very difficult for a startup, for example,
to, you know, compete with Facebook or Google or, you know, large company and industry,
you know, X because they'll have all the data.
And then the startup will, you know, will not be able to gather it and label it and all
that.
Do you agree with that in general?
Oh, yeah.
Oh, yeah, absolutely.
Absolutely.
I mean, the way that I see, you know, for, I think for quite a while, the focus was on
the algorithms themselves and, you know, how do we get better algorithms, better algorithms?
But at this point, you know, we have so many sophisticated algorithms, very flexible
algorithms, right, for solving so many different types of problems that, that really the defining
factor becomes the training data that you have underneath it to power it in terms of what
you can actually do.
So, yeah, I think that's a really valid concern.
Although, you know, I would say, you know, I mean, it definitely depends on what, you know,
what industry you're trying to jump into if you have a startup and they're trying to
do something new.
I think, yeah, I definitely think, you know, if they have a specific problem that they're
trying to tackle, that, you know, requires a very specific type of data.
I think there are so a lot of opportunities to get into that space if you have access
to, right, the ability to get that, get that label data that you need, right, which is,
which is where we come in.
Okay, so, walk us through specifically what you guys are doing to help, help companies.
Sure.
Absolutely.
So, I guess, yeah, so I would start by saying, you know, when, so when customers come to
us, you know, typically, the number one thing that they're looking for, they're looking
for high quality data, right, and they need that data at scale.
And so, and I would say, you know, traditionally companies may, you know, initially they may
start trying to label that data in-house, right, and they may say, you know, everybody
take a few hours and, you know, look through this data, add some labels, that sort of thing,
and then quickly find out, like, okay, this is going to take forever, and we don't only
have the resources, and then a next step that companies sometimes would go to is trying
to use these, you know, publicly available crowd sourcing, things like mechanical Turk,
where, you know, yeah, there's a crowd out there.
Maybe you can, you know, put your data out to them and they can label it, but that can
be just incredibly painful in terms of, you know, you never know the quality of the
work that you're getting back.
It's like you, you end up having to design an entire workflow around just trying to
QA the data that's coming back to you.
You end up having to send the data out many, many times over again to multiple different
people and try to assemble and make some sense out of the results that you're getting back.
Okay.
So that can be a real headache.
So by the time customers get to us, so what we're doing instead is we handle all of
that headache for you.
So basically the customer comes to us, what all they need to communicate to us is exactly
what correctly labeled data constitutes to them, right?
So they, usually the customer will present us with some examples, you know, these are
some images.
Here's some example annotations.
That would be the correct annotations for these images, that sort of thing.
And from there, we do all the heavy lifting in terms of, we can, we will take on the task,
we will create and generate that label data using our own community, which is like a thoroughly
vetted community.
We do all of the QA work and we guarantee the level of quality coming back to you and your
data, right?
So if you say, these are the specs, this is exactly what correctly labeled data means to us.
We want 95% of the data coming back to us to be correctly labeled to spec, right?
Then that's what, that's what we can guarantee and that's what we can provide.
And so, yeah, so definitely it's, it's quality is the major challenge that we're providing
just speed and scale.
And then one other important piece is that we, we provide, we can provide diversity among
the annotators.
And so in particular, if there's a specific audience that the customer is interested
in to say they're building an AI model and this AI model is going to be used by, you
know, women age, you know, 20 to 30, typically, right, in the US, we can target annotators from
that audience so that, you know, the keywords or, you know, whatever the labels that they're
providing are relevant and the types of things that that audience would typically use, which
is really going to improve the performance for the models themselves, you know, in those
types of settings.
So I would say, you know, those are kind of the three, three kind of pillars of problems
the customers have that, that we were able to solve for them.
Okay.
Let's come back to the diversity angle because that's super interesting.
But even before you get there, if I'm a company and I want to solve a given problem
in my industry, do you, are you able to help me find the right data or augment the data
that I do have with other data that might help me drive better predictability?
Yeah.
So we don't, we don't go out and find, like, publicly available data sets for you.
You know, we are in the business of generating the data, but we definitely do augment data.
So we've done data verification, sometimes, you know, validation, sometimes companies
have already gone through, you know, some steps of a process to assemble data on their
own, but they're hitting the point where they're realizing, like, the quality is just
not there.
And what they need, you know, what they need our community to help with is just going
through and validating, which ones are correct, which ones are incorrect, so that they
can increase the quality there.
We also, we can definitely augment data, you know, maybe they have images that have certain
annotations.
Maybe the images have tags for objects that appear in the image, but the customer now wants
to identify where in the image does that tag appear.
So the tag might be dog, and they need to know exactly where in the image the dog is.
And, you know, we can have our community either do pixel level, polygon annotation around
the dog in the image, do a bounding box annotation around the dog image, those types of things.
So yeah, there's there's a really wide variety of things that we can do in that sense.
Okay.
How much of this is best thought of as a services or consulting engagement versus some
platform that you guys have built up that that automates a ton of the, you know, this
back end work.
I mean, it's really both, and I guess it depends on, I mean, the platform, I think, is really
core and central to what we're doing and what we are able to do here.
But I would say the consulting aspect on the front end of, you know, making sure we design
the task precisely to, you know, making sure the customer is going to be very happy with
the data that they receive and that is going to do what they needed to do for their models
is also absolutely essential.
So I would say, you know, we do have some customers that come to us that have, you know, teams
that have been working on these, these problems for a long time and they know exactly what
they want and they've already got an idea of, you know, exactly how to kind of organize
the logic of, you know, what, what a correct annotation looks like.
And in those cases, it can be relatively straightforward for us to move that right into
our platform.
In other cases, you know, we've got customers that, you know, they know the types of models
they want to build, they've been struggling and they may even want, you know, some initial
consulting on, you know, what types of data are available to us?
You know, what can we do to improve, you know, improve the quality of their own models
and we can do some initial consulting there as well.
So it really just depends on the customer.
But basically, you know, that yeah, the consulting aspect is setting up all the work, making
sure we design the task correctly, going through an iterative, you know, process in the
beginning with the customer where, you know, we say, okay, we think we understand your
specs, you know, we've designed the task the way we think will work.
We run, you know, maybe we do a thousand annotations for the customer, return that back
to them and they verify, yes, this is what we're looking for, you know, yeah, you're,
you know, yeah, the annotators are understanding the task and this looks good before we go
to scale.
Okay, and so you mentioned a bunch of things that customers have typically tried before
they come to you.
Are you doing all those things as well, plus some other things like, for example, you
know, farming the labeling out to multiple people and doing some kind of quorum or voting
or something like that.
Right.
So, so no.
Okay.
So, yeah, the simple answer is no.
So, yeah, so we are not doing crowd sourcing.
So first of all, we don't use mechanical turf, we don't use any external community, we
use our own community through our spare five app and through the web that are, you know,
everyone is fully vetted, we have great detailed information on our users, we get Facebook
and LinkedIn data from our users, we do lots of survey and skill assessments, we're continuously
monitoring their, their tasking behaviors in real time, monitoring the quality of, you
know, of the tasks that are being submitted.
And so, but we are not crowd sourcing.
So on the flip side, what we do is we get really, really good at understanding the quality
of the work that the, that the community members are able to provide so that we are targeting,
we're targeting the right users from the beginning, right?
And then, so we've got predictive models in place to identify, when a new task comes
in, we can identify who are the users that we believe are most likely to do well on
that task.
And so, we can initially target the right subset of our community, then we turn the
task on and we have a real time monitoring system, so we, we turn on that process and
then as soon as the task is live, all of that real time monitoring is feeding back into
our predictive models for quality assessment on the user, and so we're making real time
decisions about when to potentially remove access to a particular, for a particular
user because we're not seeing the level of quality that we need.
And so we have a kind of that user quality model running in real time, and then we also
have an additional layer, which is an answer quality model.
So depending on the task, for some, for some task types, there are other types of data
and information available just based on the answer itself that's provided, and so we
have that additional layer just to make sure that the answer itself is, is meeting our
quality bar.
Okay.
Great.
That's interesting.
My initial reaction was, it sounds like crowdsourcing, but, you know, semantics here,
but it sounds like the key distinction that you guys would make is that, you know, with
crowdsourcing, you kind of put the task out there, and anyone can kind of take it, and
what you guys are doing is, you know, targeting it to specific people who developed a relationship
with over time.
Is that the right way to think about it?
That's true.
And I think, you know, it is a little bit semantics and just culturally help help people
use the terms, but I think that crowdsourcing often connotates that you're going to send
a question to multiple users and then assemble a correct answer from those multiple users.
Okay.
And so that's kind of the main distinction that I make.
So a lot, you know, oftentimes if we're talking to customers, especially if they've already
got a lot of experience themselves working with Mechanical Turk, they're really interested
in, you know, well, what are the metrics you're using to decide whether you have enough
consensus on a specific answer to move forward and how many users do you need to ask each
question and that sort of thing, and in our, in our setting, it's actually irrelevant.
That's not, that's not the approach we use, that's not the perspective that we follow.
Okay.
So is it fair then to think about this space as like Mechanical Turk is an API on top
of the people, but you have to build everything.
You're figuring out, figuring out how to get them your tasks, you're figuring out how
to do all this voting stuff so that you can get decent quality data, whatever.
Yeah.
Yeah, you're writing the instructions, you're doing, yeah, you're filtering, you know,
which users are you going to use, trying, trying to track their quality, all of those things
yourself.
Right.
And then crowd flower, who I think a few months ago announced some specific, some specific
offerings around labeling that I covered on the podcast, like they're kind of taking,
they actually originally were on Mechanical Turk, but I think that's right.
That's right.
And they're kind of a slightly higher level of abstraction that's doing a little bit
more of the stuff, but still fundamentally this, we're going to take the task and push
it to a bunch of people and choose the results.
And you guys are, you know, we're going to look at your problem and design a solution
to get you quality data.
That's exactly right.
Okay.
And can you talk a little bit about, you know, as a statistician, like what are some
of the interesting problems that you've, you've come up against and helping to build this
for, for spare five?
Yeah.
I think, I mean, the, the most interesting and challenging problem for me was just how,
how do we design a system and a platform that can work in a general sense at scale?
So, you know, when I, when not, when I started out, you know, we were still doing, there
was still a component of manual review internally just to, to make sure the various processes
that we had in place were working as expected.
And we had a lot of tailored, you know, for this task type, we managed it in this way,
for this task type, we managed it in this way.
And so when I came in, that was one of my initial goals was, how do I, how do I come to understand
this entire system with all the complexity for so many different types of tasks and we
have objective tasks, we have subjective tasks, we're looking at images, we're looking
at text, we're doing all of these different types of problems.
How do we, how do we develop a cohesive system to attack and address all of these different
tasks types and ensure the right level of quality?
So that was, that was really exciting for me and the, you know, and that's been the
focus, you know, over the last several months and, and now we're there.
And, and so that to me has just been a really exciting accomplishment.
That sounds pretty huge, can you talk, or can you talk to whatever level of detail you
can?
Yeah, I know.
Pipelines, slash.
Sure.
Oh, yeah, yeah.
Oh, sorry, can you, could you clarify the last part?
Oh, you're, you're, you're data science pipeline slash technology stack slash, you know,
kind of anything that can help folks get a sense for, you know, as they're building labeling
platforms, what are some of the, yeah, things that they need to consider?
Sure.
Well, so I can tell you just for the tech stack that we have here.
So on the backend, we're using Ruby, we use our Postgres, and then we have a lot of
different AWS services, and then on the front end, we have a web client, as well as
a native iOS application.
And yeah, and so let's see, yeah, so I think that there's a little bit, sorry, maybe you
can give me a little more guidance on exactly what direction you want to.
Oh, yeah.
So, so that, that is very helpful on understanding the, the tech platform, it sounds like you
guys are taking advantage of the cloud and AWS in particular.
As you, you know, when you thought about this challenge of, okay, we've got all these
different types of data, how do we unify this into a single platform that eliminates
like the, a lot of the manual steps that you described?
Are there any lessons that you've learned about building data science pipelines that helped
you achieve that goal that you think would be transferable to other people?
Yeah, and I, I don't know that this is specific to data labeling.
I would say, I would say one thing that I've learned that, that's worked really well, both
here and in previous companies that I've been in, in terms of integrating data science
with the existing tech and existing product is, I think what's, what's really essential
is you want, you want your data scientists to be focused on prototyping, like rapid prototyping.
You want, you want them to be really nimble in terms of, you know, hey, if, if something
about the product changes next week, we want to be able to like dig into the guts of
our models, make our changes really quickly and be able to push that back out into production
in a seamless way.
And, and you don't want your data scientists to have to be spending the majority of their
time, you know, maintaining and these larger systems and, and really having to, having
to be so focused on the engineering side in terms of, you know, let's make sure everything
staying up and stable and doing what it needs to be doing.
So, so one solution in the team that I led previously at my previous company, one solution
that we came to, which worked really well was, we developed, so we still wanted our data
scientists to be able to, to prototype as quickly as possible.
So I would say, you know, R is fantastic in terms of prototyping.
You have your, you know, the graphics and visualization component is, you know, on,
you know, is unsurpassed by, by any other software, you know, you have Python, has lots
of packages that are fantastic and you can definitely do some good data visualization
there.
But our team was focused on R and so we wanted our, our teams to be able to, to do their
modeling and we had a lot of predictive modeling kinds of work going on there.
We wanted our data scientists to be able to do the predictive modeling in R and hand
off the actual model component to the larger system in such a way that, you know, it was
sort of, you know, plug it in so that you have, you know, these are the inputs coming
into the model, these are the outputs coming out of R and we want that, we want to be
able to just take that, that chunk of code that is the model, pass that over into production
and, and get that plugged in and going at scale and, and that, you know, what, what worked
really well, what we've done in both situations is we've used, actually used our serve.
It doesn't have a, a fabulous amount of documentation out there, but it, it works really well and
there's a, yeah, so anyway, so, so building out a system with our serve, building out some
software around that to allow kind of, just the kind of input output portion to be handed
over so that, so that you can have, you know, other standard systems, you know, picking
it up and hitting your models and, you know, moving that all into the cloud so that you
can, you know, if you, if you start getting a lot more volume hitting your model than
you had originally anticipated, right, you just spin up some additional clusters and, and
manage that traffic.
Is our serve open source?
Yes.
Okay.
And so what I, I think what I'm hearing is that you've got the, the exploration and the
model development, that's all happening in R and then, you're able to take those models
and essentially deploy them into our serve and use that for prediction as opposed to
having to throw that over to an engineering group to, exactly, using something else.
Yeah, exactly, exactly, and what I would say too is, I mean, it really depends on the
algorithm that you come up with.
If you're prototyping in the end, you end up using something that's mathematically
very simple, then, you know, then maybe you just pass along, you know, your pseudocode,
you know what I mean?
I'm like, okay, these are the kinds of things that I've done.
These are the steps and you have that re-implemented in a faster language.
But, but if you're using, you know, there are many, many fantastic predictive modeling packages
available directly in R and if you, if you get your system set up correctly, you know,
we were using, you know, we had predictive models with, you know, 1,000 features in real
time returning results in about 100 milliseconds, right, coming straight out of R. If all you're
hitting R for is the actual modeling component, right, once it's already constructed.
So, you know, and I think, and I think keeping the model code in R in that sense just makes
it all that much easier for, you know, any modifications down the line that need to be
made and, you know, and, and I think another layer that you can add on top of that, you
know, which can work really well is, is if you can start to integrate some automated model
rebuilding mechanisms, right, so you've got, got one system going on that's pulling in
new data, continuously updating your models and then you've got another system that's just
plugging into the existing most current model to actually get the results that can work
really well.
It's interesting, I'm glad you raised that I was thinking about that as well and if you,
what you've done to address like model drift over time and if you've been able to build
in like 360 degree feedback loops, that kind of thing.
Yeah, so just somewhat, I haven't gone too deep on those sorts of things, so what, what,
I have some tricks that I like to use in terms of, kind of monitor, model monitoring, when
you are doing automatic updates and things and so there's various kinds of sanity checks.
There's a, there's a paper out of Microsoft that was just fantastic in terms of like these
are all the things that can go wrong when you put your model on autopilot and right and
these are the things that you need to be monitoring and so with just, they're like seven step-by-step
suggestions in terms of things that you might want to get implemented and that's fantastic.
I can, I can try and pull up that paper for you.
Oh, that would be amazing. That sounds like a great resource.
Yes.
Is it relatively recent?
I believe it was in the last couple of years.
Yeah, I've got to look it up.
Just making it in okay.
Yep.
And now you guys are focused on computer vision and natural language.
Is that right?
Yeah, that's right.
That's our focus right now.
And how do those domains influence the approach you've taken?
Yeah, that's an interesting question.
So clearly with computer vision, we're dealing with image data, right?
So I think it's had a huge influence in terms of the types of tooling that we're building
out to allow our users to correctly annotate the data.
Our end resulting data is only as good as the tooling allows for user accuracy, right?
So it's definitely had a major influence in the types of tasks, the types of tooling,
things like that that we've been designing.
But I would say at this point, in the general system for QA that we've constructed, that
is general, it's not specific in those areas.
But what we would like to do, continue, I guess, delving into, is internally, what can
we do in terms of natural language and computer vision modeling ourselves internally to improve
the quality of the results itself?
And that's something that we're just now starting to dive into.
Okay.
So in providing the services that you guys provide, are you needing to get into things
like deep learning and other things, or are these more the things that the customers
would use to train with the data that you're providing?
Yeah, that's right.
So we purely handle delivery of the training data.
So we can do some consulting in terms of, yeah, if you use data like this, this is
how that may affect the models, but it's really just more of a consulting aspect.
We're not doing any of the model training ourselves, we're not hosting any models, nothing
like that.
Okay.
Interesting.
Do you have a set of, you know, they're like a top three list of things that you would
want everyone to know about training data?
Oh.
That's a good question.
Let's see.
Yeah, I think, yeah, I mean, I think anyone who's got, you know, any experience in the
field knows that, you know, your model is only as good as your training data.
If you're, if you're training data really only represents, you know, a subset, a specific
subset of the space in which you expect your model to function, then, you know, you're
going to have, you're definitely going to have low accuracy in, in areas where you haven't
provided as much training data.
So definitely you need good, good coverage in terms of, you know, whatever, whatever the
inputs that you're going to be anticipating, that will be coming into this final model
that you build, you want to make sure that your training data represents those inputs
as closely as possible in order to get the best results.
Okay.
One more?
One more.
Well, and I think, I guess one interesting thing to think about is it, you know, it depends,
I think in the computer vision and natural language applications that we're focused
on, the quality of the data is really essential, but in other areas, there are situations
where you can get away with, you know, less, with lower quality training data, and the
model is, you know, as long as the, as long as the patterns are there, the patterns are
present, you know, your model, model may still be able to pick up those patterns, right?
And so, I guess just keeping in mind what level of quality is important or essential for
the type of model that you're building and the type of methods that you're using, you
know, there can be some variation there.
Okay.
How would you characterize the scenarios in which you can get away with the lower quality
training data?
I would say definitely when you're, when your model is more about summarizing and generalizing
the data, then, you know, having a few odd observations in there isn't going to dramatically
affect, you know, affect that, that summary.
Are there any examples that come to mind of customer space X?
Oh.
Let's see.
Well, I don't know, there's some, well, so here's an interesting example, it's a little
bit on the edge of what you're talking about here.
So, so Sentient is a customer of ours that is, they're a provider of AI.
We have a task that we've been running for them for quite some time now.
What they're interested in understanding is user perception of similarities between
shoots.
So they're building out, you know, they have models that they're building out that
are trying to decide what shoes belong together, not from some specific taxonomy or, you know,
hierarchy that some human person wrote down.
But, you know, like, oh, first you go by color and then by size, nothing like that.
What they want to understand is what a human person looking at a collection of shoes, you
know, if you say here's one pair of shoes, now look at these other 10 pair of shoes,
which one is most similar?
And they're really trying to understand the human's perspective of, you know, which of these
10 shoes do you think is similar?
So, it's a very ambiguous task.
It doesn't actually have a right or a wrong answer, but, but when we throw this task out
to our users and we return the data back to Sentient, they are able, they've had very good
success in terms of improving their models, which, you know, in terms of what types of
results they're able to surface at, you know, as a result of getting a very deep understanding
of what similarity means at a human level.
So, you know, there are many, many varying degrees of, you know, of going, you know, the ambiguity
versus, you know, essentially a very precise, you know, correct answer and it just absolutely
depends on the model that you're trying to build exactly what you need.
Okay.
And that example are they ultimately trying to make recommendations or do something?
I believe so.
Okay.
Man, I feel like I should have asked you about customer examples.
Yeah.
That was awesome.
Other interesting kind of use cases that you guys have taken on that we can talk about?
Sure.
Yeah.
Well, so here's one we did recently.
This was kind of different for us and it was a lot of fun.
So there's a company called Init.ai and they're building AI chatbot technology.
And so they, they're interested in building these chatbots in specific contexts.
And so they really, they need conversation data, like they need, you know, a text of conversations
in these contexts and they're having a difficult time going out and, you know, finding that
data publicly available, things like that.
And so, so we were talking with them, you know, and, you know, we've already typically
done lots of categorization of text, we'll do what's called like aspect opinion linking
of text, you know, various kinds of NL tasks, but what, what we ended up doing for Init
was we actually helped them produce the conversations and then took those conversations and labeled
the data, the text of those conversations.
So we actually ended up designing a task that we put out to our community, which was,
you know, pretend you're selling flowers and, you know, and now you'd be the, be the
person selling flowers and then to another user we're saying, you know, pretend you're
buying flowers.
And maybe we, you know, give some guidance, things that the customer is interested in learning
more about.
And we actually send, send the task back and forth to collect a complete conversation.
So, yes, I think we assembled something, I forget on the, I think it was something like
10,000 conversations that we assembled.
And then for each of those conversations, we went back and we did the labeling that they
needed in order to understand the content of what's going on, you know, in those conversations
to help train the AI models that they're building.
So that was, that was fun.
That was fun for us in terms of just designing it out, but it was also fun for the community.
We got so much feedback from people saying, like, I love this.
I could do this all day, you know, because you're just, and the conversations were fantastic.
So I mean, it was, it was really, it was a lot of fun.
That's awesome.
That reminds me of someone had a month ago or so set up basically these three kind of
conversational chatbots in a, in a chat room and they were just talking, talking to each
other.
And you sit there and monitor and when they got stuck, he just threw out some random thing
to get them.
Oh, that's fabulous.
Oh, I gotta look that up.
That's fantastic.
Oh, that's all.
So I don't know that I'll be able to find that, but if I can, I'll stick it in the
show.
Okay, that'd be great.
That'd be fantastic.
So one of your top, one of your top three things was subsetting the space, which reminded
me that we needed to talk about this diversity point.
Oh, right.
I want you to kind of start us off in this discussion with, you know, the examples that
come to mind for you of like where it's been done really poorly.
Well, well, actually, I have an example.
This is something we actually had an article in TechCrunch about this recently.
So we've been thinking about this a lot just since, you know, it's obviously a benefit
that we can provide to our customers to actually get the diversity and the, you know, the community
that they need.
But so we did a little experiment in how, so we started thinking about the question
of, you know, how different are the results?
Like how different does the training data look if you're sampling, you know, various types
of populations?
And so, you know, and it turns out we really didn't have to dig very deep.
So one of the first data sets that I went to analyze, we had a task that we had put
out to our users just as sort of a fun mental break once in a while, which was called rate
the puppies.
And so we just show you pictures of puppies and then you rate them from one to five stars,
you know, cute or okay, maybe not so cute.
And so we've collected, we've been collecting that data actually over quite a long period
of time, just, you know, a few puppies to rate, you know, here and there for our users.
And so the first thing I thought was, okay, let me just take a look at the data and see
how the ratings differ by gender.
And so I split the data by gender and it was just dramatic and obvious.
Difference that the women were rating the puppies as cuter consistently across the board,
across all puppies.
And with, and there was a wider gap on the cuter end of the spectrum and the gap was more
narrow on the not so cute end of the spectrum, but it was, but it was still there.
And yeah, it was just striking, right?
And it's, you know, it's a simple example and, you know, okay, well, how, how, doesn't
matter, you know, how cute the women of the matter rating the puppy is, okay, probably
not, but it's such a, it's such a clear example of the difference, differences that you can
get in the training data itself, right, just by sampling a different population.
And of course, the training data is what's guiding your model in terms of the output that's
coming up together.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
But yeah, so that's an article in TechCrunch, we can put a link to that article as well.
Okay, nice, nice.
And so the, do you run into any challenges in identifying diverse communities to target?
What are the challenges generally that come, come up for you guys and trying to solve
this problem for people?
Sure.
So each of our customers is going to have, you know, their own, their own demographic
that they're, that they are targeting, right?
And so at this point, we have a broad international community.
We have many, many users in the US.
We also have many, we have a good presence across just internationally.
And we have good data in terms of who our users are because we, we put out surveys to collect
demographic information, we, we put out, you know, many different surveys to our users,
you know, that they're compensated for, for completing these surveys to be able to
collect that information.
So we have a good understanding of our, our current user base, which is, you know, which
is very diverse.
But we, we occasionally still have a customer come in and ask for something very specific
that we haven't targeted before.
So they potentially could say, you know, we have this task and we need, who knows, we
need experts in bird identification to label these images of birds, you know, and tell us
precisely what species of bird, you know, this is, you know, something, something like
that, right?
And so when that comes up, you know, we can, first of all, we can go out and survey our
community and find out, you know, in our, in our broad community, do we have people who
are able, able to do this type of classification already, we can identify them.
But and if we find that we don't have enough members in the community yet to meet the
velocity needs or, you know, the volume needs for the customer, then we can go out and
do specific targeting to bring, like, you know, online marketing to bring those individuals
into our community.
And we've had good success with that.
Okay.
So we've talked about demographic targeting primarily thus far.
Have you ever done anything with, uh, psychographic targeting like, right, I don't know for whatever
reason I'm thinking, hey, we want this to be answered by my Briggs ENTJs or absolutely.
You know, we've definitely talked about it.
There's, yeah, there's, you know, there are all sorts of interesting personality profiles
out there.
And that's what's kind of lovely is because we do have this stable community that's working
with us is if we put a survey out to the community, right, you know, and we compensate them
for their time in completing that survey, we can get any, any data that we need.
So it's actually, it's actually very easy for us to target the user that the customer
is interested in.
Okay.
And this is a little bit of an aside, but I often think that in the example of like Uber
ratings, you know, I think that there's probably, well, not probably there's, you know, there
are, you know, four average radars and there are three average radars like, you know, hard
graders and easy graders.
I don't have the impression that, you know, an Uber, for example, would normalize, you know,
a person's rating against their average rating.
Right.
It has a strict interpretation, right?
Three stars.
That's what the user said.
Yeah.
Does anyone do something like that or, you know, to what degree to, to what degree to your
knowledge?
Do folks think about that in, you know, thinking about like rating schemes?
And what's the current kind of thinking in the industry around that kind of stuff?
Yeah.
So, yeah, this is a little outside of my, my area.
It's totally right.
Don't I?
Yeah.
That's okay.
I mean, I actually thought about this quite a bit when I was working on the Netflix prize
competition because in that case, we have the one to five stars rating system.
Right.
And so, you know, so I went really deep in, it's just an understanding, like, you know, what
are, what are these different user profiles or, you know, what types of users are out there
and, you know, one of these distributions generally look like.
Yeah.
It's like on one to five star rating system, you basically get one's four's and five's
and occasionally a three, you almost never get a two.
And, you know, so, I don't know, so I have some interesting tidbits and thoughts about
that in general.
But, you know, it currently at spare five from our perspective, you know, we occasionally
do ratings task.
It's not one of the, it's not one of the common customer requirements.
And we'll talk with the customer about whether, you know, is a, is a binary answer.
You're going to be more informative for them or a three level answer versus a five star
answer.
And so we do have some experience in background in thinking about what type of data is going
to come out of those different kinds of rating systems.
And, you know, and beside just the rating system itself, you know, the wording of the question
is so important in terms of, you know, you know, the words that you use, if you, if you
have a three layer system, do you say, you know, perfect, okay, terrible, you know, or
do you make it more, you know, more nuanced it, right?
And you're going to get, you're going to get different data based on different wording
that you use.
Which thing?
Yeah.
Which actually that, just to say going into, you know, another, like a whole, whole
other area of things that we are thinking about constantly here at spare five is just,
just in the, the wording and the framing of, of the question is just such an essential
piece of what we do here, whether, you know, even if it's not a rating question, even
if it's a totally open ended, you know, writing, writing captions for an image or free text
keywords versus, you know, very objective taxonomy categorization, things like that.
The wording of the question makes all the difference, right?
And so in our case, you know, we actually take our users through, or there's a, there's
a complete process.
So when, when a new task comes in, right, where we're iterating with the customer, trying
to design the task, when we start preparing our users to complete that task, we, we will
typically put up a tutorial, we'll start with a tutorial, so the user's just working
through the tutorial, they can work through it as many times as they want, and it's giving
them direct feedback on whether they're, you know, doing what's appropriate for the
task.
The next stage is a qualifier, which is more like a quiz.
You don't get the feedback as you're doing it.
At the end, you find out if you pass or not, and typically we won't allow users to continue
into the task without completing the qualifier, right?
And so, so we have instructions for the task that we're writing, we have the tutorial
that we're writing, we have the qualifier that we're writing, and then we have the task
itself and the questions that we're designing inside the task, right?
And all of the wording, logic, the orientation and design of that information on the page,
it is all part of the, you know, the whole formula of how do you get the right data coming
out at the end?
So, so that's a really important piece that I think people that are new to this field
are just finding out about it for the first time don't realize what an intense amount
of work and thought and effort goes into getting that right.
That's really interesting.
To what degree are you relying on, or do you have the benefit of relying on other folks
research to figure some of the stuff out, or is it all empirical analysis on your part?
Right.
So there is definitely a lot of great learning already out there, you know, that's been
published.
So we have Dan Weld, is a computer science professor at UW, and he consults with us regularly.
He's been fantastic.
He's a crowdsourcing expert, and he's been fantastic about pointing us to, you know, all
the good research out there about different things that have been tried in terms of, yeah,
in terms of instructions and tutorials and designing tasks and all those kinds of things.
So there's definitely a lot of learning there, but I would say, you know, given, given
that, you know, we are working in a somewhat different space in that we are not doing
traditional crowdsourcing, we are not, you know, farming answers, questions out to multiple
users at a time.
And so there has been a lot of just individualized learning on our part in terms of how do we
work with our users and what level are our, our users at, you know, how do we, how do
we bring them through the training process to get them to the level that we need.
So there's definitely a lot of internal learning, and I would say, you know, each time we do
another task, you know, each, you know, we have certain task types that we've done again
and again and again at this point, and we're learning each time we do them along the way,
how to make refinements, how to optimize that process, you know, how to make it even more
clear.
Anything that we can do to make, to make the instructions more clear, it just saves in
terms of efficiency because we have that many more answers coming through that are actually
accepted and allowed into the deliverable for the customer.
Nice.
I think we're coming up on an hour, anything else that you'd like to share with the audience?
Yes.
Absolutely.
Well, I would say, yeah, if anyone is interested in getting in touch with us, you know,
a couple of ways to get in touch, you can always head over to spare5.com.
You can also email me directly.
I'm Angie at spare5.com.
And I guess one other thing that we wanted to let the listeners know about, so we have
a blog series that we started a couple of months ago.
It's called Conversations in Machine Learning, and it's just all about any interesting
new applications in AI and ML things, you know, that are popping up all over at various
companies that we're watching in this space, and for your listeners, we're offering a
fantastically fabulous spare5 t-shirt to the first 25 people who subscribe to the blog
series.
And if anyone's interested, they can sign up at it's a spare5.com slash podcast.
Well, that's awesome.
That's awesome.
And I'll include a link to that, of course, in the show notes.
Okay.
Wonderful.
Thank you.
Awesome.
Well, thanks so much, Angie.
This has been a great conversation, and I really enjoyed it.
Thank you.
Catch you next time.
Absolutely.
Thanks, Sam.
All right.
Thanks, bye-bye.
Thank you.
All right.
Everyone, that's it for today's show.
Thanks so much for listening, and thanks once again to spare5 for sponsoring the show.
Please don't forget to sign up for their t-shirt offer at spare5.com slash podcast.
And of course, we both want to hear your feedback.
On Twitter, I'm at Twimmel AI, T-W-I-M-L-A-I, and spare5 is simply at spare5.
Reach out to us and let us know what you thought about the conversation.
Thanks so much for your continued support, and catch you next time.
Bye-bye.