So, hello. We want to be the AI cramudgeon, at least the personal AI cramudgeon. You know,
when I think about what AI could be in the promise that we have for home automation,
this personal assistance, they're just not there. I've been disappointed in voice, I've
been disappointed in a lot of my interactions where we're trying to have real artificial
intelligence to something that reads my calendar and makes recommendations or I interact
with a robot to calendar something. These lots of you desired and the idea that I have
to double check and triple check or type and re-type makes me pretty frustrated to interact
with AI's right now. So, we have a long way to go. The promise is there. There is absolutely
no doubt that we should be using much deeper computer systems to anticipate newer
behaviors and help us interact with technology and ways that are actually to humans very,
very predictable. So, the potential is there. It seems like it should be a solvable problem,
but from a personal perspective, it also feels farther off than I would like. At the same
time, I think we're using deep learning and machine learning in incredible ways in a
corporate setting where you have people with deep experience and masters and doctorate
degrees in these technologies, applying these technologies, mining our personal data.
And so, when I think about some of the stuff I'm excited as a technologist and a little
scared as a human, not from the robot takeover, but more from not understanding the social
implications of where my data is going and where people are learning about my behaviors
and applying it to things that I don't have a lot of control over. So, I'm going to be
AI-commogen here and say, it's coming, but we need to think about what it means. Thanks.