Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast why interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
If you're listening to this podcast, you probably have an opinion about AI and where it's
headed.
I personally think AI will make a huge difference in how we approach both our work and personal
lives, but as of today, the biggest impacts for me are in the little things.
But enough of what I think, I want to invite you to join the conversation.
Jump on over to Twimbleai.com slash MyAI to let us know what you think about where personal
and home AI is headed.
Sharing your thoughts takes just two minutes and qualifies you to win some great prizes.
In this episode, I'm joined by Charles Onu, PhD student at McGill University in Montreal
and founder of Benoit, a startup tackling the problem of infant mortality due to asphyxia.
Using SVMs and other techniques from the field of automatic speech recognition, Charles
and his team have built a model that detects asphyxia based on the audible noises a child
makes upon birth.
We go into the process he uses to collect his training data, including the specific methods
they use to record samples and how their samples will be used to maximize accuracy in
the field.
We also take a deep dive into some of the challenges of building and deploying who Ben was platform
and mobile application.
This is a really interesting use case, which I'm sure you'll enjoy.
Let's go.
Alright everyone, I am on the line with Charles Onu.
Charles is a PhD student at McGill University.
Charles, welcome to this weekend machine learning in AI.
Thank you very much, Sam.
I'm happy to be here.
It's great to have you on the show. I had a chance to see your presentation on, I think
the project was called the Benoit at the NIPS Black and AI workshop and it was very well
done.
Thank you.
And I'm sure you'll tell us a lot more about that project, but before we do that, why
don't you tell us how you got involved and interested in machine learning?
Well, that story is very intertwined with the project, the Benoit that you just spoke
about.
All the better.
Yeah, because indeed it was, it was, it might be to pursue that project that I got into
machine learning and took a, I say, side roads from my original path.
Okay.
Yeah.
So, so I had my undergrad education in electrical and computer engineering and when I finished
my undergrad, I worked as a software engineer.
I was doing that time that I was volunteering with an NGO called in Actus and then eventually
co-founded one called Fisher Foundation with some colleagues in Nigeria.
So I studied in Nigeria and that was when we, during our work in the local communities,
we had projects across agriculture, health care and a number of other domains.
And we came across the huge challenge of birth as fixed year, which is essentially when
the baby does not breathe well right after birth and it was such a huge cause of infant
mortality in our communities and but also in many parts of the world and particularly
in developing regions or resource poor settings.
So it was, you know, it was in a bid to see what causes this problem, how could we address
it?
I came across a research that, you know, first of all, detailed that one of the big reasons
why as fixed year is causing such huge casualties in developing countries.
So about one million babies die every year from as fixed year and another one million
suffer severe lifelong disabilities like brain damage, intellectual disability, cerebral
policy and so on.
And one of the reasons why the causality was so high was because in most resource poor
settings, the means for clinical diagnosis was too expensive, too resource intensive and
was just not happening.
Yeah.
And so there was a need for something, a low cost way of being able to screen babies early
enough for whether or not they are breathing well because when it's severe, it's easy
to know, you know, the baby usually would not cry when it's not breathing at birth.
But in many other cases, it's not as severe to cause baby not to cry, but it's there and
it's causing damage to the brain of the oxygen starvation.
And so the work we began to develop was based on clinical research done by doctors in the
70s and 80s way back.
And you know, they had looked at cries of infants suffering several pathologies and in particular
as fixed year, they used their spectograms back in the days and we were able to notice
that several perhaps characteristics of the cries, the fundamental frequencies and melodies
and very important frequency components of the cries were different or in general in
the population of babies that had some of these pathologies from those that, you know,
were okay, but normal.
And in particular, in the case of asphyxia, it's even more pronounced because breathing
and speech are coordinated by the same region of the brain and within our vocal tract as
well, the same set of organs are oscillating when a person is breathing and speaking.
And so the connection is so intertwined that the baby is not breathing well, there is a
manifestation in the frequency patterns in the scribe.
And so it was upon, you know, I'm giving the long-winded story of how I came into a machine
learning.
And it was upon the story of this that I, I first of all, to head about pattern recognition
as a discipline.
Okay.
And I began to study and take courses myself to learn more about it.
And slowly began to, to, you know, to start what has become original as a project now.
Yeah.
Oh, wow.
And you recently published a paper on this that won a Best Paper Award in the Machine
Learning and Healthcare Workshop at Neps, is that right?
Yes.
That's right.
Our paper won the Best Paper Award at Nips in 2015 Nips, actually.
And at the last Nips, we published a new one, which was a follow-up to that paper in
which we had moved from algorithm into an actual deployable device in the form of a smartphone
application.
Oh, okay.
Okay.
So maybe we can dive into that project, and you can tell us a little bit about, kind of
a little, in a little bit more detail, how you approach it.
You mentioned that the, the research came out of the 70s and 80s, is this the, the research
that identified these fundamental relationships, or were you somehow able to borrow data from
that research as well?
Yeah.
Well, the, this research, first of all, you know, told us that it was, there was something
to be explored there.
Because at the beginning, the last thing I would have thought of was to consider the infant
cry as a useful signal for diagnostic too.
And, and so it was really serendipitous, I'd say, to have stumbled upon one of these papers
and to see that it was indeed a string of studies between the 70s and 80s, exploring the,
the use of, you know, spectrograms to analyze the infant cries.
And there was this winter afterwards in which nobody seemed to carry it about, you know,
what infant cry could be used for.
And my assumption was that, you know, at the time, there was no, there are no concrete
methods for transferring this knowledge or this hypothesis into useful applications as
we now have today with machine learning being so well developed as a field now.
And several low cost technologies, like mobile phones, that was not conceivably at the time
of the 70s.
So my thoughts was, that was why some of the studies did not scale forward.
You know, when you first came across this paper and got the idea that, you know, this might
be applicable to this problem, you know, you mentioned that you started taking a bunch
of courses, but what was some of the first, like, concrete things that you did to try
to apply this knowledge that you came across?
Yeah.
Well, one of the, one of the first things I did was, you know, I had a doctor friend and
we had long conversations about it.
You know, I tried to understand physiology of the infant, of the infant breeding system
from him.
And, first of all, validated this was something worth pursuing.
And we were together, you know, worked on the early part of the work that we eventually
did.
Well, the next challenge, too, was how do we find data to validate this hypothesis that
infant cry holds information about the presence or not of asphyxia?
Right.
As you know, machine learning is based on the ability to use data and learn from it and
be able to generalize from that going forward.
But as you probably know as well, in medical space acquiring data is can be an extremely
resource intensive process, what intensive time to get approval to interact with actual
patients or time it takes to the amount of cost of funds it would require to conduct
the whole study to acquire this data.
And so one of the first things we thought was to find if someone had, by some chance, been
collecting data of infants in the world, at the time, we only interested in say, we
really thought we would find, you know, cries of babies that were normal.
And if we were able to find that at least, we thought that would be a good point to begin
to start modeling the inherent characteristics of cry.
And to begin to phrase this as maybe an anomaly detection problem, where we have a good model
of what a good cry should be, and we can say that any new example, any new sample,
that doesn't fit this model, is likely an anomaly that has to be checked, you know, has
to go for further verification and, you know, I'm referring to babies here.
And that could be useful screening too that, you know, first responders could use to
transfer babies for tertiary care.
Right.
So we saw we searched and eventually we came across the database that we used for our
work.
It's called the baby shilan to database.
And it's collected across a set of specialist hospitals in Mexico.
And this is a team of doctors who had been tracking several pathologies in babies.
And they had collected the cries of babies in several states, from normal states like,
from normal babies and in different states like hungry states, just a resting state, when
receiving some measure of pain, through maybe blood sampling, and also they collected pathological
states as well as fixier deafness and a number of other conditions.
Okay.
And so we reached out to them, you know, taught them about the work we were trying to
do.
And they gave us access to the subset of their data that had the normal baby's cries
and the XPC database cries.
Yeah.
It was fairly small to set about 69 babies in total, but over a thousand or so recordings.
And that was all we used to develop the, our first, our first work that I really showed
that there was promising, was promising signal in the cry that we could use to develop it
possibly it, it too for the agonies.
Yeah.
How did you use that data to develop a model, what kind of model did you end up pursuing
and what was your general approach there?
Yeah.
That's an interesting one.
The primary subdomain of machine learning that we looked to was that of automatic speech
recognition.
As you can imagine, this is a very similar problem as well, whereas ASR is trying to take
a speech and take a person's speech and understand what the person is saying.
In this case, we're not trying to understand what the baby is saying, what the baby's body
is communicating to us.
And so you can think that the methods developed there will be useful.
And so that was all we did.
We adopted feature extraction methods like the use of male frequency, septal coefficients,
MFCCs.
So MFCCs are an extraction of key frequency components in the speech signal.
And they've been used a lot in ASR because it's been, it's been easy, the methods of discrete
Fourier transforms to extract these key components that really put society things that are not
as relevant, you know, the artifacts of speech that are not as relevant and brings into
the, for the most important component of it.
Okay.
And so MFCCs have used a lot in ASR and we used that for speech recognition and feature
extraction path.
And we use support vector machines at the classification phase and combine these with,
you know, with non-linear kernels like the Gaussian kernels and so on.
So that's made the core of our system in general.
So you had the, you had these thousand recordings, you passed them through some pre-processing
steps that basically broke them down into frequency components and those became your features
for your SVM.
Yes, exactly.
And how, you know, beyond that initial kind of model, like, did you run into any challenges
in, in doing that?
So any challenges in building the classifier, you mean, from building the classifier,
yes.
Yeah.
Well, the good thing was, you know, we've, we've had this data that had been collected.
It had been, you know, someone had someone else had gone through all the work of getting
a clinical approval for it to conduct this study, collected the data, you know, filtered
the data, they had, you know, annotated it by labels, you know, which ones are the pathological
samples and healthy samples and so on.
So, so as you probably know, machine learning is a lot of work that goes into that early part
which we were, fortunately, saved from the engagement.
At least at that time.
So, so we spend most of the time, you know, developing the classifiers and tuning and, you
know, and searching the space of what's the best solution within this range of parameters
between the MFCs extraction and the SVMs and hyperparameters.
But, you know, ultimately, we are, we are now somewhat back to that first stage because
we're able to use that data to show the promise of this approach, to show the, the feasibility
of, of this method.
So now we need to, one, validate it, you know, with data we collect ourselves, we need to,
we need to get a larger data set to improve the performance.
So, the performance of the system we have now is about 90% on specificity and sensitivity
measures.
That's in accuracy in detecting the babies, the expiated babies and that sensitivity
and accuracy in detecting normal babies is our specificity.
And so, you know, the goal is to try to, one, robustly validate this, this, this results
we have using samples acquired from a different geographical location, different population.
And hopefully acquired this more data to use it to improve the performance of the algorithm.
And I'm beginning to develop into, into our software, very practical issues that would
have to face in the real world, like making sure it's robust to noise, and because the samples
were coded in very controlled environment without background noise, and just several optimizations
by, you know, for instance, in the presence of overlapping signals, you know, several of
these crying at one, can we separate them, the five one, can we optimize for the length
of the audio signal that we require to make a useful, a valid diagnosis, and so on,
and more of such things, we're looking at now.
Okay.
And now, one of the tools that will help you do all this is you were able to take the
work that you did initially and then build a mobile app around this.
Mel, tell us a little bit about that process and kind of what stage you are, you're in
with deploying this mobile app.
Yeah.
So, you know, in terms of the development of mobile app, one of the challenges is that
a lot of, a lot of machine learning has, you know, happens on Python and MATLAB, and
what those are not the languages that are used in mobile development, right, in general.
And so, you know, but they really help with experimentation and, and, you know, the fast
tone of our design to take process, but thinking of deployment, you know, we had to start
thinking about, first of all, we had to decide upon what was the best mobile platform
for a place like Nigeria, where I lived when this, when we started this project.
And Nigeria, Android phones are 90% or 95% of what people use.
So that was our go-to platform to start with.
Android at the time, at least, was 2014 and there about the main platform for development
or the main language for Android development was Java.
And now there's been C-shop portals to be done, I think Python, possibly now, yeah, but
also the one of the big challenges too was transferring our code to Java and maintaining
efficiency, maintaining performance as well, accuracy, and, you know, just all of that
thing.
So, it took quite a while.
That was quite a bit of a few weeks or maybe months, we spent on, on just that part
of the work, but we're able to do it ultimately and my colleague, Innocent, who is also a software
engineer.
We're able to completely move our code and maintain performance both in terms of time
to diagnosis, we're able to maintain the original classification performance on the data
set as well when we put it in the mobile application.
So that was one challenge we had to face and it was good.
And we also mentioned that we face this challenge too because we wanted to put the classification
model on the device.
We did not want it to require internet to do classification because if we are trying
to deploy in some of the poorest parts of the world, in Nigeria that's also not so poor,
the internet access is still very, very, very, very scanty in many places.
And so if the device required internet to make it a diagnosis, then the purpose is halfway
defeated already.
And we could go there in the long run, but in the media term it was the most practical
thing for our target groups.
And so we went through that and we got it onto the mobile app.
So where we are now is the questioner, so in terms of validating our mobile application
and that's really love what's taking us, it's what takes out most of our time presently.
So in Montreal, at the Maggi University Health Center, at the Children's Hospital here,
we are doing the validation exercise in one year exercise with the doctors here.
And the goal is to acquire more samples from babies who have experienced in different
levels of species from mild to moderate to severe, acquire control samples of normal babies,
and then to use a binwad to validate against, to classify the samples essentially.
So these samples are going to be, the cry samples of these babies are going to be evaluated
very clinical methods of diagnosis.
So they have blood samples be taken to be analyzed with a blood gas analyzer and a doctor,
especially doctor, would clinically determine what to label these babies as, and then
validate these against the binwad and hopefully further develop the algorithm in that process.
And the next stage after that would be to then take this to Nigeria and do field trials there.
Our regional plan was to do this stage in Nigeria and it's still not a shutdown plan completely
but we faced many challenges with that. Just because, whereas the whole clinical process
I just explained of blood gas analysis and so to confirm the presence of our species,
whereas it's a routine procedure in Montreal, in Canada, in Nigeria it doesn't happen,
which is the root of this problem differently.
Right.
Equipments do not exist in any of the public hospitals there.
There's no power, there's no electricity for the most part, so if we use it if it was
there, there's a whole workflow and process requirements that should be in place or that
would have to put in place if we were to try to do it there.
And a lot of this would cause put time, money, effort and it would be a huge deviation
from the ultimate or the precise focus of the project.
And so after much thought from back, we decided that we'll do the first stage here and then
move to do it, filter out in Nigeria with the doctors who work with there as well.
And now it sounds like the samples you're collecting at McGill are, there's a high level
of care clinically and evaluating the samples.
Are you also collecting them with more professional equipment or are you trying to collect the
samples via the mobile app so that you can kind of match the conditions that you'll be
collecting them with in the field?
Yeah, that was indeed a decision point for us, whether to use the mobile apps, the mobile
phones themselves to apply it there or to use specialized or the recorders.
And ultimately we went for special or the recorders just because of that.
Oh really?
Yeah, we did.
We really want to maintain the one, the recording quality across the subjects, across the samples.
We want to track things like sampling rates and just, you know, exclude some of the immediate
let's say Mr. Lenners' functionalities are coming with a mobile phone.
Also, you know, we've had some slight issues with the ethics before, I don't know if this
probably lands on phone things I should not talk about as well, but yeah, there's also
some ethics issues with using the phone right away for the acquisition and yeah, so we're
going to be using digital audio recorders to pick these signals at this point.
Okay.
Yeah, I'll take your word on it if it's something you can't talk about, but you certainly
pick my curiosity.
I mean, I can imagine in the U.S. we have laws like HIPAA that require a certain level
of standard of care with patient information, I imagine there's that kind of thing going
on.
Yeah, things on that line.
Okay.
Yeah, I mean, it's, it's, it can get complicated.
You've got these samples that you're capturing with specialized audio equipment.
How then do you address the issues that you mentioned previously, you know, kind of
there, the transfer, transferability of those samples to the samples that are collected,
you know, via your mobile device, so your background noises, you're overlapping, like
are you, you recreating these situations after the fact or is that just reserved for a later
stage of developing your model?
Yeah, yeah, at the current stage, we are going to be working on those optimizations more
in the research settings, so we're going to simulate what noise it looked like, okay.
We could go out, you know, the sample, one way which we could do the case of the noises
to record noise in record actual noise signals in the environment, we think the Apple
be used and think that and use that noise to, I wanted to say noisy our samples further
with a bit too much use of noise, but we use that to corrupt our samples essentially.
And then, you know, work more from the research, so our research team is going to be working
more on the research side of how can we improve the algorithm, making more robust noise.
And I guess the more practical test of whatever we develop would happen when we are able
to go through this phase of validation and begin to test on the fields in Nigerian, so
we can put it down on the field and say, and test it in reality.
How many samples are you expecting to collect in the current phase?
Oh, you shouldn't have asked that, now I'm going to, now I'm going to disappoint you
if you've heard about machine learning data, but we are collecting a total of 100 samples.
Oh, wow, okay.
You know, it's interesting because I was, I think perhaps the precursor to that question
was, you know, thinking about, you know, whether this is something you would also evaluate
like a deep learning type of approach, and I figured maybe one of the, you know, the
limitations would be the number of available samples and needing a much more efficient
model.
Yes, yes, that's correct.
I mean, first of all, getting medical data is really hard.
I work on another study at McGill, in which we are also collecting cardio respiratory
signals of newborns, and over a period of since 2014, it's taking us from then to 2017
December to collect a total of 230 newborn data.
So we're tracking, you know, respiratory difficulties in the intensive care unit.
And so the bottom line is, yeah, it's really hard, it takes time to get, you know, quality
medical data.
And, but that's also part of what turns us more towards classical machine learning and
less away from automatic representation methods like deep learning, so that we can really
have control of what features we extract and really make direct connections between,
the features and the cause they have on the system and, you know, and their projectability
as well.
On that note, are there, you know, you started with this understanding from the prior
research that the frequency components would have a big play a big role in identifying
the asphyxia samples in that kind of feature engineering process, feature identification
process.
Did you identify any new features beyond what you found in the existing research, and
in particular, was there anything that you found that surprised you?
I'll say, because there's such a wide range of audio characteristics that I was explored
back then, but one of the features that I really stood out the most was the fundamental
frequency of the cry, because the fundamental frequency is one of the most studied elements
because it's like the very first thing that describes an audio signal even in music
to the fundamental frequency determines the key of a song, and so it more or less determines
what the, at what pace or at what pitch is this child crying at.
And that would say it's been the most significant features consistently across our work.
And across the previous work that was done as well.
Okay, so it's not some, you know, there's not some kind of mysterious thing that's happening,
like some, you know, it's like just the basic, you know, most fundamental thing that you
would get out of this audio signal.
Yeah, but the interesting question comes in in the, in how it varies in the time across
time.
So the time very in nature of this signal.
And that's why it's not a simple problem that you could set it threshold or chord
and say, okay, every value above this, right, right.
So that's really why machine learning was necessitated because it's the complex time
very nature of the signals and of these characteristics that is just impossible to put down a rule
that says, you know, maybe the has this, this and this is going to be normal and otherwise
for, for us fixated.
Now, how do you capture that time very nature with the SVM?
Yeah, so SVMs inherently are not time, time series classifiers.
And so we've used the combination of several methods.
So one of the things we did was use Gaussian kernels for the SVMs, which, which primarily
do with scalar features, or we then segmented the samples into, into several time chunks
and, and use the instances in time, as if they were independent for training.
But at test, I, we test the, we test the instances, again, independently, but combine their
results to determine whether or not we've, the performance has worked, the performance
of the system is doing well at this, at the level of this subject now, at the level
of the independent time instances.
And so that way, by guiding the search, basically through our, our parameters, by guiding the search
with the ultimate performance on the subject, we can go to a better, hyper parameter space
that really optimizes performance at the level of the subject based on the nature of each
of these instances in time.
Hmm.
Yeah, can you give me an example, maybe of how that, how that works?
Like, what, how does the, the relationship between these samples, give you, you know, allow
the algorithm to, to key in on this time-sensitive variation?
Yeah, so, so you could look at it as, imagine we recorded, hypothetically, the, the length
of the samples we have was ten samples.
So that's it was one second at ten hertz.
Okay.
Ten seconds, ten, ten samples per second.
Hmm.
So this is for one subject, for one infant.
So what we do is, you know, we take each of this, the, the feature, the feature vector
at each of these time instances, so to be clear again, at each of these ten time instance,
we have a feature vector of some length, the feature vector is determined by the number
of characteristics we decide to extract from the, from the audio signals, you know, including
the fundamental frequencies and many other characteristics from the MSC features.
And so we take that feature vector of, say, some, some value, let's say it was three.
And we take that feature, those feature vectors, we decore it as, first of all, for training.
And the goal released to find in the, in the high dimensional space, is there a space
on which we can separate the instances from success samples, from the time instances
of failure samples. But when we do that training to try and separate them and find a good
hyperplane, the high dimensional space, then on the evaluation point, we take, of course,
a separate set of samples. So we don't use the same subjects we use in training as the
evaluation phase. In the evaluation phase, we take each of the instances, the ten instances
of a particular subject to evaluate it. We classify them based on the, the model that
we are choosing to evaluate at this point. And, and ultimately, we, we then use another
metric. So in our case, we, we, we explored both the use of just a simple majority count
of the instances, but also we explored using another classifier, another support vector
machine to be able to classify the predictions. So it's like a meta classifier to be able
to classify the predictions of each of the ten instances. So each of the predictions
become their own features to the next classifier. And then we use that to predict, to make
one final prediction for that subject. And is that, yeah, is the meta classifier method
more performant than a majority or some kind of quorum based system?
Yeah, in our case, it performs slightly better than just doing a majority count. And that's
partly because it's able to take into account temporal dynamics now of this, of the, the
original instances in time. It's able to, it's able to find the relationship between,
between these instances over time, pretty much, and connect the ultimate outcome.
And the example that you use was ten data points a second is, is one second, is that the,
was that just a, for illustration or is, it does one second, worth of sample, give you
enough to identify this time varying indicator in the fundamental frequency of aspects.
Yeah, so one of the, one of the things that we've done is, we use longer segments, but
we, first of all, break them down into one second segments. It's also a way of, of dealing
with the fact that we don't have so many subjects. And we want to make sure that whatever we build
is, it leaves room for, for uncertainty. And so what we do is we break down the samples
into one second segments, perform classification on each one second segment, and then average
the results to give a prediction for that subject. So there's several levels of breaking
down, including this. So we, we, we, we, we, we are the very lowest level deal with the
one second segments. And then we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we average data on
sample data at the higher level to make a prediction for each patient. So in practice
to, in the test, we did with the mobile application. What we do is, we're called lens
of 10 to 20 seconds. And we break it down that way for the classification. So we split
it. That also helps us to do parallel computations if the device supports it. And then we eventually
combine the predictions. And in terms of, you know, where you are currently, what kind
of results are you saying with the, with the method? So, so the, the paper we have published,
we obtained about precisely 86% of sensitivity. So that was the detection rate of infants who
had a sphixia. And it's 9% of a specificity. That was detection rate of infants who did
not have a sphixia who were healthy. And this is the one we published in, in 2015, that's
one the basic part of what that nips. Nips machine learning for health care. Right, right. And
practically speaking, your, your baseline is against, you know, in the field, it's against
an unated doctor trying to identify asphyxia just based on being presented with an infant
that isn't responding normally. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, that's what would, would like to,
to change. And that's, you know, that's not good enough to have the doctor just eyeball
it. Right, right. But it should be clear that there's a very clinical, there's a gold standard,
you know, there's a gold standard, which is used in, in Canada and in many other parts
of the world. That's the blood. And that's a general. Exactly. The blood class analysis.
Okay. Right. So detect this example of the baby's blood through, usually through the
cut on bleak record, the arterial blood sample. And they analyze it for several parameters,
bilirubin, acidosis and electrolytes and so on. And usually they combine this with the
abgas core of the infant. The abgas core is a, is a score assigned to literally, literally
every baby who has been born for the last 40 years. And it's a physical assessment of how
old baby is doing on five measures. So that's combined with this blood gas analysis to make
a confirmatory diagnosis of a fiction. And that is, is the blood gas analysis also something
that is routinely performed or is it performed when there's, you know, a certain level of the,
of the score or some indication of a problem? Well, in Montreal and the rest of Canada,
it's a routine process for every baby that's born. And really that's one of the things that makes
it very convenient for us to do the study here. It's because we would not have to as part of our
study design decide how we collect the gold standard. The gold standard is already a part of
day-to-day clinical operations. We just have to read the charts to get that data. So yeah,
it's routine here. Interesting. And you mentioned that you're working on another project
there as well in addition to Benoit. What's that one? It's called the APEX project. APEX has in
A4APEX, the stands for automated prediction of extubation readiness. It has, I guess, one technical
term, the extubation. And basically that refers to the process of winning a child who is on the
respiratory support. Yeah, so usually infants who are born pre-term, pre-matchell, which is
usually around seven weeks or they're about, is I usually, the lungs are actually not well developed
well-formed to support spontaneous breathing for them. And so they usually require respiratory
support. And this happens in general through the insertion of a tube down the attractor.
Yeah. And the other end of the tube is connected to a ventilator. And this ventilator provides oxygen
to the infant at a certain interval, you know, tunable by the diffusitions. But these positions
have to make a very critical choice under this setting. So they must decide when to remove the
infant from this setup, from mechanical ventilation, as it's called, because the longer you leave the
infant on that, that system, the increased chances of lung disease, because, you know, you've placed
a plastic tube in the trachea. And that causes less interactions with the walls of the trachea
and so on. And so to that degree, it causes something called BP, the bronchopulmonary dysplasia,
which effectively is lung disease. And that's bad because it's going to be a live lung disability
in most cases. So, but also you don't want to remove it too early. So that's the case when you
leave it too much too long. If you remove it too early, the infant may not be ready to breathe on
its own. And what could happen is that the infant would require re-intubation. So intubation is a
process of putting the tube in and extubation is a process of removing the tube. The infant could
require re-intubation. And re-intubation is a technically difficult challenge for infants that have
been integrated already because they're swelling the trachea and so on. And in some cases they never
succeed and the baby ends up having to die. And so there's this trade-off between how one is the
optimal time to extubate an infant on the intubation in the ICU. Can I ask the stupid question,
which is can't they remove the oxygen source without removing the tube and see if it works?
Well, that turns out to not be a stupid question.
Because for our study, that's indeed what we are tracking. Because one of the things the doctors
do as partly a way of evaluating how ready the baby is is to disconnect the ventilator and let the
child breathe through the tube first to just observe how well the infant does. The challenge with
this is that while it's a good process better than nothing, it still has resulted to
to currently North America the failure rate for re-intubation is about 25%. So the doctors get
it wrong about 25% of the time. And really that's the core of the project we're trying to fix. I
was trying to save those 25% of babies who end up either being re-intubated or who end up with
long-term disability. So in a lot of ways similar to the asphyxia problem you have doctors that
don't have an effective way of clinically assessing whether the baby is able to breathe on its own.
And so they do in fact disconnect the ventilator without taking the tube out. But they're just eyeballing
whether the baby looks to be ready. And in 25% of the cases they get it wrong, take the tube out
and only then find out it has to go back in.
Exactly. I say eyeballing, but the doctors have many medical devices connected to the baby,
respiratory monitors and so on. And you know the look at these data, look at the patterns and
make it an informed decision. And you know that explains why they do this too.
Tell you well, 75% is not too bad. It could be better and that's really the goal of the project.
To say how can we take machine learning methods, apply to an automated analysis of the heart rate
signals, respiratory signals that we get from this infant during that spontaneous
bidding trial period. So during that time when the ventilator is turned off, because that's
usually the true measure of how well the infant might do when they don't have that ventilator on.
So we take these signals at that point in time and we are building a primarily
time series methods to analyze them and say how can we make a prediction from this.
Okay. Yeah. And what stage are you in with this project?
We are at the stage where, as I mentioned earlier, you know, in December 2015, we reached
we reached our target of 200 and a set of the... Oh right.
Right. Yeah. Yeah. But that was the target of the project anyways, to get to about,
to get to 200 babies for our training and development and to get another 50 for validation.
So those 50 will be left to the very end of the project, say, five year long project.
We left to the very end before we to evaluate what about methods that we've developed on the other
parts. So we've done quite a bunch of analysis on the data over the last year,
but really much of it has been, much of the detailed work about, say, I've been starting this year
since we now have the many multitasets that we require. Yeah. We've written about a few,
a few works we've done on the data in terms of using Markov chain models to model the respiratory
patterns and how they change over time. Yeah. So we have a paper that we have published about
this work last year at the Engineering and Medicine and Biology Conference.
Okay. And what was the conclusion of that paper?
Yeah. The paper was pretty interesting. At least we find it a bit for people. It was pretty
interesting. So in that case, what we did was we did not look at the raw signals of how the
heart rate is changing, you know, the respiratory rate in particular. We looked more at states. So
so breeding in general goes through a number of states. There's five of them roughly.
There's synchronous breeding, which is when the breeding in the rib cage and abdomen,
in synchrony, it's very creative. So they're happening at the compression and expansion is
happening at the same rate pretty much in both sides. There is a synchronous breeding when they're
out of phase. That's the second pattern. The third pattern is the pause states when the infant
experiences a cessation of breeding at some point. And there's the movement artifact phase,
which is somewhat a phase induced by external factors, either the infant is moving or it's been
found by nurses and so on. And then there's the last phase is called an unknown state.
And that is just the ones that don't fit into any of the four defined patterns. And so the
goal of this project was to see how we could use switching models like the Markov chain,
which models the transitions from one state to another. How we could take that and apply to this
to learn more about what kind of transitions do infants who are ready for excavation go through
and walk on of transitions to infants who are not ready for excavation go through and could this
inform the classifiers will build in the future. And so it was a more of a modeling task using chain
models. And do you think that the Markov chain model will play a big role in the approach you
eventually take to create a diagnostic tool? Yeah. On one hand, it emphasized some of the things
I was known somewhat within the clinical community that for instance pause states are bad.
Session of breeding is not good because that means there's no power to drive the longer activity.
So it's very important for some things like that. But also we observed some interesting trends
in terms of the transitions from some of these phases to the others. That would eventually serve
us features into whatever classifiers we build in the near future. Awesome. Awesome. Well,
you've been very gracious with your time and we're running out of it. So I'd love to dig more
into this. But I think in lieu of that we'll just make sure that we have a link to
to this second paper here. But Charles, thank you so much for taking the time. You're doing
some really interesting work. And I appreciate it having the opportunity to learn about it.
Yeah, thank you very much. Some of us had a nice chat to meet you as well. Awesome. Thanks.
All right, everyone. That's our show for today. For more information on Charles or any of the topics
covered in this episode, head on over to twimlai.com slash talk slash 112. And remember to submit your
thoughts on AI in your life at twimlai.com slash my AI. Thanks so much for listening and catch you
next time.