Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast why interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
I want to start out with a huge thanks to everyone who joined in on our My AI discussion
over the last few weeks.
We received some outstanding entries to the contest, and now it's your turn to check
them out and vote for a winner.
Do this by visiting our contest page at twimbleai.com slash My AI.
Swimming remains open through Sunday March 14th at 11.59pm Eastern time.
A quick bit about the next Twimble online meetup.
The meetup will be on Tuesday March 13th, and Sean Devlin will be doing an in-depth review
of reinforcement learning and presenting the Google Deep Mind paper, playing Atari with
deep reinforcement learning.
Get on over to twimbleai.com slash Meetup to learn more or register.
For today's show, the final episode in our Black and AI series, I'm speaking with Zena
Tavarez, a PhD student in both the Department of Brain and Cognitive Sciences and the Computer
Science and Artificial Intelligence Lab at MIT.
I spent some time with Zena after his talk at the Strange Loop Conference, titled Running
Programs in Reverse for Deeper AI.
Zena shared some great insight into his work on program inversion, an area which lies
at the intersection of Bayesian modeling, deep learning, and computational logic.
We set the stage with the discussion of inverse graphics and the similarity between graphic
inversion and vision inversion.
We then discussed the application of these techniques to intelligent systems, including
the idea of parametric inversion.
Last, but not least, Zena details how these techniques might be implemented and discusses
his work on reverse flow, a library to execute tensorflow programs backwards, and sigma.jl,
a probabilistic programming environment implemented in the Dynamic Programming Language, Julia.
This talk packs a punch, and I'm glad to share it with you.
Let's get to it.
Hey everyone, I am here at the Strange Loop Conference, and I have the pleasure of being
joined by Zena Tavarez, and Zena is a PhD student at MIT, and he is, actually, he spoke
this morning here at the conference on Running Programs in Reverse for Deeper AI, and I'm
really interested in hearing more about what that's all about.
So welcome.
Thank you, Zena.
Great to have you on.
So why don't we start by having you tell us a little bit about your background, how
you got interested in AI, what are you up to at MIT, all that stuff?
Yeah, so I'm from London.
I studied electronic engineering for my undergrad, and I think I first got into research.
I became interested in research when I studied abroad in Japan, and so I went to Japan,
and I worked in this lab, the PI for that lab, the advisor for that lab.
His famous Japanese guy, you might have seen him, he builds these really lifelike robots,
so he builds them of people in the lab, so look, there's one of him, and there's one
of some of the lab students, oh wow, and so that was my first kind of touch of research,
and I thought, this is a cool environment, and also I thought studying the brain is a
cool thing, and so I finished my undergrad, I did a master's degree, which is in basically
neuroscience, and so then after that I thought, okay, let me come to the States, and I came
to MIT, and I joined MIT in the BCS, which is the brain and cognitive sciences department,
so it's a mixture of neuroscience and cognitive science, which is basically psychology,
okay, and from there I kind of transitioned more into the computer science side, and so
now I sit in C cell, the computer science AI lab, and where I work on basically using
ideas from computer science and programming languages to study things about how the mind
works.
But wow, wow, sounds like a, you've been a bunch of interesting places, for sure.
So I read the abstract for your talk, running programs in reverse, and it sounds like
that's a thing, like programming version, I hadn't heard about that before, you tell
us a little bit about programming version and like, how, where's the intersection between
that and AI?
Sure, so maybe the best way to describe it is how I came to the problem, and so there's
a professor at MIT called Just Ten and Bound, and when I joined MIT he was talking about
this idea.
Just Ten and Bound, the networking guy, or operating systems, I don't think so, he's
more of a psychologist, a co, okay, I think there's another Just Ten and Bound that wrote
a book, and I forget which book that we use in, in my engineering program, either networking
or operating systems or something.
Yeah, well I think it's the same thing, it could be the same thing, anyway, so Just Ten
and Bound, MIT and MIT, okay, and he told me about this idea of inverse graphics, and
the way he describes it is basically like this, so you can think of rendering this process,
which using animation films like Toy Story to go from a 3D representation of the world
to 2D images or a video that you're going to see when you go to the movies, and you
can think of vision as in seeing as the inverse of that process, in the sense that I get
into my eyes two dimensional images, and somehow from now I infer the three dimensional
structure of the world, I infer the geometry I can figure out where the light saw, I can
figure out where I am in relation to the world, and so there's this like inverse relationship
between rendering or graphics and vision, okay, and so it's not, I don't think it's his
idea, it's an old idea in computer vision, but nobody's really taking it literally,
right, and so some other people in Josh's lab, like Tedges and Elka, they've worked on similar
projects, and the idea I had was okay, what if we like literally literally took this
idea, like what if we took a rendering algorithm similar to the kind they use in computer graphics
and tried to run that algorithm backwards, from the output, from the image literally backwards
to the 3D structure, oh wow, okay, so that was the kind of the motivation, like how I came
to this project, and then after we started, I mean there's many issues that arise, but
we realized that it's actually kind of a general framework that we can use to think about
many different kinds of problems, okay, and it sounds like at least in the graphics case,
it works generally, I mean it works in the research sense, right, so I mean it produces
something, yeah, we have a working prototype for a particular kind of graphics, so we can
take in 2D images from a fairly primitive voxel renderer, so the images in the output
are 3D voxel shapes, so we can't do like super complicated geometric structure, but we
can do kind of cool interesting shapes, and we're doing it in a way which I don't think
anybody has done before, so we hope that we can scale up to these, to real realistic
scenes, but that's going to require a lot more work, okay, okay, and so what you were talking
about here was applying that to AI, so yeah, so I started with this example of inverse
rendering, inverse graphics, right, but the way I opened my talk was talking about this
idea of mental simulation, so mental simulation is an idea, it's an old idea in psychology,
and the basic idea is that the way that you can reason about the world, like the way that
I can pick up objects or know that something is stable or unstable, is that I have a kind
of simulator in my head, right, and so I look at the world, I can show up to model of
the world inside my head, and then I can run that simulation and figure out what's going
to happen, so I can figure out, oh, this is, this is, this object's not stable because
in my simulation it falls over, right, and so one of the ways that we're trying to basically
extend this idea of inverse graphics to more general problems is say, or can we like
do inverse physical simulation, right, so for example, you could say things like, oh,
what I want to do is fold some clothes, right, or I want to, you know, pick up some object
in some, you know, in some dynamic environment, and so one way to frame that problem is to
say, well, I have some end state that I'm trying to get to, let me run a kind of a physical
simulation backwards and say, okay, what are the inputs that have to go into that system
for me to reach the desired end state, okay, and so that's the way that we're trying to solve
the problem, I mean, many people approach the problem in various different ways, I would
say that the kind of the main distinguishing point about our approach is that we really
try to take this idea literally, we take real physical simulations and we're trying
to run them backwards, the tools that we've developed, they're quite general, so they
can apply to many different problems, so if you can reformulate your problem in terms
of a kind of programming version, then hopefully we can have a like a stab at trying to solve
it.
And so do I need to reformulate my problem in terms of, in the terms of programming
version, or is that something that your tools will do or help me do?
That's something you need to do, but I mean, it's not like, you're speaking of me reformulating
my problem at the level of a problem statement, or like, I've got the, okay, not my program.
Yeah, yeah, so the problem statement, that's what I'm talking about, so if you can formulate
your problem in your head or like, as a former programming version, and what I would argue
is that actually many problems can be formulated in terms of programming version, right, because
programs are very general things, right, can you give us some examples of ones that will
help us wrap our heads around the concept?
Sure, so, okay, so for example, and I'm not saying that we can solve this kind of problem
yet, right, but for example, you know, if you had a big kind of quantum simulator, right,
which takes this input, some molecules, and as output, you know, it says, okay, how efficient
would this molecule be as, you know, in a solar panel, for example, okay, so this is like
a forward simulator, it does all kind of quantum simulations, and it says, okay, the efficiency
of this molecule, you know, is 90%, whatever, right, so you can think of the inverse of that
process as going from the efficiency that you want back to the molecule, so now you have
a kind of discovery of chemicals, right, got it, or optimization, right, so, you know,
optimization, optimization comes up in all kinds of fields, and so you have some loss function
which takes in something and says, okay, how good is that thing, right, if you can invert
an optimization, so if you can invert a loss function, you can do optimization, you can say,
okay, here is the cost that I'm trying to achieve, right, what is the input that, you know,
realizes that cost, right, it strikes me from hearing the examples that you gave that,
you know, the challenges that the, in the forward direction, the output space is like much more
constrained, it's a number, right, whereas in the reverse direction, the output space is massive,
if not infinite, yeah, yeah, yeah, exactly, so, yeah, so when I first came to this, you know,
this idea, you know, I remember I was sitting in one of Josh's, just telling Bob, so that
means, I think, okay, why don't we just try and run this program backwards, right, and obviously,
the first thing you get into is that often these functions or these programs are not invertible,
right, which means that there are many outputs which map to the same, so many inputs which map
to the same output, and so in the inverse direction, you have a choice, like, which way should you go,
which way should you go backwards, right, if I've got any x's which map to y, and I'm going
backwards from y to x, like, what should I choose, how do I do that, right, and so the theory that
I came up with, we now call parametric inversion, okay, and basically says, if you're trying to invert
a non-invertical function, so there's multiple x, there's multiple inputs which map to the same
output, we can parameterize that choice, okay, we construct this new thing, we call it a parametric
inverse, so we'll take in some value y, but also a parameter theta, and give you back one of the
x's which map to y, so just to give me a very simple example, absolute value function is not invertible,
right, so because if I take the absolute value of five, I get five, yeah, if I take absolute value
of minus five, I get also get five, right, but I can construct this thing called a parametric
inverse, and it will take in some value, let's call it y, five in this case, and the parameter,
let's say it's either one or minus one, and it will just return this parameter theta times y,
right, so the point is that the output, depending on your choice of theta, will be either
five or minus five, right, obviously that's a kind of a trivial example, but the intuition or the
idea that we had was, oh, you can define these simple inverses for all of our simple functions,
like absolute value, addition, multiplication, sign, and so on, and it turns out with a little bit of
work, actually you can define inverses for much more complicated functions, or much more complicated
programs. And is the idea then for, with the example that you gave around finding a molecule that
achieves x, you know, a level of efficiency in a solar panel that you would be able to
constrain by some set of molecules, or for example, that would be your parameter.
So in this case, so, yeah, so suppose you give me some program, it's forward simulation,
right, and I think I can construct this parametric inverse, so you'll have many parameters,
and as you vary over the parameters, you'll get out different molecules with the desired
efficiency. And so if you have some further constraints, I don't know, maybe you want a small
molecule, or maybe you want a molecule that you can synthesize, then you can add these constraints
to the, you can impose those constraints on the parameter space, right, and so a parametric
inverse basically gives you the choice, you choose a parameter value, and it'll be back one of
like a different input which maps to the same output. And so you mentioned that you have
your current researches, or you mentioned in your abstract, I should say your current researches
applying this specifically to TensorFlow programs, and inverting the computational graphs for
deep neural nets. So yeah, so we built a lot of machinery around TensorFlow programs.
Okay. It's not so much that we're focused on inverting neural networks, although that's
something that we've been considering, just that TensorFlow programs have a nice kind of
representation which is amenable to our algorithms, right, and so TensorFlow, you know,
the graph structure, the graph structure, yeah, so people often use it for, you know,
neural networks, but really it's a general kind of programming language, like in a better
programming language. And so we have a tool, some GitHub, in some kind of slightly broken
state, but one thing I would say is that more recently we've been moving over to using the
Julia program in language. Okay. And so we've kind of been building our own version of TensorFlow
in Julia. It's still thing. Yeah, so we still can compile down to TensorFlow if you want to use
TensorFlow. Okay. TensorFlow has all these great things for optimization and so on that we want to,
you know, I don't want to re-implement. Right. So we can still compile down to TensorFlow and Python,
but we basically we move to Julia because, um, basically because of the type system it allows us
to do a lot more things more efficiently with a lot less code. So that's the, that's the
direction we're going. And I would also recommend other people check out Julia if they get the
chance. Huh. So can you give me some examples of the application of this AI systems or deep learning
systems? Yeah. So, so the ones, I mean, the ones I've spoken about in vision. So, you know,
basically if we're trying to build robots that act in the real world, they're going to have to
manipulate objects in the real world. Right. So, you know, for example, you can pick up a cup,
right. This cup on the table and you know, it's, you know, it's a little bit elastic. It has a
particular shape. It has some, you know, resistance. All these things you know about the physical world
allow you to freely interact with the physical world. Right. And so you have some physical
intuition. And I would argue that in order to build robots that aren't so rigid in how they
interact with the world, we're going, we're going to have to kind of embed that physical knowledge
into their brains as well. Okay. And one way to do that is to allow them to have a simulator in
a mind. But many of the things that they'll use this simulation for are kind of inverse simulation.
So they'll, you know, for example, they may see the cup on the floor and they can figure out,
oh, it fell over at some point in time. Or to go to the lower, like the lower perceptual things,
like how does a robot learn to see? How does a robot see in the world? Well, it's got to take in
images, you know, in its camera eyes and somehow figure out the geometric structure of the world.
So it knows that the door, you know, is so, you know, so far away, it can just
ambiguous between the colors of the lights versus the color of the material. So I think many of
like the core, I don't have a like a concrete thing that we're trying to build, but I think many of
the core problems in AI, you know, this kind of technology is relevant to me. It's still a research
project. I mean, yeah. So it's kind of thing that we do. And so you were careful to kind of
distinguish between TensorFlow as a general programming framework and it's common use in deep
learning. But does the work that you've done and the results that you've seen with reverse flow
apply to deep neural nets that are constructed in TensorFlow? And like, what are there any like
practical examples that you can cite of taking like a real TensorFlow program and doing this program
in version to it and having it produce something? Yeah. So there was a lot of, I mean, there's a
lot of work with like adversarial examples recently. And like, but before, you know, those work
basically say, okay, if I've trained some neural network, I want to find out, you know, what
inputs would cause a kind of weird misclassification. People have worked on this for a little while.
And so in some sense, we can invert neural networks in a kind of, in a sense that, you know,
even a complicated neural network eventually just boils down to some sequence of primitive operations.
Sure. Basically multiplications, sounds, and some right, nonlinearity. Even that nonlinearity
also boils down to even simpler things. So because our inversion algorithm is defined in terms
of these primitive operations, in principle, we can invert, you know, a neural network with
the current framework. But in practice, it's not the best way to do it. And so one of the things
that we've been working on is how can we kind of take a better approach to inverting neural networks?
And so to the second part of your question, like, why might you want to do that?
But for me, I think the most interesting application is, again, inverting models of the world. So
I've worked on inverse graphics. And to do that, I write down a normal render in algorithm.
I happen to write it in TensorFlow, but, you know, I could have written it in Python or see
or so on. But I think humans, we learn algorithms. We learn algorithms, you know, from experience.
And so it'll be nice if we could take a learned algorithm. So something like a neural network
and also invert that. So I do, I can do inverse graphics. But the algorithm that I'm
inverting is a more realistic version of reality. Is there an implication there that you're
inverting not a, I guess the picture that I had in my head of this was that you're
not you're inverting a, I guess an architecture absence of like having been trained.
Yeah. But it sounds like what you're saying is you're, you know, the learning is coming in through
the training. And so we're inverting this trained. No, it's not something that we're doing right now.
Right. Right now we think conceptual. This is conceptual. I mean, maybe like a better example would be
in like physics and dynamics. So we can build pretty impressive physical simulators that work
well for, you know, rigid bodies and, you know, some elastic bodies. But they're not so good at
things like hair, for example, and they're not so good at simulating things like cloth. And yet
humans can still, you know, manipulate cloth. We still have a good intuition about how that works.
And so I think a learning approach could supplement that so we can maybe have some part of that
model which is, you know, handwritten and some part of that model is learn from experience. And there
are people who are working on this right now. It's interesting. So one of the examples that
comes to mind for me is there are some folks at Berkeley in their intelligent robotics lab that
are applying reinforcement learning to teaching a robot how to tie a knot. Right. Right. And a rope.
And so, you know, they're, you know, the rope, the rope is basically trying to mess around with
the rope and learn the rope dynamics. And it sounds like, you know, the approach that you're describing
would be, I don't know, how, how would the approach you're describing fit into that? It's like,
once you learn this model for kind of basic rope dynamics, you can invert it to what is the
conceptual thing that you're inverting it to? So like the way you have to formulate this,
formulate it in this way, you'd say, okay, I have a model of, you know, rope dynamics.
Right. And you can think about this as a, probably a temporal model, right. So the time is
available. And I have some desired state, like I want, you know, after some amount of time to
whatever, right. I want the rope to be in a knotted state. Right. And so the inputs that
at system are my actions. And obviously the system also acts in the absence of me doing anything.
Right. Right. And so it's the inversion in the sense that I have to figure out what are the
actions that I need to input into the system for me to tie them not. Right. Right. And so this is,
I'm supposed to, these actions produce this model. Right. And so like, I mean, in some ways,
you know, people have an intuition. It's like, if I want to do something, like, what do I have to
do for that to be true? Yeah. And so that's how you would formulate the problem in this way.
Um, but the rope dynamics, as I'm saying, as I've been saying, this is something I think you
could learn. Right. We don't, I mean, maybe people do have, you know, good models for rope dynamics,
I'm not sure. I think it's so work in progress. Right. Okay. So yeah.
Interesting. Interesting. So what else did you cover in the talk?
So the third, I mean, the first, I talked a bit about Julia. I would say that the first,
you know, 10 minutes was, actually, I talked a little about psychology experiments.
Okay. Um, from what perspective? So there's an experiment from the 1970s. I mean, so
these are all about this idea of mental simulation. Okay. And it's kind of, you know,
it's kind of hard to describe without diagrams, but the basic idea, it's called mental rotation,
the basic idea is that you can see different shapes. And they're either the same shape,
but rotate it from different angles or their different shapes. Like different shapes entirely.
Okay. And so people did these studies where they said, okay, look at many of these shapes and
say whether you think they're the same or whether you think they're different. And what they found
is a very tight linear correlation with the angle of rotation and the amount of time it took people
to respond. Okay. Like, lending some support to the idea that the way people answer this question
is that they look at these, they look at the shapes and they do a kind of mental rotation. And they
say, oh, I can rotate shape A into shape B. And like, if they're more, you know, if they're more
rotated, they're longer than simulation takes. Yeah. And so like a whole subfield of psychological
research came out of that idea. And so some part of my talk was saying, okay, this is, you know,
obviously there's a lot of who work there. And I always see they've done a lot of studies,
can we take that idea and make it computational? Can we build computational models of it?
And can we build an AI that can do something similar? And if we were to do that, what kind of
technologies would we need? What kind of algorithm would we need? So like, personally, I'm
motivated by like core interest in small studies like this, which pinpoint something interesting
about how the mind works. And then you realize that despite all the kind of core stuff that's
happening in AI at the moment, deep learning, there are all these really simple things that we really
haven't even got the right way to think about. Right. And so those are the things that interest
the most. Right. Right. Cool. And then you mentioned Julia. You mentioned the type, the type safe
aspect of it. Is Julia something that comes up a lot in the context of AI? Does it lend
itself to that type of work? Specifically, I haven't heard it come up in that context much.
Yeah. So I'm in the main frameworks for AI definitely in Python. Sure. Right. And I guess
that's taught, which is a lure. Right. But I would say Julia is building momentum. So Julia,
I mean, it came out of MIT and the people who did it, you know, well, kind of data scientists,
maybe not machine learning people as such, but people who use MATLAB or see, I think that
I was watching a guy watching a talk. And one of the main developers who said he had this
huge stack of C, R, MATLAB, and Python. Right. And it's like, why is it so complicated? And so
that was kind of the birth of of this language. To the main point, so that one, it's very fast.
Okay. It's dynamic. It's also compiled. And it has a kind of interest in type system,
like a multi-method dispatch type system. I mean, it's what does that mean?
So like in an object-oriented language, like Python, for example, or C++, you have some
object, like, I don't know, you have like cat, and you do cat dot, you know, make a sound, right?
Cat dot meow. Cat dot meow. Um, in Julia, the methods, so this is what people call a single
dispatch, right? But in Julia, the methods are not part of the object. They live, they live in
like a separate space. Okay. And so you would do meow, which takes in an object of type cat,
and it would meow that cat. And so obviously you can do more things. You can have meow
taking an object of type cat and some other object, dog and, you know, the cat meow as a dog.
So it sounds like a, you know, a simple thing, but it turns out that if you build your language
on that principle, lots of nice, elegant features fall out. Um, is this related to the content
of mixes? It's, you know, it's definitely not used in machine learning so much, but I would say there's
a few packages like flux.jl. There's also a TensorFlow binding, TensorFlow.jl. Okay.
Um, and so I think it's getting momentum. And I think because it's built on like a, like a nice
set of core principles, I think actually it has the opportunity to strive as a machine learning,
language. Okay. That's what I want. Nice. Nice. And does it, it presumably, it has some kind of,
you know, native or provided by a package, uh, strong notion of matrices and arrays and all
that stuff. Yeah. Yeah. So yeah, all of that stuff is. Oh, that's there. And it's really well designed
as well. They put a lot of thought into how to take what's good about MATLAB, discard, what's bad.
And so you have multi-dimensional arrays and you have all the kind of things that you would expect
from like a numerical program language. Right. And it's fascinating. Also, there's like a GPU
library now so you can call native CUDA. Okay. So there's a lot of stuff. Okay. Cool.
Uh, did we hit on everything? Did you cover it in your talk? I think so pretty much. Yeah. Awesome.
Awesome. Well, thanks so much for taking a few minutes to chat with us. All right. Thanks a lot. Appreciate it. Thanks.
All right, everyone. That's our show for today. For more information on Xenna or any of the topics
covered in this episode, head on over to twimlai.com slash talk slash 114.
And definitely remember to vote for your favorite My AI video at twimlai.com slash My AI.
And of course, thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.