Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast why interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
In this episode, I speak with Cassinia Konyashkova, a PhD student in a CV lab at Acole Polytechnic
Ferrahal de Lozan in Switzerland.
Cassinia and I connected at Nips back in December to discuss her very interesting research into
some ways we might apply machine learning to ease the challenge of creating label data sets
for machine learning.
The first paper we discuss is learning active learning from data, which suggests a data-driven
approach to active learning that trains a secondary model to identify unlabeled data points
which, when labeled, would likely have the greatest impact on our primary model's performance.
We also discuss our paper, Learning Intelligent Dialogues for Bounding Box Annotation, in
which she trains an agent to guide the actions of a human annotator to more quickly produce
bounding boxes.
Last week, I attended an investor conference in San Francisco.
Having spent a couple of packed days being peppered with questions about the state of the
AI market and its various players, I wrote about some of the key themes that emerged
for the latest issue of my newsletter.
If you're interested in the commercial side of the AI industry, you'll definitely want
to check it out.
If you don't already subscribed to my newsletter, visit twimmolai.com slash newsletter or just
email info at twimmolai.com asking to be added.
You'll automatically get the latest issue when you sign up.
Quickly, a bit about the next Twimmol online meetup.
On Tuesday, March 13th, Sean Devlin will be doing an in-depth review of reinforcement
learning and presenting the Google Deep Mind paper, playing Atari with deep reinforcement
learning.
Head over to twimmolai.com slash meetup to learn more or register.
All right, let's roll.
All right, everyone, we are here at NIPS and I am with Cassinia Konošková.
Cassinia is a PhD student in the computer vision lab at EPFL in Lozan, Switzerland.
Cassinia, welcome to the podcast.
Thank you.
Nice to meet you today.
Absolutely.
Great to meet you as well.
So why don't we get started by having you tell us a little bit about your background and
how you got involved in computer vision and machine learning, artificial intelligence?
Okay, so it probably all started with my master degree when I just heard this cool name,
machine learning.
Okay.
I had a very little idea of what it is all about, but it sounded exciting, and then I learned
that you can actually recognize Cassinia in the pictures if you use machine learning and
then I thought, great, that's the thing for me.
No, I'm kidding.
No, it wasn't the real motivation, but yeah, it just sounds fun.
But yeah, it sounded like a fun field to be, and it was probably a little bit before,
it became so popular and so famous, but I was likely to be there at the beginning.
So I joined the program in machine learning and algorithms in the University of Helsinki.
And after that, I went from my PhD program in Switzerland at a quality technique for the
Grand de la Sant, and I joined the computer vision lab with Pascal Four, who is famous in
the computer vision community, but as you know, today computer vision very much depends
on machine learning, so it was a great match to combine this two fields that interest
me.
Okay, awesome.
Awesome.
And you're here at NIPS, sharing some of the work you're doing, some of your research.
Can you tell me a little bit about that?
Mm-hmm.
Yes, sure.
So I'm working in the field that is called active learning.
Okay.
So the basic idea is that normally in the traditional machine learning, we have a lot of training
data, which we collect from human experts, and then they provide us with the labels for
this data when we're doing the supervised machine learning, and having this huge annotated
corpus of data, we can train a model, which will help us to predict for the new coming
data what labels were assigned, either it's a classification or a regression task.
The problem that we're dealing with is that we don't have this training data available,
and we're trying to select the data in the optimal way, so that if we annotate it, we can
learn the machine learning model as quickly as possible.
So the idea is to reduce human annotation efforts, and at the same time achieve similar
quality of performance of the machine learning algorithms.
And what I'm doing, I'm presenting the work that is called learning active learning from
data.
Okay.
So we're going even one step further, and instead of trying to construct some specific
algorithm that would select data for us, we're trying to learn an algorithm from the
previous examples of active learning algorithms runs.
Okay.
So for example, the very popular active learning algorithm is called uncertainty sampling.
In this case, we have, for example, suppose we have 10 data points that are labeled for
us, it's very little and we probably cannot predict much based on them, but we can still
have a very rough idea of how the model should be, and then we can construct, for example,
the decision hyperplane, and then we will select points that lie closest to the decision
boundary, and we would think that as the model is the most uncertain right now about this
points, if we annotate these kind of points, they would help to train a better model in
the future.
So instead of labeling the data just uniformly a trend from the very big corpus, we select
the data that would help the model the most.
And this kind of algorithms, like I mentioned, uncertainty sampling, and there are many
other ones that were introduced in the literature.
The problem is that on different applications, they're all competing, some of them are doing
better in this scenario, some are doing better in that scenario.
And for example, in my previous work, I worked on specific algorithm to work with images,
so to take the advantage of the structure and some smoothness assumptions of the images
to annotate data.
But then there is nothing principle there, and we don't know which of the algorithm would
actually perform the best at priority, so we have to test them, and this is all human
annotation costs.
So my idea is that we have some annotated data sets already, and then if we simulate
the runs of this data collection process, we can actually see what kind of points led
to a good behavior of active learning algorithm, and which points didn't improve the quality
much.
And then we can try to predict in the future what kind of points should be selected.
So in particular, I'm dealing with station where I just generate a lot of data myself,
just like some synthetic data sets of very simple shapes, but they still have a lot
of variability of them, some in some cases, if I deal with binary classification, sometimes
the classes overlap a lot, sometimes they're easily separable, two-dimensional shapes
or...
Yes, right now it's just very simple, we can do it with a very kind of cheap procedure
with just two-dimensional data, and then we run active learning on them, just kind of
this data collection, and then we look at the state of the classifier, how the classifier
was trained, and the data points, and we look how much adding each kind of data point
reduced the classification error for us.
So for example, we label two data points, we train a model, we look at what kind of
error this model resulted in, as we know all the ground rules, as this is the simulated
data.
Then we try to select one more data point, and we get three points.
Now in these three points, we can learn a new model, and it results in a new error.
And now we can look at the difference between the error of the model with two points and
the error of the model with three points, and the difference would show us how much adding
this third data point helped the model.
And so now as we go on in training, we memorize the states of the classifier, for example
I'm dealing with something very simple, like random forest classification, I can look
at what was the depth of the tree, what was the variance of the forest, what was the cross
for the data accuracy, and then we look at the data points, for example what was the probability
to belong to a certain class for a certain point, and we have how much in this situation,
this particular data point reduced the error.
So based on this data, after we collected for all synthetic data sets, we can train a regressor
that will predict in the future, based on the state of the classifier, and given data
points from the pool of unlabeled data, which of them would result in the highest reduction
in error, and this is the sample that we select to be annotated.
And we all started with this very simple two-dimensional data, and of course the easiest is to train
it on the similar kind of data, and this is our simplest scenario, then we try to complicate
it more and more, for example we deal with the soil-like problems when we have a classification
where the data is in the form of checkerboard, and imagine so we have like positive class,
negative class, positive class, negative class, or they're kind of repeating in the checkerboard
style.
And this kind of data sets are more tricky for machine learning, usually and active learning
is not an exception.
And if we apply the very famous and very popular uncertainty something algorithm, that
is often difficult to outperform in normal situations, in this case it would perform even
worse than random, because it is confused by this checkerboard structure.
And is the difficulty with this structure because the regions are non-contiguous or is
it something else?
The thing is that for example if we imagine the checkerboard is 2x2, so we have, suppose
we have rent class on the top left, then blue class on the top right, and then blue
class again on the bottom left, 10 red class on the bottom right, suppose that we selected
one sample from the upper red class, and one sample from the upper blue class as our
initial examples, then we construct some kind of decision boundary, and what and so does
something we do, we would try to refine this boundary and it would take a very long time
to discover that there are two other regions of these classes that are in completely different
order.
So what uncertainty something is good at is it's refining boundary when we already have
some reasonable approximation of this boundary.
And this can be a problem in many real data sets when one class can be represented by
some several modalities of examples.
And so in this case we show that then this very popular algorithm performs worse than
just random something, by random something I mean that we would just select data, random,
and then we label everything.
So it's definitely not a very efficient strategy, but in this case it does better than uncertainty
something.
However, if we learn this strategy from the previous examples of this active learning
runs, it figures out that it shouldn't follow the strategy of refining the boundary.
And for example, in this case what it seems that it learns is that when the classifier
is uncertain, it's better not to trust it at all, not to follow any of the predictions
of the classifier, but instead just do some random exploration in the beginning until
we collect enough data on which we can train a better classifier.
And then we would be able to refine the boundary that would be more efficient.
And so this method doesn't involve trying to identify data points that are close to your
decision boundary.
No, not anymore.
Okay.
So as a feature, as we have the regressor, it has some features as an input.
And some of them are features of the classifier that just characterize how certain our classifier
is, how good is cross-validated accuracy, for example.
And then some features they characterize the data points.
And one of the features could be the distance to the boundary, but it can also include some
other features.
For example, we can look at the distance to the other labeled points or distance to the
unlabeled points.
For example, it can characterize for us if the point is an outlier or if it lies in the
dense region of the feature space.
So it includes many more features and including the distance to the boundary.
But then if I study how much each of these features influences the decision of the regressor,
the decision of which point to select by the active learning strategy, the distance to
the boundary is not the first and most important criteria.
It comes maybe like the fourth and the first one was actually the certainty, the confidence
of the classifier.
So the strategy is adaptive as the active learning progresses and we collect more and
more data.
The classifier becomes more and more confident and the strategy adapts accordingly.
And next we try to test this kind of algorithm that was learned from the data on the real
data sets that are very different from these synthetic examples.
In the synthetic examples we just had this two-dimensional features for the data points, but you
cannot go very far with it and it doesn't sound like a very exciting problem in the
learning.
It definitely won't help us to classify cats.
So next we move to the real data sets and I'm a part of human brain project that is
a very big European project with a huge funding trying to address the problem of understanding
how human brain functions and there are many many researchers who work on it from very
different perspectives, biologists, neuroscientists, physicists and all kind of people.
And so I'm also part of this project is trying to understand brain imaging.
For example we're dealing with the electron microscopy scans of red tissue, of red brain
tissue and we're trying to segment some cellular structures in it.
For example we're on the cellular resolution and we can see the mitochondria, the synopsis
between neurons, we can identify membranes or other kinds of things.
So the other application which I'm interested is having MRI scans of the brain and try
to segment brain tumor of different types.
And then I apply the same kind of strategy that I learned on the synthetic data to this
real data sets of much higher dimensionality, much higher complexity.
And also I have a very different data set for example for detecting credit card fraud transactions.
So I have transactions from the bank for which we know that 99% of them are normal transactions
and then we have around 1% or even less of fraud transactions.
And it's also very laborious task to annotate this kind of data because you need to annotate
like thousands of data points before you start having only a dozen of examples of fraud.
And this is only humans they can do it.
And the same goes of course for this biomedical imaging like as a person who's not into biology
or neuroscience it is a very hard task to understand what is going on.
And the time of these people is quite expensive and we would better want them spend it on something
more intelligent rather than annotating data for algorithms.
So these are the applications where active learning is the most interesting in cases when
only very specialized and educated humans can annotate data for us.
And in this case we also apply the same kind of strategy that we learned from synthetic
data.
And surprisingly it works even in this cases it can generalize to very different data sets
and how we understand it is that it learns a very general knowledge about active learning.
For example the rule such as when the classifier is uncertain do random exploration and when
classifier is rather certain refine the boundary.
This should hold no matter how the data set looks like and it would hold in the case of
this simple to dimensional data and the case of very complex electron microscopy imaging
data.
And so is the idea you know when you take a step back and think about this in the context
of a system like the imaging data is the idea that you yeah how does this unfold in practice
like you have some minimal set of training data and then you're envisioning that you
would generate some other set of data and kind of send it out for annotation or okay I see
so okay now example for example let's talk about this electron microscopy segmenting
cellular structures how we imagine it is that the user has a stack of tissues so it's actually
not a real image it's a three-dimensional image so it's kind of a cube and in whatever direction
we look at it we can count it in all directions and we'll get to the images of how the tissue
looked like that.
And so what we ask at the beginning as the user to kind of take a brush and some program
and indicate here is like some part of mitochondria and here is a part of background and then based
on this our model would train some initial classify a very very very rough one that would
just like say okay mitochondria is for example they're darker than background on average so
let's just use this as discriminative feature it would train such a model and then there will
be some kind of grayish part in the tissue and it would think that classify I would think
I'm not sure what it belongs to does it belong to mitochondria or does it belong to the
background and then the active learning would select this as the some special part in the tissue
which we want to be annotated and then it brings the user to this part of the tissue and kind of
highlights this error in which we would like to get more labels and ask the user please get
take a brush again and indicate whether this particular error is background or if this particular
error is mitochondria and then the user annotates it's again and then the procedure iterates
until we're satisfied with results or until some budget of time is reached or something of the type
and do you have that whole system running at this point end to end or you more modeling it from
the data itself so right now I was mostly working just with from the data okay so we already have
the labeled data and we simulate this active learning procedure because in this case we can of
course test many strategies we can study how different parameters influence our algorithms we
can compare to many strategies but we actually have students and master's student who is working
on putting it into a plugin that the neuroscientist would use and I actually know some people who work
in neuroscience and I know one girl whose PhD topic is mostly at identifying mitochondria
and trying to understand how they influence the neural diseases and the human brain and what she
does is a big part of her PhD work she's just she has to annotate this data manually and I believe
that she's very knowledgeable and she can do something more useful at that time if we can provide
her with this plugin that only with you know 100 samples can provide the same quality of
classification as with 10,000 samples for example so in some cases we can reduce the annotation
effort like very significantly so is that you know going from 10,000 required samples to 100 is
that representative of the kind of results you've seen for different scenarios you mean across
different applications right okay it depends on the application how much active learning can
actually improve our results okay yeah so in some cases we can get a very dramatic decrease
in the annotation time in some cases it's not that much but in any case we're reaching the same
quality faster and we can stop the procedure at any time when we reach the budget of time and
the classifier that we constructed at that point of time would be better than what we would construct
if we just sample points at random then the thing that we can look at is how human friendly this
kind of annotation environment is for example in my previous work I worked particularly for images
and I tried to design a particular strategy for the 3D imaging stacks and in this case what we
were saying is that it is very cumbersome if we have to annotate the stack just kind of pixel by
pixel suppose that you are brought like in some part of the stack and ask to annotate what is
here then you brought to some other place you ask to annotate something then some islands and other
and it can actually take quite a lot of time just because of this context switches and you have to
understand what is going on and like it's also trivial to understand how this neurons connect
with each other for example so one thing that we're looking at we're trying to find some
optimal cuts in this 3D plane so we're just cutting them in various directions and we're projecting
data on this direction on these planes on these cuts and we're trying to annotate some batches
of samples instead of asking to annotate one by one whatever samples are you can try to think of
it kind of like maximum uncertainty cuts or something yeah so we had some some uncertainty measure
that wasn't like maybe not a standard one but something special for the images but then here we're
trying to find a cut with a maximum uncertainty and then there are other ways to work on this
direction so in as I see it in active learning there are two components one of them is we want to
design an algorithm that would select the best possible sample but on the other hand we should
still remember that there will be humans annotate data for us so we should make it as convenient and
as easy for humans to label the data and yeah another thing that I've been working on also in
this direction is getting label data for object detection so the problem is very different we just
like want to localize objects in images like I don't know the bottle the TV screen a human
and these kind of things and there are various and for this we need bounding box annotations so we
need someone to draw a bounding box around every object and from this with chain and there are
various ways how we can collect it we can ask the humans to draw it manually this kind of this is
the normal way of doing it but on that the hand we already have some kind of detectors that maybe
not as strong as we would like them to be but we can already try to use the output of these
detectors and show them show it to the users and as the users to correct for the mistakes and
this is what we're talking about mistakes in terms of identifying the bounding boxes or labeling
what's in the bounding boxes or both okay so now I'm talking about identifying the location of
the bounding box because in this scenario we simplify the problem and we say that we already have
image level annotations so we already know that there is a bottle in this image there is a door
in this image and now we want to know where this door is okay so we split the problem in two
separate ones and we deal with the second one where we want to get the coordinates of this
bounding boxes okay and in this case on the one hand if we ask humans to draw an object it is
very fast it is not very fast it takes in the very in kind of in the standard protocols it might
take up to 35 seconds to get a one bounding box per image and we need thousands of them for
every class which results like in years and years of human work and on the other hand if we ask
the users to verify the prediction of the classify it can be very fast it takes around two seconds
for example just to say yes or no if it is a correct identification of the object but it is not
guaranteed to provide a bounding box that we would like to get so if the user answers no we have
to repeat the procedure again and we have to ask the user again where the box was so what we are
trying to do in this work we are trying to balance between these two modalities of data
annotation and trying to decide in what situations it's better to ask to draw a bounding box that is
expensive but guaranteed to produce a label and with which situations it's easier to verify
the detection detected proposals and to result in a positively verified box quicker
and is the methodology the same for this project as the one you previously described?
no it's not exactly the same but what unifies them is that we're still dealing with the problem
of reducing human efforts just approaching it from the other direction so one direction is
select what to annotate and the other direction select how to annotate so what I believe is that
both of them would be important and if we just deal with one of them we can get some good results
on paper and some simulations but in practice both of these directions would be important
interesting I'm curious about how the system would go about directing the annotator to a
specific area meaning you have these you have these data points that are annotated what is it
asking for is it asking for like some coordinate does it know like coordinates of uncertainty or
does it know something else okay so I didn't go into details of the protocol but actually how
we start the task is to segment something to segment mitochondria's and we started from
over-sigmenting images so we use something that is called sleek super pixels or sleek super voxels
so the idea is that it is unsupervised method that can provide segmentation of the image of the
very fine fine grain that is not reflecting actually the boundaries of the object but the uniform
more or less so we get like very small segments in the images that are all more or less uniform
in their appearance and every object would compile would consist for example of 100 of such objects
of this super voxels or super pixels and then what the algorithm the active learning algorithm
identifies it selects which super voxel is the most uncertain and are the super voxels they're
all uniform in shape and size yes this is the property of this sleek super voxels is that a
more or less uniform and of a shape that is close to spherical or circular depending if it's 3D
or 2D stacks and so you can have multiple adjacent super voxels that are the same value essentially
the same color or yes yes so it's still even if there is a very uniform part of the image it would
still try to divide it in some way so that they're still kept of more or less the same size
okay the same shape it depends on the parameters how you specify it's it's unsupervised algorithm
but you need to identify how compact you want them to be how smooth you want them to be this kind
of things but what we're trying to do is like to have them roughly circular small objects
okay and the overlapping no they're not overlapping so it's just kind of assignment of every pixel
of the object to a super pixel okay so we call they're called super pixels because they consist
of multiple pixels or super voxels the same for voxels okay and then what active learning does
it select super voxel or super pixel that needs to be annotated in this case or in case of
this identifying the planes it just identifies the error with several super voxels that are uncertain
so in this case it would be just as if we have an image and then we highlight some kind of round
errors and that we're interested in annotations there okay yeah and there were also suggesting that
if the objects are big enough like mitochondria are rather big and the selected error that we want
to use it to annotate is small we can approximate it that just with two clicks of the mouse just
identifying the boundary of mitochondria if it is in the image so it makes it even faster like this
okay so this is another example of working on this other direction of how convenient it is for
user to annotate the data combines together with the algorithm that selects what to annotate
okay and so if the presumably if you're if the user task is to then identify whether the
boundary is in the image or in the the voxel super voxel then you can kind of go from there to
multiple super voxels with boundaries and determine which is where the mitochondria is is that
what you're saying so how it looks like is that suppose we have a circle that overlaps the mitochondria
bit but because mitochondria is rather big compared to the size of the circle right the boundary
of mitochondria is more or less just a line yeah and we can ask the user to draw this line with two
clicks and to identify on which side the the mitochondria is right and then it would we are able
from this line we're able to go towards the assignment of super voxels to particular classes
so when we have just that one assignment in this one super voxel can tell you
a whole about the whole area exactly yeah okay interesting interesting um well this is
really fascinating work I appreciate you taking the time to to share it with us work and folks
learn more about your research do you have a website up on uh yes I have a website that is
xenia.conishcaller.com and I try to keep it more or less updated about the recent research that
I'm doing for example what I mentioned today the work about bounding boxes I just finished
an internship last Friday at Google Research in Zurich okay and this is a project that we're
working on okay and it's soon to be there and okay before it is going to appear anywhere else
awesome awesome well thank you once again yeah thank you
oh all right everyone that's our show for today for more information on cousinia or any of the
topics covered in this episode head on over to twimlai.com slash talk slash 116 if you haven't
already done so make sure you head on over to iTunes as well to leave us your most gracious
rating and review it helps new listeners finds us which helps us grow and of course
thanks so much for listening and catch you next time