Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast why interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington, I want to send a quick thanks to everyone who commented
on and shared last week's show with Jeff Dean.
We were super excited to share that show with you and the feedback and love you sent
our way was amazing.
Weeks like last are how we expand the Twimble community and get into the ears of people
who don't know about us yet.
All your shares, likes, tweets and retweets matter a great deal to us, so thanks.
Before I introduce today's show, the details for April's Twimble Online Meetup are set.
Join us on April 18th at 5pm Pacific time as Chris Butler dives headfirst into the topic
of Trust in AI, covering a myriad of papers in the process.
To register or for more details, head on over to twimbleai.com slash meetup.
In this episode, I'm joined by David Rosenberg, data scientist in the office of the CTO at
Financial Publisher Bloomberg to discuss his work on extracting data from tables and charts
in natural document formats.
Bloomberg deals with tons of financial and company data and PDFs and other unstructured
document formats on a daily basis.
To make meaning from this information more efficiently, David and his team have implemented
a deep learning pipeline for extracting data from the documents.
In our conversation, we dig into the information extraction process, including how it was built,
how they source their training data, why they use Latech as an intermediate representation,
and how and why they optimize for pixel-perfect accuracy.
There's a lot of interesting info in this show, and I think you're going to really enjoy
it.
Alright everyone, I am on the line with David Rosenberg.
David is a data scientist in the CTO's office at Bloomberg, the Financial Publisher.
He's also an adjunct associate professor in the Center for Data Science at NYU.
David, welcome to this week in Machine Learning and AI.
Thanks so much, happy to be here.
Awesome.
It's our tradition to have our guests start by introducing themselves to the audience.
So tell us how did you get involved in data science and machine learning?
Yeah, sure.
I've been interested in AI since I was a kid reading science fiction books as an elementary
school about robots and artificial intelligence really grabbed my interest, and I guess it
was in eighth grade, there's a summer program, and we got to build these Fisher Technic
Kit projects that's kind of like motorized and computer controllable Lego Kit, but it
was made by this company Fisher Technic, and I loved it.
I thought it was a most amazing thing to be able to control a robot-like device with
computer programming, and then a few years later, I guess in high school then, I started
hearing about neural networks, which was my first exposure to machine learning.
And yeah, for a project, I bought a textbook and I implemented a neural network to do some
classification on some medical data, and yeah, frankly at the time, I didn't really
understand very well how the neural network was working at the detailed mathematical level,
but I had a taste of the ML framework even as like early 90s.
That's pretty amazing that you were exposed to neural nets in high school.
Where did you go to high school?
I went to Montgomery Blair High School in Silver Spring, Maryland.
It was a math science computer science magnet program.
I don't remember how I first heard about neural networks, but somehow it came to my attention
and found a way to special order these books that the local Barnes and Noble, and I coded
it up in Pascal.
Nice.
How did you end up at Bloomberg, and what's your focus there?
Right.
So, yeah, two hops to Bloomberg.
So after grad school, I moved to New York and I joined a startup company that was Tony
Jabara, who's a machine learning professor, who's a machine learning professor from Columbia.
Now he's at Netflix.
I joined his startup company, we're doing a lot of spatial temporal data, machine learning
based on spatial temporal data, and then eventually got into mobile advertising.
So doing things like building bidders for ad exchanges, and those kind of fun problems
that a lot of ML gets applied to these days.
We got acquired by YP, which is yellow pages, and I stayed there for about a year or
so, and then I looked for my next step and I ended up at Bloomberg, where at Bloomberg
I'm in the office of the CTO, and just a small group, I think about 25 people total within
that group, there's a five person data science group that I'm a member of, and kind of our
task is to work on strategic projects or plan strategic projects on kind of a two to four
year time horizon.
Things that are a little bit too long term for any individual engineering group to really
plan for, so we kind of make strategic initiatives and kind of point the data science part of
the company in different different directions.
So that's kind of the big picture, another way, another way we think about it is if some
other company were to gain a large advantage over Bloomberg because of some new technology
in data science that we did not pursue, that would be our fault.
We're responsible for making sure we're not missing out on important new tech developments.
Right.
Can you give us some examples of the kinds of things that you're looking at, or have looked
at the past that kind of fall into this two to four year time frame?
Sure, I can.
So one thing, maybe not quite so such a long term play, but when I joined maybe three
years ago, there was a machine learning was at this interesting time where neural networks
were starting to do very well on many tasks, but just kind of specific tasks, like certainly
vision and some NLP tasks, but it was kind of to get into neural networks, it's a pretty
big investment in terms of hardware.
At Bloomberg, we don't have the ability to use the Amazon Cloud or something.
We need to use internal machines.
So the CTO office kind of led the movement to try out neural networks, which involves
investing in cluster GPU machines and seeding projects with various engineering teams
to see if neural networks was going to benefit the types of problems that we work on.
And indeed, we have found within a couple of years that it's very important to some areas
of the work that we do.
So I could say that strategic, not so much because of the time horizon, but because of
the investment required that was kind of too large for any individual engineering group
to take that risk.
I guess I'm curious about the evolution of the use of machine learning at a company like
Bloomberg.
And you said, how long have you been there now?
I've been coming up on three years.
Coming up on three years.
So maybe you'll have a sense of this.
I talk to people all the time about how enterprises, large businesses kind of evolve these types
of technologies.
It's interesting in that there are some businesses where there are parts of the business that
have used machine learning for a really long time.
Like it's been baked into, you know, just core ways that they deliver their products.
But yet and still even at those businesses, there's been like a shift over the past five
years in the way they've thought about machine learning.
I'm just curious.
Like in your words, like, does any of that resonate and how have you seen that evolve at
Bloomberg?
Yeah.
So, I think Bloomberg was fairly early in bringing machine learning into the product,
which I could tell you a little bit about.
So I think machine learning at Bloomberg was well underway, I mean, you know, there's
close to a hundred people doing machine learning at Bloomberg before I even arrived.
So I can't really speak to how that developed.
But I can say that even now we're continually trying to find areas where machine learning
can help via by automation or just kind of maybe more broadly the machine learning, just
a good data science statistical approach to assessing new, even if it's a rules based
method to use kind of proper methodology and assessing performance and these sorts of
things.
In fact, to that end, to try to see where we can leverage ML more or data science more
at Bloomberg, another strategic initiative that is almost a year old now coming from the
CTO department is what we're calling ML EDU, so machine learning education.
But the purview is broader than ML, it's kind of just data science more broadly.
And we're trying to educate people at all different levels, basically from the most
basic understanding of the main concepts of machine learning things like the notion
of splitting your data into training and test and notions of overfitting these fundamental
ideas of machine learning that we have a course called ML1, which is two half days and
it's a few hours lecture and a few hours lab where people go through that.
And that kind of gives people just a sense of what is this ML about.
And then we have at the other extreme we have a kind of fairly in-depth course called
ML101, which is kind of like a master's level machine learning class.
That's kind of fairly mathematical, but with practical end, which is learning all the
connections between things like gradient boosting and random forest and L1L2 regularization,
kind of a standard master's level machine learning class.
And we're trying to fill in everything in between.
So how to manipulate data, explore data, visualize it, how to do basic statistics, things like
AB testing, hypothesis testing, confidence intervals, and then machine learning, predictive
theory.
Awesome.
I am shortly going to be jumping on a plane to head out to the Bay Area for the GTC
conference.
Yeah.
And you will too, probably not before me since I'm getting on a plane in a few hours.
But you're going to be presenting there on what is presumably one of these projects within
the CTO's office, data science team that you've been working on.
Can you tell us about that?
Sure.
So the title is information extraction for natural document formats.
So natural document format, to my knowledge is not really a common terminology, but we
encountered a lot of Bloomberg.
And what we mean by that is a document that was designed for easy human consumption and
comprehension, things like a word document, a PDF document.
And in particular, what we have in mind for the projects I'll be speaking about is where
some kind of, there's some kind of underlying data that is represented or that are represented
in this natural document format in a way that's just fine for a person to comprehend, but
is not easy at all to extract that data back out into say a database or an Excel spreadsheet
or something like that.
And this is a problem that we have a lot of at Bloomberg.
A Bloomberg.
So an example of this might be like a chart or graph or something like that.
Is that the?
Absolutely.
Yeah.
So a scatter plot, a pie chart, a bar chart, or a table, a table of numbers, a table of
all things, you think should be very easy to extract the data out into an spreadsheet
or a database or something, but when a table is just represented in a PDF document in the
middle of a, say, company filing, Bloomberg collects all these documents from other companies,
things like company filings and these sorts of things.
And we, these documents that they deliver in a PDF format typically has important data
in it that we need to extract that it's easy for our Bloomberg's customers to use to
get to.
And so traditionally, I think almost since the founding of the company 30 years ago, there's
been a whole organization within the company called Global Data where it's people's jobs
to figure out the most efficient and most correct way to extract this information from
the documents.
And there's, I can't say exactly how much, but certainly at least hundreds of people
working on these problems, not necessarily, and it's been going on for 30 years.
So it's started off mostly by hand.
And a big effort over the years has been to see how to automate this as much as possible
or make it more efficient for the people doing it.
That's kind of the business driver.
In this particular scenario, I kind of thought this was a solve problem like for 10 years
now, I thought that financial filings, I forget where, I thought there was the development
of some standardized XML formats that were used for S1s and all these financial filings
now.
It sounds like that it's, I know that maybe the largest companies kind of submit their
things via these XML formats, but there's still a ton of traditional documents flying
around with this information.
They're sure.
And maybe it's a letter to shareholders that is not necessarily regulated.
There's no requirements on a format to use.
And we kind of want to get as much data as we can.
And even if the US were to go in a certain direction, there's still all the other countries
that may or may not have these requirements.
And so, yes, in some sense, perhaps someday everyone will kind of publish all their,
any data that show up in any inconvenient document will be paired with a, you know, some
kind of standard XML format, but we're surely not there yet.
Interesting.
So, tell me about the approach you're taking with us.
Sure.
So, there's kind of three different tasks that I'll be talking about.
One of them is as far as extracting data from tables that show up in documents.
And the first task there is to just find the tables in the PDF documents.
So for that, we're using fairly off the shelf image detection methods.
The same thing as you would use to find a CAD or a kite or whatever it is in an image.
One advantage that we have is because we've been solving this problem by hand for so
many years, we have a tremendous amount of labeled training data.
And so now we're able to leverage that to build models.
And one interesting aspect we have is we need, we basically can't afford to automate unless
the performance will be at least as good as the humans.
And so before we're willing to cut a human out of the loop completely.
And so in fact, we've done that for this relatively straightforward problem of at least
for some kind of sub-problems of finding charts and documents.
We've been able to exceed human precision and recall, which was great.
And then the downstream tasks of actually extracting the numbers from the table use some
other techniques for.
And so that's the second thing that I'm going to talk about in the presentation, which
is a little bit futuristic.
It's not something that we kind of, it's purely research right now.
That's not something we're planning to productize anytime soon because it's kind of a long
path.
But we were inspired by this image captioning work that started a few years ago where you
could show a picture of a man crossing the street and what it would produce using an image
to sequence model the sentence man crossed the street or something like that.
And the idea was like boy, if we could feed in a page of a document and have it output
directly in one step kind of a well-structured XML or JSON or standardized formatting of
all the content in that kind of picture of the page or the document wouldn't that be great
then you could because that's so much easier.
That's so there's so much you can do with that downstream as far as automated processing.
It's hard to begin if you just have kind of a raw PDF, the format, if I could show
you the format of the internal PDF or even a parsed PDF is not very easy to extract the
structure from.
So for that problem, so how are we going to apply image caption to this sort of thing?
So I partnered with a student from Harvard, Yun Tian Dang who had this really cool work
a year or two ago with Sasha Rush and some others was to convert a picture of an equation
of mathematical equation that was generated by latex which is kind of mark up for making
equations and scientific documents.
And to go from the image and reproduce latex code that you would need to generate that
equation.
Interesting.
You can see as kind of a simple version of going from the image of something to a structured
representation of kind of the underlying information in the picture that you could then do further
information extraction on.
So we wanted to adapt that idea to this problem of information extraction from tables.
So given the image of a table, that was, and we're restricting here to kind of somewhat
of a toy problem where we assume the table is generated from latex in the first place
from a latex document.
And so the problem is can we regenerate the latex code that would reproduce that table exactly,
kind of pixel level, exact.
And so that's another thing I'll be talking about.
We had a fairly impressive results for that.
The kind of the exact match rate isn't so high, and it's 40%.
But the errors are even when it makes errors that are pretty minor.
So this seems like an interesting line of work that we're saying.
And the last thing was extracting data from scatter plots.
So in a document, they'll offer me scatter plots or plots containing information.
And we found ourselves once or twice with the ruler trying to figure out exactly what points
are represented in this chart, lining up the point with the axis.
Right.
It seems like, boy, this should be automatable with all the computer vision technologies
we have now.
And this was an interesting thing where we actually thought that this was close enough to something
we could make a product out of that we kind of went straight for what's the most direct
way to solve this problem without, you know, it's very tempting to try to make kind of the
end-to-end solution that are, you know, so striking these days with the neural networks.
Like for instance, the image of the table to the late echo that produces that would be,
I consider that an end-to-end solution.
But so we were tempted to make the input, the chart and the output just be the list of
points in one fell swoop.
But it seems to be a little bit too hard for right now for us.
So we broke that down into a pipeline of steps.
Each one of which was just using off-the-shelf techniques, start with kind of image recognition
to find the components of the charts.
Then we used some various heuristics to put them together and at the end, I could do a fairly
good job of extracting the data from scatterplots and currently we're working on pie charts
and next I guess we bar charts and line charts.
And I mean the goal is to solve the problem in this particular case rather than to come
up with a very kind of one shot end-to-end solution.
Right, right.
So the first of the problems you described was just really localizing these graphical
the tables.
The tables in particular or any kind?
Tables and charts.
Okay.
But we were focusing particularly on the tables initially.
And if you're just looking at tables and charts like I'm curious, how much of the PDF internals
do you actually use or do you just like take a picture of the page essentially and do
your image recognition on the page itself?
Yeah, good question.
So the punchline is that it can do just fine using just the picture.
So if you treat each PDF page as a picture just render it and use that as input, that
works just fine.
Initially, we were concerned that it would be too hard.
So we tried to use a part of the PDF to simplify the image.
So for instance, we figured it doesn't really know you to know exactly what characters
are there.
Maybe just needs to know the character type, like letter versus number, this sort of thing.
Okay.
You know, render a simpler version of the page that would be easier for the object detection
system to learn from.
But it turns out it works just fine with the rendering of the raw.
I mean, sometimes one works a little better, sometimes the other works a little better,
but it can go directly from the rendered image.
So the result of this first step is just, you know, is it like a bounding box and a label
that says table or chart or?
It is a bounding box.
And it sounds, when I first heard about it, I felt like this sounds so easy.
Why?
I'm sure everyone's thinking that.
And it mostly is, but the issue is that, you know, if you don't get the bounding box
exactly right, if you leave off a column or leave off some of the header, or you don't
properly separate the headers from the rest of the table, which is another part of finding
the table in the first place, then the entire extraction is messed up.
And we don't, and kind of 95% accuracy isn't really good enough.
So it's always about the, again, if I had pictures, I could show you some.
So at the, if you go to the presentation, we could show you some really weird looking
tables that heuristics just will fail on.
This is actually really, really easy for me to visualize.
And the reason why is because I often use my cell phone camera to take pictures of receipts
or pages or things like that.
And the particular app that I use, you know, whether it's there or several that I use,
ever notice one cam scanner as another, but these apps will try to, you know, do exactly
what you're describing, like draw a bounding box around the document and then like use
that to like, you know, rewarp it or straighten it and crop it from the background.
But it is uncanny the mistakes that these things will make and how, you know, I don't think
the accuracy is anywhere near 95% on, you know, what, you know, even if I've got the
paper on a black notebook or something like that, like it's still seems to be a challenging
problem.
And, you know, it's perhaps complicated by the fact that it's running on a mobile device,
I don't know.
But I can certainly imagine if you now, kind of, you know, you don't even have the benefit
of the back, the contrasting background, you've got all different kinds of, you know, shapes
and sizes of tables and, you know, adjacency of one table to the next.
And, you know, I can, I can, you know, I said, is it, you know, just this issue of creating
the back, the bounding box, but as you're describing this, I can imagine all of the complexities
associated with getting this right.
Right. And, and you nailed one of the challenges, which is when tables are adjacent, the problem
of multiple columns, you know, there's often two column or three column documents.
Yeah, I, I think you appreciate the, it's harder than it sounds, it's harder than it
sounds.
Is this a system that you've, you've tried to, or gotten to the point of operationalizing
it, or is this, this is deployed, this is deployment.
So this is in, this is kind of in the pipeline, helping people, either it's assisting people
to annotate documents, so someone will load the document, the document will be kind of
pre annotated with a guess by this system of finding the tables, and then a human can
approve or edit those annotations.
And then for some classes of documents, it's just straight pass through with no human
oversight needed with decided.
And that was, and that was going to be my exact question like, do you, you know, are
you utilizing a model where you identify like a, or you kind of surface when, when the system
isn't sure to the user and allow the, you know, that human in the loop to kind of make
the final decision when there's some uncertainty or, you know, does it have to be kind of all
or nothing?
It sounds like, it sounds like you are kind of doing that, you know, taking that middle
ground where you're surfacing the, you know, where there's some ambiguity.
Right.
So, yes.
So I think what one thing that you seem to be speaking about is where the system will perhaps
based on, you know, what it sees, and it will give a measured response.
Like, you know, I think this is the bounding box, but my confidence is low or, or they may
give a numeric score to the confidence or something.
And then the ones that are low confidence will be highlighted to a user.
But we feel see for with for now is finding classes of documents that overall have a very
high performance kind of above human level accuracy or precision recall measures.
And as a group, those will be kind of passed through because the issue with confidence
is that you have to trust the confidence measure, you have to trust the confidence score.
And so that would have to be kind of assessed on its own.
Okay.
So, how are these classes of documents described?
Like is it, you know, all of the, you know, S1s for a major fortune, you know, 500 companies
all kind of look the same or all of AT&T's, S1s, we've got good performance on or that
kind of thing.
Right.
Yeah.
It's like a class of documents, like, filings of a certain type, for example, that have
such a certain regularity to them.
And the performance is very high that will kind of shun those to automatic pass through,
which is to say doesn't need a human oversight.
Okay.
And it sounds like by implication, then when, you know, when the system's nailed a document
class, yeah, it's confident, well, you know, aside from confidence, like it, it performs
extremely well, like, you know, above human levels of performance on every document in
that class, there's not a lot of variability within the class.
Yeah.
That's the idea, right?
You'd like a more fine-grained certainty measure that one could leverage.
Yeah.
I mean, I don't know that it's like, I guess I would expect that within, even within
a document class, there are still ambiguous situations.
And I would expect you to want to somehow kind of surface that ambiguity.
But you don't want to do that.
You want it to be kind of all or nothing, and I'm really trying to get into the thinking
there.
Well, I, you know, it's interesting.
I think part of it is the way our annotation system works, but the annotation system works
at the document level.
So a doc, maybe 10 to 50 pages, and in some sense, we either have a person annotated document
or we don't.
At this point, don't have a kind of page-by-page decision on whether it will be annotated.
Okay.
So I think that's that part of it.
That's a bit of it.
Perhaps an idiosyncrasy of our setup.
Right.
So if you had, if you could just throw ambiguous pages on a stack and, you know, someone
goes through those page-by-page, then that might have changed the way you approach that
piece.
I think that's right.
Yeah.
Although I think, I think being able to trust a confidence score is a interesting problem
in and of itself.
You know, it's, it's very, you know, most, most machine learning methods these days output
something that you are tempted to interpret as a probability, but whether those, oh, for
a probability of, for classification, for instance, probability of being a cat versus
not a cat.
Mm-hmm.
That's sort of things.
Right.
But whether those probabilities are calibrated in the sense that it will actually be right
that number of times, if, when you predict cat is, that has to be confirmed.
That's just because a method gives a probability score doesn't mean that's actually the probability,
I guess.
Right.
There's an implicit weighting of kind of trusting that confidence versus like assuming
that it's 100% and kind of pushing those documents through like how is, I don't have
an intuitive feel for why that trust is any, any better than, you know, even in the case
where you've got general high level of trust in a class, like, you might, you know, in
that case, seems like there'd be information in a low confidence, an exceedingly low confidence
level for a document.
Right.
So I think you have the impression.
Which do we have in better?
Yeah.
So I guess, I guess that's all I'm saying.
So we have a class of documents, which without any information about the individual page
or the individual document, the overall performance will be, say, 98% precision and recall while
human is 97 or 98.
Okay.
So match or exceed human performance.
And then you're pointing out, maybe we could do even better by going page by page and
highlighting the ones that are somewhat less certain and maybe sending those to a human
and then we can do even better overall.
Yeah.
Right.
I appreciate you.
I appreciate you putting it like that.
It's certainly not my job to, there's often a way to do better.
But then there are, you know, the trade offs that, you know, come with trying it with doing
that.
And if you've achieved a level of performance that you need for your use case, then, you
know, great.
Yeah.
So for the past through the, it's not even 97, 90, it's like essentially a hundred.
Oh, really?
Yeah.
For the 96, 97, I think they're still good at humans.
I could, I'm not 100% sure, I'd have to double check that.
And so another kind of thought that I'm wondering if you are thinking about it and tracking
is the whole kind of adversarial attack conversation and like, you use some scenario where, you
know, a company kind of, you know, manipulates the presentation of their data to, you know,
change the way your parser interprets their charts and tables and, you know, somehow
affect trades of Bloomberg customers.
Like, I'm assuming that's something that you folks are thinking about.
I mean, that's really important.
So there's a little bit of that we've already seen where there'll be a document that if
you look at it to the eye, nothing unusual going on.
But if you parse it with a PDF parser, which tries to extract the text and stuff for you,
but what we found is some documents will put incorrect information or confusing information
in a kind of invisible font color.
And so when you parse it, it's very difficult to figure out what's going on if you use
like a PDF parser.
But we've been able to get around those because we just use the rendering of the page.
And so if the human can't see it, I mean, it can, let me just say that the network can
figure out what are kind of relevant colors and irrelevant colors and that sort of thing.
But we're not protected against kind of not necessarily protected against adversarial
images that could mess up a network, but a human wouldn't see.
I mean, I don't know how that would work through after being printed out and stuff, I assume
it would.
But yeah, of course, we've seen, I assume you're talking about these pretty cool examples
where there'll be a picture that's clearly a cat and the classifier will give it 99%
confidence that it's a car or something like that.
Exactly.
That's really interesting.
We have noticed things like that happening, but it's definitely something we need to keep
it I have for.
Yeah.
I like the way you describe the tricks that folks do with like kind of background colored
text makes me think of, I just struck me that like in some ways you can think of like
fine print and some of these things as like adversarial attacks against a human brain,
right?
It's like things we do to like, you know, present information so as to missly the
reader.
Right.
So the first part is identifying these tables and charts.
The second part is then parsing the tables and you talked about, you know, some of the
challenges associated with that as a high level over there.
You know, where did the kind of the bulk of the work on that particular piece take place
or were there any like major, you know, what were the major challenges that you had to overcome
on that, the table interpretation part?
The finding the tables part or the late tech, the late tech extraction, the reverse engineering
the tables, I guess.
Right.
One issue is that the images are just bigger.
There's just much more information in a table potentially than in an equation that which
has a lot of information, but a table is just can be a whole lot of numbers.
It could be quite large.
And there we get into kind of memory issues with these convolutional neural networks.
When you're training, for instance, if you have, you know, a large input image, you're
restricted to how big a batch you can use at one time and this will slow down training.
And so the first challenge is that these things, you know, we're taking two weeks to train,
which is, you know, it's hard to iterate on a problem when it takes along the train.
So we did some work at that.
We happened to have to have received the new Nvidia GPUs at that time.
So that had 16-bit kind of floating, 16-bit floating point capabilities which are kind
of theoretically going to be twice as fast and you can kind of have too many weight-storted
memory because you're only using half as many bits for them.
So we spent a lot of time trying to adapt to this 16-bit technology so we could have,
you know, the speed up and the kind of access to put more stuff in memory, but it turned
out to be much harder than we thought it would be.
There are a whole bunch of kind of technical issues when we represented our weights in
our network with only 16 bits.
And it turns out we weren't alone.
It turns out this has kind of been, it's kind of a known issue at this point that you don't
really want to store everything in 16 bits.
You can do some calculations in 16 bits, but your weights eventually should be stored
in 32 bits.
So we spent a lot of time kind of working through that problem.
And what we're working on now is, I mean, so what's the basic issue with this table to
latex is that it looks fine, but it doesn't really work that well if you're going for an
exact match and we're going for an exact match, you know, 40%, that's 40% correct.
That's pretty low by any of those standards.
The equations were kind of more up like 80% exactly correct.
So I mean, and this is ongoing work.
Is your measure of correctness?
Is this like pixel, like, you know, pixel overlay or is it something else?
So is it more information based, I guess?
Right.
Yeah.
So it's not information based.
During training time, we're just trying to maximize kind of the likelihood of the
correct latex, but that's training time.
But when it actually comes to evaluation, we're going for exact pixel-to-pixel match.
So it's binary.
You either got it exactly correct or not.
So what that means is, the inputs the image of the table, the outputs a string of latex
tokens, which feed that string into a latex compiler, it renders an image.
And then we compare that image pixel by pixel to be original image.
And if it's an exact match, it's correct.
And otherwise, it's incorrect.
And why do you care about that?
Why do we care about the exact match?
You know, why is your bar, I guess there are multiple ways to ask a question like, why
do you care about kind of the latex representation?
Why do you care about pixel-to-pixel match?
You know, why is it just that you've extracted the, you know, the rows and columns of data,
the headings, the text, the numbers, all that stuff?
Okay.
So there's a few things in there.
Let's see.
So latex, I don't care about latex per se, latex is kind of a stand-in for a structured
representation from which it should be easy to do the things you said, extract the rows
and columns and that sort of thing.
So why latex, we happen to have access to a huge collection of real world latex documents
that have tables in them.
And so that's kind of our label trainings that we went to archive, we scraped out all
these papers, we found almost a half million tables with the original latex.
Oh, nice.
Yeah.
So I mean, we could have generated artificial tables, but it's really better to work with
kind of real live natural data.
So that's, that's part, that's basically how we ended up with latteque.
Then the question, why do we care about exact match?
And well, one reason is expedience, which is that it's easy to do and it's actually quite
difficult to figure out how you would score something that's not an exact match.
I mean, you could do it in the image space where you then you have this kind of, the image
is not an exact match and then if you want to rate it by how off it is, you'd have to
kind of do some alignment and find, it seems like a very complicated problem in itself.
And then, and then you're asking, what about just measuring how it does a downstream task,
which is just finding the data, like extracting the data from the latex and, you know, are
the numbers correct or the headers correct?
And that would be possible.
That would, it's still very difficult to score.
We actually have the same problem with when we're extracting data from scattered plots,
you know, there's 60 points in the chart, the system finds 57 and the points, you know,
have to root the amounts of error ranging from 100% to, like by celebrating back there.
Yeah.
Sorry about that.
Is it kind of a, awards thing going on just starting now next door to me.
So it sounds like in both the table and the, the scatter plots, you're using the visual
domain and visual domain accuracy is really, it's just a connection.
Convenient intermediary for you to be able to test whether you've accomplished the goal,
whether you're able to replicate the system and because, at least in the case of the tables.
And I think you're doing the same thing with the, the scatter plots because the table that
you're generating or predicting is generated via via a structured representation.
It doesn't really matter what it is, but you happen to have training data that's
in the tech because you're generating it via a structured representation.
You know that, you know, downstream, you'll be able to pull the data out the way you
need to.
That's, that's right.
Also, it's, it's convenience to do in the image domain, but also it's, it's hard to
know exactly what downstream tasks we're going to want to do on the structured representation.
And maybe there's important information in that boldface versus italics, which you might
think isn't necessarily part of the core information of the table.
So the harder tables to extract, a lot of that complexity comes from things like hierarchical
column headers or row headers or cells that span multiple rows or columns.
And this is actually difficult to represent in a, it's difficult to score the performance
on those sorts of mistakes, like what if it didn't properly represent the cell spanning
to column headers or these sorts of things.
So I guess, yes, it comes down to simplicity, but also it just not being exactly clear
how, what else we would do, how else we would score in a way that would be, you know, good
for any possible downstream task we'd want to do.
Yeah, now that makes it, that makes a ton of sense, that makes a ton of sense.
Awesome. So you, in your presentation, you kind of go through these three sub projects.
Yeah.
Were there any closing or parting thoughts that would make a good wrap up for us here?
Well, I guess one, one thing that people often wonder about is, what about all these people
who are labeling documents and now are they going to be automated away?
And we're really not worried about it, not because we don't care about people's jobs,
we absolutely do.
But because the people doing the labeling are actually often fairly highly trained and
we'd, we'd love to have them working on harder and deeper problems that they'll have
time for once the more, the problems that a computer can solve are solved.
So, you know, questions about we can find the data and then we can flag things that are
unexpected, then the human can go and tag the unexpected behavior with perhaps linking
to a possible reason why.
These sorts of things are more still human level tasks that's not clear are automatable
in the near future and kind of automating the menial tasks will hopefully be humans
free to do the tasks that we don't yet know how to automate and maybe are more like specific
to needing human intelligence at least for now.
And it sounds like in the example you gave more valuable.
Right.
Awesome.
Well, David, you've been very generous with your time.
Thank you so much for chatting with us.
It's been my pleasure.
Thanks so much.
All right, everyone, that's our show for today.
For more information on David or any of the topics covered in this episode, you'll find
the show notes at twomolei.com slash talk slash one, two, six.
Thanks once again for listening and catch you next time.