Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast why interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
I'd like to start out by thanking everyone who joined me last week at the Twimble AI Summit
in Las Vegas.
It was a great event.
For a summary of the event and my key takeaways from each of the event sessions, sign up for
my newsletter at twimbleai.com slash newsletter.
I wrote about it right after returning from the event last week and when you sign up,
you'll automatically get an email telling you how to get access to back issues.
Again, that's twimbleai.com slash newsletter.
Event season continues this week.
Tomorrow I'm key noting at the Prepare AI event here in St. Louis and then making my way
out to San Francisco for Figure H's Train AI Conference.
The Train AI agenda looks awesome and I'll be on site all day podcasting so if you're
in the Bay area, you should definitely plan to stop by.
Of course, if you do, use the discount code Twimbleai for 30% off of registration.
Be sure to give me a shout if you're planning to be around.
In this episode, I'm joined by John Bohannon, Director of Science at AI Startup Primer.
As you all may know, a few weeks ago, we released my interview with Google Legend, Jeff
Dean, which by the way, you should definitely check out if you haven't already.
Anyway, in that interview, Jeff mentions the recent explosion of machine learning papers
on archive, which I responded to jokingly by asking whether Google had already developed
the AI system to help them summarize and track all of them.
While Jeff didn't have anything specific to offer, a listener reached out and let me
know that John was in fact already working on this problem.
In our conversation, John and I discuss his work on Primer Science, a tool that harvests
content uploaded to archive, sorts it into natural topics using unsupervised learning,
then gives relevant summaries of the activity happening in different innovation areas.
We spend a good amount of time on the inner workings of Primer Science, including their
data pipeline and some of the tools they use, how they determine ground truth for training
their models, and the use of heuristics to supplement NLP in their processing.
Alright, let's do it.
Alright, everyone, I am on the line with John Bohannon.
John is Director of Science at a startup called Primer.
John, welcome to this week in machine learning and AI.
Hey!
So this conversation is an interesting one.
They grew out of a listener response to a comment made in my recent interview with Jeff Dean.
Jeff commented on the explosion of machine learning papers on archive, and I jokingly
asked if Google had already developed the deep learning based summarization techniques
to help us all keep up.
And it turns out that one of your colleagues, John, reached out to let me know that you
have been working on this and have built it.
And I think just before we got started, you showed it to me and it's pretty cool.
So here we are, but before we get into the details of that project, you've got an interesting
background in molecular biology and data journalism.
How did you find your way to AI?
It's a long journey, but I think it started in computer camp when I was nine years old.
So that's the kind of summer camp I went to.
And yeah, as my studies progressed, I actually drifted away into biology in a PhD in molecular
biology, and then before doing my next postdoc, I wanted to take a break and do something
different.
So I tried being a journalist, a science journalist, and fell in love with it and basically jumped
off the academic track and became eventually a computational journalist, basically using
data and code to find and tell stories that are impossible to tell otherwise.
And a friend of mine named Sean Gorley, who did his PhD with me in England at the same
time, I actually lived in the same house, our fate eventually became intertwined again.
I moved to the Bay area to do a visiting scholar stint at Berkeley, and he's in San Francisco.
He says, hey, John, I've got this startup called Primer.
And you really should come by and check out what we're doing.
I think you're going to find that the stuff we're working on really, really matches with
the stuff you work on.
And so eventually I had some time and I was like, okay, I'll pop over there for a week.
And sure enough, within one day, it was clear that they were solving problems that I just
find so hard and I wanted so badly to solve myself, that basically if you can't beat
them, join them.
Nice, nice.
So maybe for context, you can tell us a little bit about what the company does and the
kinds of problems that they're working on or you're working on.
Yeah.
So Primer at its core is an AI company that's trying to make machines that read and write.
That's the fundamental problem that underlies all this.
In terms of a business model, we, for example, automate a lot of the work that a junior analyst
would do in, say, a bank or the intelligence community.
Also frankly, what a journalist does.
I feel like I'm reverse engineering myself every day because a lot of what you have to
do.
It's also somewhat automating a lot of what you do, Sam, like all of our jobs, what we
have in common is that we have to read a ton of stuff, often very technical stuff, and
makes sense of it.
And then tell stories, like that is the fundamental unit of information.
That's our data structure, a story.
And that is really hard for computers to do.
It's really hard for people to do.
Exactly.
Yeah, it's one of those things that's both, that's hard for everyone.
So I think you're relatively new to this podcast, but those that have been around for a while
from the beginning know that it started out as more of a news-oriented format as opposed
to an interview format.
And basically, my mission was to kind of summarize the most interesting AI and ML tidbits from
the previous week's news.
But that is super, super hard, especially with so much news happening all the time.
It would take a ton of time to curate all of that information and digest it and turn it
into stories as you're saying.
Exactly.
And so, like you face several problems, and what we're trying to do at Primer is break
it down into reasonable problems that you can actually attack.
So one is, for example, what's relevant?
What are you telling a story about?
It's not enough to just say, I want to tell a story about last week's AI research.
It's like, okay, well, what documents are relevant?
Even if you could get the papers, then it's like, well, where do you get all the conversations
about those papers?
How do you figure out what those papers were about?
If there were a thousand papers published over the past several months and you wanted to
tell a story of a thousand papers, I don't know how a human would do that.
Well, actually, I can tell you, humans simply don't do that.
What we do is we take shortcuts.
We sort of fly blind.
We grab the zeitgeist, and that's kind of a random process.
It's like, well, I overheard some conversations, and this seems to be a hot topic, I'm going
to decide, and so I'm going to amplify it.
And what you end up with are coherent stories, but they're not necessarily what actually was
the most important thing that happened.
It's just some strange sampling of the space of all things that happened, and that's the
best you can do.
But what if you had a machine that could actually read everything and show you, in some sense,
everything that happened?
That's the goal.
So you showed me a kind of a portal into research papers, is the idea to provide that
as a service or more of the platform that allows someone to create that thing.
So we're in a pretty privileged position, we're privileged in the sense that we've already
got some really big customers.
So the federal government, Walmart, Singapore's sovereign trust, with several others coming
online soon, those are the relationships that actually pay the bills.
And so we do things like if you have a portfolio manager who's trying to keep track of a ton
of companies, that portfolio manager needs to stay on top of all the relevant developments
in the space roughly defined by all those companies.
All the news about them, maybe SEC filings, if you want to assess changes in risk profile,
it's sort of an overwhelming task.
And so primer basically superpowers those analysts by automating all the things that are really
hard and tedious and time consuming, and it basically reduces the cost of curiosity.
It allows those analysts to not spend half their day reading a million things just to find
out what was worth reading, instead they can see summaries of 100 papers at once, get
a sense of whether it's worth diving deeper or look at another batch of 100 papers.
It also gives alerts with predefined conditions so that you don't lose a second if something
that you know in retrospect is going to be a situation worth knowing about, you'll get
a heads up.
So meanwhile though, you can use the same machinery that does reading and writing and
summarization to do things like the thing I sent you, like read all of archive.
So we do have a business model for this system going forward, we're going to be developing
it into products for, for example, the pharmaceutical industry.
But for the time being, we just have this beautiful laboratory where we get to really push the
edge of natural language processing.
Tell us more about this archive project that you've built.
Yeah, archive is a really good illustration of this problem that we all face of too much
information.
If you ever go to the archive website, you basically see a fire hose of research coming in.
Archive is amazing because it is literally the place where research gets debuted.
It's the first place you'll see a paper coming out from Google or Microsoft or MIT on
topics that are basically going to define machine learning progress over the next 10 years.
In retrospect, you can look back and you can see the timeline of this amazing scientific
revolution unfolding.
But it's not at all human readable.
Even if you are an expert, even if you have a PhD in machine learning, you just can't
make sense of all of archive.
You might be able to make sense of the papers in your own subdomain, but even there, it's
tough.
You've got to find them.
Archive isn't designed for humans in a way.
I mean, it is, but it's just not user friendly.
Primer science is a stab at making sense of that.
Basically, it's a really hard problem that's well-scoped.
But what it does is it harvests all these papers and it does unsupervised learning on the
content of the papers to try and figure out what are the topics that this naturally falls
into.
Within machine learning, for example, I'm just looking now at some of the latest.
The system has discovered that there are not only image reconstruction papers.
There's like 58 papers actually in this bag that are on that theme, but it has discovered
that there's a whole bunch of research on traffic and temporal analysis.
There's something on mathematical optimization.
There's a whole bunch of papers about semantic segmentation.
All of this is happening without an ontology or a knowledge base.
You're going to have to have such a system if you want it to work on any corpus of papers.
You could imagine building some super ontology that captures everything there is to know
about science, but then it's going to be out of date next month.
I wouldn't want to build that thing because maintaining it would be a nightmare.
Instead, you need a system that does more or less what humans do on a smaller scale.
What we do is we look at things and we just sort of eyeball it and say, these are kind
of about this and these are about that, so you get a natural segmentation of the space.
Within each of these topics, it does a time series analysis and it tries to figure out,
if I take all the news and the social media signal, all the tweets about this research
as it was published and afterwards, all the commentary, all the real-time online critique,
sort of the peer review that's happening in real time out in the open, can I detect events?
And so an event can be more than just the publication of a paper.
It could be that, for example, a self-driving car crashes somewhere and suddenly the world
is looking intensely at an issue related to what we do and don't know about these systems.
And some of this research may get pulled into that.
If you want to detect that real-world event, you need a system that can actually divide
all those documents, all those tweets, all those things that are relevant to the same thing
and figure out how to segment them in time.
And so it does that too.
It tries to figure out, essentially, what were the big events in this space?
How was human attention in the world divided in relation to this corpus of papers?
And then it does some other cute tricks to make it useful to you as you dive into all
of this information.
It pulls out all the people and tries to tell you what it knows about them, just based
on the corpus, mind you.
We're also developing a version of this that is building a knowledge base and actually
learning about people as it reads the news and as papers are published.
And what I sent you this morning is just, essentially, out of the box, I don't know anything about
the world, but I know this group of thousands of papers you sent me.
And this is what I can tell you about them.
These are all the people.
These are all the topics.
These are the events that seem to all of this information seems to be pointing at out
in the real world.
And another cute one is, if you're finding the jargon really hard to understand, I've
generated a dictionary for you that is kind of a magical dictionary where if you click
on a technical term, it actually shows you who coined that term, how is it defined?
Give me some context about how to use this kind of like a Oxford English dictionary on
steroids.
Nice.
I'm finding this interview more challenging than most because as you're speaking, I've
got the tool in the background and I keep seeing papers that look really interesting.
It's working.
Super, super distracting.
So maybe can you tell us a little bit about the technology that's making it all happen?
Yeah.
You know, what does the stack look like?
What does the pipeline look like?
How are you approaching the unsupervised learning piece?
So it all begins with a gigantic elastic search index.
Okay.
I think if you talk to a lot of the people that you've interviewed, even already about what's
at the bottom of this whole stack, there's often like some massive index of documents.
So we're ingesting the news and blogs and tweets and scientific papers every day.
And that's the starting point of this whole system.
It has this growing corpus.
And so if you query, as we've done today on artificial intelligence, for example, the
first thing it has to do is retrieve all the information that is relevant.
And then kicks off this pipeline where basically the first thing it does is it tries with unsupervised
learning plus several other steps to divide all the information up into natural topics.
So within each topic, it then tries to detect the events in the real world that any of these
documents might be referring to.
So if you've got like 100 documents that might be news documents and scientific papers
and social media signal about all the above, you do a time series analysis.
And you try and figure out, are there real world events?
It's trying to make an inference here.
Are there real world events that all of this information is pointing at and describing?
It looks at events basically from the perspective of news articles, is that right?
The system you're looking at does, yeah, but you can imagine any document that has a meaningful
publication timestamp and includes a description or commentary about something that happened
in the real world.
It could in principle be mapped to something called an event.
The concept of an event is bigger than what a human intuitively would call event.
It might actually be, for example, an explosion of discussion around an issue.
For example, the Me Too movement is not just an event, right? It's made up of many events.
And some of these events might not even be something that could have been observed in
one place at one time, but there is a natural segmentation of all the things happening
in the world into something that we call events.
So that's the theory behind this.
Then if you click over to overview, sorry to distract you again, then it tries to tell
you a story.
So we've got many versions of this.
What you're looking at is basically the one of the earliest versions of this.
But basically, if you asked a machine to go and read thousands of things and you give
it a budget of one page to tell you what it learned, this is starting to get at what
you'd expect to come back.
This is what you get.
It's basically, and it's kind of like a technical report on these are things that I learned.
These are the big events.
These are the big papers.
This is what's getting us attention.
Oh, and then by the way, my topic analysis has revealed that there are some changes
of foot in artificial intelligence, and these are the things that seem to be trending
upwards and are really interesting.
And oh, by the way, I discovered there's this weird paper that seems to fall in this topic,
but it's deeply connected to this other topic, and that's statistically strange.
I need to tell you about it.
And by the way, here's some people who seem to be getting a ton of attention, and here's
another person who has collaborated with them on a high profile paper, and they've never
worked together before.
That's interesting.
So you can see what's going on here is the system has a model of what humans find interesting.
And of course, we humans at Primer built that in.
There's a story logic that I don't realize this.
You don't want a system to tell you everything it learned.
It's just going to be another fire hose.
You've made no progress.
A one-to-one map of the world is not a useful map.
So you need something that will compress the information and try and tell you a story.
So that's what the system does.
I think I interrupted you as you were about to start talking about the pipeline that you're
sending some of this stuff through.
And just going back to the beginning with archives, are you ingesting all of the archive
papers or crawling that site?
Yeah.
So Paul Ginsberg, who founded and still runs archive, is a friend of mine from a good
while back.
And he uses Primer Science as well.
I think actually he's the very first one I made a user account for.
Oh wow.
Yeah.
And so he's really helped out over the past year, making sure that we have direct access.
So we don't have to scrape the site.
We basically just pull down the entire day's new papers on one go.
And we do the same with news, except it arrives more or less in real time.
So we have a real-time stream, more or less, of the news with maybe a 10 minute delay.
And we've got a real-time stream of all the tweets that are relevant to the space.
Yeah, those via commercial APIs of some sort.
We get them directly from Twitter.
Okay.
So yeah, we have a data deal with them.
And the news?
The news we actually have several sources of.
One of the most convenient is Lexus Nexus.
They have a service called Morover.
You can actually purchase a fire hose of news.
They do a really good job, actually.
Oh wow.
Okay.
So you pull all that into your Elasticsearch index and maybe talk a little bit about some
of the underlying NLP bits that are enabling all this.
Yeah.
So when you kick off a query, what's happening is you're making a lot of reading happening.
So for example, if you take a look at the topics that have been generated, text and word
embeddings, quantum, and all of those topic labels that is generated, it actually
discovered and chose those from the content of the articles themselves.
So the first step in any NLP task on documents is to tokenize the entire document.
So are you familiar with tokenizing?
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
So you basically discover all the words and punctuation and you run an analysis that
gets you the parts of speech.
It's kind of like what you did in grade school when you made the sentence diagrams to try
and make sense of all the different parts of what someone says.
And then a whole bunch of things happen in parallel.
Basically, there's some things that are useful if you give it a bag of words so you can
take an entire scientific paper or even a thousand scientific papers.
They turn into bags of words.
And with that kind of analysis, you could, for example, discover the groups of words,
the Ngrams, that basically best describe this space and you can generate a label.
So if you go into any of those topics, it has decided to give that topic a name based
on the language within the documents themselves within the topic.
So I'm still amazed that it works, frankly.
NLP is kind of magical.
When something makes sense to a human, when there's a machine that didn't really understand
it in the same way you did, it's kind of magical.
Are you using kind of off-the-shelf NLP toolkits, NLTK-5000 stuff, or are you rolling your
arms off?
No, we started off that way.
So we've been using this tool Spacey from the very beginning.
It's free, it's open source, and it's really powerful.
And it's really what shocks me is that there are just two people at the heart of this project,
a fellow named Hannibal and a gal named Enis, who live in Berlin.
Not far from where I lived for a few years, and I've gotten to know them a little bit
just recently.
And it does the nuts and bolts NLP that you need.
So it will tokenize, but it'll also discover named entities.
It'll help you find the people and organizations and so forth.
But you need to train it.
That's something that we have discovered is just probably like everyone else.
It'll get you started, but then you need to solve your own problems.
It's only a starting point.
So for example, with the people and all the information that we can extract about them
and tell you a story based on the people in this space.
Spacey is one of the things that we use early in the pipeline, but then there's a ton
of custom code that we had to build to basically get the kind of information that Spacey can't
get to clean up the stuff that Spacey gets wrong to link it with all the other information
we're extracting by other means.
And it's a mixture of machine learning and good old fashioned regular expressions.
What I find so fun about being at an AI startup is the goal here is not to generate research
papers.
The goal is to just solve problems really well by whatever means you can.
So which I think is like the right motivation to have.
If you're just motivated to publish cutting-edge papers, you don't care if it works.
I went to this conference called NIPS, which is essentially where all this cutting-edge
research is being debuted, and something that really struck me is like half the stuff
that people are bragging about doesn't even really practically work.
Or works within such a narrowly constrained way of a problem that will work, but it's
computationally intractable.
That's fine.
That's the whole point is to debut tomorrow's technology, but it's frustrating when you're
trying to build something.
You get excited about some new idea and you chase it down, only to discover, oh, this
actually never could have worked.
I've had that experience.
I've found a paper using primer science, of course.
It's a pretty weird situation to have AI eating itself.
We basically have an AI system that reads AI papers, which we then used to try and improve
the AI that reads papers.
We came across a really exciting paper and fully replicated it, and it just doesn't work.
That's okay.
But how it goes in this space, when you're right at the edge of knowledge, it's not all
going to work.
We have this principle, a primer, of always trying to find the practical solution as quickly
as possible.
Don't get seduced by ideas that are sexy to talk about, but it's not actually solving
your problem.
Yeah.
I should throw in a plug for my newsletter.
I've recently written on this topic of reproducibility in both science and AI, drawing off of a
recent interview I did with Claire Galnick on this same topic.
But I really appreciate you owning up to that broader pipeline.
One of the questions I get a lot when talking with folks about their products or projects
is people want to know like, okay, granted you've applied some great cutting edge machine
learning AI stuff, but what else is there required to make it work?
What are the, how much heuristics are kind of in and around these tools to actually make
it work?
So to hear you note that, yeah, good old regular expressions are used liberally to make
sure that this all works.
I think it's important for, it's important to realize that and, oh, yeah, absolutely.
I guarantee you, you go into some of the biggest, most cutting edge groups at giant tech
companies.
You think that they're doing some kind of pristine AI that you just press a button and
it understands things.
I guarantee you look under the hood and there's just a ton of regular expressions.
Now, that's not to say that machine learning isn't the way forward, like it totally is,
but to make these things work on actual problems, it's still a labor of love.
So you're doing a lot with Spacey, are you also, which I'm assuming is more traditional
NLP technology approach?
Are you also doing things with, like, word-to-vec and deep learning based approaches?
Yeah.
In particular, as we've expanded into other languages beyond English, Spacey is just
not going to cut it when you want to make something that understands Russian and Chinese.
So we've actually had to pretty much make a bunch of tools from scratch, but it relies
on word vectors and word embeddings and where things get complicated is actually where
you try and pull this all together.
If you use deep learning to extract, for example, some pattern in a corpus of 10,000 documents,
the harder thing, once you've extracted, is knowing whether you're right and whether
it's worth saying.
I can find a bunch of patterns in text pretty easily, but the harder thing is assessing
how confident am I that I've found something that I haven't just misextracted.
It's not just a spurious pattern.
And then even harder than that, is it worth telling you, like, how do I square this with
my model of what humans are interested in?
Right.
Where we're headed with this is basically a model of stories, which ultimately is a model
of humans.
Humans are storytellers.
We've evolved to do this thing.
We just take it for granted.
What we're doing right now, this conversation, is incredibly high tech.
You and I, in real time, are gliding through a narrative that this is.
Many years of technology evolution.
It's amazing.
Yeah.
So I think this is actually the next frontier of AI decoding what story is.
So what does that mean practically?
How are you approaching that?
Yeah, so here's a bite-sized example, if you make something that reads scientific papers
and tries to tell you what you need to know about AI research last week, for example.
It's not enough to just give you a dashboard of, here's the most shared paper.
Here's the paper that got the most news.
Here's the paper that currently has the most citations.
That's not doing much heavy lifting for you.
If you were to hire a thousand human analysts to just work for you, like imagine you had
that luxury, what would you ask them to do?
That's kind of the better guiding question and what sort of story would they tell you?
What would the format be?
I guarantee the humans wouldn't come back and give you a dashboard.
They would say, okay, the big deal last week is that a self-driving car crashed and it's
kicked off a huge discussion about quality control and where system errors are going to
creep in and how you can make machine learning systems understandable from an engineering
point of view.
How are we going to deal with this emerging problem?
The people who are weighing in on this are the following researchers in deep learning,
but here's some other people who are very knowledgeable, but they're in a adjacent domain.
We think this is really worth knowing, but meanwhile, by the way, we discovered a paper
published by a couple of researchers that you've rarely heard of, but it's getting a lot
of traction and it seems to be on a topic that is emerging and you're probably going to
care about this.
It's basically, it has to do with voice recognition and we know that that's an interesting topic,
but the more interesting thing is that this researcher is really well known in a totally
different field and is just like diving into this and that's unusual.
So check it out.
Here's the paper.
I'm just going to go out on a limb here and say, you really should read this paper.
By the way, here's basically a new concept that is creeping into the space and we haven't
seen it before.
This might be a fluke, but I think this is actually something that's worth knowing
about.
Here are five papers that you should read.
I'm working within your budget here.
That's what all the humans would do.
It's basically the one-to-two-page presidential intelligence briefing.
Ideally, that's what it would look like.
A ton of research has gone into boiling things down to a very tight story and that's all
you need to know.
The idea then is that you've got some kind of generative model for creating these, basically
you're briefing over and it has two steps.
Like at least two steps.
One is what information can I find that's truly relevant, the wrong ingredients of a story.
And then the next step is, well, how can I synthesize this into an actual story?
I have to do text generation, document planning.
You give me a budget, a page, a paragraph, maybe you just want a bullet point and I'll
work with it.
I'll be able to express this as a story given that constraint.
And so kind of going back to our earlier exchange about good old fashion heuristics, how to
what degree?
I haven't looked at compared one of these briefing pages versus another, but how much is
generation and how much is more templates and things like that?
Yeah, so the philosophy we followed is always start fast and doable, put another way.
You always want to start with a model that you can fully understand yourself and implement
quickly so that you have some baseline.
So yeah, we've always started with, first can you do it yourself as a human, maybe even
no computer involved.
If you were to read 10 papers and try and say something intelligent about them, for example,
tell me, tell me, for example, what, if you were to classify events and I gave you a
pile of papers and I said, how would you classify these events, kind of tags would you attach
to them?
Or if you were looking for a particular kind of event, could you divide papers into yes
and no?
Always start with yourself, you the engineer, can you yourself do it?
Because if you can't, you're probably going to have a hard time teaching a computer
do it.
And then if you get some other humans, probably the person just to chairs away from you,
if you can get someone else to do the same task independently and get the same ideally
or a similar answer, okay, now you're in good shape.
Only then do you start building a computational system to try and do this automatically.
And your first stab at that should be something's great forward.
A set of regular expressions, heuristics, can you actually find this yourself using rules
that you yourself devise?
And then if the only way really to get beyond that, to really tackle increasing complexity
is to have something that will learn on its own, you'll never do that with regular
expressions.
You have to use machine learning to have a system find patterns itself in a changing
world.
So I think you're saying then that there's, you know, you're somewhere on the spectrum
of templates and machine learning.
Oh yeah, always.
In fact, I think the best things out there are always somewhere in the middle.
Right.
I think by definition.
And essentially it becomes a race.
Can we build something that can learn faster and output better, smarter content than the
system we have?
We had a little race actually recently to try and build an event classifier and a brilliant
engineer named Leonard Appleton took a stab at just using regular expressions, no machine
learning.
And another brilliant engineer named Yash took on the task of solving the same problem
using a really complicated machine learning graphical model and sometimes John Henry wins
the race.
Frankly, Yash could not build a system at least last I checked that could do better than Leonard's
massive, complicated, regular expression, heuristic engine.
But eventually, eventually machine learning will win.
Like we all know that, right.
But that's the beauty of a practical approach when you're really driven by practical principles.
You're willing to say, well, we've got a better solution that's actually simpler and
easier to understand.
Let's use that for now.
Keep trying.
But it's never long before a machine learning based system does better.
It's just an incredibly powerful tool.
When you're using machine learning for tasks like summarization where you referenced earlier,
you know, first you do it, then you get someone else to do it and you compare them.
You know, your summary of a given paper or a given paragraph is likely to be very different
from mine.
What do you find ground truth so that you can train learning models?
Yeah.
You've really put your finger on the hardest problem.
Stories by their nature can be told infinite ways.
There are some automated techniques that have been around for a decade.
They have French color names.
I don't know how that came about, but there's something called russian, something called
blue.
What they do is they treat the output as bag of word problems and they try and find out
how much information overlap.
There is between a human summary and a computer summary.
As you can imagine, that's great if you're trying to measure whether you got it terribly
wrong.
Right.
If we make two summaries and they have nothing to do with each other, then they're probably
they're probably not talking about the same thing.
Maybe.
That's right.
For summarizing fiction, we could be summarizing on two totally different levels and both be
right.
That's true.
That's absolutely true.
I think the same holds true for news.
I'll let you continue, but that seems like a very, very rudimentary metric.
Well, you'd be surprised then to learn that the latest greatest papers in this field are
still using those metrics, because they're easy.
It's a one click measurement, but it really doesn't help when you want to assess a subtle
output of a story that could be sliced and diced in sort of infinite ways.
Fortunately, it becomes a capture.
You need some human to read it and go, oh yeah, that makes sense, or that's crazy.
But there are some techniques you can use, so one is you can actually crowdsource assessment
of narrative.
You can give human annotators and scorers a system, a rigorous system, so like you can
measure the coherence, you can measure the sophistication, whether or not you've really
summarized the space well in various ways.
So those sounds like they would require a fairly sophisticated crowdsource.
Yeah, so that's right, like the more technical and sophisticated this task becomes, the less
you can rely on mechanical Turk.
In fact, eventually you've got your own engineers doing this, so it's definitely not scalable.
But there are some tricks that you can use.
So for example, if I generate a bunch of summaries on a topic that I've already summarized, for
example, if I have a Wikipedia article about it, I can at least find out if the most important
entities in the narrative have been represented.
And I can also turn the system around and do extraction on the summary.
You can even, I will suggest to make a generative adversarial network that generates stories
and critiques them.
You can see where this is going.
Eventually, you can have a system that tries to check off all the boxes of what counts
as a good story, like you've talked about the most important entities and you've expressed
their relationships, you've come in under budget in terms of space on the page.
But ultimately, you're going to need a human to assess whether it's a well-written story.
Until we can crack the code of text style transfer, where you can actually say, tell me the
story and the style of a New York Times reporter, or tell me the story and the style of a, you
know, a terse military briefing.
Send on my text in Hemingway style.
Exactly.
Until we can actually have networks that can both detect and reproduce narrative style.
I think we're for the time being stuck in a world where it's really hard to assess how
well our systems are doing.
Ultimately, you want to hook this up to your users and either passively or actively
harvest their feedback.
The simplest version of this, of course, is A-B testing.
If you write many versions of a summary and you expose a large number of humans to A versus
B, you can just find out what they think of it by, for example,
whether they click through and read it.
You can also make it active.
You can let users say, yeah, that was good or that was bad.
We're going back to my Hemingway text summaries.
Google inbox presenting you three choices for how to summarize the appropriate response
to an email.
Yep.
And we've played with that as well.
We generate alternative summaries to events, for example.
It's a really powerful way of real-time, effortless, quality checking.
You don't want to have to pause your whole engineering operation in order, all the time,
just to assess how well you're doing.
You really want it to be continual.
You want to always be reading the output of your own computational systems.
We call it dog fooding.
You've got to be real-time dog fooding.
The nice thing about primary science is this thing that I'm building is we use it to
discover the research that is going to help us make it better.
And so if you keep on using the thing, you are your own quality assessor.
That really helps.
Right.
But hard to scale.
I wish I could clone myself in some way to assess sort of at 1,000X.
Now one thing that I didn't see in what you've built, it seems like it is, it does a really
good job at this meta characterization of archive and what's happening in different categories.
But I didn't see it attempting to summarize individual papers.
Which is the thing that Jeff Dean and I were originally talking about.
Is it trying to do that somewhere?
Not in what you're looking at.
But we are actually working on that summarization problem.
Yeah, so we've taken two strategies and they're kind of running in parallel.
One is extractive summarization where you, the system is allowed to pull words and even
whole sentences directly from the text and then kind of pull them together into a summary.
That works extremely well when you have a large number of docs.
If you have 100 documents all about the same thing, extractive summarization is really powerful
and really efficient.
And then the alternative is abstractive summarization where the system is going to write its own words,
often character by character, out of thin air.
And it has a language model.
So it reads all these things and it basically makes a prediction about what it should say
next as it generates a summary.
A really nice bit of progress in this field that we've been using is abstractive summarization
with pointers.
So the idea here is you also have a sense of your confidence about whether the word or
phrase that you're putting into the summary at any given time is going to be a good choice.
And if you're not so confident, you point back to the text and you grab the thing itself.
So for example, if you had a sentence that said one of the most exciting areas of artificial
intelligence these days is generative adversarial networks.
If generative adversarial networks, that phrase is something that you haven't encountered
or your model basically says, I'm not sure if I can actually paraphrase that.
Then what you want to do is what a good human writer would do.
You just go back and you grab that thing.
So you can summarize while also having some of the advantages of extractive.
So summarizing basically around the entities that you aren't too sure about.
Exactly.
It basically becomes a sliding scale between abstractive and extractive.
The more confident it gets, the more abstractive it gets, the more flexible it gets, which
will allow you to summarize a single scientific paper, for example, in a couple of sentences.
And if you're not so sure, then it slides over to extractive and it will just pull out
the sentences that it deem and the phrases that it deems are the most central and informative.
Interesting.
It's a hard problem though.
It's a really hard problem.
Another thing that makes it hard when it comes to scientific papers is they already have
their own summaries.
They're called abstracts.
And you'd think that, oh, great, this job done, but as you know, abstracts themselves
can be so riddled with jargon and references to arcane things that it's hardly a summary
at all.
It's really only a summary for the authors of the paper.
Right.
So you really need a summary of the summary.
And that's what we're working on.
We're finding that you really do need to power this with an ontology and a knowledge base
though.
A library on that.
Okay, so let's take, for example, a problem that I'm just starting to work on.
How do you summarize and make sense of pharmaceutical research papers?
So there is an ontology that is available to everyone that basically the NIH paid for
called MASH.
And it's kind of like every jargon term in biochemistry and molecular biology, gene names and gene
types, all of that is captured in this very rich ontology that was hand-built by no
doubt by un thanked graduate students.
And something that's really nice about MASH is that it's actually a subset of wiki data.
And wiki data is the database that stands behind wikipedia.
Now I say that in an idealistic way because actually, in reality, that's the way it was
dreamed up.
Oh, wiki data is going to basically be the database that powers wikipedia.
But in fact, it's not there yet.
Humans vastly prefer to update wikipedia with content and wiki data basically plays catch-up.
Nonetheless, it is a huge powerful open source knowledge base and the MASH ontology is a
subset of it.
And so if you want to summarize a scientific paper, just a single scientific paper, the
first thing you need to do is make sense of it.
You need to map all of those words which to the computer or just, it could be random numbers
for all they cares, has no idea what it means.
You need to map them to concepts and that's what systems like MASH were designed to help
us do.
So the idea of being instead of what you're doing in science primer, and doing this in
a totally unsupervised manner, here you're using the additional information you're getting
from the pre-existing ontology to help the machine make sense of the various documents.
And to paraphrase it.
So like a good summary is something that doesn't just say less.
It also says just as much but in a compressed way.
Right.
If I just tell you the beginning of a story, I haven't really compressed that story for
you.
I need to give you the sense of the beginning, middle, and end and compress that all
down into three sentences.
And you're not going to be able to do that just using the standard NLP techniques on a
scientific paper.
You're just not going to be able to do it, no way.
You have to map that out to an ontology and say, oh, you know, this long sentence describing
this genetic pathway, I can boil that down to a single sentence that says, the genetic
pathway X, you know, interesting, but yeah, you need a lot of tacit knowledge to be able
to do that.
So that's what we're working on.
Awesome.
Well, John, this has been super interesting.
I really appreciate you taking the time.
Thank you.
Anything else you'd like to share with the audience?
Oh, just that I'd like to make a prediction.
Go ahead.
Well, I predict that the kind of stuff we're working on is going to accelerate artificial
intelligence research more than anything else.
I think building AI that can read the latest research on AI and help the engineers who
build it, build it faster is going to vastly accelerate the whole process.
Awesome.
Well, we will put your prediction on the blockchain and just to make sure we get all the jargon
in.
Exactly.
Then we'll do an ICU.
We'll do an ICU, right?
Awesome.
Thanks so much, John.
Thanks, Sam.
All right, everyone.
That's our show for today.
For more information on John or any of the topics covered in this episode, head on over
to twomolei.com slash talk slash one, three, six.
Thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.