Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast why interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
This week we're celebrating the second anniversary of this podcast.
If the pod has made a difference for you, please show us some love by letting us know how
over on our second anniversary page at twimlai.com slash 2av.
You want to hear the ways the podcast has helped you or your business, how it's enabled
you to find or connect to resources you found valuable, or how it's educated you about
new and interesting topics.
Submit your written or audio comments via the page we've set up, and we'll be sharing
a few of your stories with your permission of course, in a special podcast episode celebrating
the Twimble community.
In today's show, I sit down with David Van Veilin, assistant professor of bioengineering
and biology at Caltech.
David joined me after his talk at the Figure 8 train AI conference to chat about his research
using image recognition and segmentation techniques in biological settings.
In particular, we discuss his use of deep learning to automate the analysis of individual
cells and live cell imaging experiments.
We had a really interesting discussion around the various practicalities he's learned
about training deep neural networks for image analysis, and he shares some awesome insights
into which of the techniques from the deep learning research have worked for him and
which haven't.
If you're a fan of our nerd alert shows, you'll really like this one.
Before we jump in, I'd like to send a shout out to our friends over at Figure 8 for their
continued support of the show and their sponsorship of this week's series which all took place
at train AI.
Figure 8 is the essential human and loop AI platform for data science and machine learning teams.
The Figure 8 software platform trains, tests, and tunes machine learning models to make
AI work in the real world.
Learn more at www.figure-8.com
Just a reminder, this episode was recorded live on site so there's some unavoidable
background noise.
And now on to the show.
All right everyone, I am here with David Van Bellen at the train AI conference.
David is a system professor in the biology and bioengineering department at Caltech.
David, welcome to this week in machine learning and AI.
Thank you for having me.
Awesome.
Why don't we get started by having you tell us a little bit about your background and
how you came into AI as a biologist?
Yeah.
So I can start from the beginning.
So I was born in Los Angeles, grew up on the East Coast, upstate New York for middle school
and West Virginia for high school, where upstate.
So we lived in Liverpool, which is, I want to say like within like an hour of Syracuse.
So it was very, it was upstate enough where things like like effects know were a very,
is a reality.
Yeah, I asked because I grew up in New York City and went to school, upstate it.
Okay.
Awesome.
And that's our New York.
Yeah.
I'm familiar with RPI.
They have very, very good students.
Yeah.
And so I went to high school in West Virginia and graduated, went to college.
So I went to MIT and I was a double major in math and physics.
At the same time, I had the luxury of having like fresh and biology taught by like Eric
Lander, who's, you know, big shot scientists who like runs like the Broad Institute, between
like MIT and Harvard.
You know, he was like one of the big early pioneers in like the human genome research project.
And he was also as a background as a mathematician.
And so the way he explained biology really resonated with me and made me want to like sort
of continue that thread further.
And so after I finished at MIT, I went to the MD PhD program at UCLA and Caltech.
And so the way that program works is you spend two years, first two years, doing medical
school, then you do your PhD and then you return for your clinical training.
And I did my PhD at Caltech in the employee phase of the department with Rob Phillips.
And there, it was a really great environment because there's exposure to sort of, you
know, thinking about problems in biology, using like ideas from physics.
But then there was also some very quantitative experiments that we're doing as well.
And so there was a lot of imaging.
There was a lot of image analysis.
And there was a lot of image segmentation and so image segmentation, you know, figuring
out what parts of your images correspond to like which objects you care about.
We have to do a lot of that.
So that was sort of like my first exposure to those sorts of problems.
And there was sort of this given where if you were sort of the more mathy type and you
could do the physics calculations, then people just assume that you're going to be good
at doing the image segmentation and that you'd figure out how to get those tools to work
to solve like your problems of interest.
And by and large, like, you know, they're right, but it's still like a separate skill set
that you have to learn.
And yeah, and so that was probably like my first introduction to computer vision, to image
segmentation, image recognition was during my graduate training.
Finished my PhD on 2011, finished my MD 2013.
So I went back to clinical training from 2011 to 2013 and you know, got like more exposure
to problems in clinical medicine.
And then after that, I went up to Stanford to continue training as a postdoctoral fellow.
And so I was up at Stanford for about four or five years with Marcus Cover in the bioengineering
department.
And there there's when I started getting into sort of like the more machine learning
slash AI space and so your initial exposure to computer vision was more traditional tools
that are close to machine learning, so if you're doing edge finding filtering, thresholding,
watershed transforms, you know, wavelets, all of that, you know, that was my first exposure.
And so what you would usually end up doing is you, you know, you have an idea of like what
these tools did and how each one worked.
And then you'd basically bash some collection of these tools together to work on like your
problem like of interest.
And so the experiments that we were doing at the time, and so I think you probably saw
some of it at the talk that I gave yesterday is, you know, we have these images of cells
and so at the, so let me just give it back story of the talk for like your listeners.
So part of the talk I was sort of showing like what I was doing during my graduate work.
We were very interested in like the life cycle of these viruses and in particular how these
viruses got their DNA from inside the viral capsid into like the bacterial cell.
We didn't really have an idea of how it worked and so we had this idea to create an experiment
to like let us watch.
And so the challenge was, can you figure out a way to look at one piece of DNA being transferred
from like inside the virus to inside the cell?
The answer is yes you can, you have to use these very particular kind of dye that will
stain the DNA while it's inside the viral capsid and then you can watch the dye molecules
get transferred between the virus into the bacterial cell.
So you get these gorgeous movies but we then have to do is quantify these movies so you
can, you know, have some sense of the dynamics of this process.
And to get a sense of the type of movie that we're looking at, like what's the field of
view and in terms of how zoomed in this is this, is are you looking at one transfer, one
organism or is it many, many that you have to figure out?
For one paper's worth of data, there's roughly about 50 or so events that you're looking
at.
And it's not that often.
So you're generally looking at maybe like a few hundreds of you live you, there might
be, you know, somewhere between 20 to 100 is those cells within that field of view.
And you know, all of those cells maybe like a couple will have like an infection event
within what time period within the time period of about 30 minutes.
So these movies were taken in roughly like one snapshot every 30 seconds to every minute.
And you know, that's sort of like how the, that data was collected, granted it's been
about seven years since I collected that data set.
But from what I remember, that's, that's what we, that's what we did.
And so you get these like, you get these gorgeous movies.
And so what you need to then do is, you know, identify, okay, which part of the movie
are which pixels within each frame correspond to like the cells, which ones correspond to
background, which ones correspond to the virus, which ones correspond to the viruses that
we actually care about.
And then once you've done that, then you can go and quantify your images, right?
And so you can ask, you know, how bright were the viruses over time, how bright were the
cells over time and use that to generate, you know, some like quantitative curves of,
here's how much DNA was being transferred as a function of time.
And then once you have like that, those curves, then you can go and do your, you know, your
fancy modeling, your physics and, you know, determine, okay, well, from this set of hypotheses
for how I think this process is happening, you know, which ones are actually like consistent
with like the data that we've generated.
And so when you're trying to determine the, the brightness, which tells you how much DNA
was transferred, is this, how much in terms of the length of the sequences transferred
or some of the other.
It's ideally like what you want to, that's ideally like what you want is like how many
base pairs or how many nanometers worth of DNA has been transferred like over time.
And so you kind of use a calibration curve.
And so you know at the beginning of the event, you know, the virus has about 48 kilobase
pairs of DNA at the end of the event, like it should have zero and use some like linear
interpolation, you know, assuming that, you know, you know, linearly related, you know,
brightness versus like how much DNA, and then you can like infer from the movies, go from
brightness to like the amount of DNA.
So where does machine learning and AI fit into all that?
Yeah.
So machine learning and AI fits in, and how do you do like the object, how do you do like
the object recognition, the image segmentation?
And, you know, that experiment was, you know, it was sort of like the classical computer
vision approaches that we used to analyze that data.
And when I started my postdoctoral fellowship at Stanford, I had ideas for experiments that
I'd like to do.
And basically what I wanted to do was, you know, look at genome scale knockout libraries
with image them and then look at them with single cell resolution.
So what's a genome scale knockout library?
Genome scale knockout library is a collection of strains where in each strain, you have one
gene that's been removed or inactivated.
And so if you're interested in, you know, say like a particular like biological process.
So the ones that the one that I was interested in at the time and that my lab is currently
interested in are host virus interactions.
And so you want to understand how do viruses and their host talk to each other and what
parts of the host are important for that communication.
There are experiments that you can do where if you have a way to look at the communication
using imaging, then you can basically go one by one, remove a gene from like the host.
And if that gene was important, then that's going to alter what the communication was
or what like the outcome of the violent infection ended up being.
And you know, that's what you know, the host in this case is the host in this case is not
the virus, but the cell that's infecting.
Right.
Yeah.
So moving that particular sequence prior to the infection, prior to the infection.
And so you've got a control experiment, you've got a control where nothing's been removed
and then you have a collection of strains where in each strain, one gene has been removed.
And so there are collections that like this that exists for certain strains of E. coli,
there are collections that exist for East.
People at the Chan's upper initiative are creating collections like this that exist for, you
know, mammalian cells.
And these are really powerful tools because, you know, because they exist in like this
array format where one well of additional have one strain that has one gene removed, then
you can systematically go one by one and ask, okay, does this removal, does that influence
what I was interested in studying?
So in this case, does it influence the outcome of particular viral infection?
So what we want to do is to be able to read out a screen of this library using imaging
and imaging with single star resolution, there you're going from the case of where you're
doing, you know, 50 or 100 or 1000 cells to doing millions.
And there you don't have the luxury of being able to like go back and like manually correct
like segmentation errors.
You really need something that's going to work 99% of the time if not, if not better.
And that's where the machine learning comes in.
And so I remember when I was a medical student, I was sort of like browsing Facebook and
I realized like, hey, you know, Facebook actually knows like where the faces are in, you know,
in like all the images I'm uploading, not only that, but it has like ideas of like who's
in these, who's in these pictures?
Like, is it you? Is it like your, you know, like you're one of your three like best friends?
And you know, just, you know, I've done like a lot of microscopy in my, um, over my
career.
And it's like, I know that the images that I collect on microscope are a lot simpler than
the images of like me doing Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu or hanging out with my friends that like
a part of your whatnot.
Right.
You know, what are those guys doing and can I steal it, um, or borrow or co-op, but, you
know, rallies like, you know, blatant theft, you know, can I take those tools and then repurpose
them to like work on our microscopy data?
And so the answer was, you know, the answer was yes, um, and on the time that I started
my postdoc and started like, think about these issues again, was literally right as the
deep learning and fletch and curve, um, started to take off.
Okay.
And so it turned out, you know, yes, you can repurpose these tools and it, you know, it
ends up working like really, really, really well.
And so we had a paper that we did, um, and plus computation biology, um, basically showing
that for the single cell image segmentation problem, the existing tools, um, work as
well as a state of the art, um, for a cross a variety of different cell types.
So whether you're imaging bacteria, whether you're imaging mammalian cells in cell culture,
if you're looking at phase images, if you're looking at fluorescence, microscopy images,
that, you know, the tools work really well and it's at a point that, you know, people
in the cell biology community, you know, really need to start taking like a really close
look at these tools and, you know, start thinking about like, how can these, um, how can
these change the way that I do my experiments and what experiments will they let me do?
That would previously have been like impossible.
Okay.
Yeah.
And so did you use off the shelf CNNs and all the kind of stuff, or did you have to start?
And yeah, so like I started at the beginning.
And so yeah, so at the time, um, when I first started, um, Andre Carpathi put together
and faithfully put together like their first CS231 end course, which I think is now kind
of like iconic in the field.
I got to sit on that for a couple of weeks, um, to like sort of like get, um, familiarize
myself with the field, enough of the point where I can go and like, you know, hack some
piece of code together, Karrist didn't really, um, was didn't really exist at the time.
Um, cafe was like a new thing.
Um, TensorFlow didn't exist and it was basically, you know, do you want to learn kuda?
Or were you like, okay, like learning like piano?
And so when I first started, um, I was programming in like naked piano, had to figure
out how to pipe data into like, you know, simple like CNN, um, architectures.
How do you like save models?
How do you like, you know, once you like save parameters, like how do you load it?
Like the really nice frameworks that exist today, like those didn't, um, those didn't
exist at the time.
And so, you know, sort of like had to like figure like all those things out, get some like
hacky pieces of code that would work.
But the first, like, basically like the very simplest, you know, CNN architectures that
you could write down ended up working, um, really well.
And so actually like, as far as this stuff that my lab uses, um, in production for the
data that we analyze, um, the data that we analyze with, um, well, with our collaborators,
um, we, you know, still use those like very simple, um, neural network architectures.
Um, I would say like there's, um, there's a lot of like really cool stuff that people
have done.
Um, but I found it very useful to pay attention to what's going to generalize on small datasets,
as opposed to, you know, what's the latest and greatest that are out there.
And, you know, just from like my own personal experience, you know, some of the things that
will perform like really well on image net, like say like residual networks, um, they have
issues with overfitting.
And if you don't have like that large corpus of data where your network can learn all
of the edge cases, you'll still, you'll get more like practical utility from like, you
know, the simpler neural networks trained, um, in an approach, in a way where you like,
you're doing like the regularization, um, and the, you know, normalization and like the
post processing, like correctly.
And so was your, your training data, the datasets that you had traditionally created using
manual segmentation or traditional computer vision?
Yeah.
So those were, so I would say like this is true and academia is true in life is that if
you want to get people excited about something, like first you have to prove that it's going
to work.
Um, and so the first generation of training data, um, like I created like myself.
And so I annotated a couple images of bacterial cells in image J and, you know, image J is
a, um, Java, a Java program that people have labeling box bounding box tools.
It's like a general, it's a general purpose, um, image visualization and also image analysis,
um, toolkit that the NIH supports.
Okay.
So they have tools for annotating images.
It's relatively clunky, but it worked then and it works now, um, for some cases like
we, um, we still use it.
Mm-hmm.
But yeah, I generated it.
It worked.
You threw out a few different numbers when you said a couple of images.
Yeah.
Is this a couple of images with 50 things that need to be annotated or a couple of images
with a million things that need to be annotated?
A couple of images with a couple with about a hundred-ish things that need to be annotated.
Okay.
And we paid, um, for the plus computation biology paper and even now, we paid very close
attention to data augmentation.
We paid a lot of attention to normalizing images before they go into like the neural network.
So you can account for like variations in image acquisition.
And we paid a lot of a tent, we paid like a good amount of attention to post-processing
what happens to like the output of the neural networks afterwards.
And can you still leverage some of the, some of the classical tools that you use in computer
vision, like the watershed transform, like active contours or whatnot to sort of refine
like what the neural network produces to produce something that you can like actually like
use on like real data.
And we found that by like paying attention like those things, you know, you don't have to
use like the latest and greatest, you know, stuff in the neural networks in the deep learning
space, relatively simple things with those things like paid attention to work like really
well.
And did you iterate to paying attention to all those things?
Or did you just kind of start there and that's what work?
We were always iterating people create like really, really great pieces of work all the
time.
And like there's just an innately curious part of me wondering like how well will that
stuff work on the data sets that we've generated and the other people have generated sort
of like in this space.
And now that I'm running my own group, I have people to sort of like help explore like
that space.
I will say that we're primarily interested in like the scientific questions that we can
answer with these tools.
And that curiosity kind of like drives our interest in the deep learning space.
We're well, I find it like interesting and mathematically elegant.
We're not necessarily like deep learning for like deep learning sake.
It's more like deep learning, you know, because like we have like real problems that
we're trying to, um, that we're trying to address.
That's the way it should be.
I think so.
Yeah.
So you mentioned a few kind of tricks and techniques that you paid attention to, data
augmentation.
Yeah.
How did you go about that or what were some of the highlights or anything stand out in
terms of, you know, doing this really made it work for us.
Was it standard kind of, you know, rotating things around and changing brightness levels
and that kind of thing?
I would say like the things that like, the things that like we found that worked, um,
is just like being like trying to be a systematic, um, as we could with the things that we tried.
And so like we have tried, um, so I can like just go through the list of things that we
tried for our plus computational, um, biology paper.
The usual like data augmentation things that we've tried, um, so image rotations, image
flipping, those things like really matter, um, I would say there were some things that
we tried that didn't really make so much of an impact.
So image sharing and so sharing is like another like another operation that you can, um, that
you can do to augment your data.
We found that that didn't really like impact like performance of like the neural networks
that we got.
Um, I would say paying attention to how you're doing the training, um, made an impact.
And so we found that for us, the simpler, you know, simpler stochastic gradient is sent
with, with Nesterov momentum that ended up being, um, better, roughly speaking than, you
know, RMS prop, Adam, et cetera, et cetera.
But that was also conditioned on like what networks that we were using and like what features
we had within those networks.
And so bash normalization, um, sort of influences like which one is going to work better, um,
whether using like dropout or using like bash normalization, like with dropout, we tend
not to do that.
To not to use dropout or to not to use bash normalization, then we generally speaking,
don't use dropout.
And I would say like I, we generally speaking, don't use dropout that much.
Uh, I don't know how general this quote unquote finding is.
But one thing that we noticed was if you look at the, let me just take like a brief second
to sort of like stay like how we do like our neural network training.
And so we sort of repose.
Yeah.
So basically like the task that we're trying to do is instant segmentation.
And so for your listeners who are sort of like familiar with this space, it's the same
task that networks like mask our CNN, um, solve.
We started working on this before mask our CNN came out.
And so there's sort of like, you know, different ways of like slicing that up.
Well, the way that, uh, we did it is, is a framework that Dan Cirisson posed in a paper,
um, many years ago, which is recasting the instant segmentation problem as an image
classification problem.
And trying to classify like every pixel as either being, um, in interior, being inside
a object, in this case, inside a single cell, being at the boundary of a single cell,
or being as part of the background.
And you can looking at things in that way, then, you know, it's basically like an image
classification problem, um, we train using like sample wise, um, training.
And so we basically have these, we have like these maps of what every pixel like should
be, we crop like a small area around like each pixel, feed that into a deep convolutional
neural network to do the classification.
And once it's trained, um, we basically use dilated convolutions and dilated pooling
kernels to run that classification neural network on entire image, um, to generate like
dance predictions.
What are the, what are dilated convolutions and dilated, um, so dilated convolutions
are basically, if you take your convolutional kernel, um, dilations are basically just like
inserting zeros in between, um, the weights of your, of your convolutional kernel.
And there's a similar, um, there's a similar thing, um, in the pooling kernel.
Yeah.
And so it turns out you, you kind of have to do that because, because you're training
this neural network, uh, to do pixel wise classification, once it's trained to do dance prediction, if
you try to feed it in patch by patch, if you have two neighboring pixels, then basically
all of the patches around it are essentially redundant computations.
And so you need, um, you need to use like the dilated, um, kernels to, you know, get like
a fully convolutional, um, execution instead of your, your dilation factor end up being
like a hyper parameter.
No, it's like, it's like mathematically like exact.
If you dilate things in the right way, then it ends up being like mathematically the same
as like running everything like, um, doing like patch wise, um, patch wise predict show.
Okay.
So I got like sidetracked on, on, on, on that.
So like there's a reason, I mean, this happens to me like all the time as I'm getting, as
I'm getting older, um, we were talking about the kind of various ways you've tweaked
the process, and you mentioned that, um, you know, while there are some, uh, newer approaches
to segmentation, you, um, kind of rolled your own based on a paper, yeah, and, uh, ended
up using this dilation as a way to do the pixel by pixel.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, and we're all, I think we're also talking about like what parts did we find, or what
authentic, and what wasn't.
Yeah.
So like the output of this, um, the output of like this approach is you get like probably
maps for what's like inside of it, so what's the cell boundary, and what's like a background.
Um, if you use drop, and so for the post processing, it's actually helpful to have like some notion
of uncertainty.
And so if the neural network is like not sure, it's easier for the post processing for, let's
say, the picture was not, pixel where it's not sure.
It's more useful to have that pixel value be like 0.5 instead of, you know, making a very
certain like false call.
And so what we found, uh, with some of our experiments with dropout is that it was essentially
removing some of the uncertainty that was encoded in these probability maps, and that
made it a little harder to do like the downstream, um, processing.
That's why I, I kind of like shy away from dropout.
Um, I don't know like how general this is, and, but this is like that was like one of
the, um, empirical observations on that, um, you know, I've noted during like my, um,
time-experiment of these things, um, other things that like really help, um, more, like
more training data, the more data that you have to capture more and more edge cases, then
like the better, um, the better the neural networks are going to perform, uh, we found that
roughly if you have like standardized like acquisition, um, conditions, and you collect
your training data on like the same acquisition conditions, then you really only need, I'd
say like on the order of like a few hundred, um, to a thousand cells to get like neural
networks and it'd be like good enough to analyze like subsequent experiments, but the more,
the more training data that you get, then the better that it's going to be.
And I think now we're getting to the point, I mean, we're getting the point we're having
like more and more like data sets that are like publicly available.
So when we published our paper in plus computational biology, we released like all the data sets
we annotated, I think it was on the order of like maybe like, you know, 10 to 15-ish
images, it was quite a bit of work to do, um, but you know, I'm a big fan of if you're
publishing something, you know, make everything they're doing like openly available, um, and
I think like as we're seeing, there is more people are recognizing that the challenges
in this space aren't necessarily like the algorithms anymore.
It's like having access to like good like high quality data, right?
If you give someone, you know, a good data set, you know, there's going to be like some
nerd in some basement, you know, who's like lives on stack overflow is going to be able
to put together like some kind of machine learning solution, uh, using that data set.
It's just are there data sets that are out there.
And I think now we're starting to see like more and more data sets, um, like in this space.
And so the ones that come to mind.
So I think there's, there was one that was released by, um, the Broad Institute, um, it was
like part of like the 2018, um, Kaggle data science competition, uh, for doing nuclear
segmentation.
Um, that was one of the things that we tackled in our plus computation biology paper.
But more data sets on more data types and you'll get better on better neural networks.
And as we saw today, um, you know, figure eight is releasing annotated data on H&E pathology
images, um, for doing nuclear segmentation on a variety of like different tissue types.
And so I think like the more and more data sets that we have that cover more and more,
um, use cases, then like the closer we're going to get to actually having like general tools
that, you know, people be able to use like off the shelf, um, which I think is going to
be like really, really awesome.
So yeah.
Uh, in my view, like I view this space as the challenges, I don't want to like downplay
how hard it is to like it started like in machine learning and deep learning.
It's like, you know, of course, there's like, there's like challenges and issues, but
it's really, I'd say like data sets, um, are like one big challenge and deployment, um,
challenges and other challenge, um, once you have like a neural network, um, that's trained
to like do your task.
How do you give it to like other people so they can use it for their problems and like
their data?
Yeah.
And have you, have you started to tackle that one at all or one thing that I talked about
at my talk, um, yesterday was, you know, sort of like what are, what are we working on
on the deep learning space, um, one is, yeah.
So one is just deployment and experiments, experiments that we do in our lab.
That requires, you know, a little bit more training data because like the experience that
we like to do or sort of like, like large scale imaging and then also deploying, um, these
neural networks so you can do like segmentation in, in tissues, right?
And so there's sort of like the, you know, well controls, you know, cell culture type experiments,
but then there's a messier world of, you know, imaging and, you know, real life tissues
that, you know, pathologists, um, pathologists do.
And so these require different scales of training data and the things that you'd really like
to do in these spaces are either like very complicated tissues or having three dimensional
data sets.
So being able to do two dimensions in space plus time or being able to do like three
dimensional, um, spatial, um, three dimensions in space, say like you're using like a confocal
microscopy, um, setup or, um, another like more sophisticated instrument.
And so that requires a different scale of training data because instead of annotating
a couple of frames to be able to look at the objects, you have to be able to like annotate
like entire movies.
And that's what I've been working with, um, people that figure it with, um, is, how do
you train people on the crowd to like do these, um, sorts of tasks?
Oh, I think we're just, I think they ended up talking.
I think we showed, you know, sort of like some of like the stuff that's off the press.
I think we're just now getting people, um, in the crowd able to annotate the 3D data
sets, um, Robert Monroe show being able to, you know, do like object tracking, um, in
the crowd.
I'm super, super excited about that because I think that's one of the, you know, one of
the big, um, challenges, um, in lifestyle imaging and, you know, to do that, what you need
are, you know, nice, um, annotated, um, annotated data sets.
And so we've been working on annotating on issues with like crowdsourcing, like, um,
data set annotation, we're also, um, thinking about deployment as well.
And so there are a lot of things to think about there.
Um, so yeah, I would say there's a difference between what I like to call like academic
software, which is, you know, someone has like a cool idea they put together a nice set
of scripts, um, in Python or MATLAB or R. And for, well, for MATLAB and R, they're relatively
like well-contained environments and you can give someone a dot M file, um, or an R file
and it'll kind of work on another MATLAB installation.
But Python's a different beast.
Everybody's got like their own version, their own limitation and for all of the different
stacks on the library, does a different libraries.
And so that's a, that's a problem, right?
Is that I can't give somebody like a link to my GitHub and say like, good luck.
Um, you have to, there's a lot more, um, there's a lot more work that has to be done.
So, you know, it's basically, you know, doing your due diligence, looking at like the best
tools that are out there for solving these problems, um, we have switched to doing like
our development inside of NVIDIA Docker now.
And we're looking as, um, to use that for, you know, deployment.
So like we have collaborators who use some of those scripts that we generate, um, and
now instead of, you know, giving them like, hey, here's like the Python file, um, you
know, hey, here's like a Docker container, um, that has like all of the packages, um,
installed.
And, you know, there's layers of work to, uh, that has to be done like on top of that.
Ideally, you know, you'd have like your Docker container, um, up and running, you'd have
stuff like wrap within like a web framework.
You have, you know, that backend talking to like a front end with some semblance of like
user interface, um, and now that I have like a team of people thinking of these sorts
of issues, um, you know, we're thinking of, um, we're thinking of like just implementing
on some of these things to like have it easier for people like within the lab, um, people
within the labs that we collaborate with and also like the people who, um, you know, download
our stuff and use it, um, make it easier for them to use too.
Awesome.
Yeah.
Uh, well, David, this has been really, really interesting.
Thanks so much for taking the time to chat with us.
Um, it's been absolute pleasure.
Um, thank you very much.
Uh, I should like, I mean, I would like to think like a few people, um, if I'm like a
lot, go right ahead.
Yeah.
Uh, like I think the graduate students, um, who have, um, been worth rotating with me,
like the last, um, this quarter.
So Dylan Bannon and Nadia Vilevich, uh, I've got to thank, um, people I've worked with
at Stanford.
And so I had the privilege of working with Nicholas Quatt.
She's a very talented undergrad who did a lot of the experiments I talked about yesterday.
Um, my postdoctoral advisor, um, Marcus covert, um, he was great.
And it was his lab that, um, sort of gave me like the intellectual freedom to start exploring
like these, um, sets of issues, um, you know, looking at like AI and the interface with
uh, the biological sciences, um, I had a great, great ongoing collaboration with, uh, Michael
Angelo, who's a professor at the college department at Stanford.
Um, he's done amazing, um, amazing stuff, um, on digital pathology and developing like
the next platform of digital pathology instruments.
I will let you look at literally, you know, dozens of different biological markers within
tissues.
And he's had an amazing postdoctoral fellow, um, Leot Karen, um, who I worked with as
well, uh, unfortunately, you didn't get to stick around for the talk yesterday, um, but
I talked about some of the work I was doing with them.
And also like to think, um, Casey Wong and long, hi, um, I do, I do work with their labs,
um, as well.
Awesome.
So yeah.
And of course, the folks that figure eight for the support of your work and having us
here at the podcast, folks that figure eight, um, Andy, Justin, Robert, um, everybody's
been like, everybody's been amazing.
Their openness has, I think is, I was like, it's a model that people in academia should
pay attention to as far as like collaborations between like academia and industry, like the
things that figure eight's allowing my lab to do.
And the resources they've given us, like the work that, you know, we're doing and we're
going to do would not be possible like without them.
Fantastic.
Yeah.
Other funders, uh, NH, or welcome fund, uh, Paul Allen Family Foundation, um, they funded,
um, a large, um, large amount of work and also the division of biology and engineering
at Caltech for posting my laboratory and also, um, funding us as well.
Awesome.
Well, thanks so much, David.
Thank you.
All right, everyone.
That's our show for today for more information on David or any of the topics covered
in this episode, head on over to twimlai.com slash talk slash one forty one.
Thanks again to figure eight for their sponsorship of this episode.
To follow along with the train AI series, visit twimlai.com slash train AI 2018.
And last, but not least, go ahead and show us some love for our second anniversary and
share how the podcast has been helpful to you over at twimlai.com slash two A V, the
number two A V.
Thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.