Hi, it's Sam, a quick story before we get going.
A few weeks ago at the Twomel AI Summit, I met a listener, Nicholas, who works for a leading
energy company.
We spent a bit of time chatting, and he mentioned a few of the things he'd learned about on
the podcast that he went ahead and implemented at his company.
He was particularly excited about the semantic folding technology he learned about on Twomel
Talk Number 10.
Then, a couple of weeks later, I spoke with Alex, who works at a leading German career
site.
Alex mentioned that he'd recently kicked off a project there to explore applying zero-shop
machine learning.
Once again, an idea he learned about on the podcast.
I'd really like to hear more stories like this.
If the podcast has helped you at work or school, if it's educated or connected to you
to resources or techniques you've found useful or valuable, please take a moment to share
them over at twomelai.com slash 2av, the number 2av.
The occasion, of course, is the podcast's second birthday.
So go ahead, give it this birthday present.
Okay, Nick, hit it.
Hello, and welcome to another episode of Twomel Talk.
The podcast why interview interesting people, doing interesting things in machine learning
and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host, Sam Charrington.
In this episode of our train AI series, I sit down with Anima Anon Kumar, brand professor
at Caltech and principal scientist with Amazon Web Services to discuss the research she's
doing out of her tensor lab.
In our conversation, we review the application of tensor operations to machine learning and
discuss how an example problem, document categorization, might be approached using three-dimensional
tensors to discover topics and relationships between them.
We touch on multi-dimensionality, expectation maximization, and the Amazon products Sage
Maker and Comprehend.
Anima also goes into how to tensorize neural networks and apply our understanding of tensor
algebra to perform better architecture searches.
Before we start, though, a shout out to our friends over at Figure 8 for their sponsorship
of this week's series.
Figure 8 is the essential human and aloop AI platform for data science and machine learning
teams.
The Figure 8 software platform trains, tests, and tunes machine learning models to make
AI work in the real world.
Learn more at www.figure-8.com.
Just a reminder, this episode was recorded on site at Train AI, so there is some unavoidable
background noise.
And now on to the show.
All right, everyone.
I am pleased to be seated here with Anima Anankumar.
Anima is Bren Professor and Microsoft and Sloan Fellow in the Department of Computing
and Mathematical Sciences at Caltech, as well as a principal scientist with Amazon Web
Services.
Anima, welcome to this weekend machine learning and AI.
Thank you, Sam.
It's a pleasure to be here.
Yeah.
It's absolutely a pleasure to finally get an interview going.
It's not been that long since I saw you last, scaled ML, I think.
Stanford.
That's right.
I mean, the scaled ML was a small and an intimate event, but just so many amazing speakers
and the audience was also really cool to interact with.
Absolutely.
Can you tell us a little bit about your background and how you got interested and started down the
path of ML and AI?
Yeah.
I guess you could say, like, even as a child, I was always interested in math, you know,
like to me, like kind of just the aspect of understanding a lot of structure and explaining
the world through math seem magical.
And then through the years, you know, I did engineering and in the beginning of my PhD,
I wanted to ask questions on how we can use mathematical techniques to understand data
better, to process them better, scale that up and run them in real systems.
Of course, my beginning was humble, you know, I was looking at purely the theoretical aspects
I was asking questions and sensor networks.
Now you might call them Internet of Things.
IoT.
Right.
It didn't exist, which dates me.
But the questions were still very relevant today.
How much of learning do you do on the edge, on the devices?
How do you transmit this?
What about bandwidth constraints?
How do you route them?
How do you exploit the correlations of measurements between different sensors?
So these were the questions that I started tackling.
And to me, like solving these math problems was very fascinating.
But I wanted to also get them working on real systems, right?
So because back then, we didn't have the IoT revolution going at, I decided to switch
to settings where I could just purely work with data.
So I suppose we have all the data in one place.
Can we do something interesting and can I try this out in different scenarios?
And that's when I started working on probabilistic graphical models, understanding relationships
between variables, how we can discover those graphical relationships at scale.
And what techniques would allow us to provide guarantees?
Like, when do we successfully discover them?
And understanding really, when we can discover information about hidden variables.
So as you can imagine, every model is wrong, right?
So there's only better models which can approximate the real world.
In some ways, you know, better than others.
But the question is whether having hidden variables will allow us to have a more realistic model.
Because so many times we cannot measure everything about the real world.
So the ones that are hidden from the measurements can be incorporated them into the model
and how do we discover them.
As an example, you know, think about categorizing documents, right?
So there's a whole bunch of news articles.
But suppose there's no human annotation of what the documents are talking about,
then that's a hidden variable.
We don't know those categories for the documents.
So suppose we can incorporate them as hidden variables
and use the text as absurd variables.
Can we now learn about these relationships from data?
Even when the variables are not directly absurd?
Okay, great.
And so your lab at Caltech is called the tensor lab.
And you spend a lot of your time focusing on researching tensors
and tensor implementations of machine learning algorithms and things like that.
Can you maybe walk us through that line of research and what it's all about
and tie it back to this problem that you started with?
Absolutely.
I mean, it's been a very interesting journey.
It's taken me about six years now to see the tensor field mature more, right?
So I do want to add a caveat.
You know, the research on tensor algebra is very different from tensor flow.
You know, there is always this one person in the audience
who will ask me about tensor flow when I give the talk on tensor.
The common point there is the phrase tensor, which means what?
Yeah, so tensor, you know, as a naive definition, right,
is a multi-dimensional array.
So now you don't just have two dimensions.
It's not just rows and columns, you have many more dimensions in your array
that can be thought of a tensor.
But then there is a deeper algebraic meaning that I think many people
who are not in the field may not be aware, right?
So just as we treat the matrix not just as rows or columns,
there's a whole host of linear algebraic techniques.
So matrix really can be thought of as an operator.
You're operating matrix on a field, you know,
you're using that to change your vector, right,
when you multiply a vector.
The transformation of some sort.
Exactly, exactly.
And so tensors could be thought of as a richer class of such transformations.
And so in that sense, the tensor flow term is apt
because you have an input data, which can be thought of as a tensor.
And there's an output that's also a tensor, right?
I mean, if it's just a vector, that's a special case of tensor.
So tensor flow is one that kind of flows through the network
as a series of tensor transformations.
But the shortcoming in most of the current networks
is we are still using linear algebraic computations
in different layers.
Whether it's a fully connected layer
where we are doing a matrix multiplication,
it could be a convolutional layer
where we have these set of filters.
So can we now expand these set of operations to more dimensions?
To give you an example, you know, can we now in a layer
instead of doing just a matrix multiplication?
Can we directly operate on higher dimensional tensors?
If the input to a layer is now a three-dimensional set of activations
from the previous layer, can we now set up a computation
that doesn't just turn into a matrix multiplication?
That directly operates on all the three dimensions.
And so can exploit the information of different dimensions more effectively.
Is it just me or as part of the challenge with this,
the general trouble we have visualizing higher dimensions than three?
Yeah, no, it's interesting that you ask.
Actually, people, you know, this is not new, right?
Like, thinking in high dimensions.
There is a book I discovered a few years ago called Flatland from...
Edwin Abbott.
Yeah, exactly.
Right? So it's been in arts.
It's been in literature, the general theory of relativity
thinks about many dimensions, right?
So to tell the audience about what this book is about,
the part that I found it fascinating is this is set up in a two-dimensional world.
Like every person is a two-dimensional object like a square or a polygon.
And then there's a three-dimensional monster that visits this world, right?
So as the three-dimensional object is moving through the two-dimensional world,
it's rapidly changing shapes.
And so that's very scary to the two-dimensional people.
So I would use this analogy that many people,
when they cannot visualize something,
they feel that's way too abstract or that's confusing.
But then math is much richer than just the three dimensions that we live in.
Or the four-dimension, if you use time, right?
So they can formulate and solve problems in infinite dimensions.
And that form of thinking and that form of algorithms
will help us process all the multimodal data we are obtaining today.
So it's not just visual data, it could be textual data.
There's, again, to other domain knowledge.
So how do we use all this in an integrated approach?
And that's where tensors can have a big impact.
And so maybe give us some concrete examples.
I mean, one of the things that strikes me is that when we're talking about sensor data,
we're talking about sensor data that, and this is perhaps maybe naive,
but we're talking about sensor data that comes from an inherently three-dimensional world.
I guess if you start layering on time and maybe channels and things like that,
it gets more complex.
Is that where the multi-dimensionality comes from?
You know, when we're extracting fundamentally,
we're extracting things from our real world.
It's interesting that you ask, because indeed, one direct way of using tensors
is when the data itself has many dimensions, right?
But another more nuanced way of using it is to model the relationships between data.
So let me go back to the example of document categorization.
So I talked about how do we automatically discover
the categories or topics in documents when there are no labels available, right?
So unsupervised learning problems tend to be really hard,
because we don't have a human label saying, example saying,
where, what are the topics?
So in this scenario, what you can do is intuitively look at frequency of words,
right? This bag of words is the simplest technique that's out there.
So you can just count words.
So let's say the word apple, it appears a lot in the document.
I mean, this by itself is not informative because it could be the fruit
or it could be the company, right?
So now you can say, okay, let me not just count one word,
let me count occurrences, pairwise occurrences of words.
So what if the word apple and orange occurs together, right?
So even in this case, maybe it's likely to be fruit,
but orange is also a company, right?
So now what about three words?
If I count like occurrences of triplets of words,
if it's apple, orange, banana, then likely it's a fruit, right?
But it's humanly impossible to go label every triplets of categories
and say what topics they should belong to, right?
So can there be algorithms that can automatically discover at scale
these higher order relationships?
Right, so if you think about pairwise relationships, they are correlations.
So you can represent that as a matrix.
So you list all the words as rows and columns,
which count the core occurrences that can be represented as a matrix.
But if you have to do that-
So N-Y's relationships correlates to end-dimensional tensors.
Precisely.
And now the question is, what class of operations can you do on them
to discover these hidden variables to discover the topics in documents?
And what I showed in one of my first papers is how we can decompose
a certain tensor, a three-dimensional tensor,
and discover the topics and discover the relationship
between those topics and the words in the documents.
Interesting.
And so prior to this work or prior to a tensor-oriented approach,
we would first go through the step of mapping this all
to linear algebra and matrix operations and things like that.
And it sounds like the argument is that that's inefficient.
Is it an inefficiency or are we missing out on key tools in doing that?
So there is a bit of everything.
So for this specific, as always, the problem is complicated.
For this specific topic of modeling and other latent variable estimation,
there were two sets of approaches.
One is expectation maximization.
So you have the likelihood function.
So you do a sort of local search method and hope
to reach globally optimal solution.
But many times, it gets stuck, especially
for high-dimensional problems.
And it's also slow.
And the other approach, these matrix approaches,
tend to do simple linear dimensionality reduction techniques.
The principle component analysis is the most common one.
So if you try to do a matrix approach or a linear algebra approach
for topic modeling, you would only discover the subspace
of the topic vectors.
So you won't discover the actual modeling.
And also, there is the class of spectral clustering
where if the documents have separated topics,
you could try to do a clustering approach.
But in many cases, they are not.
There are news articles talking both about science and politics and so on.
So there is no separation of documents into distinct categories.
And in those problems, there is really
no other approach other than expectation maximization
that people have used in practice before.
And what we found is in our experiments
that these tensor methods can be scaled up very efficiently
because they can build on current linear algebra techniques
and be parallelized in an embarrassingly parallel way.
And we have that actually now available
with Amazon SageMaker and the Comprehend Service.
So with that, we have benchmarks that we've released
comparing it to open source topic modeling frameworks
that use expectation maximization.
And we see SageMaker and what?
So SageMaker is the machine learning platform to run experiments.
And the comprehend is the natural language processing service.
OK.
So with Comprehend, you can go and directly
access the results of topic modeling with SageMaker.
You can even play around with the algorithm and run benchmarks and so on.
Tell me if this is right.
It strikes me that your work is kind of operating in two dimensions.
Well, now I'm overusing the term dimensions.
But there's this one angle where there are different approaches.
There's expectation maximization.
There's PCA and others.
And your work is not just that, or is it, the tenserization
of expectation maximization.
It's another approach, but it's an approach
that is made possible because you can operate in this tensor domain.
Is that correct?
Or it really is another approach.
It's looking at a different objective.
So if you have a probabilistic model,
the standard approach is maximized likelihood.
But classically, there was another approach which
was to match the moments.
It goes back to spearmen.
In fact, it goes back to even Gauss, if you go.
If you only match the first two moments,
that's when you get a Gaussian distribution
as an approximation to your true distribution.
And what this is doing is now expanding
those two higher order moments and also
to many coordinates, to multivariate distributions.
Because the intuition is now, if you have a mixture of Gaussians,
you can all just do with two second order moments.
You need to go to higher order moments
to try to separate the mixture components.
And that applies to a broad class of models.
Is tenser and tensor operations a tool
that we can kind of naively go back and apply
to these other things like expectation maximization PCA?
And is it a magic wand that we can wave at other results
and make them better or do we need a whole new set of approaches
that are designed with this set of operations in mind?
So I would say there's this whole spectrum of problems.
Some are more low-hanging fruit than the other ones.
So there are indeed some straightforward use of tensors
where you say, like, oh, PCA.
Now I can do PCA in more dimensions.
Let me tenserize it.
On the other hand, there are more sophisticated approaches
where I can ask, can I now look at the problem
in a new light because I can use tensor methods?
Is this really the right approach there?
And so yeah, so there is a whole spectrum.
And the one that I'm recently been exploring a lot more
on has been on tenserizing neural networks,
but in interesting ways, because the question is,
when can we win over simple linear algebraic techniques
over different layers?
Or can we even think of the overall deep layers
as some kind of hierarchical tensor transformation?
Because that's what it really is.
And one of the works that some of the researchers
have looked at, Nadok Cohen as the primary author,
has been precisely to ask that.
Can we look at algebraic techniques, the group theory,
to understand neural networks better?
So walk us through that because I think you presented that
at scale.ml, and one of the examples
you use if I'm remembering this correctly
was looking at a computer vision task
and convolutional neural nets and kind of mapping that
to what that might look like in a tensor world.
Am I remembering that correctly?
A little bit.
I mean, yes, I think so the basic problem there
is we have these convolutional layers,
and then you feed the output of the convolutional layers
to the fully connected layers.
So the output of the convolutional layers
is actually a three-dimensional structure
because there is the spatial dimensions
and then there's the number of channels.
But then when we are feeding them to the fully connected layers,
we are flattening them and just turning it
to a matrix multiplication.
So we are all losing all the three-dimensional information.
And the question we asked was a very simple one.
What if we try to preserve this three-dimensional information
all the way to the end?
And the way to do it is instead of doing matrix multiplication,
turn that into a three-dimensional tensor contraction.
So multiply with weights on each of the dimensions
of the three-dimensional tensor.
And in the last layer, do a tensor regression
and use a low-rank tensor weights as a way
to reduce the number of parameters.
And that's what we found.
We found a huge amount of space savings
compared to the standard neural networks
up to 65% in these fully connected layers.
Space savings in what sense?
In terms of the number of parameters.
So the idea is by exploiting all the dimensionality
information, we can have more compact networks.
OK.
How else are you looking at applying this work?
Yeah.
And so that was one example.
The other set of examples is, as I said,
to investigate the ability of tensors
to capture higher-order correlations better.
And so we looked at time series.
And so here, this can be very challenging
because there can be all kinds of higher-order correlations
that affect forecasting outcomes.
And especially if you want to forecast
way into the future, there can be much more important.
And so what we did was we took RNNs and LSTMs
and used a window of measurements
and looked at tensorizations of them.
And of course, if you naively tensorize that blows up
the number of parameters, because that's a high-order
tensor.
But then you can do efficient tensor
train approximations, a low-rank approximation.
So what that yields is a succinct representation
of higher-order correlations.
And we found a lot of benefit compared
to baseline LSTMs on a range of data sets,
like forecasting, traffic, hour-saheads, forecasting,
weather, hundreds of days into the future.
So there is a much better performance in those settings.
So I can foresee a lot of such cases
where we have a diverse set of measurements.
So in tensors become a natural framework
to encode the input.
But then even during their processing
through all the layers, you kind of treat them
as tensor operations.
So you can exploit the information
in different dimensions more effectively.
Do you see this tensorization as it's applied
to neural networks?
Is this something that is automatable
or is it akin to network architecture
in its level of complexity?
Did you do this via graduate student descent,
or did you want it through some process?
I mean, so I would say as a great starting point,
would be to have a software framework that makes it easy
to define these layers.
So that's where John Kosofi, he
interned with our group last year, and he's been working
with me and also his advisors back in London
on developing tensorly framework.
So the tensorly software, you can think of it as Keras.
It has a front end that makes it very easy
to define these tensor operations.
But you can now connect it to multiple different backends.
TensorFlow, PyTor, TirmixNet, and the baseline NAMPI
as well.
So if you don't want to bother about deep learning,
you can even just do basic NAMPI
and do the operations on CPU.
But the benefit with this is now different researchers
and developers can go try out different architectures,
see what works well in their domain for their data sets.
And so I would say that's a good starting point.
But indeed, the architecture design
would be more complex because we
have a broader set of operations.
But on the other hand, I do think
there's some nice research to be done
in terms of how we can use group theories,
how we can use our understanding of tensor algebra
to do better architecture search.
elaborate on that, what are you thinking there?
I mean, this kind of, you know, has also
been seen in quantum systems and other areas of physics
on asking different forms of tensor representations,
what kind of correlation structures to the end use,
and what would make sense for a particular domain?
And we're just basically touching the surface of this,
so it's not still an algorithm that we can automate.
But I think those kinds of understanding
could help us design better architecture search.
So again, I would say like, you know,
we're talking about architecture search, right?
And that is indeed a hard problem.
I mean, right now, even simple, greedy search
kind of approaches take up a lot of resources.
So if we want to solve it at scale very efficiently,
that's out there.
OK.
But on the other hand, there are some immediate things
we can do to improve the current state of art.
What are the things that you're working on?
Yeah, it's been really a broad set of problems.
I recently, I think I shared it online on slide share
that talks about how to, you know,
bring our thinking of all aspects of AI together, right?
So I see three facets.
There is data, there are algorithms,
and then there's the infrastructure.
And until now, we've been kind of thinking of each separately,
but there's a need to bring them together
to have the best efficiency, the best impact.
To give an example, you know, typically,
we first collect data, feed them into machine learning algorithms.
But in most practical applications,
data is such a crucial aspect.
And what we found in a series of studies
is you can drastically improve data collection, aggregation,
and augment our current data better.
To give an example, we looked at the name-density recognition
task, and the on-to-notes is the biggest public benchmark there.
The one is what's it called?
On-to-notes.
OK.
Yeah.
And so then we ran a simple active learning heuristic
which says, you know, feed the current model
a set of labeled examples.
And after it updates, look for the examples
that have a high uncertainty in the current model.
So this is the basic active learning framework.
And we found that we could reach the state of the art
with just 25% of the dataset.
So there are two aspects to it.
One is that active learning can drastically reduce
our data requirements.
And the other is, most of the time, we are collecting data
that's really relevant.
We don't need huge datasets.
Many times, you can even do deep learning on small data.
And that, to me, presents a lot of promise
because in so many domains, we don't
have the luxury of large datasets.
So how do you map this to this idea of data algorithms
and infrastructure?
Because in this case, what we are doing
is we're planning our data collection
in the loop with our model training.
So we can ask the same in terms of even aggregating data.
You have a whole crowd of workers.
How do you reconcile differences in their answers?
The standard approaches, we do majority voting.
We have a whole bunch of annotators.
We try to clean up the input data very carefully.
Then we feed it to the machine learning model.
But what we show is you can, in fact,
do them both in the loop.
You can try to keep learning about the annotator quality
as you go along to train the machine learning model.
And the machine learning model can help you
come up with better estimates of annotator quality.
And with this, in fact, with the Microsoft Coco data
sets, we took the raw annotations that were available
for this data set.
And we found that the optimal thing to do
was to have just a single annotator per sample.
So if you had a fixed budget of annotations,
you're better off labeling more samples
than to be very careful about labeling every sample
and having a whole lot of annotators
to reduce the noise on a single sample.
Oh, interesting.
Interesting.
Of the three, you haven't mentioned infrastructure.
How does that tie into the loop?
Or how do we tie that more closely into the loop?
Right.
So this ties in with the work I've been doing
at Amazon Web Services.
So naturally, I think the answer will be the cloud
because they're not just saying because I'm
in the cloud division.
I mean, as we scale up these models,
as we have data requirements grow,
the only answer will be to allow for elastic scaling
and put computing at the hands of every individual.
Anybody can go access large amounts of infrastructure.
So that's the basic aspect, like making
GPUs available to everyone is the starting point.
But where I find a lot of interesting challenges
is when we try to build machine learning services
across all levels of the stack.
So there's an expert developer who likes to maybe tweak
with the backend to enterprises that just want
to run application services and not even worry
about any machine learning that's going on underneath.
How do we satisfy the needs of these diverse customers?
And I've been involved in building SageMaker.
That's the machine learning platform
that removes a lot of heavy lifting associated
with DevOps work when it comes to productionizing AI.
So how do we go from prototyping
to a full-scale production machine learning service
very easily?
And the idea is we have built all these algorithms
where there's a backend that automatically scales
to multiple machines and gives high efficiency.
And there's also the model serving aspect that helps you
to manage different models, do A, B testing very easily,
and deploy the models in a very scalable way.
So I think all these aspects, so we are just
beginning to think in an integrated way
and there'll be more of it in the future.
Awesome, awesome.
You were just on a panel here at Train AI.
What was the panel about?
Yeah, so Rob Monroe, the CDO figure eight,
you know, formerly crowd flower,
was earlier in our group in Amazon AI.
So we've interacted a lot.
We've had a lot of discussions about data,
about the state of machine learning,
about his adventures around the world.
He's, I don't know if you know, he's cycle large parts
of India, Africa, like, you know, there is, you know,
so Rob is great.
And so it's very happy to be on a panel when he invited me
that asks about taking somebody from PhD to products, right?
So academia versus industry, and for me,
being in both the world, I felt like, you know,
this was a great fit.
How would you summarize the panel,
like, what were the main insights offered?
Yeah, I think the main one is, like, you know,
the question of like, why PhD, right?
Like, it looks like, oh, there's so much happening
in industry, why PhD?
I think there is a lot of relevance for PhD,
even today, in fact, more than before,
because first of all, there's a whole set of unsolved problems
and industry is looking at only a sliver of them.
And in industry, sometimes things are so fast moving,
you have to kind of get ship products
and you don't have that opportunity for a deeper thinking.
Right? So if you're kind of in a position to say,
I want this adventure.
I want to, like, explore on my own.
I want to ask my own questions, right?
Then PhD is the right fit.
But it's not for everybody.
So it's like, I would never advise somebody to do a PhD
just to get a machine learning job, right?
So that's like the novelism, yeah, exactly.
And so, yeah, they were useful
and very interesting discussions like that.
Fantastic.
Well, Nima, before we wind down any other thoughts
that you'd like to share?
No, I think I really appreciate all the great work
that you're doing.
I think it's very important to publicize all the efforts
that are happening in AI and machine learning.
And more importantly, like, kind of give a realistic view
of the field, right?
So I do think there is a lot of hype in the media on one hand
and at the same time, a lot of fear mongering
and sometimes by big and powerful names that I'm sure of.
So we may name us.
Yeah, but it's very easy to infer.
And I completely disagree.
I think it's a, I would call it an abuse of power
to kind of use their positions to do this kind of a fear
mongering because there's a lot of real world impact
to be had, especially a lot of social impact to be had
through the use of AI.
And we are still very much at the beginning.
There is so much development to be done.
And investing in AI, investing in AI education
should be the priorities of governments and organizations.
So I'm so happy that, you know, you have this podcast
and you're making efforts to provide a balanced view
of the topic.
Great.
Well, thank you so much.
It's great to chat with you.
Thank you.
All right, everyone.
That's our show for today.
For more information on Anima or any of the topics
covered in this episode, head on over to twimlai.com slash
talk slash 142.
Thanks again to figure eight for their sponsorship
of this show.
To follow along with the train AI series,
visit twimlai.com slash train AI 2018.
Finally, show us some love for the podcast second anniversary
and share how it's been helpful to you.
You can do that over at twimlai.com slash 2AV.
Thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.