Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast why interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host, Sam Charrington. Before we dive into today's show, just a few quick
meet up related announcements. First, let me say thanks to everyone who participated
in this weekend's fast AI deep learning course study group. We had a great discussion
about lesson one. If you missed it, the recap will be posted later this week, so be sure
to subscribe to our YouTube channel or follow at Twimble AI on Twitter for updates.
Also, this is your final reminder that the next Twimble online meet up will be tomorrow
Tuesday June 12th at 5pm US Pacific time. Kelvin Ross will be reviewing the paper, cardiologist
level arrhythmia detection with convolutional neural networks, which is worked by researchers
and Andrew Ings lab at Stanford. For more information, visit twimbleai.com slash meetup.
In this episode, I'm joined by Romero Salas, director of AI at LinkedIn. We begin with
a discussion of graphical models and approximate probability inference, and he helps me make
an important connection in the way I think about that topic. We then review some of the applications
of machine learning at LinkedIn and how what Homer calls their holistic approach guides
the evolution of machine learning projects at the company. This leads us into a really
interesting discussion about problem formulation and selecting the right objective function
for a given problem. We then talk through some of the tools LinkedIn has built to scale
their data science efforts, including large scale constrained optimization solvers, online
hyperparameter optimization, and more. This is a really fun conversation that I'm sure
you'll enjoy. Let's go.
All right, everyone. I am on the line with Romero Salas, who is director of artificial intelligence
at LinkedIn. Romero, welcome to this week in machine learning and AI.
Thank you, Sam. How are you? Glad to be here. Really excited to talk a little bit more
about AI with you. I'm really a listener of your show in the past, and I really enjoy
them. So looking forward to this. Awesome. That's great to hear, and I am doing great.
And I'm excited to dig into our conversation, which as a listener, you know that I'll
start by asking you how you got into artificial intelligence. Tell us a little bit about your
background.
OK, yes, so I guess my background as an undergraduate student is on something that is called informatics
or informatics engineering. And this is something a term that is not used here in the States
because I study in Venezuela for my undergrad. And that's kind of like a combination of math,
computer science and stats or operations research. And, you know, looking back 20 years ago,
this is exactly what you need to get into machine learning, right? So I was really interested
in these topics from very long ago. And once I go into graduate school, I try to explore
those more and more, first studying computer vision, which was kind of like my first subject
area in graduate school. And then realizing that, you know, you could do a lot more in
computer vision with the right sort of machine intelligence, right? And that got me more
and more interested in AI. For example, I was looking at things like how do you recover
the 3D structure of an object? And of course, the first thing you do in computer vision is
you're going to the 3D geometry. And, you know, all of these things related to, you know,
epipolar geometry or recovering the camera parameters. But then I try to approach the same
type of problems using machine learning. And it just felt much more natural to me. And
then I can go in in that direction and exploring a little bit more of a, you know, in-depth
machine learning, did a couple of postdocs in the area, one in what I call image analysis
and another one more related to how we scale inference in systems that are so large or
so complicated that you cannot really do exact inference, but you have to go into approximate
inference. So the area is really called approximate inference in graphical models.
So, you know, that area really reinforces more and more, you know, what I really wanted
to do in machine learning, which is to deal with these very large problems, large systems.
And even if you cannot come up with an exact solution to all of these problems, to come
up with a good approximations. So after that, I went to industry and I started working
in the area of healthcare. So, which is a great area. It's a very, very meaningful area,
which really needs, you see a lot of applications of artificial intelligence in this area. I
spent about five or six years in the area of healthcare. And then I moved to Silicon
Valley and right now I am here at LinkedIn. I think I'm very happy and I think I've been
lucky to work on two areas that I consider that are pretty useful in general for the socially
one is healthcare and the other one is my work here at LinkedIn, which is, as you know,
deals with the subject of creating economic opportunity for everyone.
Awesome. Well, I am curious about the work that you mentioned on approximate inference.
Is that model specific?
Yes. So approximate inference in graphical models is this area of machine learning where
you know that if you really want to compute a posterior distribution, what we call, for
a given random variable, given all the information that you know about the system around this
random variable, they say you have a system of 100 random variables and you know a lot
about 99 variables, but you don't, you want to know what those 99 variables tell you
about these one variable, right? How do you compute the distribution over that random
variable, right? So for example, you know, everything about the state of a patient, right,
the result of many tests, how, how you can calculate the probability that this patient
has a particular disease, for example, right? So we know that in complicated systems, depending
on how these variables interact with each other, you can easily go into the field of, you
know, such large computations that you cannot really compute is even if you have a very large
computational resources. And you have to go and explore areas of approximations, right,
of this posterior distribution. So basically approximate probability inference is the field
of trying to come up with the best possible approximations to these very large problems
that you cannot solve because they are either too large or simply because you don't
have the time to wait for, for an answer. So anyway, that's a, that's in general what,
what this area is. And you will surprise how quickly you go into these intractable models.
For example, you have a, you have random variables that can take 10 values and you have a maybe
50 of those, right? The number of possible states that the system could be in is already
quite large. It approximates, I guess, in the number of particles in the, in the universe.
So, wow, this is why you need this type of approximate algorithms and, and they actually
very useful for a lot of the things that we do. Is the common theme between the work you've
done in healthcare and the work you're doing at LinkedIn, this notion of graphical models,
do you, do you use graphical models much at LinkedIn? Thinking in terms of graphical
models is, is, to me, has been a really great way to think in terms of probability, a general
way to think in terms, in terms of probability. And if you're in the field of machine learning,
I think thinking in terms of probability, it's extremely useful. And even though you can
do a lot of things, maybe without thinking directly in terms of probability, this, I
think for most of the things that I have done in the past, the notion of probability,
probability distribution, approximations have played a very important role. So, I think
of graphical models as an excellent way to think in general about probability distributions
and, and useful in, you know, many areas. In the healthcare field, for example, every
time that you need to think about, well, what is the probability that this particular
patient has this disease, given that we know the result of this test and this test and
this other test, you know, it is court where everything we do, right? In the same way, in,
in a large internet company like LinkedIn, understanding what is the probability that
this member is going to really find value in this information that we are providing to
him via the application, right? It's core to a lot of the things we do, right? So, we
want to, at the end of the day, maximize the value that this member gets from interacting
with LinkedIn and encoding this in terms of probabilities, right? Probability that the
member is going to engage with this post or the probability that the member is going to
invite a colleague to join LinkedIn or the probability that this member is going to maybe
disable this notification because this notification wasn't the appropriate one to send, is something
that we consider every day at my work. So, yes, I mean, thinking in terms of probabilities
is, is at the core of everything we do. Graphical models provide a language to speaking in terms
of probability that is very general and this is why, you know, I, I find it really useful
and I, I was lucky to explore this field back when I was in academia and, you know, turns
out that I'm using it every day, basically. It's really interesting. I've done a number
of interviews on topic of graphical models and I've tended to think of them in the context
of either computational graphs or like graph databases, things like that and always think
of them visually. And it wasn't really until you just, until I heard your description
that it really clicked, clicked for me that the, the graph we're really talking about
is an application of baserol and conditional probabilities and that's really what their
relationships are between these nodes and the graph. Is that the right way to think
about this? You, you, you, you, you hit right on target, basically, approximate inference
in graphical models is a way to efficiently apply Bayes rule. That's a, that is what
this reduces to really, right? So, yeah, that's a, for example, algorithms like belief
propagation, right? In a graph, right? It's an exact, exact way to apply Bayes rule, right?
In some cases, you cannot apply the Bayes rule exactly, right? Because the computation
is too large and these, they believe propagation algorithm becomes intractable, right? The exact
one and approximating what belief propagation should do is, is basically core part of these
algorithms for doing approximate inference in, in graphical models. So, yeah, I think
that, that's another way to put it, right? So inference equates in these probabilistic
systems as applying Bayes rule and when you cannot apply Bayes rule, you have to go into
approximations, right? So, so now there is, that is not to say there are a lot of, there
is a large field of machine learning that maybe you don't have to think directly in terms
of probability, right? And for example, you know, I'll argue that even though it is useful,
in many cases, thinking of when you need to use a neural network, let's say to address
a classification task, you may or may not think in terms of probability and will be fine
with it, right? But introducing probability in, in the thinking, in the reasoning about
how machine learning works is, is super useful. And it's a, it's a great tool, right? Even
if you are using, you know, neural networks or, or any of the things that on the surface
don't require you to think in terms of probability directly, right? So, for example, in, in, you
have a neural network trained to predict, let me use the same example in healthcare. The,
you want to predict whether the patient is healthy or not, you can use as input the result
of all the tests that you apply to this patient. And the output is going to be an activation
of this normally referred to as a, as a neuron in the, in the, in the neural network that
tells you whether the patient is sick or is not, right? Based on what he has learned from
the past. And so far, I haven't brought up the term probability. But if you start thinking
about how the activation of the neurons, right, relate to this, how certain the system
is that the patient is sick or not, then you can translate that to, to a more probabilistic
concept and start doing, you know, additional analysis on, let's say, the, how reliable
the neural network is or how, how much it captures the true relationship between the inputs
and outputs, right? So, anyway, that is kind of like my summary of why, you know, thinking
in terms of probabilities is, to me, it's always helpful, even if you are not dealing with
them directly, like in, like in some versions of neural networks.
Yeah, I'm really glad we went down this path. I don't, you know, it seems so, so obvious
in hindsight, but that way of thinking about graphical models is, is going to be helpful
for me, I think. You know, maybe let's jump over to, to LinkedIn and, and what you're
up to at LinkedIn. Can you talk a little bit about why AI at LinkedIn? I mean, some of
that is going to be obvious, but maybe give us a lay of the land of how LinkedIn thinks
about artificial intelligence and machine learning. So, basically, in everything you see
on the LinkedIn app has, to a large extent, some form of machine learning in the background,
right? Let's, let's start from the things that you normally see when you open the LinkedIn
app, let's say the feet, right? The first thing you see normally is, is the LinkedIn
feet, which ranks the conversations or updates or information that, in general, we believe
is the most relevant to you. So, this, the reason why we rank things in, in that way, is
because of the, how you have interacted with the LinkedIn application in the past, right?
So we try to understand what interests you, what is relevant, right? You have a limited
amount of time to invest on, using the LinkedIn app, we want to make sure that that's the
most relevant that we can show you. In the same way, connection recommendations, who,
who would you like to connect to? We try to infer from past activities and your past
connections, you know, who you would be interested to connect with. Follows recommendation, who,
would you like to follow? What topics do you like to follow? How to make messaging interactions
simpler, right? How to, what to notify you off, right? So we know that notifications,
too many notifications could be negative because we don't want to overwhelm anybody by sending
too many notifications all the time, but so we want to really, really choose what is the
best possible use of your time if we were to send you a notification. So machine learning
plays a role there in trying to decide what is, what, what, what notification for all the
notifications that we could send you has the high chance of providing value to you. And
even in other areas that are not directly consumer or member focus, we use artificial intelligence
a lot, for example, preventing some forms of abuse to the site, right? That's another
area that understanding the patterns in the past that we have seen of abuse, let's say,
to the site. I think we can prevent future problems with it, right? So jobs recommendations,
right? So how to connect you with the right job, with the right company requires of understanding,
you know, your skills. How do they, how they relate to certain types of jobs? What is your
job title? So what type of jobs probably makes the most sense for us to recommend to you? And
things like that, in addition to that, maybe your job requires you to know or to learn certain
subject areas. So we can also recommend to you learning courses that you can also find in LinkedIn
that will maximize the chances of you getting that next job, for example. In the same way,
you know, in our search results, when you search for a particular topic or member or product or
company in the app, we use artificial intelligence to show you what are the most likely matches to
what you are intended to identify in the app. So, you know, I could, I could talk about all of
these subjects for hours, right? But it's basically everywhere, yeah. I'm curious a lot of what you've
described sounds common across internet companies and social types of applications, feeds,
recommendations, things like that. I'm curious where LinkedIn's requirements and use cases might
be different from some other companies in ways that are interesting. There are going to be things
that are probably in common with other companies and things that are special to LinkedIn.
One of the main things that we truly care at LinkedIn is that notion of, you know, are we providing
the most possible value, right? The highest possible value to the member by showing the member
a particular recommendation, for example, right? So, we think about this whole
interaction with the application in a holistic way. And I think that's pretty interesting. I
am not too familiar with other industries or companies thinking this holistically, right? So,
and what do I mean by that, right? So, for example, recently, or maybe a couple of years ago,
not so recently, we receive a lot of feedback that maybe LinkedIn was sending too much email,
right, to people, right? And some of this feedback was public and that we have acknowledged this. So,
what, we decided to think about, you know, what we need to do something about this, right? And
why is it that, you know, we're sending so much email? And if you think short term, right?
Well, you know, the more messages you send, the more email you send, in this case, you know,
the higher the chances of engagement, right? So, if you want to maximize engagement, you know,
sure, at least in the short term, send more email, right? And, well, that is a very, you know,
short-sighted strategy, right? So, instead, what if you start thinking about if you want to improve
the overall ecosystem of LinkedIn, right? And at the same time, the overall value that the member
gets from using LinkedIn, then you start thinking much differently, right? And one of the
early projects that we did in this area was, well, you know, engagement, you know, as a proxy for
value is interesting, but we should also take into account negative signals, like, for example,
is a member disabling or marking the email as spam, for example, right? So, so let's speak one
email type and let's try to change the problem from trying to maximize engagement to a constraint
optimization problem, where we think a little bit more holistically and say, well, let's try to
maximize some form of engagement, which is a proxy to value, subject to some constraints on, let's
say, negative feedback, like marking the email as spam. And, you know, that turns out, you know,
that's that relatively simple optimization problem, you know, only one email type to utilities,
one is related to engagement, one is related to negative feedback, had a huge impact on that
particular type of notification or email that we were sending, right? And how do you characterize
that impact? So, the way that we can address that impact is how many, how much negative feedback
are we reducing? And so how much how much of a reduction negative feedback we can we can measure,
right? How many fewer emails we can send at what level of engagement? So, it turns out that
we could reduce the number of emails notification that we send by a pretty large amount. I think
for that initial test that we run, it was at least 40% of email reduction with a equivalent
percentage of negative feedback. And the engagement, the proxy to engagement that we were using
at the time, which were sessions, right? We're almost unchanged, maybe negative 0.5 reduction
in sessions. So, that's that's a great trade off to make, right? So, we we provide a much better
experience at a very similar level of engagement and we actually could measure that there is a
reduction in the negative feedback that we were getting, right? So, thinking holistically,
basically gave us so many more insight into how we can do this across LinkedIn. So, so we didn't
stop here. We said, well, you know, this is this is great. So, it may sound crazy, but what if we do
this across all notifications that we're sending and at the time we were sending the primary
form of notifications that we were sending were emails. So, let's say that we now instead of just
why stop it at one email type, let's let's across all the possible emails that LinkedIn could send
you. What if we apply a similar way of thinking, right? And then you you're running to scalability
problems and having to work with an entire set of, you know, product managers within the company.
And how do you deal with that, right? So, and this experience really gave us a lot of insights
about how we approach future problems, right? But what we did basically was less, less formulate
the problem again as a constraint optimization problem where you are less minimize the amount
of messages that we send. Let's say that we want to really, you know, if we don't have to send any
messages and provide the same amount of value to the members, then why not do that, right? So,
the way that we formulated the problem was, well, less minimize the number of messages that we
send in this case emails, subject to a maximum amount of negative feedback that we're willing to
tolerate. We want, you know, less than 2% of negative feedback or 0.2% of negative feedback.
And let's also make sure that there is certain level of engagement. So, we don't want to reduce the
engagement too much because that's our proxy for for member value, right? So, let's let's play
second strain on on the member value that we believe we are providing, right? And since we have
maybe 20 different products or 30 different products across LinkedIn that are all sending some
form of email or notification, let's make sure that we don't decrease the engagement that we are
directing to those products more than a percentage, right? And then you see how we can we keep
increasing the complexity of the problems and the number of constraints, right? So, this turnout
to be a project that we, you know, decided to do and which enormously reduce the amount of emails
that we sent to our members, all the product partners were positive about the impact that this
was having across the product and basically address this very critical problem that we really,
really wanted to solve, which is provide better member value while at the same time reducing the
amount of notifications that we were sending, right? So, I believe that at the time the reduction
of total messages sent to members was close to 65% or close to 50% overall without decreasing
in negative feedback of 65% and less than 1% reduction in sessions overall, right? But,
you know, we believe this is the right thing to do and we did it, right? This, even though
this came at some cost, which is, you know, 1% reduction in sessions that in a large company that
may be a large cost, but it was a right thing to do and it opened the door to a lot of other
things that a lot of our future thinking about how to approach these problems. This is a really,
really interesting story, a great story and really timely for me, I was just giving a talk
earlier this week and talked about how the metric that you choose to optimize around, you know,
has a huge impact in the way you can approach a machine learning problem, even if it's fundamentally
the same kind of problem, you know, a recommendation problem, you could look at it from the perspective of
revenue or profit or a lifetime customer value and there are all kinds of choices to make there
that have different implications on the ultimate performance of your models, but also the user
experience, the customer experience. So it's really interesting to hear how you've applied this.
Are there other areas outside of this email domain that you've applied this kind of holistic thinking
to? Yeah, so we're now using these to all the types of notifications as well, but I think
one interesting example is also in the area of forming connections, right? So in LinkedIn,
we have this product called BYNK or people you may know and this product is basically powered by
machine learning algorithm that determines for a particular person. What are the connections that
in the past, you know, we also think about what are the connections that are most likely to respond,
yes, I want to connect with you, right? And when you then rethink the problem and think, well,
you know, maybe we should think about the problem in terms of what are the most valuable connections,
right? Or what are the connections that will in the future, you think of value as how much
interaction you will have with these connections, then, you know, you start thinking about different
objective functions and different ways to provide what we think is a better value to the members,
right? So what we started to do was to instead of creating connections after connections,
trying to maximize the number of connections that a person creates, try to maximize the
valuable connections or the connections that are, that the connections that matter, right, or that
we think that matter, right? So, so we reformulate the problem into less maximize the chances that
you're going to really engage with this person, you connect with the person, subject to some constraints
on, you know, I want you to be connected, right? I don't want the members to be all severely
undreconnected because we are too picky about the type of connection we're recommending to
this member, right? So, this had an interesting impact on, well, you know, the new connections
that you're making are actually, you're actually interacting more with them because of the new,
this new recommendation algorithm and it's probably of higher value to you, right? So,
as another example where we were thinking about maybe the more of the ecosystem value, you know,
or long-term value to the member, right? And another example is in the area of, so for example,
on the feet, right, which is a core part of LinkedIn, you know, we want to make sure that everybody
in the feet feels hurt, right? So, you know, when I post something in the feet, I want to make sure
that people, you know, can see what I posted and I get feedback, right? You want to maximize
click to rate, which is a usual metric that you will first think about. You will normally
promote members that are very, very popular and get a lot of clicks, right? So, but you want to
create a really a better sense of community and people, you want people to feel that they're
hurt, right? You want to also take into account that maybe some members that are less active, right,
will deserve the chance to get feedback as well, right? So, we want to maximize overall
engagement, not just the gain of a few members, right, while other members feel that they are not
hurt, right? So, that's another area. And so, what we did is we basically focused on a group of
members that are new sharers or not very common sharers or contributors and decided to make a
trade-off, basically. We want to have this, we want to have most members receiving feedback
as compared to just a few members receiving a lot of feedback. And again, this had a very
positive effect on the members who contributed and they were not necessarily the most popular
members or heavy contributors, but because of the feedback they got, there was a considerable
increase in how much these members contribute again and share another article or share their views
again on the site. And again, this is something that maybe it is obvious once you think about it,
but it is not how usually most companies start when they want to optimize something like the
feed, for example, or connection recommendations. Usually, the tendency is to optimize for the
metric that you can see the most now and hope that that is the metric that in the long term is
going to be the best metric to optimize. And we have realized that that's not the case in many
instances and instead you need to think a little bit more holistically and come up with a better
proxy of what is the metric that is better for the overall good of the member and the
engagement overall in the site. Now, this is not to say that we have solved the problem of what
is the best long-term metric that you should optimize for. I think that's a really difficult
problem and in many cases you get counterintuitive results into I want to optimize
how much daily active users they are in the site in one year. What should I optimize more
in the short term in order to get there? And I think that's a tougher question. That's a tougher
question. Basically, this reflects our idea that you should try to optimize whatever is closer
to the long-term metric you want to see change. As long as you have a way to more or less
approximate that metric with something that you can measure in the short term. If we wanted
to apply this idea, I would like to optimize the feed or LinkedIn overall for a metric that says
how many people in the global workforce are employed and believe that have economic opportunity,
right? But what is the, is that my objective function? What did you get pretty broad?
Yeah, what is the derivative of that with respect to the variables that I can control? That is
a, that is a problem. So that is trying to fill in the intermediate proxy objective functions
that you think will get you to that overall ideal, right, is where there is so much
interesting work and ideas in machine learning that this is such a broad subject. But this is
more or less how we want to think about it. What is the true metric that you really want to go
towards? So now that you have this experience, do you find that teams are starting with more
holistic models from the beginning of a modeling process like for new features or do you find that
it needs to be more of a crawl walk run and, you know, they should still start simple and
evolve and mature over time? Yeah, so I think that definitely I always go for the, you know,
try the simplest thing first, right? And try to understand from the simple approaches first,
right? And, you know, for a new company that needs to grow very fast, right, in order to get
that engagement going, especially say you're starting a new application for which the,
the social aspect is very important, you know, perhaps trying to maximize the number of connections
as much as possible is the best, right? Well, the cake and not the icing or the cherry.
Exactly, right? So now, once you start learning and realizing that, you know, maybe, you know,
our members have a limited amount of time and energy and attention, what is the next best thing
that we could do to provide that value to them? Right? Then you probably start thinking into
more sophisticated way to optimize for that. Also, you know, at the same time, when you are early,
you know, when a company is an early in the early stages, you probably don't have a very
large investment in machine learning, so you need to try simple things first, right? Because
the ROI is this largest, right? At that stage, right? But once you have understood a lot about
the members or people who use your application, it's really, it turns into an ethical question,
you know, what is the best thing that we could do for our members, given that we have this level
of maturity, you know, the standing, how to bring value, right? And this is what we are trying to do,
right? We try to do the best we can, given, given all that we have learned throughout the many years
at LinkedIn. There are certainly implicit, if not explicit, tones to, you know, fairness implications
of some of the things that you describe, like, you know, particularly around the feed and what
goes into the feed and that kind of thing. Yeah, exactly. I think that's something that
we always keep in mind. I think that we always try to think about all of these considerations
in terms of fairness, you know, reducing bias, and I'm members' privacy, of course, right? That
go into all the things we do, but as long as all of those aspects are satisfied,
they're thinking about how to think holistically to provide the best possible value, right?
To the members is something that is now reflected in many of the things we do. So
and I guess he helps that my team is responsible for a lot of the products that I mentioned earlier,
so we really try to make sure that this this way of thinking permeates across the organization
and it starts at that level instead of thinking too narrowly or too greedily in terms of maximizing
one particular metric at the expense of all the things that we may be missing, right? That can
be better for the overall ecosystem, right? So anyway, so that's just wanted to summarize
maybe how how it is that we're thinking about all of these problems at a high level and maybe
provide a few examples like the email example that where we could touch a little bit at the low level.
Yeah, absolutely. I'm curious as your team takes on more of these constrained optimization
types of problems, has it changed or to what degree has it changed? The tools that you use,
the data pipelines, the modeling process, you know, the general approach to rolling these out.
Okay. Yeah, that's a good question because we had to build tools for doing this more efficiently,
right? And some of the tools, for example, that we had to build are this large scale
constrained optimization solvers that can use, can take advantage of some level of distributed
processing, right? And provide a result to the problem very quickly, right? Because a lot of
these problems really, what something that is common about all of these problems is that you're
normally computing a trade off across many different objectives, for example, you know,
a number of negative feedback that you get, a number of sessions that we see, perhaps sessions
to a particular product and so on, right? A number of connections that you make. So what is
common across all of these kind of applications, or examples that I've given, is that you always
end up with how do you set the right trade off across all of these possible objectives?
Right? So in optimization, I think that's what's normally referred as the Pareto curve, right?
What is the right point in the frontier where you want to operate, right? So in two dimensions,
this is just a curve and two variables and, you know, usually an increase in the return that
you're getting one variable implies that you will get a negative impact on the other variable,
right? So, you know, and that's a, you know, that's a very large set of combinations of variables
that you could get, right? In just in two dimensions, what if you have three different
objectives, or we call it utilities, three different utilities that you need to balance,
or four utilities? How do you quickly solve these problems? Now, one thing you could do is that
you could solve these problems offline, right? And wait for your cube quadratic programming,
or linear programming, a solver to give you the solution, and then put the solution into the
system and, you know, a measure just to make sure that things are going the way you expect.
So that's one way to deal with the problem, and we continue to build ways to scale these
constraint optimization problems in our systems. Another way that you could think of of these problems
is let's say I try to do this online, right? And this is an interesting problem that we're working
on these days. Let's say we have three utilities, right? And I want to learn what is the best
combination of those utilities that satisfy my constraints as I serve the traffic so that I
can adjust these things as the traffic is being served, right? So there are working online,
we call it online model selection methods that allow you to, well, you know, a member comes,
we serve this with a particular combination of parameters, and we determine, you know,
how well the response to that combination of parameters was, and then the system automatically
says, you know, well, you know, based on all the information that I have collected in the past about
how how members are interacting given this parameter setting, what is the next best set of
parameter settings that I could try to improve my utilities and still satisfy the constraints,
right? So there are actually ways that we are trying to adjust solve this optimization problem
where you have a few, we call it hyperparameters, right? That determine how much importance
each of the utilities has, right? And, you know, the process of trying to adjust this in real time
as we see more and more data is one of the areas that I think is very exciting and we have seen
quite a few positive results in this direction. Of course, this method may not be able to scale
for a very large dimensions where you need, you probably will need to solve a full offline
constraint optimization problem, but in many practical situations, being able to do this
parameter tuning in the online form seems possible. And I think this is one of the areas where
I think we are we're very excited to see positive results these days. So in this context of an
online system, you mentioned the dynamic model selection, which makes me think of, you know,
not so much updating hyperparameters or parameters in real time, but you have offline developed as
opposed to one single model, multiple models, and you're trying to fit a given user to a model
online and then use that model. But it also, it sounds like you're doing a bit of both. I guess
I'm trying to get some confirmation of my hearing right that there are two different types of
things that work as you're trying to make the system more dynamic. Yeah, I think the two examples
you provided are very related problems. I was and I think one could approach them in a very
similar way. I was referring mostly about the problem of fitting hyperparameters, right?
Okay. Which is basically when you have a linear combination of utilities, you have that
hyperparameter that that is specific is how much of each utility, you know, what is the weight
for each utility, right? And how you should change the that weight to satisfy your constraints and
to at the same time maximize an objective, right? So I just seen those parameters in real time is
what mostly I was referring to. I got it. However, however, that is you are right on target when you
when you relate this with the with the other problem of trying to decide in real time what is
what is the best model variant, right? That you could use instead of having to run different
AB tests separately. You may want to run just one AB test and let the AB test itself out to
tune it, right? Self-tune it. So that you can decide what is the what is the best model variant.
And yeah, those those two problems are very related and we are exploring these directions as well.
Just in terms of the time check, we've had a really interesting conversation so far. There are
other things that you would add in and around this topic of trying to approximate more holistic
metrics in the way we model. No, I think I think that reflects at a high level. I think what
how we're thinking about it. There are there are some papers that I can also share with you offline
into that they're going to more details about these. We have a pretty active group of
scientists, engineers, analysts that publish papers and attend conferences and pre-active in
the research community. And you know, we have the data website at LinkedIn. You can search for
a few blog posts and articles that we normally publish there to go into a lot more detail into
what I just said. You know, we're pre-active overall in the research community. And you know,
something that I found I guess that I think it's also probably interesting to mention here is that
you know, I spent a lot of times many years in academia and I actually did several postdocs and
you know, was very interested in co-research in this area. But you know, working in industry,
you you you never run out of problems. That that that is no answer for and or that the answers
are just not that great when you try them, right? That this creates a constant influx of problems
that you wish you have more time to solve that that that are pretty advanced or research driven
problems that you know, you can publish and make a lot of impact on. So I found the working in
industry as one of the main sources of interesting problems that I can think of
you know, for publishing or for you know, just personal satisfaction of of being able to to
approach the problem for for a greater good, right? So I think that that's that's one message that
I also wanted to share because it took me some time to realize this but once I realized it as well
this is this is so obvious, right? So this is this is such a great place to think of, you know, to
realize what are the really important problems that matter and if you solve them now, it will have
a big impact not only on on on just core research but also on the impact that you can have to
to society in general, right? Right. So I think I find it a great place to to do that and
LinkedIn has a different initiative is also with academia. For example, we run this what we call
the economic graph research program, right? Which is another way for us to share, hey, you know, he
here is here is a data that has been of course properly, you know, to identify and this information
has been properly processed to be shared with a certain group of people, right? And we work together
with professors or people from academia and other parts of outside of LinkedIn to be able to
share, hey, you know, this is the data, this is a problem we have. What are all the problems that you
see that for which you can use this data and actually, you know, to research make a positive impact,
right? So I just wanted to mention that as well as one of the things that I'm pretty excited about.
What LinkedIn does overall and if anybody is interested, I think this is something that you can
check out also in our web pages. Okay, great. Well, we will include links to those sites in our
show notes as well as any papers that you want to send over. But Romeo, thank you so much for
taking this time. It was really a pleasure to chat with you. Thank you very much. It's my pleasure.
Talk to you later, Sam.
All right, everyone, that's our show for today. For more information on the Romeo or any of the topics
covered in this episode, head on over to twimmolai.com slash talk slash 149. For the details of our
upcoming meetup for the fast AI study group we formed, visit twimmolai.com slash meetup.
As always, thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.