Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast why interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
In today's episode, I'm joined by Zach Costello, host doctoral fellow at the Joint Bioenergy
Institute.
Zach joined me to discuss his recent paper, a machine learning approach to predict metabolic
pathway dynamics from time series multiomics data.
In our conversation, we start with an overview of synthetic biology and from there dig into
Zach's particular application, which is the use of ML techniques to optimize metabolic
reactions for engineering biofuels at scale.
We get into an interesting chat about biohacking as well at the end of our interview.
It turns out it's pretty easy for hobbyists to get started in this type of work, which
is pretty wild.
For the interview, remember that the next Twimble online meetup is coming up next Tuesday.
Nick Teague will lead a discussion on the paper Quantum Machine Learning, which explores
creating quantum software for machine learning tasks.
Visit twimlai.com slash meetup for more details or to register.
Enjoy.
Alright everyone, I am on the line with Zach Costello.
Zach is a postdoctoral fellow at the Joint Bioenergy Institute.
Zach, welcome to this week in machine learning and AI.
Hi, happy to be here.
Why don't we get started by having you tell us a little bit about your background and
how it led you to working on machine learning?
Absolutely, yeah.
So I'm a researcher whose goal is to sort of advance the transition of biology into an
engineering discipline.
I spend my time solving challenging problems in synthetic biology where I apply a various
set of skills that I've developed over my education, like machine learning, control theory,
applied mathematics more generally, and robotic automation.
My work is kind of situated in between biological theory and practice so that the techniques
I develop can be validated by either me or my colleagues in the lab.
And whenever I undertake a project, the goal is to sort of advance the idea of creating
a world where organisms can be engineered predictably, rapidly, and at low cost.
In terms of my education, I started out actually as an electrical engineer where I focused
on electromagnetics as an undergraduate.
And then I took a position in between that at the Georgia Tech Research Institute where
I kind of did a little bit of biological application and I started to get into some sort, some
classification problems involving that.
But for me, during my education, one of the guiding principles was to sort of pick the
best teacher over the coolest problem so I could learn as much as possible and as deeply
as possible.
I figure there's like fascinating problems everywhere.
And so, you know, in that vein, I kind of did a little bit of a switch up for my PhD and
was in a swarm robotics lab under my advisor, Magnus Agerstead, who is just an excellent
teacher and the theoretical focus in the lab there was a network control theory.
And my PhD was focused on studying what a certain class of network dynamical systems could
compute.
And the fundamental question here was how do you do computation when you actually don't
have any leaders in charge of it?
So there's no single thing orchestrating it.
And there are certain places computers can't go, but they still have to process information
and react to complex environments.
So in some sense, even then, I had biological applications in mind.
And one particular example I was always thinking about is how cells can coordinate to compute.
And I figured once I finished my doctorate, though I either need to start working in biology
or I'd never really find my way in.
So for my postdoc, I made the transition into synthetic biology and I'm doing my postdoc
now at the Joint Bioenergy Institute in the quantitative metabolic modeling group under
Dr. Hector Garcia Martin, who has been an excellent advocate for the integration of mathematics,
machine learning and automation and synthetic biology where it's still pretty nascent.
And this is where I actually started doing my work formally in machine learning.
I picked up machine learning as the way to speed up the rate at which I could deal with
the complex subject of synthetic biology because I did not have a biological background.
I work with really talented chemical engineers and biochemists and I just won't be able
to compete for probably another few years on raw biological knowledge.
So for me, the machine learning provided a way of handling some of that complexity and
giving me the ability to contribute where I was still developing skills.
So I love that.
I often, you know, in talking to people about machine learning and AI, refer to it as
a superpower that eventually gives folks who wielded a tremendous advantage and your
story is kind of a great example of that.
Tell us a little bit more about synthetic bio and what are the kinds of problems you're
working on there.
Yeah, absolutely.
So the way I think about it is when any science becomes sufficiently mature, it sort of
births a corresponding engineering discipline.
And so in this case, biology has accumulated a lot of different knowledge over the years
and these are sort of in the form of individual properties of different parts of biology.
And synthetic biology is maybe just a rebranding of genetic engineering, but the aim is to make
biological systems predictably engineerable so that you can solve an array of human challenges.
And for me specifically, I work in sort of a sub discipline of that called metabolic engineering.
And in metabolic engineering, we aim to add reactions to metabolisms, to make molecules
that are useful to people.
So some examples of those might be fuels, pharmaceuticals, or biomaterials, say spider
silk or plastics.
And maybe just to sort of, I think there's probably one key analogy that people can kind
of key in on to understand what's going on in the context of the conversation I think
we're likely to have going forward.
And so I think maybe one of your guests mentioned this before, the central dogma of biology
is kind of important here, which is DNA is transcribed into RNA, RNA is translated into
proteins.
In metabolic engineering, proteins are used to catalyze reactions and so we add reactions
to an organism to make new chemicals.
And sort of a good way to think about metabolism as a whole is say a subway system.
So if you imagine the subway system in the Bay area, each station would represent a particular
chemical that's present in the body for an important reason.
And then those are connected through tunnels between these stations.
So if you want to get from say San Francisco to Oakland, there might be a series of stops.
Now the tunnels that connect it are actually the proteins here.
So as we produce protein in the body, what we're actually doing, or produce protein in
a particular organism, what we're actually doing is sort of providing the track to allow
us to go from one metabolite to another.
And in metabolic engineering, it's like a build out.
So we have an organism that already has sort of like a subway station like layout.
And we're finding the closest station where we have to build out to a particular molecule.
And then we find the proteins that will allow us to sort of build out there.
So the idea is that you've got proteins or what allow you to create these metabolites
that create some chemical reaction within the body that's desired.
And you're trying to engineer the protein so that you can goose the creation of these
metabolites.
Is that the idea?
Yeah, in a sense.
So a lot of times we don't necessarily even create the protein.
So what we might do when we're building a particular strain, a J. Bay, we build different
strains of microorganisms by, and we add to their metabolism.
We might look across all domains of life.
So we might borrow from mint, breweries, yeast, evergreen trees.
And inside of all these organisms are tons of different proteins.
And each protein, you can think of it just like a little nano machine.
I mean, that's what they are.
That basically is a factory for turning one chemical into another.
And so we'll scour these things across life and essentially borrow the important machines
that each one has painstakingly developed over the many years of its evolution and put
them into our organism of interest so that they can actually make that thing.
Is that that aspect of a protein, kind of this micro machine idea?
Is that fundamental to what a protein is or kind of a side product of the way they
exist or how they're used in the body?
Oh, that's absolutely fundamental.
So every enzyme does this.
And in fact, there's a great deal of really cool YouTube videos out there that show sort
of how much like machines they actually are.
I think that oftentimes people kind of think of them very abstractly, but they're doing
physical things.
So for example, there are proteins that literally walk along these structures inside of your
cells called actin fibers.
They're essentially the skeleton.
But it's like a highway.
So you've got these little proteins and they've got these two little molecular legs and
they're literally walking along at Dragon Cargo.
I mean, inside the human body, it's just, it's molecular clockwork.
It's incredibly complex.
Wow.
Yeah.
So maybe talk through a specific example.
You're working on specific metabolic pathways in your research.
Is that right?
Yeah, absolutely.
One of the ones that, while we deal with two in the paper, in a recent paper, republished,
and one of them is producing a molecule called Lymanine, which is a candidate fuel molecule.
Lymanine is a major component of citrus fruit oils and is actually used as a fragrance.
If you were to smell it, it has like a lemony scent.
But it also turns out it can be used as a fuel.
You can burn it and make your car go.
And in this case, yeah, so we, like I was saying before, we borrowed several different
proteins.
And I think actually the examples I gave you before were for this particular strain.
For mint and brewers, yeast and evergreen trees, they're about 10 proteins.
We had to add to this organism.
And the goal here is to basically take these organisms once you've genetically modified
them.
And you put them through a similar process that you brew beer with.
So essentially you put them in this broth, which contains the sugars they need to live.
And then you let them grow up.
And in the process of growing, they release their metabolite.
So your Lymanine, you make a lot of that.
If your strain is good, they make as much as possible.
And you'll actually be able to just skim that off the top or find a way of isolating
it pretty easily.
And then you're good.
So a lot of the problems that we deal with in metabolic engineering involve maximizing
the production of a particular biomolecule so that we can extract it and use it.
And so you mentioned a bunch of substances, mint and other things.
Are these needed to be put into, like, in proportion into this concoction, or are you,
is it, you know, you've got your trying, you know, just mint or just something else and
just something else and seeing which ones you can kind of get the most of this Lymanate
from?
Oh, so yeah.
So what we do is we actually never use those organisms.
We look in their genomes and we pull out parts of their genetic code.
And that part of the genetic code codes for the particular nano-machine of interest
inside of those organisms.
So then we take out, you know, we'll take a protein from men to protein from brewers
used to protein from evergreen trees.
And then we will put that in our organism of interest and put that DNA in there and it
will learn how to make though it then from that DNA, it's able to use that as a blueprint
to make the proteins that it needs to actually make Lymanate, which is our compound of interest.
But the challenging part is to make sure you get the proportions of all those proteins
correct.
Yeah.
And in this particular example, the organism of interest is absolutely.
So in this study, we were using E. coli.
E. coli is just one of the standard model organisms in synthetic biology.
The reason we use it is because it has a lot of genetic tools and it's been studied.
So it's easy to use things like CRISPR-Cas9, based systems for integrating things and it's
easy to get DNA out into the organism and it's pretty easy to grow and it grows quickly.
So E. coli is this, you know, it's basically like a macro machine, if you will.
And your process is changing some of its micro machinery to let it do different things.
And you kind of inject these proteins or add these proteins to it to get it to be better
at producing a particular result for you.
Yeah, exactly.
So yeah, we're just adding things to it to help to change its metabolism so it can make
our target compound 100%.
Awesome.
And so how does machine learning and data science fit into all that?
Oh, yeah.
This is, so there's a few challenges actually that people, so when we're trying to actually
put things into these organisms, we have to figure out sort of what proportions we ultimately
want the proteins to be at, right?
We want, and we also want to understand the dynamic behavior of these organisms.
So in order to do that traditionally, it was a very, very complicated process.
You need a domain expert and that domain expert has to write down very complicated differential
equations which describe the dynamic behavior of this system.
And so, you know, we actually went through the process and did that, but it turns out
that it's really hard to do this well enough because oftentimes the information you need
to build that model isn't present in the literature.
So you have to guess.
You have to make a lot of guessing and you create a very structured model.
But we saw an opportunity to, instead of just building these models by hand, find a way
to use machine learning so that we didn't have to make any assumptions about the structure
of the dynamics of these systems.
And okay, so maybe the best way to go here is sort of to a 30,000 foot view of what
we were trying to do in that paper, does that sound reasonable?
Sure.
Okay, cool.
So, once we actually had, so in our case, we were trying to use time series data to actually
figure out what the dynamic behavior of these systems were.
And the problem, I think, can be phrased pretty simply, which is, let's say I give you,
so imagine a ball and a hill.
And the hill can have any kind of shape.
Maybe it's oblong, maybe it's bumpy, maybe it's tall or short.
You don't really know.
But I'm going to give you a set of trajectories for how the ball rolls down the hill, given
different starting points.
So I'm going to put the ball maybe at the top and maybe somewhere down the side of this
hill.
And then I'm going to give you just what it looks like for the ball to roll down the
And essentially what we were trying to do is, given all these time series data sets, can
you actually reconstruct the hill?
Can you tell me what the hill looks like?
And in that way, we can actually figure out how the entire system will behave regardless
of the setup of the proteins in the cell.
So we're actually able to determine production.
We're able to simulate all these cells without actually having a model a priori defined.
So this hill analogy, I think, will be familiar to many or most listeners from kind of conversations
around gradient descent and finding local optima on the hill.
It sounds like you're doing something a little different, which is trying to capture the
hill itself.
Exactly.
Yeah.
So we figure with time series data, what you have is this relationship for how something
moves.
And in our case, when you have the whole of metabolism, it's this very complicated dynamic
process.
And we want to understand.
And when I say dynamic process, all that I mean is that let's say we know something about
what chemicals are present at, what concentrations in the cell at this particular moment, then
I should be able to tell you, at the next moment, what those chemical compositions are
going to look like based on the state of the cell.
And so if we have time series, essentially, we have examples of all those transitions.
And we can back out, essentially, what should happen more generally if we have enough
of those transitions.
And the time series data that you have is what, in particular?
Yeah.
So we had initially a really great data set, which I think by most, compared to most of
the guests here is probably very small.
But this data set contained a total of six different strains.
And each of those strains had a time series set of measurements for both proteins.
So those are the machines.
So we have protein concentrations.
And we have metabolite concentrations.
So these are all sort of the intermediate stations between where, you know, using going
back to the analogy for the subway station, there's sort of the intermediate chemical stations
between where I am in metabolism and where I want to go.
So I've got these two separate concentrations for a set of time points.
And what I'm trying to do is predict what happens to the metabolites at the very next time
point.
Okay.
And the, maybe going back to the analogy of the hill, the hill then represents, is it
your ability to predict forward at any point in time or is it, is it something else?
No, you're exactly right.
So if you know the hill, right, you can put the ball down anywhere and you can tell me
what happens next.
And the same way, if you know how a strain starts out its life, I can tell you how it's
going to evolve.
And ultimately, how much limony that will end up producing over time.
And we can also look to see if there's any problems.
As these metabolites change, they can signal toxicity issues or other problems that want
to address in the metabolic engineering process.
So it gives us a lot of information if we can sort of do these experiments in silico.
Maybe it's also worth making some points about how there are challenges in synthetic biology
with machine learning and sort of what are some unique things that we face.
Before we do that, maybe talk a little bit about the kind of the method, right?
So you've got this time series data that you captured you're trying to ultimately characterize
the complex behavior of the system with that time series data.
How did you get from the data to the characterization?
What was your overall process?
Yeah.
Okay.
So you have this data, like I said before.
And from these time series, essentially what we do is we smooth it out because we actually
have not that many time points.
And then we calculate the time derivatives for each of the metabolites on this path.
And so that gives us this relationship between the metabolites at a given time to the metabolites
at the next instant in time.
So in other words, how does the internal chemical state of the cell change at each unit in
that particular time series?
And once or these are, do you think of these metabolites, these are like partial derivatives
of this equation that you're ultimately trying to figure out?
Yeah, just time derivatives, yeah.
So we have time derivatives of these, we have time derivatives of these metabolic paths
through time.
And then each metabolite state derivative pair, including, and also their proteins are
included in the features for each of these at each time point represents one example that
will feed to our model.
And so essentially from the three or six time series, we're able to expand that out.
And since if we've sampled enough along that curve, then we can actually augment the
data set and produce on the order of say maybe a hundred examples for each one of those,
each one of those complete time series curves.
So it's still relatively small in terms of the total amount of data we have to work
with.
Okay.
So you've got your input features are basically these time series derivatives.
And then you're using these to predict the overall system characteristics.
What kind of models did you, are you applying to this?
Yeah, so because we have sort of limited data, we use more traditional machine learning
approaches.
And for us, that meant, you know, random forest, so ensemble tree-based approaches.
We actually used one of the freely available meta learners, this package called T-POT,
which allowed us to sort of search for the best models that would help us find the relationship
between the metabolism state and the metabolism derivative at each time point.
And yeah, so once we get, once we extract one of those models, then we use that to do
downstream processing.
The downstream processing in this case is what?
Okay.
So as soon as we have that relationship, the model itself, you can think of that as the
hill from before.
So we have, so that model tells us in the context of the hill, if we find a good model,
we feed it a bunch of time series and then we get a model.
That model represents our hill.
So at any time point, or at any point we put the ball down on, we will know exactly where
it moves at the next point.
And what we want to actually extract from these models are entirely new time series.
So what we do is we take that model and we integrate it over time and allow us to get
trajectories.
So we can put the ball down at the top of the hill and then essentially use a numerical
integration technique to let us understand the trajectory of that ball as it rolls down
the hill.
And how does that ultimately tie in to allowing you to kind of manufacture these compounds
more efficiently?
Yeah.
So once we have a model that tells us how the organism state evolves over time, then
what this does is addresses one of the key challenges that we have in synthetic biology,
which is every time you want to make any data, the reason why our data sets are so small
is that we can actually make lots of features, so that's not too bad.
Every time we build a particular strain that makes a particular molecule, it can take
maybe two, three, six months to get that strain to work, depending on what we're trying
to do.
And once we have that strain working, we can actually extract many, many features from
it.
But using this model, what we're actually able to do is take relatively few strains, which
again are very time-consuming and difficult to make, often very expensive as well.
And then use that to build an in silico model, where we can then do a bunch of experiments
where we vary a lot of parameters to try to find the best strain to make next.
And so oftentimes what we're doing is just trying to minimize the amount of things we
actually have to build because it is so expensive.
When you're trying to vary the proportions of these strains and kind of come up with a
next set of things to test, have you applied a machine learning to that particular part
of the problem, or is that more traditional simulation and things like that?
Well, traditionally, actually, this is something that we're working on now.
We have a paper in preparation to kind of handle this issue, absolutely.
So oftentimes what's traditionally done is that biologists who make the strains themselves
will basically, they'll make their strains and they'll test them out, and then they'll
use intuition or knowledge from the literature to make those decisions.
But once you have a lot of variables, you have a lot of, let's say, a lot of proteins
that you need to change at once, their intuition often breaks down.
And so absolutely, we're applying various kinds of methods to making predictions on how
to change the strain next.
And that's sort of an extension to this method that we describe in the paper.
If we use a Bayesian optimization-like approaches to handle that, along with some Monte Carlo
sampling type approaches.
So yeah, that work is forthcoming, and hopefully soon we'll be out in the world, so.
Cool.
How does the Monte Carlo sampling apply here?
Oh, I'm not sure I can give this stuff away just yet, but I'd be happy with it.
It's pre-pub.
Yeah, it's pre-pub.
Got it.
So yeah, I'd love to share, I really would, but as soon as it's out, I'll definitely share
with everybody.
Sure enough, fair enough.
You know, this conversation is interesting.
It reminds me of an interview that I did recently that hasn't been posted yet with our researcher
named Nathan Kuts out of the University of Washington, who is trying to also apply control
systems theory and time series data in his case to the problem of tuning lasers and also
building models that describe neurological pathways and simple organisms.
And the thing that he did that is kind of potentially interesting to you, like he's
also trying to find the shape of the hill, right?
Like in your case, you know, these things are traditionally models with explicit equations
and differentiated and all that kind of stuff, and so he created this model that is the
model is a linear combination of all different kinds of features that you might expect to
be in one of the physics equations.
You know, so exponentials and squares and qubits and all these, all these like higher order
types of factors and then use some relatively simple, you know, linear regression types
of techniques to fit a model to the time series data and ultimately use that to determine
like the empirical equations that govern these relationships for the problems that he's
trying to solve, which sounds kind of interesting, you know, I said that mostly to kind of
challenge myself to explain what he described to me, but also because it sounds like an
interesting kind of parallel approach to solving this ultimate problem that you're trying
to solve.
Yeah, I mean, I think it's one of these things where you take down deep enough in enough
fields and there's fundamentally shared challenges.
And I think definitely one of the big ones right now, one of the things I see cropping
up in different fields is this issue of how do you understand dynamic behavior just from
data and anybody who's doing that in a different context is certainly really interesting to
me.
You've got this, these systems, like can you talk at all about what the impact of this
work has been or what kind of results you've seen or like, how is this fundamentally
changed this work for you?
Yeah, so we're moving forward now from the paper and we're trying to basically go from
the smaller data sets that have been collected and motivate bigger data collections so that
we can see what happens once we actually get into the realm where we can start using
more sophisticated models.
And so I mean, so far it's relatively new so there's, we've gotten a lot of interest
from other researchers and trying to use this for other applications.
People have been interested in the microbiome, that's one of the big things that people
are interested in right now, figuring out how this interplay between all these different
microbes actually plays out because right now there's a real challenge with predactivity
in that arena.
So I think the impact going forward is likely to be providing predactivity where before
a lack of experimental knowledge or a lack of scientific knowledge would have limited
us for making good models.
And ultimately, I want to live in a world where more data in some sense equals greater
predactivity and more knowledge.
But right now, those things aren't actually all that coupled.
Are you personally involved in some of these applications to adjacent areas or is this
just things that you're seeing in the community kind of grow out of some of your work?
Those things will just be starting for us.
So we're definitely reaching out and looking for collaborations.
That's definitely a big thing that, you know, is, is for us.
And yeah, I mean, definitely, we're, and you know, there's, there's other things
ongoing recently we've, we've acquired a new robot here at, at a J Bay in order to actually
start producing the kind of data we really want in order to rigorously evaluate this
for bigger data sets and see if we can really learn substantial things that will let us
solve the major challenges of metabolic engineering and do this effectively, effectively
increase the titers without so much failure in our guessing, yeah.
But one of the questions that I did have was you mentioned that the kind of cycle time
of setting up an experiment or, or creating one of these organisms is, you know, on the
order of months to the, to six months to kind of get it right.
What all happens in that two to six months?
Oh, yeah.
So this is, this is the, the messy and interesting world of the lab.
So, you know, if, if we, we start out with essentially an idea, which is, all right, here's
the pro, we're trying to make substance acts.
Let's go back to, you know, Lymanine say, maybe even we could, we could do a different,
let's say, Pynine.
Pynine can, is, is a substance you can find in, in pine nuts and it also, you can use it
as a jet fuel, it turns out.
And so, you know, the reaches, researchers, researchers say they want to create, create
Pynine using one of their strains.
And so first they go into the literature and they look for all the, the proteins they're
going to need to put into the organism.
And so first you need to get those synthesized.
You have to go send those off to a company who makes that DNA.
They go ahead and they, they make all that DNA, they send it to us.
And then, then the next step is the researchers have to test out each one of those proteins
to make sure they work because we're taking it from some other organism and putting it into
a new context.
It's like, if you went to some, you know, semiconductor factory and you used a machine that was
kind of similar to what you needed and say like a textile factory, you have to bring
it back and make sure it's still working in that context.
And so they go through the process of validating all these different enzymes, making sure they
work.
And then you have to put them all together into a single piece of DNA and put them in.
And depending on the organism, this can be a time-consuming process.
So first you have to put it all together and that can take, you know, a few days to
a week to do that.
If it works, if it doesn't, you have to go through a set of troubleshooting steps.
And then, you know, let's say you actually get it all assembled and you put it in, you
know, maybe it does certain parts of it don't express well enough.
Maybe, you know, there's a lot of issues that can go wrong.
So that can take a period of time as well.
And then once you get past that point of putting it all in, you have a strain and then you
can test that strain.
So all of these things, you know, there's like for almost all those steps, there's like,
you know, weeks to months, depending on how much difficulty you encounter.
And then you put it all together and you hope it does what you want it to do.
So.
And I've got to imagine that in the kind of scenarios you're describing, the data that
you're collecting can be fairly noisy, fairly messy, which I think would compound or be
compounded by the fact that you're not collecting a ton of it.
Are there things that you've had to do in your pipelines or modeling processes that you've
had to do specifically because of those issues?
Yeah.
We're definitely very aware of it.
There's a limited amount we can actually do about it right now.
I mean, really it's going towards future challenges.
Usually all these experiments, kind of the field standard, which, you know, may have to
change is you do everything in triplicate.
So if you do an experiment, you do three copies of the same experiment.
And then you can use that triplicate data to sort of narrow down where you expect it
actually to show up.
And so you can get, you know, tighter bounds on the error for each one of your measurements.
But oftentimes even after you do that, even after you take into account, you know, all of
the variation, you still can have really substantial variation in your data.
And part of that is just because it's a messy process, you know, you have human beings doing
the sampling and human beings have to be, you know, their lives are taken into account.
So for example, the data set we're working with was collected by two postdocs.
Over 72 hours.
They literally were sitting beside the fermenter and every two to four hours.
They had to go collect their samples, prep them and deal with them.
And so like, you know, they took turns like sleeping so that they could do this.
And that's part of the reason why we don't have a lot of data sets like that.
Not to mention, you know, it's lack of sleep and then maybe you miss it by 20 minutes
on the measurement.
You know, if you've got a time, a variation in your time measurement by plus or minus
20 minutes, you know, that, that of course can introduce error.
And there's just little things like that.
So, you know, one of the things we're hoping is that as we move towards more robotic solutions,
we can sort of key in on all the components of the error and tighten it up much more.
And there's definitely, you know, there's definitely industrial players in the field who
are, who are doing this kind of thing as well.
Awesome.
Any advice or pointers for folks that are interested in this area and want to learn
more about what's happening in it?
Oh, yeah.
So pretty much now it's become very accessible.
If you're interested in biotechnology, there are a lot, at least in San Francisco, there
are a lot of sort of places where you can learn this, these sort of biohacker spaces.
So if you're interested, it's out there.
You can go and visit one of these things, look up your local biohacker space and you can
go out and figure out, you know, what's going on.
You can, you can do CRISPR, you know, it's, it's at the end of the day, it's very much
like cooking.
And if you know how to follow a recipe, you can learn how to do synthetic biology.
So then, I had no idea that CRISPR was that accessible, like what is, what's an example
of something that someone could do, you know, with CRISPR, just accessing a machine at
one of these biohacker spaces?
Yeah.
So CRISPR, you know, just like all the things we were talking about today, it's a protein.
And so it's defined by a piece of genetic code.
And so all you need to do is make these genetic constructs and you can use it.
In our case, you know, typically in biohacker spaces, you're not going to be dealing with
human cells.
That's a little bit more challenging.
There's issues with biosafety and things like that and getting approval.
So that'll be a little harder.
But if you want to work with plants or you want to work with, you want to work with microorganisms,
that's totally doable.
And so really at the end of the day, all you have is essentially a construct, just a piece
of DNA that you put into your cells and it will express CRISPR, which is, you know, these
genetic scissors that will allow you to essentially make cuts in the genome where you want that
are targeted by these guides.
And yeah, it's actually very accessible, you know, it's really at the end of the day,
you're transferring liquids from one thing to another and then if you do this in the right
order and you design your experiment right, you get, you know, the genetic modifications
you want and you can verify them in the lab pretty easily.
What would be in the book of 10 weekend projects to do at a biohacker space?
Oh, so this is actually, when I was first getting into it, I had very little syn bio experience.
So I visited some of these.
I think I guess shout out to bio curious, which is one of the ones in the day that was very
accessible, very friendly people.
At first, like the first thing you do in biology typically is you make things glow.
It turns out.
And you probably don't need CRISPR for this, but this might be one of the first things
you do is you sort of put these, you put in a piece of DNA that expresses a glowing protein
on this thing called GFP that comes from jellyfish and then you put these things under a light
and you can see them glow.
And so that, that way you can see the work you want done.
But in terms of like the cool projects they were doing, I'm not really up to date on what
everybody's doing now, but at the time they were working on making animal-free milk products
and things like that or animal-free cheese, I think, vegan cheese and by expressing a protein
called casin.
And I'm not sure which genetic tools they were using, but almost certainly you can find
a way to use, like if you want to get some experience with CRISPR, you can do it at one
of those places.
Wow.
Yeah.
It's really accessible.
High school kids are doing it these days.
Yeah.
Well, Zach, thanks so much for taking the time to chat with me.
I learned a ton and I appreciate your explanations and analogies.
Oh, yeah.
Absolutely.
Any time.
It's been a pleasure.
Thank you.
All right, everyone, that's our show for today.
For more information on Zach or any of the topics covered in today's show, head on over
to twomolei.com slash talk slash 163.
Please don't forget to head over to twomolei.com slash nominate to cast your vote for us in the
People's Choice Podcast Awards.
And of course, as always, thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.