Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast why interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
I'd like to start today's show with a huge shout out for everyone who's taken the time
to vote for us in the People's Choice Podcast Awards.
It's been awesome to hear from those of you who have loved words of encouragement and
we certainly appreciate all the love.
If you're a fan of the pod and you've already voted, we'd also like to encourage you to
head over to your Apple or Google podcast app or wherever you listen to podcasts and
leave us a five star rating or review.
They are super helpful as we push to grow this show and community.
In this episode, I'm joined by Prashant Warrior, CEO and co-founder of cure.ai, a company
building AI-powered software for radiology.
In our conversation, Prashant and I discussed the company's work building products for
interpreting head CT scans and chest X-rays.
Prashant shares with us some great insights into some of the things he and his team have
learned in bringing a commercial product to market in this space, including the gap between
academic research papers and commercially viable software, the challenge of data acquisition
and how to best capitalize on what data you do have access to and much more.
We also touch on the application of transfer learning in this space and the algorithms
and annotation pipelines, Cure has developed to support 3D scans.
Let's get to it.
All right, everyone.
I am on the line with Prashant Warrior.
Prashant is the CEO of cure.ai.
Prashant, welcome to this week in machine learning and AI.
Great to be here, Sam.
Thank you so much for inviting me.
Absolutely.
Let's get started by having you tell the audience a little bit about your background
and how you got involved in working in ML and AI.
Great.
I have been working in the applied math space for a long time.
My undergraduate degree was in operations research.
I got a PhD in operations research and then started working on it.
At that time, this was not part of data science.
There was no field like data science when I did my PhD.
But after my PhD, which was in our research, where we were basically optimizing
truck routes, so figuring out how shipments should be routed from origin to destination,
how we should assign drivers to trucks, and then again, there are lots of rules around
how many hours a driver can drive and the duty time that it has.
So I mean incorporating all those rules to figure out how drivers should be allocated
to trucks.
I mean, assigned to trucks.
So those are the kinds of problems that I was solving during my PhD, which were primarily
integer programming problems.
So I did a lot of work around optimization then.
And then immediately after that, I started working on price optimization and McDonald optimization
demand forecasting for, I started working for SAP.
And so there, I mean, we were working on these problems in the retail space, retail and
fashion retail space.
So this, I mean demand forecasting, some of these problems are very much, I mean, they
are basically your dependent variable as a sales.
And then you have a bunch of independent variables, which are, I mean, which again depend
upon the kind of product that you're selling.
I mean, so a fashion product will have very different independent variables than if you
look at, for example, products which are retail, I mean, typical retail products like a can
of milk, for example, or fruits or vegetables, right?
So we were sort of worked on that for a while.
And then I mean, I was in the US at that time, came back to India and then I was, I set
up a company, which is called Imagna, which was basically using machine learning to understand
customer behavior from cookie data.
So we were basically dropping cookies at, on multiple e-commerce websites and getting
a lot of detailed information about how customers are behaving on those websites.
So you can actually see how they buy clothing, for example, what products they looked at,
what kind of sizes they looked at, what colors they looked at, what styles they looked
at, and all of that, or for example, I mean, integrating, for example, what, what travel
sites they went into, I mean, how they, where they're traveling to, what travel locations
they've looked at, or what kind of movie shows they're watching.
So we had a very consolidated set of data from cookies, which we were then utilized to do
real-time bidding on ads, on basically online ads.
And we had a built a real-time bidding platform.
And that was then, I mean, so that was again, I mean, yeah, even I was, I was heading
that company.
So I was also, I mean, playing more of a commercial role in that.
And then that got acquired by the organization that I currently work for called Tractil Analytics.
I acquired my previous company.
And then I joined Fractil Active Data Scientist.
And in that role, again, I mean, Active Data Scientist, I was working on some problems.
And then we sort of identified there is a large gap in the radiology space where we felt
that deep learning could make a substantial impact by automating interpretation of images.
So that's how I sort of transitioned from the Active Data Scientist role at Fractil
into becoming the CEO of QR.AI.
And I've been working on building this over the last two and a half years.
And so that's, that's, that's my story.
And Cure is currently in the process of rolling out a kind of a packet solution focused on
chest radiology, is that right?
So we have exactly, I mean, so one of our solutions is in chest radiology, which basically
can automatically interpret chest X-rays.
And a second solution is on head CD scans.
So which is basically automatically interpreting head CD scans, those are the two main solutions
we have built.
I mean, there are some more solutions that we've built over the last several years.
But we, I mean, from a commercial perspective, we focus on these two.
And so there's been over the past few years, there've been a ton of work.
You know, in a lot of ways, it feels like a kind of gold rush in the medical field.
When you look at the research journals, it's, hey, we've got this new tool, CNN, let's
apply it to radiological image type A, type B, type C. There's a, you know, a series of
these types of papers.
I'm curious what you've learned about the gap between what you might read in a paper
and actually bringing a product to market.
So that's a, that's a very good question, Sam.
I think I think I have a very strong point of view on that.
I figured you might.
So I mean, there are lots of papers.
I mean, because CNN's, I mean, can read images really well, right?
And so people tell that, okay, I'll just take a CNN and apply it to this medical data
that I have and I'll get good results.
And they do get good results because they're overfitting on the data.
So you have 2000 images.
Let's say you have got 2000 X-rays to train your algorithm on and you sort of label them.
You label each of those images as normal.
Let's say these are X-rays, right?
You label them as normal or abnormal.
And you order on that and you will get some, I mean, you basically put some as validation
testing and so on.
And you get good results, but what happens is that especially with X-rays, right?
There is a huge variety of data.
I mean, if you go from a Philips machine to a GE machine or you go from one set into
another, one center to another, I mean, there are different settings, different in machines.
There is a wide variation and what, what happens typically is you take a data set, you train
on the data set, you validate, you test, I mean, you do all the right things.
But when you take that algorithm and you try to generalize to a new data set, it does
not work well at all.
And we saw this initially.
And when we started working out, working on this problem, on the chest X-ray problem,
we had around 25,000 scans, 25,000 X-rays along with their reports.
So we did what we did is we took the reports, we ran NLP on those reports, some rule-based
NLP, not machine learning base, but rule-based natural language processing, which basically
extracted out the abnormality from the report.
So if, for example, one of the abnormalities is called floral effusion, where it's fluid
in the lungs.
We said we will extract out a bunch of abnormalities, so we trained the algorithms to do that,
to train these NLP algorithms.
So now they've got an X-ray and the corresponding abnormality, the chest X-ray and the corresponding
abnormality.
And we trained our models on that.
And then what we saw is that when we had a new data set, that was trained on 25,000
images.
And when we got a new data set, it did not translate at all, we were getting around
90% accuracy on the first data set, on the second data set that we got from another hospital,
we were somewhere in the 60s, I think.
And so it was, I mean, substantially lower.
And then we figured that I think, I mean, there is a lot of variation in the data, and then
that's also, that's one challenge.
And of course, I mean, over the last 20,500 years, we have increased our X-ray database
from that to 25,000 number to around 1.5 plus million.
So today, we have a huge amount of data, so it sort of has learned a wide variety of data
patterns that it sees, I mean, acquisition data, acquisition patterns, because X-ray acquisition
can occur, I mean, in many different ways.
And so it has learned a lot of these acquisition patterns, learned about a lot of different machines
that are generating those X-rays.
So that makes it a little bit more generalizable.
I mean, I think the more amount of data that you have, it becomes more generalized.
You mentioned using NLP to pull information out of reports or records.
Is this kind of data mining, the electronic medical records to produce labels for your
data set?
Or was there something else happening?
It's not electronic medical records.
So it's basically, I mean, for, I mean, you could think of it as a medical record, but
basically for every radiology image, you will have a radiology report.
It's part of radiology information systems.
So you can, so you are basically just putting that radiology report.
You're not pulling any more medical records.
So ideally, I mean, a patient will have a lot more.
I mean, they will have the history of why they came to the hospital, why they took strain
the first place.
And then maybe there is some microbiological test, which gets done afterwards, where they
are diagnosed with some disease, right?
A radiology report may not contain all of that.
It will basically tell you that I found these patterns on the X-ray.
For example, it might say that I found a fluid effusion, which is basically some fluid
in the lungs, or that could be due to tuberculosis or other disease.
But a radiologist will not report on that.
They will report on what they see in the X-ray.
So it's more visible, visible features.
Okay.
These radiology reports, are they coded or are they, is it just kind of natural text notes
from the radiologists?
They are natural text.
I mean, sometimes, I mean, again, every hospital will have their own format template for reporting.
There are some standard plates recommended by the radiology society of North America.
But again, I mean, I think a lot of people don't use those templates, I mean, but so to
answer your question, I mean, they are very varied, but they have some structure to it.
These questions may be inspired by an image that you have on the Cure website.
You're basically looking at a brain scan on the monitor.
I'm wondering if setting aside machine learning and AI, are we getting to a point where radiologists
are looking at these images digitally and creating bounding boxes and electronically
notating these images in a way that will make it easier for future ML and AI applications
or is it still all manual today?
I mean, absolutely.
I think what we are seeing is that definitely there is, I mean, a lot of work going into
words, creating annotated data sets.
And so a lot of hospitals are working on that.
I mean, I think a lot of the hospitals in the US, I mean, for example, a mass general
hospital, they have their own data science teams.
And those teams are also working on similar problems.
So there is definitely a lot of effort going towards creating these annotated data sets.
So I would not say that, I mean, a lot of radiologists are working on it.
I think focused groups in different parts of the world are working on these kinds of annotations.
And it's not something which is completely standardized yet.
Right.
But it sounds like you're also saying that it's not, you know, we're not necessarily seeing
the radiologists tool change to be more like a data annotation exercise.
It's happening separately and it's some data science team that may be, you know, doing
some of our things to what you were doing.
Exactly.
Because I mean, I'll tell you why.
Right.
So for example, one of the things we had to do was to when we were trying to detect bleeds
from, I mean, bleeds from head CT scans, they had to actually go in or not as, but I
mean, trained specialists had to go in and mark out the bleed on those scans.
And that's a time-taking process because the CT scan of the head will somewhere between
50 to 100 slices.
And for each slice, there'll be either there's some, some of those slices, obviously, will
not have a bleed.
Or maybe all of them don't have a bleed, but some, you have a bleed, you have to actually
mark the boundary of the bleed, which is not a continuous boundary.
I mean, it's sort of a ragged boundary and then you have to mark through, mark all of
that.
That's time-consuming for radiologists.
And so it will not be easy for somebody to sort of incorporate that into the radiology
workflow because they want to see a scan, they want to report on it in a few minutes and
then be done with that.
And marking out the boundaries will take them maybe 20, 30 minutes.
So I don't think some of these are easily incorporated into the workflow, which is why we sort
of started doing this national language processing because we said there is a lot of data already
available in the report because I am saying that, I mean, the radiologist is already writing
that there is this plural effusion in this part of the lung.
So we can extract out all that information from those reports and use that for training.
So rather than getting them to sort of manually mark out these abnormalities.
So you also mentioned these different acquisition patterns.
These are related to the different types of radiology machines.
These are radiology machines.
The amount of exposure, I mean, amount of radiation that you produce.
I mean, so there are, I mean, everybody will have a different setting.
I mean, so these machines also have some settings.
And so there are many different settings and so the, especially for X-rays, I mean, especially
for X-rays, the data from each center is sort of slightly different.
I mean, there is not exactly the same.
Okay.
It's interesting.
I think, you know, there's a tendency to think about the, you know, CNNs or ML and AI
in general as these, you know, maybe give them, give them more credit for being naturally
generalized than they are.
My daughter is doing an internship with the podcast currently where she's taking podcasts
that we've already recorded and running them through automated transcription and looking
at a bunch of different services and kind of rating their performance and, you know,
over time, we've learned that some of the services do better with, you know, phone calls,
some of them do better with podcasts, some of them do better with audio that's recorded
in a room like the, the characteristics, the, you know, very subtle characteristics of
the input data have a, a huge impact on the algorithm's ability to perform all and extract
texts from them, much more so than you might think.
And it sounds like you've, you've had very similar experiences on the, on the input side
with these radiological images.
So I have a very interesting story in this, I mean, so that's, when we started working
on X-rays, this probably around two years back, so we, we were sort of still tying up
with hospitals, we did not have any, any hospital data, any, any real data coming from our
collaborators.
So we were, we said, we will mine the internet for data.
So we looked at some internet sources, we collected some 10,000 images and we said, let's,
let's try to train a model on this and train the model on that and that was very accurate.
I mean, it was super accurate in determining normal from abnormal.
So it was classifying normal versus abnormal.
And then we said, I mean, I mean, this is a very small amount of data, right?
I mean, typically if you're looking at images, you'll look at millions, millions of images
to train algorithms.
Let me say it.
Let's, let's see.
I mean, so we look, we create an attribution algorithm.
So we were attributing the figuring out which, I mean, if you attribute what exactly the
algorithm is learning, you can find out boxes.
So we can basically, for example, there is a something called occlusion, occlusion based,
occlusion based attribution where you can black out one box, one small box within the
whole image and then see what is the attribution of that to the prediction.
So if you, if you black out a box because of which the algorithm is saying that that particular
x-rays abnormal, then suddenly it becomes normal, the prediction changes from normal to abnormal.
And you look at how each box is impacting the probability of being normal or abnormal.
So the boxes which have the highest impact will have the highest difference between the
normal versus abnormal probability when they are blacked out.
So we created these attribution methods and we were trying to attribute the algorithm,
what the algorithm was learning.
And we found that the algorithm actually was learning to distinguish something very simple
because what was there, these were internet images.
So typically, all the abnormal images had a lot of text on them.
So some typing or some written text and the normal images did not have any annotation,
any kind of text or anything like that.
So it was basically any to recognize typewritten letters.
I mean, that's what it's pointing to.
So if it sees typewritten letters, it will assume that it's abnormal.
If it doesn't see typewritten letters, it's normal.
So that is what it was learning.
And so these algorithms are very, very good.
I mean, they're very smart, but also they can learn very different things.
I mean, then what do you expect them to learn?
So you've learned the importance of real data and these different input patterns.
And you've kind of learned some things about the model's ability to generalize across
this.
What else have you learned?
See, other things that we have learned are also that, I mean, if you look at, when we
look at all the research in image and all of them are 224 by 224 images, because that's
the image net size.
And we look at most research is about that size of image.
And if you look at an x ray, I mean, typical chest x ray will be around 4,000 by 4,000 pixels.
So if you are downsizing, so initially, when we started out doing research, we started
with taking that 4,000 by 4,000 or I mean, that size image and downsizing it to, to
2, 2, 2, 2, 2, 3, 4, 24, 24, which basically takes away a lot of the detail that you're looking
at.
I mean, so you cannot, I mean, obviously, if you have a lot of data, it'll, it'll
learn.
Well, I mean, it will be able to detect really large abnormalities, it'll not be able to detect
subtle abnormalities.
And so then we had to devise our own methods to sort of work with higher resolution images.
So today, we are able to work with full resolution images.
So we had to sort of look at patches at a time and do a lot of different techniques.
I mean, some of these are our own IP, so we have not published it yet.
So I cannot reveal it, but there is, there's a lot of work which we have done which sort
of enables us to look at the full size image rather than looking at these down sampled
images.
And that's all the backs of what I see, I mean, out there in terms of literature.
I mean, everybody is taking these standard sort of dense nets or resonates and then applying
them to the down sampled images.
And that also loses a lot of information from that original image.
So that's, if you look at most of the literature, that's what is happening right now.
Is there anything that you can say generally about the approach that you've taken to look
at the large images?
Are you like windowing across the images or any hints you can give us?
So it's a patch based approach.
I mean, we look at patches, we determine some patches and so that's, that's all I can
see.
There is definitely some very, very strong IP in there which sort of, because I don't
think anybody right now is working on large images.
I think everybody else is working on smaller sized images.
And we also tried, I mean, so we also tried training these, I mean, larger sized using the
typical dense nets, and it sort of doesn't perform as well.
I mean, or sometimes it doesn't converge at all.
So we saw lots of convergence problems with larger sized images.
And do you have any intuition for why that is?
I don't actually, I don't, I mean, we have tried that and I really don't have clue why
why that doesn't work typically.
I mean, so not sure.
But there is not much testing.
I mean, honestly, when I look at research, there is not much testing that has been done
on larger images because most of the work, I mean, 224 by 224 is a decent size for your
regular images.
So that's, that's sort of, I don't, I don't see that there is a lot of work done in
that, in that area.
In your approach and or the literature that you've seen, does transfer learning play a lot
or are you looking at pre-trained models or models, you know, that are pre-trained with
image net or some other data set, or are you just training from scratch?
So we have, we found that a pre-training with ImageNet and then using that on our data
set running, I mean, using pre-training on image net did not improve performance on
the on our data sets.
But what we found is that there is opportunity to do transfer learning within the domain.
So I could basically learn from other types of x-rays and use that learning to test x-rays.
So there is some, some of that learning that we have been able to use.
But again, that the transfer learning there, the impact of that is very small.
I mean, I think it also has to do with the amount of data that we have because we have so
much data.
Probably, I mean, the transfer learning is not that impactful.
But if you have a amount of data, then maybe if you transfer knowledge from other other
domains, it might be more useful.
What else have you learned?
I think, I mean, some of the learnings are about the annotations also.
I mean, so what we have learned is that we can do annotations at multiple levels and
bring, I mean, train models which can do multi-level, so basically there are multiple types
of classification.
So one is that, one is to segment out the abnormality.
So you're actually, the annotation will involve actually going into that image or that slice
of a CD scan and then saying that this is the boundary of the abnormality.
So clearly marking that out, a second type of annotation that we have done is looking
at, for example, on a CD scan, slice by slice.
So you can basically look at one slice and say whether that slice is abnormal or not,
which is a much easier task than actually annotating and going out and marking out the
abnormality on that.
So that's a second type of annotation and then the third type of annotation is at a scan
level, either at the whole CD scan level or at the extra level, using the report, we can
extract out the abnormality on that particular scan.
So I mean, we have models which combine all three of these.
So we can, we have losses, I mean, losses which will take the segmentation losses and
add the classification losses at a slice level and the classification losses at the scan
level and combine all of that.
So those are the models where we can actually take all the data that we have because we
have 350,000 HD scans and we cannot expect to label all of them.
I mean, we cannot expect to sort of, 350,000 HD scans each with, let's say, 100 slices.
So you're talking about 35 million slices.
So we cannot expect to sort of mark out all of them.
So you have to mark out a subset of that and so we have marked out a subset of that.
We have labeled at a slice level, a subset of that and then of course, for each of those
350,000 scans, we have got a report so we have, we can extract out the abnormalities
from those as well.
So we have combined all of this and then the models that perform the best on our data
are ones which combine all this knowledge, all the knowledge from all of these types
of annotation.
So just to clarify then, if you're, you know, when I think about a traditional, like
a resonant type of a model, that's a model that is basically looking at a single image.
Is the implication that you've built out an architecture that, you know, is almost,
I'm almost thinking of it like a 3D type of architecture that is, that takes in multiple
slices and kind of understands the relationship between these slices relative to the whole
scan.
Right.
Exactly.
Tell me a little bit about the process of defining or coming up with this model architecture.
How did you arrive at the final architecture for doing that?
So I think, I mean, it's, I mean, primarily trial and error.
I mean, reading the latest papers and, I mean, we have, I mean, around 10 plus deep learning
scientists now.
I mean, so, I mean, each person focused on their own problem.
And I mean, I think what, what we have basically been doing is, I mean, looking at what is
the latest research in a physics space and trying to implement that.
I mean, so we've implemented many different techniques from many different papers.
Some of them work.
Some of them don't work.
Or a lot of them don't work.
I mean, very few of them work.
But so a lot of them don't translate directly.
I mean, I think what we have seen is that there are lots of new techniques out there, lots
of new, I mean, which show very promising results on the paper itself shows very promising
results.
But then when we apply it to the domain that we are working in, it doesn't really translate
well.
So we have seen that.
But I mean, typically our architectures are very simple. I mean, in fact, what we have
found is that the simpler you make it, the better it is.
Can you give me an example of something that you tried that was more on the complex side
that you thought would add a lot of value, but it ended up doing something simpler, worked
out better?
You were trying GANs at some point of time to see if we could generate abnormal and normal
X-rays using GANs and then use that for training or use that to do a data augmentation.
And we have tried other techniques, I mean, even some of the techniques from video action
recognition and videos we've tried for our head CD scan technology.
And some of these, I mean, again, some of these have not really worked out.
I mean, I think more complex technology, we have not seen that it sort of translates
to real.
I mean, again, I mean, I would not say that some of the technologies that we developed have
not been complex.
But again, I think in general, I mean, I would not, I would say that a lot of things that
we've tried have not worked out.
Yeah, it sounds like you're, you know, you're describing a world in which we might think
of as applied ML and AI, there's still a lot of research involved in your process for
developing this product suite and bringing it to market.
Absolutely.
I mean, I think there is a huge amount of research, there is a huge amount of domain
knowledge, which we have brought in, I mean, which just makes the algorithm much better.
So I mean, simple things actually make it easier.
I mean, so for example, if you're detecting fractures, if you see, I mean, if you just
train a model on fractures, you'll probably see a lower accuracy.
But if you look at what is around the fracture, I mean, if you also detect bleeds and use
that to, I mean, prove your knowledge about the situation, you'll probably get, we actually
get a better accuracy, better probability.
So I mean, if you have a fracture, you most likely have a bleed in the brain also.
So I think bringing in a lot of domain knowledge is critical in some of the areas that we're
working on.
I mean, for example, detecting tuberculosis, you have to look at certain types of features.
So you have looking at certain things, I mean, on the upper lungs, I mean, so it fits
in the lower part of the lungs, that's not going to be very relevant.
So we have, I mean, brought in a huge amount of radiology knowledge into what the algorithms
have developed and those actually add a lot of value.
And of course, I mean, the research also is the, I mean, we also have to do a lot of research
because as I mentioned earlier, most of the material out there is focused on the types of
images that are much smaller and also two-dimensional, right?
I mean, so you're looking at mostly two-dimensional videos, two-dimensional images.
Only in case of videos, you're looking at something which is not too dimensional, but
at least your sequence of images.
And we look at a CD scan or a MRI, I mean, all of these are three-dimensional images.
You have to sort of get knowledge from all of the slides and bring that all together
to infer a classification there.
So we have to, I mean, congest, I mean, sort of ingest knowledge from these sources, which
again, there is not much literature out there on some of these topics.
So though, of course, I mean, there are lots of people now working on this, on technologies
in the medical space.
But when we started, I mean, which we started around two and a half years back, there were
very few people who were working on deep learning in the healthcare space, which is exponentially
increased in the last couple of years.
And out of curiosity, have you directly applied any of the work or models that originated
in looking at videos to this CT scan problem?
We have.
Did that work out or was that another dead end or?
Well, I think that that's something that has worked out for us.
I mean, some of these techniques have worked out for us.
But I would not be able to go into much detail on that right now because it's still something
that we are working on and we don't have, I mean, I, yeah, so we have not published anything
on that yet.
The company has been active in publishing some of his research findings.
What are some of the recent work that you've published?
So we have published recently.
We published our work on head CT algorithm, which basically detects in multiple kinds
of bleeds, fractures, midland shift, mass effect from head CT scans.
And this, we sort of published some details of the algorithm or, I mean, this is our,
the earlier version of our algorithm, which is probably around nine, I mean, around a year
old.
And we sort of did a validation study of that on on a data set where, so we, we, we had
a data set of 350,000 of which we had basically a training set, a validation set and a testing
set.
But then what we did is we went out and collected an additional 500 scans, which was from
a very different source, completely new source.
And we had those three sort of reported or basically a radiologist had to go in and mild on
a user interface, whether they found an interapparent primal bleed, whether they found a fracture
and so on.
So just a tick box.
And we had sort of three radiologists do that on those 500 scans.
And we also compared our accuracy against that.
And we found that we were 95% at 0.95 plus you see on all of these, all of these detecting
all of these abnormalities.
Now this is, this is slightly older.
I mean, so the technology that we have published there is maybe around a year old.
Now it is currently, I mean, what we are looking at is around 0.97 plus 0.97 plus on abnormalities.
So it's, it's improved a little bit since we published that work.
Has, have you published any data sets in this space?
Yes.
So we also open sourced this data set of 500 scans.
So it's actually for exactly 491, we have published that, we open sourced that data set along
with the ground truth for that, which is basically the reading of the radiologists.
So I mean, one of the challenges that we found is that everybody claims their own accuracy
and there is no common data set on which people can sort of compare their accuracies.
Like, for example, imagine it is there, you can compare accuracy and imagine it.
There is nothing in the, in the, in most of these space.
I mean, so head CT, we said, let's put together this data set.
And then let's, I mean, we, we published our results for that.
I mean, of course, we anticipate that other people can also use that to publish their results
on that particular data set.
And you said, how many scans in the data set?
491.
And is, is that that number of scans enough to really build interesting models against?
It will be hard to get a very accurate model.
You could start and you could build some models on that.
It, it definitely, you could build models.
I mean, maybe the accuracy will suffer a little bit because it's not very large.
I mean, so basically if you, we have 491 of which, I would say around 300 or so, I mean,
I don't remember the exact numbers, but around 300 of them are abnormal.
And of those abnormalities, if you look at a specific kind of bleed, let's say an extra
dual bleed, there are probably around 40, 50 scans which have got extra dual bleeds.
So that itself may not be enough for you to determine and be able to train a model to determine,
to identify an extra dual bleed.
But this data set, the intention was not for people to train more, more for people to validate.
So you can get and measure your algorithm, which you've trained on another data set.
And you can measure your performance on this data set and you can definitely measure that
to a very high level of accuracy.
Okay.
So it's four of more of a testing data set.
Got it.
And are the scans, these full three-dimensional scans with multiple slices each as well?
Or are they static slices?
They are there three-dimensional.
So they have, I would say, anywhere from 5200 slices per scan.
What kind of uptake have you seen on that, has anyone, have you seen other groups doing
validation against it and publishing their results?
I mean, I have not seen, at least, I have not looked at it in the last month or so.
But I mean, before that, I have not seen, we released this data set in March.
So it's not been a long time.
But we have seen, so I don't know if other people have published, I mean, I have not seen
anybody publish against it as far as I know.
But I have seen, we have seen, I mean, hundreds of people download that data.
And so hopefully we'll see some publications out of that soon enough.
When you're building out these models, so you've looked at head CT scans, you've looked
at chest X-rays, you've looked at skull fractures, is your objective to create a single model
that is able to detect abnormalities in each of these different, very different scenarios
or are you building a suite of very specialized tools that is specially trained and focused
on one particular problem space?
I mean, it's much more, I mean, actually, we are building very, very specialized tools.
In fact, if you look at chest X-ray, we detect 15 different types of abnormalities.
And for each abnormality, we have multiple models.
And so it's an ensemble of many models.
So the number of models that go into even detecting these abnormalities from a single
chest X-ray, on a single chest X-ray, we run around 112 models right now to determine
all the different things we can report on that X-ray.
So we are building very, very specialized models.
And I don't think, I mean, there is no, I mean, we will not, definitely, I do not anticipate
that we will be building models, which can detect multiple kinds of abnormalities from
different kinds of images.
So we'll have very specialized algorithms for each.
When you take a step back and you think about bringing these types of tools to market,
what are some of the things that you've done with this and mine to build?
I want to say build scale, but that's not really the right word.
It's almost like manage technical debt to manage all of these models and to allow you to efficiently
manage all of these models, I guess, and bring them to market.
Is there tooling that you build or an approach that you've taken that helps you manage all
of the complexity created by having so many very specific models?
I mean, I would also add, there is one more complexity is that these models are improving
at a very, very fast rate.
I mean, so every month are models improved by a few percentage points.
So that is also there.
I mean, so in terms of a release cycle for our algorithms, we also have to figure that
out.
So there are multiple challenges, but what we are, one of the things that we are doing
is to deploy these models as a cloud-based service.
So that is the preferred model of deployment for us.
So in that cloud-based service, then you can sort of, you are basically, you can host
those models and you have a full ownership of the models.
And if you want to sort of upgrade them, it's not too much of an effort because you are
owning that.
So that's sort of the model that we prefer in terms of deployment.
Of course, I mean, some places we are working towards an on-premise deployment and then
in those scenarios, upgrading the models, I mean, they get a static version, I mean, they
get a current version and then upgrading them will be challenging.
So cloud-based service allows us to, allows us to mitigate some of the problems that you
talk about.
Prashant, thanks so much for taking the time to chat with me.
This has been super interesting and I've enjoyed learning from what you've learned.
Thank you so much, Sam.
Great talking to you as well and thank you for inviting me on this podcast.
Great talking to you.
Fantastic.
Thank you.
All right, everyone, that's our show for today.
For more information on Prashant or any of the topics covered in this episode, head over
to twimmalai.com slash talk slash 165.
Don't forget to visit twimmalai.com slash nominate and cast your vote for us in the People's
Choice Podcast Awards.
As always, thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.