Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast why interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
In this episode we're joined by Kristi Denison, machine learning engineer at OpenAI.
Since joining OpenAI earlier this year, Kristi's been working on OpenAI's efforts to build
an AI-powered agent to play the Dota 2 video game.
Our conversation begins with an overview of Dota 2 gameplay and the recent OpenAI 5 benchmark,
which put the OpenAI agent up against the team of professional human players.
We then dig into the underlying technology used to create OpenAI 5, including their use
of deep reinforcement learning and LSTM recurrent neural networks and their liberal use of
entity embeddings, plus some of the other tricks and techniques they used to train the
model on 256 GPUs and 128,000 CPU cores.
This was a fun interview and I hope you enjoy it.
Let's go.
All right everyone, I am on the line with Kristi Denison.
Kristi is a machine learning engineer at OpenAI.
Kristi, welcome to this week in machine learning and AI.
Thank you.
It's nice to be here.
Fantastic.
So you've been at OpenAI for coming up on a year now.
I guess you started there in January and you've been working on Dota, the Dota 2 project
there.
And tell us about some of your experiences in joining that team.
Yeah, it's been a lot of fun.
I've gotten to learn everything from interfacing with the game to also our machine learning architecture.
It's really, it's super interesting.
As a machine learning engineer, I've gotten to add features so the model can observe different
parts of the game and I've also gotten to learn about how you actually interface with
the game.
So I think like if you wanted to, you know, have a bot play in Dota, we do have an API,
but there's a lot of things to understand there.
It's not just, we don't look at pixels.
So instead of pixels, you have to use the API and find ways to represent that in a way
that our model can understand it.
Are you a Dota player before joining OpenAI?
I have to admit that I don't play Dota very well and I did not play beforehand or many
games at all.
But I hope by helping OpenAI 5 that it can play well for me.
I think you and I both are in that same boat.
In fact, I don't know much about the game at all or at least I didn't until learning about
it in the context of what OpenAI is doing and I suspect that there are plenty of folks
in our audience that don't know much about the game.
So maybe you can tell us a little bit about Dota starting from, you know, why is it an
interesting environment around which to experiment with AI?
Sure.
So again, this is a research company.
So our, we don't just play games all day are one of the things we really are trying
to do with Dota is use it as a test bed for these RL algorithms and that's a reinforcement
learning.
So why Dota?
We've seen a lot of strides recently with or even actually not just recently for decades
with Chast and Go and the real question is what do you do next, right?
You want something that's close to the real world and that's the main application for
a lot of AI's to the world like how well can you affect the real world?
Dota is probably one of the most complex in terms of strategy games that are popular
out there right now.
So there's tons of people who have already been playing it for forever and or at least
as long as it's existed and it's a complex game not just because of, oh well, it's not
just an eight by eight board because the board does have a size, right?
You have a map and Dota and you have two sides, two different teams that try to fight
each other and there are these buildings you're trying to destroy and eventually there's
one building and you destroy the call of the ancient if you destroyed this particular
building you win the game and it's not as simple as just taking all your characters and
charging right at that other building because there is this complex rule set that makes
it so that you can't just simply win in one way and that's something that they do a
really good job at at these, you know, multiplayer games is try to keep everything balanced.
So there's lots of items you can use that can give you certain advantages at different
parts in the game.
They also have some downsides in some cases or they don't give you strength another or
they cost money and you have to get money by killing these little minions that each side
has. There's a ton of complexity behind Dota and I would take many of your episodes to
get through it all, I think, but the core of the issue is that it's a great test bed
for reinforcement learning because it's so complex because you can't understand it
and it's simple an eight by eight board.
Is there any one particular factoid or metric that kind of captures for you the complexity
of the game?
Well, okay, so I think the thing that really makes it interesting, I think, from a machine
learning perspective is that there's partial information and that's all you work off of
is partial information all day long.
Each side has this what they call a fog of war and it covers your enemies team and unless
you place certain items in certain spots, you can't see things and if you can't see
how are you supposed to win, how are you supposed to attack the enemy.
So this partial information is I think probably the reason that makes it the most complex
is because if you did know where everyone was, it would be a lot easier game.
So OpenAI recently held an event that was called the OpenAI 5 benchmark.
What's the significance of this benchmark in OpenAI 5?
Sure, so we've been, so actually, I should probably maybe give you a little bit of a
timeline of what we've been going through so far.
So last year we had our 1v1 bot and it beat some of the top players in the world at 1v1,
but as many Dota players know, 1v1 has a restricted set of rules, it's only like kill the
first tower, it's only mid lane, basically it's a much simpler game.
And so in order to really do Dota and really do the full complexity again, you have to do
5v5 with 5 players on each side.
So that was last year and this last year we've been working really hard to, you know, bring
you OpenAI 5 as it is today.
And having 5 instead of 1 presents a lot more challenges than just adding 4 more bots,
we had to allow, as I said before, like the game features, going back to this last May,
we had an inhouse team and they were still, I mean, they're pretty good and probably
average players were able to beat our OpenAI 5.
And then in June, our OpenAI 5 was able to beat our inhouse team.
And so we're like, well now what do we do, right?
How do we figure out how good our OpenAI 5 is?
We don't have a way of knowing.
So we found some, you know, some very stronger test teams to test out OpenAI 5 and they were
also winning.
The OpenAI 5 was winning.
So now we're like, well now what do we do, right?
We need to find, how do you, how do you, like, for something that you can't measure in
a scripted way, something this complex, how do you do the next thing?
So that's the point of the benchmark match was to get some, you know, 99.95% out players
and have them play OpenAI 5 to see how good is it.
Like where are we?
What do we need to do for TI?
And TI is the big competition and at the end of August, it's coming up in a couple
weeks.
It's called the International and Dota players from around the world get together to compete.
There's this large prize pool at the end.
But the thing that we really want to know is, you know, is self-play?
Does it work or do you have this thing we call strategy collapse where it learns only
one strategy can't recover?
It's a really interesting problem and I feel like the only way we can know if it's actually
learning well is if by testing against these really strong teams.
And now this prize pool for the TI, that's like $30 million or something like that.
Something like that.
I'm not too connected with the specifics, but yes, it's a pretty big prize pool.
I vaguely remember from last year's 1v1 work around Dota that there was some controversy.
Do you recall what that was?
I maybe if you have more details on that, I mean.
I remember there was dig into it in a lot of detail.
But I recall at around the time that OpenAI published its 1v1 results, there were, I guess,
the usual questions around kind of the applicability and the generality of the results, whether the
system had, you know, some things that were, you know, hard-coded or, or, you know, rules
that were baked in versus purely learned, whether, you know, it had access to more better
information than a human might have that kind of thing.
So I was not working here last year, but I can at least answer your questions about specifically
doesn't have better information than a human.
And the answer there is just, it doesn't have any extra information.
And if anything, it actually has less.
When you get all the information we get, we get from the official API, which gives us information
of, like, where the hero is and what are your abilities that are available and can you
use those abilities?
And there's, in fact, one of the things we've realized is that as we've been adding more
features, the, you know, OpenAI 5 has actually been doing really well, even when it doesn't
have any vision into certain things, like for a long time, it didn't see a wooden
zone.
And it actually sort of did okay.
It's a lot better now that I can't see them.
It didn't see what?
Oh, sorry.
So there are these things called avoidant zones.
One example is there's a character, they call them a heroes, called Sniper, who has this
ability called, that's called Trapnel.
And it's basically this area of effect spell that gives damage if you walk into it.
And because OpenAI 5 didn't know where they were, they would walk in the middle and be
like, I'm taking damage now what?
And just kind of stand there and take it.
So in some cases, it started to sort of learn how to get out of it, but it was a lot better
when it had a map around itself indicating where it was so it knew how to get out.
But so the thing is, even without that, it still was doing pretty well against Story
and House team.
So there's nothing that it had, no information, it has extra.
The one advantage it does have, and I think this is just because, you know, you do have
the API, you do have all the observations up front.
Humans have to check other heroes manually, they have to do that switching, and pro players
are very fast at it.
But they do have, there's that delay of switching on the thing, whereas OpenAI 5 just can access
it as it comes in.
But I can't react instantly, that's another thing I think some people have been talking
about.
So originally, when we were doing this, we do this thing called FrameSkip, and it is
that there's 30 frames in a second, and we could take an action on every frame, but it
actually makes training super difficult too long to do.
So we take an action every four frames and then collect observation and create an action.
The problem with that is that means your reaction time is around 80 milliseconds, which seems
on fair compared to even in top humans.
So we actually slowed it down, although it had to admit, it wasn't because, necessarily,
we were ready to take that step of, you know, making it even.
We were just trying to speed up training, because the forward past time took so much time
and doing the game time took so much time, made a lot of more sense to offset our actions.
So it is now closer to 200 milliseconds, reaction time, which is closer to humans.
I think a lot more fair, but other than that, other than the fact that it does get all
the observations at once, it also the other thing too, is that the time to think is very
different, right?
Even if you have, you see an observation, and it's not until 200 milliseconds later, you
can respond to it, you know, opening a five doesn't need time to think like a human
does.
A human, it's not just about need your reaction time, it's also about the thinking time,
and you know, depending on how good you are, it might be like, involuntary or not, and
that's another thing that humans don't, like, the opening a five doesn't really, there's
not a good way.
I mean, we could delay them, but it's just a disadvantage humans just naturally have.
So you've mentioned some things like Shrapnel and some aspects of the heroes.
It's kind of making me want to take a step back and talk about some, you know, nuances
or details of the game that might help.
Again, those of us who aren't really familiar with it fully understand, or at least not
fully understand, but at least get a sense of, you know, what gameplay is like.
So the standard game is five by five, or is it a game that you would have, you know, unlimited
number of people playing simultaneously?
Yeah, so the standard game is five by five, and again, you can play 1v1, but yes, that
is a standard game.
Sorry, so I should probably give a little more context about the game.
So there are, I think, 100 and 100 something heroes, I think it's over 110, I think.
And each of these heroes has, you know, like, at least for abilities that they have that
each have a slightly different effect than every other ability.
Some of them are similar, but some of them are very different.
And that's part of the reason that for OpenA5 right now, we have a limited hero set.
It's actually not because that we didn't want the, you know, OpenA5 to train on it.
It's mainly just because there's just so many things to represent that like we have to
do manual effort every single time we input a new feature of the model.
And that is really where a lot of the complexity of this project exists.
It's just in, like, how do you, you know, coerce all of these API inputs into something that
this, you know, the LSTM can understand.
So that's part of it, the other part of it too is that, I think I mentioned this a little
bit before that, you know, we have a lot of, we have a lot of items and each of these
items, there's probably like 100 plus items, something like that, I don't go beyond that
number.
I don't know exactly, but there are a bunch of items that the, you know, each have their
own effect and their own caveats and everything.
There's also other actions, there's an action called scan where you can point to the map.
You can only use it every three minutes and it will tell you, oh, is there, you know,
an enemy in this area, there are things called words and they give you vision.
They also can give you, like, they also call them sentry words and they give you vision
over invisible units.
So there are a number of items that can make you invisible, but so you need these other
type of words to see the invisible units.
There's other items that can also help you with that.
So there's like every single aspect of the game has either an item or an ability that
you can, you can change it with and there's also a bunch of complex rules, like there's
this thing called backdoor protection, which means that your towers will start healing
if you try to just rush at them at the enemy's towers because they want to make sure that
everything is even in fair so that, like, you actually have to have your little minions
with you in order to actually get far enough to attack other enemy's towers.
It's because otherwise people would just try to, like, you know, surge and run towards
the asian, just kill the ancient and that wouldn't be a very interesting game.
Like, the game developers valve has done a very good job of keeping it balanced and interesting.
And then I also mentioned the fog of war before, which covers the enemy's map and even what
you can see, you have this circle around your hero that is influenced by trees and other
items and other, like, obstructions in the map that you can't see around.
So like, all these things come together to really make it a complex, interesting game.
And you mentioned that OpenAI currently supports a subset of the full number of heroes.
How many heroes does it support?
And I'm assuming that there are some limitations as a result of that in the 5x5 matches.
Like, I think I read somewhere that it's in, like, a mirror mode, like both teams are playing
the same five heroes, or is that right?
So that's, yes.
So we used to do mirror mode.
And recently we've worked on a way to make it so they can play multiple, multiple sets
of heroes.
And we really did that with just adding this embedding that says, okay, this is the hero
you're playing right now, so that the model can know, oh, I see, I have this thing.
Now I use this different ability instead or is basically as aware of the different abilities
it has to use.
So yes, we have 18 heroes now.
It doesn't have to be a mirror match.
And if anyone was watching the benchmark saw, we actually introduced drafting as well.
And the drafting is super interesting because our opening of 5 picks the heroes in the order
that it thinks will have the best chance of success.
So again, it's based on the strategy it has learned.
And so what specifically is drafting?
So drafting is picking the set of heroes you want to use in your team.
So from 18 heroes, the two teams, so each side, one side is called Radiant, the other
one's called dire, the two teams go back and forth picking heroes.
There's actually a set up where you know, usually Radiant picks first and then dire picks
two heroes and then Radiant picks two heroes.
But those are just the specifics.
The idea is that you get a chance to pick heroes that you want on your team.
And that way it's not just a mirror match, everyone has the same heroes.
It's just, we're trying very hard to make this as real Dota as we can because we want it
to be like a honest evaluation of this research project.
We want this to show like, can you actually make something superhuman for something that's
more complex than games that we've already solved?
So you've mentioned a few technical topics so far, reinforcement learning was one, embeddings
or another.
Can you talk a little bit about the technology that underlies the Open AI 5?
For sure.
So basically our model is just one enormous LSTM.
And the rest of the complexity is just coercing these Dota API inputs into something that the
LSTM can process.
We have this model architecture diagram that's kind of overwhelming, but there's just so
much to observing the game.
So the different modifiers that are going to apply, the different abilities that you have
and also what items you have in your backpack.
But when it comes down to it, we have all these inputs.
We try to put them in reasonable representations.
One thing that I've worked on recently when I mentioned the avoidance zones before is
making an embedding for the invoiting zones.
So the idea is that before it didn't really matter if we just say, hey, there's an avoidance
zone here.
Just stay away because we were doing the mirror match and there were only two avoidance
zones.
Now that we have 18 heroes, there can be more.
So what we want to do is actually tell it, okay, which type of avoidance zone are you
dealing with?
Because you might want to step out of it.
Maybe you don't, maybe you'd rather take it so that you can, because you know how much
damage you'll take, so you can get to this other goal.
And that's basically implemented as a map around the hero itself and just see the different
cells are how the embedding type in them.
So how does the map get translated into an embedding?
Oh, so it's literally like an 8-by-grid around the hero and we, if we see, oh, the avoidance
zone covers the cell, you know, just by like, you know, distance detection from the center
of the avoidance zone, we say, okay, this one is this type.
And then we put it through the embedding and then feed it to the LSTM.
So folks that are listening, that have been following along with the fast AI course with
us, we've been doing a study group around this fast AI, practical deep learning course
and embeddings has figured pretty prominently in that course as a way for us to capture
a pretty broad variety of characteristics about different entities into deep learning models.
So it's interesting to hear that they play so prominently in the Dota model as well.
Oh, for sure.
And we use them for, I mean, I can't show you the diagram, but like they are across the
board here because there's just so many things that have different types.
Like there are, I don't know, several hundred modifiers and modifiers are ways of knowing
if there's a spell cast on you or something, something like that or if there's an ability
to be using, there's so many different things that have different types.
So it's, it's absolutely essential that so many things go through embeddings.
And so the embeddings are you, are you training the embeddings separately or are you training
all of this end to end?
It's all end to end.
And so you've got this gigantic LSTM, I think I read it was like a 1024 units, is that
still accurate?
I think, you know, that's been changing so much.
I think we might have, it's actually 2048 now, because I think that 20, the 1024 was
for 1v1 and so we figured it should probably raise it for five heroes.
And is the, are the steps in the units in the LSTM are those time steps in the game?
Like frames or are they some other unit?
For each time step, we have all of these different inputs.
I've not worked on that specific section, but the time step we look at right now, actually
do not remember with, I think it's like 16, it changes based on like if we're doing local
training or not, but I believe in when we're doing it training for an experiment, we're
looking at 16 time steps at a time.
And that's with the frame skip.
Okay.
Maybe like, I guess two seconds, something like that.
You mentioned that you do a lot of different types of transformations to, that a big part
of the challenge here is figuring out how to feed information into these LSTMs, sounds
like a big part of that is using embeddings, but there's some other things that you're doing
to, in terms of representations for making all of this tractable.
Sure.
And besides embeddings, well, so one other thing that I've worked on recently is adding
a mini map.
So this is a part of the game that everyone, all the humans get to see and opening up
five never got to see.
And it's just this high level view of like what vision you have, where are the enemy units
are, things like that.
And the way we handled this, because we couldn't talk to the client code, is just trying
to recreate the vision.
So what we have is this input, we start out with this large grid.
It's 260 by 260, and we draw all of, where all the vision is on the map.
So you get vision from towers, from heroes, and we overlay it.
And so you've got this one nice vision channel.
And then we add other channels, like, here's where your heroes are, and another channel
for where your words are, and another channel for all these things.
A channel for your creeps, the minions.
So we add all these up, and then we actually put that through a confnet for the model
to understand.
And so far it has been helping with word placement, or so we think it's hard, word placement
is really hard to figure out, because it's a, it's something that requires a lot of strategy.
And not every single, word placement makes sense for every single part of the game.
What's a word?
Oh, sorry.
So the word is something that gives you vision, remember?
Just like the entire map is covered because it's all war.
So what you really want to, like, you can't evaluate, that's the thing that makes this
really complex, is that it's hard to evaluate good behavior.
A lot of this behavior we can't see till really late in the game.
So I guess for the word placement, like, it's, I'm sorry, but late in the game, I don't
mean this actual game, I mean, late in training, like, and that's something we actually don't
have a lot of, without comparing to agents that are similar skill levels.
It's hard to tell, like, are you doing this well or not?
And that's part of the reason we had this show match.
But we have a scripted bot we made a year ago that, you know, it does okay.
I think it beats me pretty consistently.
But in an average play, I would probably be able to beat it, because you can't, you can't
script these complex behaviors that well.
That's the thing we ran into first, is you just, you can't create a, you know, a set
of, you know, the open A5 with just scripting, you have to have something else that's learning
that knows, can figure out these complex strategies, because you can't, you just, you can't
code them up.
You mentioned, I guess what I think of as kind of a reward attribution type of a problem,
meaning things happen in the game, and if you're just measuring the agents progress on
wins and loses, you don't really know until late in training.
But I read something about how there's been some experimentation with that binary type
of a reward relative to more incremental types of a reward, so looking at, you know, kills
and hits and things like that, specifically some experiments that were done comparing
like sparse rewards versus dense rewards.
So yeah, this is something, actually, that interestingly enough, we have been, we have
been doing some research on.
So it, when we first started doing one V1 bot, one of the things that we really wanted
it to learn was creep blocking, and it's the idea that just statistically, if your creeps
end up in the middle of the map, sorry, slowly over, middle of the map, like into the enemy's
territory, the enemy can start taking those creeps and killing them faster, and you tend
to statistically do worse, and so a lot of people tend to creep block at the beginning
of the game where they'll stand in front of their creeps and prevent them from running
to the beginning of the map, and so if your opponent is not doing that, what they'll,
they will end up getting their creeps on your side, your tower will try to take them
out, and you generally do better that way.
They couldn't even, with all the training they did, they never saw this happen for one
V1, so they had to do this shaped reward, basically, you know, give a reward for blocking
the creeps.
So however, when we did let it run longer, and this was, I think, earlier this year, we
actually did start seeing a little bit of that behavior, so I think when it comes to sparse
or dense reward, and this is, again, this is just off of some of the experiments we've
seen, you can sometimes see these, like, these good behaviors that you could get out of a
dense reward, but you have to give it a lot more training time, and so it's really as
a trade-off of, like, how much, like, how much training time do you need to give it?
So we do give rewards for kills and things like that, but, you know, in taking towers,
you get the gold reward, you have to do that, otherwise it would just, I think, it would
just take too long to see any good results, and sort of interesting fact of this, and
we saw, actually, in the recent benchmark, is the third game.
And one of the things that happened is the crowd picked the draft, and so the draft was
terrible for opening I-5.
Absolutely terrible.
It predicted a 2.9% chance of winning, which is pretty abysmal, so it did lose, but the
interesting thing was, is that we started to see these behaviors where the heroes would
sacrifice themselves to take a tower, which is kind of strange, like, why are you changing
your behavior so much to do something like taking out of tower?
And we realized, is that we've kept the rewards, you know, symmetric, you know, if you win,
you get one, if you lose, you get negative one, and, but, you know, standard aisle practice,
you generally have, you know, scam a term that is your horizon, right?
And so you generally discount the rewards, positive and negative.
And so if you think you're going to win, it makes sense, you're going to try to drag
that game out as long as you can to make sure that that penalty is as low as possible.
So I know, right, it's kind of hilarious.
And this is what we saw.
So now we're like, well, now some of that behavior makes sense.
You sacrifice yourself because of the towers down.
Then there's more time in the game, because now the enemy team is going to have to work
harder to keep it balanced.
And if you eventually lose, you're like, okay, well, now I, you know, got a much smaller
penalty, but it's hard because you don't want the two teams collaborating, right?
Yeah, like in general, asymmetrical words are not good.
And we did try a little experiment so far, trying to see how that works, but like, it's
tricky.
It's really tricky to try to get these things right.
Yeah, you end up with a lot of possibilities for unintended consequences and things that
unfurl and unexpected ways, I would think.
Oh, yeah.
I mean, it's just so many tweaking.
I think that's, and that's the reason we're doing the research, right, is to figure all
these things out.
But even like a few weeks ago, we were talking about how just changing our learning rate.
We're just like, hey, why don't we explore an experiment with a lower learning rate?
And oh, guess what?
That helps.
Like, there's just, there's so many.
No, it's too, too bad we can't have the opening of five figure out how to do all these
things, right?
You've talked quite a bit about reinforcement learning and some of the papers that I've
seen referred to in the context of the Open AI 5 and the previous versions were PPO and
Rainbow and Observe and look further.
Do you, can you talk a little bit about the roles that each of these plays and how they're
used in the kind of the training regime?
Sure.
So we basically use a pretty scaled out version of PPO.
We have our training setup, we call, I guess it's training framework, we call rapid, that
allows us to scale out a lot of, like all of this training, because you know, with reinforcement
learning, you need lots and lots of samples.
So we have, I think in our recent blog post, we were talking about how we have 180 days,
180, sorry, years of training every single day.
And that's because we're running all of these games in parallel.
So yeah, so again, it's just, it's basically scaled up PPO.
One of our, our recent experiment had, so our recent large experiment that we used for
the benchmark had 80,000 CPUs and 1000 GPUs.
And about half of those were optimizers, the other half were just doing roll outs.
And we also have infrastructure for doing evaluations, so that we have like this giant
tensed word that tells us like how everything's going, we look at sample reuse, we look
at the, you know, the mean reward, we look at all these different aspects of the training
to figure out like, is this going well for us?
Is it not like, what can we tweak, what can we not tweak?
It's a really great framework for running experiments.
And we use another teams at OpenAI as well.
So there are two different types of nodes.
One was for updates and the other was for something else, what were those two?
So part of what Rapid does is it does, it handles a lot of like the scaling out.
We have a whole, you know, different clusters and machines that are used for the whole training
process.
And one of those are the optimizers, the optimizers handle all the back prop, you know,
it's, you know, taking the new parameters, spreading them out to the machines again, combining
the parameters.
And then the other half of the machines for the most part are the roll outs.
And we have both GPU roll outs and non-GPU roll outs because you, so it's basically if you
want your, as you're running the game, doing your forward passes, do you want to be run
on GPU?
And recently we've made that infrastructure change so that it can run on GPU.
And that does help us not as much speed up training except when we've made the models
sufficient size than it actually is faster to run it on a GPU.
What is a roll out specifically?
Oh, yeah, so roll out is just playing the game, right?
So it's creating samples.
So we have all these machines that are creating samples playing the game, you know, seeing
here's an observation, here's the, you know, here's the next observation, next action,
you know, your action.
And then all that gets packaged up and sent to the optimizers.
And, and then we also have a bunch of machines that do evaluations.
And so the able to do is, you know, take a snapshot of the parameters and play again against
our scripted bot.
And then it will report the results.
Of course, those, that's usually only useful for the very early part of training because
again, the scripted bot can only do so much.
So it's used for new experiments, but later on we have this other piece of infrastructure
we call scoreboard where we can snapshot parameters played against other snapshots and see how
they compare.
And that's really how we decide, you know, coming up to a match if like what is really
the best of something because otherwise you just can't tell.
And at a certain point, like even with all these snapshots, we still need humans to evaluate
because there are, there are probably, as I said, I mentioned this early before very
quickly, the problem of strategy collapse is what we've been calling it where your opening
of five might be learning only a small handful of strategies and maybe not learning everything
just hasn't practiced that.
So you have five different models that come from five different training iterations.
Could each of those play a different hero in the same game on the same team?
You could do that.
It would require extra infrastructure work.
Right now we're just sort of doing all of them in parallel with the same brain.
So they all do have the same brain.
They're just giving them different inputs and running all of the four passes in parallel.
You've got these brains that you train for the heroes.
They use these embedding so that they can, you know, the brain can control any of the heroes
that open AI five supports at a given time.
And then it sounds like you play different versions, one against the other to determine
which ones are best, how long do you play them against?
Is it a certain number of games or a certain number of quote unquote years, days of play
to assess, you know, a given model versus against another model?
So the way our scoreboard is set up right now is that it will try to find the like most
recent agent that's been uploaded and played against other ones that have the same environment.
The environment just basically means like we can set up an environment.
So it's just like sniper versus sniper in which we've done a lot of tests for that.
And then more recently we've had the ones where we have our 18 hero set.
So scoreboard looks around and says, okay, like who are the new agents and tries to, you
know, bias it so they get the most new games, but then other agents like also get games.
I think it tops out around thing.
I don't know the exact numbers, but something around maybe like 10,000 games, it'll start
to ignore you entirely, because it's like, well, we've established what your skill level
is.
But other ones, yeah, it's just basically on a need basis, depending on the, because so
many people are constantly uploading things for their individual experiment, because once
you get past the scripted bot, you can't really tell very well.
Okay.
So it's kind of like a CICD system, you create this model, you experiment with it.
And then you upload it into this testing infrastructure that basically just pits it against
other models and determine how it fairs against them.
Maybe jumping ahead to the actual benchmark match, can you give us the highlights of the
benchmark match?
First of all, what were the results?
Yeah.
So the results of the benchmark match were the first two games, opening a 5-1 against
the humans.
And just one thing you have to understand, like these humans have played for 10,000 hours
against this game.
These people are very good at what they do.
The players we had at the game were like, were some were previous pros, but our casters,
but they understand the game so well that they're able to talk to other people about it.
And I think that's really a great demonstration of how well they know it.
So they're excellent, 99.95% percentile players.
And they lost the first two games, and the only reason they won the last game was because
of this adversarial drafting that our audience and Twitch chat were able to assist with.
So that's the big thing.
And I think it's not as much, there's a couple things with the drafting results.
I mean, so the first ones, for the first few minutes of the first two games, it was
tracking pretty even, but that's how most games go.
You don't really know if you're winning or not even if things are even like, well,
opening five got a kill, they got a kill, it was sort of even, but then things changed
because then opening five starts pushing and they push their lanes and pushing the lanes
basically means going to the other side of the base and really trying to take the other
side.
So even humans had to sacrifice a lot to get some of their first towers.
And so even though they were getting the towers, it didn't mean that they're really ahead
because they had to sacrifice so much.
And then after that, it just kind of went uphill for opening five.
The fact that the game opens up late in the game is it have to do with that open AI is
kind of figured out some the right time to start pushing or is it do you see like the
culmination of some longer term strategy that open AI had been playing all along that,
you know, either the humans were oblivious to or couldn't effectively counter or something
like that.
So I think it's both and it's again, because I think this is actually a complex problem
because, you know, a lot of professional games even will be pretty even at the beginning
or even just amateur games.
So having a advantage at the very beginning does not mean you'll have an advantage later
in the game, but it can, it's sort of a hard answer.
I think the thing, how I was talking really about the asymmetric awards, we did start
doing an experiment where we said, okay, fine, no penalties, right?
And the games do finish faster because they're trying to maximize that reward.
So it could be, I think it's a little above, if it's, you know, most games do start out
even.
But then also, I think, you know, open AI 5 is motivated to, you know, make it a little
longer than normal.
Hmm, where are the humans down?
Yeah, there you go.
So it's, yeah, it's all these things, this is why I think after TI certainly will be doing
a lot more like ablation studies, things like that, to figure out exactly how much of a
contribution each of these things make, because right now we're just sort of rushing to
the end, trying to make the best open AI 5 we can, but we really want to understand more
in depth how, how each of these little knobs affects the performance.
Are there any other observations that are noteworthy coming out of the benchmark?
I mean, certainly there are.
What were some of the main things that, you know, either the open AI team or the audience
or the commentators observed about the way open AI had learned to play relative to humans?
Yeah, so I don't know too much about specific strategies.
I feel like you have to have a certain level of Dota understanding to really understand
how these things work.
One thing the commentators did say is that they tend to go very much for pushing lanes,
which means that like they'll just kind of go straight forward.
There, again, there are numerous valid strategies in Dota because it is a very complex game.
They tend to take on these more, I guess, hard fought strategies like where you just kind
of go for it in some cases and they have the confidence to make it through most of the
time.
Not always, but they, and they also support each other.
That's the other thing that we saw in the last even our internal games is that we have
this, this Piper parameter called Team Spirit and what we do is, you know, if we turn it
up, it's basically it's like a shared reward.
So if the higher it is, the more reward you get for some of your teammates kills rather
than just one of your kills.
And interesting things as down at zero, they play terribly and if it's a one, they play
terribly.
So there is a mid-ground where you have to be a little bit selfish, but also care about
your teammates enough to go help them when they're dying.
But it does, it is interesting, they seem to play more collaboratively than humans at
times.
I'm seem to care about each other a little more.
So I think that is part of the reason that they have done so well.
You mentioned or I saw in a video somewhere, one of the commentators was talking about
some strategy that he observed the bots playing.
I think it was something like keeping the center of the board clear or something to that
effect that, you know, it took him eight years to figure out or something.
Yeah.
So at our first, I think, so we had a, we published a video in a blog post a while back.
And one of the interesting things about the Dota board is that it's not symmetrical.
So I mean, it's sort of symmetrical, but there are some different parts.
And so what Blitz, who was commentating that those games was saying is that there are,
like, so bottom, the bottom towers on the radiant side are surrounded by forests.
So it's actually really hard to defend those towers.
And so his advice is like if you're playing radiant, don't even bother.
Just let them take those towers because you have a much better chance of taking out the
enemy and your mid towers and your top towers if you're radiant.
So it just says, just said that it's like it's very hard to defend the ones in the weeds.
So again, there's a lot of a lot of strategies there and it's I think the kind of the questions
you're asking me is like one of these high level strategies.
It's part of the reason we had these very well practice humans come look at these things
because these are things that a lot of us just as, you know, as machine learning engineers
and researchers, we can't spot ourselves because it requires so many hours of gameplay
that we haven't done yet.
So maybe to wrap up, can you talk a little bit about how this fits into the broader
landscape of projects at OpenAI?
You mentioned that the next big challenge is TI.
Is this OpenAI 5 allowed to compete in TI like for the 30, 40 million or is it just a
milestone or are you planning some additional benchmarking kind of there?
Yeah, so we're just doing this for, I mean, again, OpenAI is a research organization.
So we're not planning on being part of the human pool as we're not entering a human.
But I think the main thing for us is really just to see how well we can get OpenAI 5 to work.
That's our main and only goal is feeling to see, can we get super human performance from
reinforcement learning and self play?
Well, Chris, you thanks so much for taking the time to explain all this complicated stuff
to us and help us understand what OpenAI is doing and why you're also excited about
the OpenAI 5 playing Dota.
Great.
Well, thank you for having me.
It's been a pleasure.
All right, everyone, that's our show for today.
For more information on Christie or any of the topics covered in this episode, head over
to twimmelai.com slash talk slash 176.
If you're a fan of the podcast, we'd like to encourage you to head to your Apple or
Google podcast app and leave us a five-star rating and review.
The reviews help inspire us to create more and better content and they help new listeners
find and enjoy the show.
As always, thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.