Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast why interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
In today's episode we're joined by Jay Newby, assistant professor in the Department of
Mathematical and Statistical Sciences at the University of Alberta.
Jay joins us to discuss his work applying deep learning to biology, including his paper,
deep neural networks, automate detection for tracking of sub-micron scale particles
in 2D and 3D.
In our conversation, Jay gives us an overview of particle tracking and a look at how he combines
neural networks with physics-based particle filter models.
We also touch on some of the unique challenges to working at the micron level in biology,
how we evaluated the success of his experiments, and the next steps for his research.
A couple of quick meet-up related updates for you.
Our next Twimble online meet-up is coming up on September 19th and will feature David
Clement presenting the paper DeepMimic, example guided deep reinforcement learning of physics-based
character skills.
This should be a fun one and I encourage you to join us.
Next up, our second session of the fast.ai study group is starting soon.
If you've got some coding experience and would like to learn state of the art deep learning,
this is a great way to do it.
To join either of these programs, please sign up for the meet-up at twimbleai.com slash
meet-up.
All right.
On to the show.
All right, everyone.
I am on the line with Jay Noobie.
Jay is an assistant professor in the Department of Mathematical and Statistical Sciences at
the University of Alberta.
Jay, welcome to this weekend machine learning and AI.
Thanks, Sam.
I'm happy to be here.
Awesome.
Well, let's get started by having you tell us a little bit about your background and
your research focus.
Thanks.
My background is applied math, specifically modeling, biological phenomena.
I study small things that move in small spaces, so small things can be pathogens like virus
or bacteria, they can be biomolecules.
For the most part, I study things that are moving around inside of cells, but I also study
extra cellular spaces too.
These tend to be spaces that are on the scale of a micron, and the objects can be anywhere
from a few nanometers on up to several microns.
One of the hallmarks of motion at this scale is that objects when they're in a fluid
like inside of a cell, they move randomly, and so my area of mathematical focus is
stochastic processes, and these are dynamical systems that have random elements, so something
that's changing randomly through time, and that describes the motion of molecules and
small objects in living systems.
My PhD thesis was on modeling molecular motor transport.
Molecular motors are, they are molecular machines that move things literally.
They burn energy, fuel to move objects, cellular resources, large distances.
We studied that in neurons, neurons are unique among cells because they have to cast this
very wide net, they have to cover so much space to construct neural networks, and that
requires actively moving cellular resources around, and we studied the role of molecular
motor transport in learning and memory, and that's what led me to study particle tracking.
When you say particle tracking, what specifically are you referring to, or is there a specific
type of particle that you're interested in in this research?
Particle tracking really refers to taking images with the microscope of these small objects
and small spaces, so this can be the cells, to virus, to many different things.
We take videos of these objects moving, and then we localize the center of the object
through time and track its motion.
From that, we can learn many things about hidden factors, things we can't see about, for
instance, the fluid of a cell or of a mucosal barrier, mucosal barriers, by the way, they
defend us against infections and, among many other things, so we can learn things about
stuff we can see by analyzing the random motion of these particles, but we also learn things
about the objects themselves.
For instance, we might be interested in how bacteria move around in mucosal barriers, because
as we know, there's this very rich ecosystem that we're becoming aware of, that live in
our GI tract, our lungs, and they play this very symbiotic role in our physiology.
Really, this task of particle tracking has many different applications in biology.
Your research is using images and neural networks to do this tracking.
Can you talk a little bit about the origins of that work?
Have you been using images and neural nets for a while?
Sure.
My background, as I said, isn't in image analysis or machine learning.
When I started a post-doc at UNC Chapel Hill with Greg Forest, I was working on many different
projects, and at the root of all of these projects, the data source, it was all particle
tracking data.
We would take this particle tracking, which consisted of what we call position time series,
so X, Y, Z, T, basically, for a list of different particles, and then we would apply stochastic
modeling to try and learn things.
It became apparent to me that I needed to really study how this was being done, because
it's this mixture of software-assisted tools based on traditional image analysis and
really, really heavy human interaction, so it's a very labor-intensive process.
As I learn more about how particle tracking software worked, I started to think about
ways to automate it.
That's what led me down the road to learning about convolutional neural networks.
It's kind of a weird road.
My PhD advisor had done a lot of research on modeling visual cortex, specifically explaining
how visual hallucination patterns form through various perturbations, like drugs or injury,
and how those form in the visual cortex.
It's vaguely aware of how neural networks in the visual system worked and are organized.
I found it was one of the most amazing things reading how these things were actually trained,
that these feature, the sequential layered pattern matching was spontaneously emerging from
the training procedure.
I tried to apply that technology to the particle tracking task, because what is very time-consuming
about particle tracking is a very mundane task that humans are really good at doing over
short periods of time, and that is just staring at a screen at a fixed image and pointing
out bright blobs.
I mean, it's a very tedious job, and it's usually left to students and lab technicians,
and it's very time-consuming.
The patterns, the way these show up in a microscope image, well, I should back up.
First of all, for virus, typically are around 10 nanometers to several hundred nanometers
in diameter, and almost all of them are below what we call the diffraction limit, meaning
that we can't resolve them with ordinary light microscopes.
They show up as blurry blobs, sometimes with these diffraction, like these wavy patterns,
so picture a, dropping a pebble in a pond, and then freezing that, you know, the ripples,
and then putting them around the bright blob.
That's kind of what it looks like.
It's called an airy disc, right?
So you get these super-imposed particles with little waves around them, and then you
have to find the center of those patterns, right, where the particle center is.
And when the wave-like patterns intersect, sometimes, that can really throw off a particle
tracking software and generate lots of false positives.
So the patterns are relatively simple, however, a microscope images do present some unique
challenges.
So first of all, we're talking about biological fluorophores that emit light that we are
trying to detect with the microscope, and they emit very small amounts of light.
We have to have very sensitive cameras that detect, and they're getting very, very good,
they can detect upwards of 98% of the photons that they're being exposed to.
But that comes with the price, and that is very low, what we call signal-to-noise ratio.
That's a common term, I think, that people understand.
So these images are very noisy.
So the patterns might be simple, but the conditions are very harsh.
So I did an interview not too long ago with a guy named David Van Veilin, who's doing
something very similar at the cellular level.
He was using, I think, kind of the annotation software that he was using before he started
looking at applying CNNs was something called Atlas Toolkit.
Have you heard of that?
Or do you use something similar?
I've heard of the Atlas Toolkit, I haven't used that.
I'm aware of David's work.
I tried before encountering his paper to do a similar, the very similar thing, and that
is a cell segmentation.
It's a very similar idea to track cells as it is to track particles.
It's very difficult to do the segmentation part of that to distinguish one cell from
another as individual entities when they're very close together.
That's a big challenge.
I just started my group here at the University of Alberta, and that's one of the directions
that I would like to go.
There are many, many people I've talked to that are very interested in being able to
do cell tracking.
So there's a lot of opportunity, I think.
I think this is a great playground for people more broadly interested in object tracking,
because the patterns are very simple, so it's a great way to do a lot of experimentation
and to also have an impact on the scientific community.
So with your work at the particle level, I imagine that segmentation comes into play
in addition to, it sounds like you're trying to maybe relate some particles between frames
and maybe determine motion vectors and things like that from one frame to the next.
That's right.
Yes.
We try to do that in a way that is as robust and widely applicable as we can.
But we also have the option to bring in physical models.
This is where my background is as stochastic processes, in stochastic processes comes
in.
It's hard to write down a really physics-based model for the motion of a person, for example.
But we can write down very good models for the motion of a molecule that's undergoing
brownie and motion, the classic example of a stochastic process.
It's the drunkards walk.
You imagine that at every time point, you roll the dice, the proverbial dice, to figure
out where you're going to step in the next instant, and how far you're going to step.
And you assume that you're not going, you don't have a bias or a preference to go in any
particular direction, and so you will just wander about aimlessly.
And that is what we see particles doing in these videos.
So it's a very concrete and direct and invaluable mathematical model.
We can do this for even more exotic, say, for example, molecular motors, which sort of
processively move in a particular direction and other things as well.
So the tracking through time has its own unique challenges, but of course, the main principles
are very similar to tracking of sort of the macro human scale objects as well.
One of the recurring themes that I've explored on the podcast is this idea of combining
neural networks deep learning with physics-based models, and it can be challenging.
Can you talk a little bit about how you went about that?
Well right now, we can apply methods separately.
So we do like a first we'll run the CNN and do object recognition, find the centroid
of all the particles, and then we kind of have this separate tracking step.
Now the tracking step can also employ machine learning methods like hidden Markov models,
easy and networks, basically particle filters, and that's an unfortunate name conflict, right?
The particle and particle filters is not the same as particles and particle tracking,
but those ideas are the same.
So those physical models port directly, these stochastic models of the motion port directly
into those methods, then everything is an optimization.
And we can even infer things that are hidden things that we don't see, such as the hidden
state of a bacteria which uses a flagella like a motor to move around actively, and they
spread out much more quickly this way.
And so we can determine if a bacteria say is using its flagella in a certain way, or
if it's just passively sitting around, and it makes a very powerful tool.
And what's great about it is all the physical assumptions, right?
These are very important when you're writing a scientific paper.
You want to explicitly say all these assumptions that you make in your analysis pipeline, and
when you use a method like this, they're all in the model, all in this physical model,
right?
And then everything is an optimization, just using standard basing statistical tools, everything
is an optimization, finding the best parameters, the best fit for that model.
You mentioned particle filters, can you explain what those are?
Physical filters, they're basically a way of taking observations and inferring hidden
factors that are, so you might assume that you have, I think the classic example is
a GPS detector in a truck, and so you would like to be able to get an inference of the
truck's position based on the noisy GPS recordings.
So you have some sort of model that relates the GPS recording to the truck's actual position,
but also where the truck has been in the past influences the inference of where it is
in the next sort of like time step.
And so you have an observation model, an emotion model, and you build these all in together.
So from the neural network perspective, I think the closest analogy maybe is the recurrent
neural networks, which use kind of like information about the past, the most recent past to make
inferences about the future.
And so given your familiarity with David's work and some of the audience's familiarity
with that work, I'm wondering if there are specific unique challenges that you encounter
here working at the micron level?
Yeah, there are many challenges.
One being that the microscopy sort of developed alongside in the computer age, regular
photography, I guess you could say, or video compression.
So all the formats and everything are, there's a million of them and they're all different.
So it's difficult to work with the data most of the time, everything is uncompressed so
the data says can be quite large.
And add to that the difficulties of imaging biological entities that are very dim in
their emitting very low levels of light.
And so you also have to deal with very low signal noise ratios.
So we actually also do 3D video microscopy.
And that is another unique challenge here.
And so how do you apply this convolutional neural networks to 3D videos and to also extract
useful information there?
So this 3D video sets, of course, are much larger than their 2D counterparts.
So we have to actually build up special tools to be able to work with those.
And in the case of 3D, it's using stereo microscopes, is that where the 3D models come
from or are they generated in a different way?
So one of the projects that we're really excited about now is doing particle tracking inside
living cells.
And so we do 3D particles, we collect 3D videos, so we try to image the entire cytoplasm
of the cell.
And the cytoplasm is just the fluid on the inside of the cell.
So the way this works is that the microscope has a stage, what's called a piezoelectric
stage, which just has a motor that can move really fast and very accurate small movements.
And so it moves that stage up and down.
And then the camera just takes the images sequentially.
So you kind of one layer at a time, you build up a 3D volume.
And then it's like a typewriter, you collect one volume and then you restart the beginning
again and collect the next volume.
So and in that way, you get this time sequence of volumes that comprise a 3D video.
One of the things that struck me in looking at some of the images of these particles is
that they're very dense.
And so there's a lot of occlusion, there's a lot of overlapping.
How did you have to do anything special to deal with that?
Well, the answer is yes and no.
So that is a very difficult problem that you identified.
So not only that, but the particles are appearing and disappearing.
They're overlapping, including, but then they leave, they're too dim, they basically
leave what we call the focal depth that we're actually imaging.
And then of course, since they're moving randomly, they can come back in.
So we have to be able to track them only while they're there and decide when they're
gone.
And the way the neural network does this, it sort of, it makes automatically does a couple
of things that allows us to at least have a first start that doesn't generate any errors.
Not perfect.
So for example, when two particles overlap each other in 2D microscopy, what the neural
network will do is just localize a single particle in that position, leading up to that or
just after they overlap, one of the particles is typically dimmer or smaller, and the neural
network will pick up only on the stronger signal.
So what typically happens is we just stop tracking an object once two particles get close
enough.
And so it does chop short that particular particle track, and we might pick it up again later,
but this is preferable to making errors and mistakes.
So we can actually do things to correct for this on the linking stage where we assemble
these centroids into tracks.
And there's been probably 10 to 20 years of work on this problem, actually, some really
great methods out there for this.
So we're in the process of kind of building up this tool box to correct for these little
things that we see.
And one of the, so one of the other things I mentioned was the particles appear and disappear.
So the neural network always outputs a confidence, right?
It's not just a yes or no answer.
It tells you how confident it is about a classification.
We do, you know, foreground versus background, so it's just a binary classification.
But when particles are dimmer and they're about to leave the field of focus, that confidence
goes down, and so we can actually take that information into account when we're deciding
how to link a particle in one frame with an observation in one frame with an observation
in the next frame.
And so you, you're using CNNs to do this.
Does that mean that someone went through and manually annotated some number of frames
in order to give you training data?
Great question.
So yes, somebody did do that.
Somebody is, well, one of three people was me, and that was not the funnest thing I've
ever done.
But the funny thing is we actually didn't up using the hand annotated data.
So in the lead up to this, as I was learning, frankly, learning about this technology, CNNs,
how they work, experimenting around with them, I just built up synthetic data, just simulated
the way that these videos looked.
And over time that built up to be good enough that we were, when we trained the neural network
with the synthetic data, I was never able to get anywhere close to the accuracy when
I replaced that synthetic data with, with manually segmented data.
So I don't know why, I don't know what the reason for that is.
I think my guess is that it's because the ground truth was so absolute in the synthetic
data set, and we were able to randomize the appearance and get the appearance accurate
enough that we were able to get a robust neural network out of it.
This is basically impossible, right, to do with human scale images.
How to use synthetically create an image of a cat, I mean, that's a very hard problem
in itself.
But for the scale we were working on, because these objects tend to be below the diffraction
limit, like I explained, these blurry, wavy patterns, they're relatively simple to create
synthetically.
Huh.
Oh, that's really interesting.
So what types of, you mentioned that you applied, presumably some kind of noise or filters
to augment your data, or at least tune it to get as realistic as possible.
What, can you elaborate on some of those things that you did?
Yes, I, I, I randomized everything.
So every sort of parameter I could think of, like how particle size details about the
shape, I put random background patterns, random amounts of background noise, I tried
to, to shotgun as wide a field of, of conditions as I possibly could so that, so that we could,
we could in turn, you know, use this on, on, the idea is to automate this and, and what
we found in, and extensively testing it in, for over about the last two years now, on
data from dozens of labs, that it is a surprisingly robust to different conditions, the conditions
that were outside of what we ever trained it on.
For example,
and just a point of clarification, are you saying that the training data that you developed
is robust, and other people could build models against it, or the models that you built
are robust, and they work with other people's images.
The second, right, we saw, we've seen that the, the, the tracker is capable of accurately
tracking conditions that we've received from labs that were beyond what we actually included
in the training data, the synthetic training data.
One example is tracking salmonella.
These are about one to two microns in size, so they're above the diffraction limit, barely,
and which means that we can actually resolve the shape, and they're rod shaped.
So there, we trained everything to recognize, sort of like these, rotationally symmetric
blurry shapes with the waves, and, and so as we, as we get images that have perturbations
from that, from that rotationally symmetric pattern, we, we still get recognition.
So we can track rod shaped, we've, we've tracked comet shaped objects, lots of different
kinds of background, so we never trained it to ignore large, bright spots, these, these
show up all the time, though, in experimental videos, but the neural network tracker evades
those, it ignores those.
So it's been surprisingly robust, and that's, that's really the key here of what we see
this, this technology is enabling for us, it's automation.
Do you think that the advantage of your synthetic data over the manual, you know, granted you
said you're not really sure why, why it worked the way it did, but did you have just a lot
more of it?
Could it be explained by volume alone, do you think, or did you compare comparable training
data set sizes, synthetic versus real?
I, I don't think it was the size of the data set, we had a fairly large set of, of hand
segmented data, it gets so, and this is part of the problem, it's very subjective, there
are certain really bright particles that show up and, and there's no ambiguity, there's
no mistaking what they are, but you start getting so particularly when the, when the particles
get dimmer, they're about to leave the field of focus and reappear, it's a very subjective
call, whether or not to label them as particles or not.
So I think that that probably has more to do with it, the synthetic set is very consistent.
So we, I tried layering in the, the hand segmented data with the synthetic data, with varying proportions
and, and the performance always went down sharply with the amount of, of the hand segmented
data that we used for training.
I can't give a definitive reason why that's true.
Huh, it's, it's very surprising relative to the way we usually think about this manually
produced ground truth data.
And, and also the, the degree to which the CNN models are, you know, they can be very
sensitive to undesirable characteristics of the, your actual data, and so the simulated
data that you think might be, looks great, you know, and close, totally confounds these
models because it's missing some, you know, undesirable or very subtle nuance that is
in the real data, so it's very interesting result.
I completely agree.
I was, I was very surprised when I learned about this technology, everything that I was
learning, that, that real data was absolutely essential, just turned out, surprisingly
not to be the case here.
And so you developed the, the model, how do you, how did you combine the model with the
tracking element?
Oh, so how do I combine the, the output of the, of the convolutional neural net with the
path linking?
Yes.
Right.
So right now they're, they're actually quite separated.
So the first stage is, is processing with the neural net and then, and then we, we segment
and what we call localized, which means just estimate the centroid of, of the spots.
And that's all basically done with the output of the neural network.
And then we take, you know, this disorganizer, a, a, un sequenced collection of particle
locations at each frame and then we link them together.
And that is, is, is done, the most robust and most widely applicable method is just to
use something called the Munkres algorithm, which just says, I'm going to take two sets
of objects and find the best match between all of those objects that sort of minimizes
some, some cost in this case distance.
So that's a, that's a classic tool and object tracking and, and we, we use an, an adaptive
method.
Again, we also have to decide when to stop tracking or when to start tracking a new object
that's appeared and we do that with the confidence from the neural network output.
But there are a lot of possibilities, I think, that are very exciting in, in machine learning
or unifying both of these parts together and really taking the linking side and maybe
using a stochastic model that's physically based or not, but using machine learning
and training end to end, not just end to end in the CNN, but end to end between the,
the object recognition and the object tracking side.
How did you evaluate the ultimate performance of the experiment?
What were your, the key metrics that you were tracking?
So we, we looked primarily at the, the success of object recognition in, in, in, in our
first paper.
And so there was an assessment of, basically, false positives, false negatives, right?
But also how accurately it, we detected the center of the particle, the centroid, which
is important a lot of applications.
So we, we did a combination of synthetic videos that randomized across a lot of different
conditions so that we could sort of assess the robustness.
And this was mostly to compare it to existing software that's, that's already out there
to emphasize the software that, the currently existing software really requires manually
tuning parameters on a per video basis.
So we wanted to emphasize the automation part.
So that's on synthetic training data.
But we also of course tested it on experimental videos as well.
And those were generated in samly's lab where we were tracking synthetic nanoparticles,
virus, bacteria, and, and then assessing again, the, the, the object accuracy.
Since then, we have a number of collaborations in, in over, around the last two years where
we've applied this technique.
And so we've, I guess, field tested it pretty extensively as well.
You mentioned that when you incorporated the real data, your performance, dropped significantly.
How would you characterize the performance differences between just applying the model
to synthetic data versus real data?
It's a great question.
So, of course, the synthetic videos that we used to test it were minor alterations of
the synthetic videos that we used to train it.
So of course, it's going to perform very well on those, even though all the conditions
are sort of randomized.
The real data, there, there have been some surprises, little things where the neural network
has failed.
And so that's given us the opportunity to, to tweak things over time and improve things.
For example, we noticed that sometimes there is this mixture of, of intensities, pixel intensity.
So how bright the objects show up.
So there might be some particles of type A and type B, for example, some that are very
dim and some that are very, very bright.
And the neural network would only track the bright ones.
So that's something we had to go back and, and we built that into our synthetic video generation.
So the workflow has been that we noticed something that the neural network doesn't quite
do correctly, and then we go back and build that into this synthetic video generation
and retrain.
And that's worked really well for us.
What are some of the next steps for your research group and in this research direction in general?
Well, I mentioned before that we're, we're very excited about doing particle tracking
inside living cells.
This gives us a, a spatial temporal measurement of, of the, the entire cytoplasm of a cell.
So we can measure things like crowding, confinement, viscosity.
You have to remember that all of the chemical reactions, a chemical reaction is just molecule
A molecule B coming together and they, they come together by random motion, by brownie
motion usually.
So they're moving through this fluid and in all of these things like crowding and, and confinement
and viscosity, they influence the chemical reactions, all of them that are happening inside
the cells.
So this, everything that's going on inside physiologically of a cell is, it depends on
this.
And so this gives us a quantitative measurement of window into that, and to these conditions.
Like I mentioned before, we're, we're doing 3D, we're collecting 3D videos for this.
And one of the real challenges there has been to deal with these large data sets.
So on a 2D experiment usually generates around 1 to 50 gigabytes of video data, where a
3D experiment is, it's going to be roughly 10 to 20 times larger than that.
So we're easily, a single experiment can generate, you know, terabyte or more of data.
So we needed, so the, and 3D videos themselves are very large files.
So we needed a way of implementing the neural network, right, that could handle these, these
large videos.
And we did this in, with cloud computing resources, we've been using Google Cloud, which has been
extremely generous in supporting our commercial and our research projects.
And we've been using Apache Beam to basically implement a map-reduced style processing
pipeline to, to break up these videos and, and press them, process them once a piece of
time.
The great thing about Apache Beam and Google's data flow is that it dynamically manages
the hardware.
So if I have a, a small set, maybe I only need 20 CPUs.
If I have a terabyte, you know, maybe I need a thousand CPUs over hours, and, and, and,
dynamically instantiates those, those virtual machines and then shuts them down when they're
no longer needed.
We're also very interested in delivering this as a commercial web app that people can
use.
We want to, we want to empower biologists working in labs that typically don't have a technical
computer science background with programming skills.
So we needed, we needed to build something that's very easy to use, platform independent,
could handle large sets of data.
And so a cloud-based web app seemed like the best option for us.
Early on in the discussion, you mentioned a couple of application areas.
One was looking at neurons and the other was looking at some of these micromotors or
cellular motors.
Have you, did you learn anything through the development of the particle tracking system
about the systems that you ultimately care about?
Absolutely.
That's ultimately what we're most excited about doing is learning, learning new things
biologically speaking.
So we have applied this to tracking these small fluorescent molecules, we call them gems.
They are, they're actually synthesized by the cell.
They're about 30 nanometers in diameter and we're looking at how cells basically programmed
the cytoplasm, the fluid, that everything moves around inside in these fungal cells.
They're called aspia, this is in collaboration with Amy Gladfelter's lab at UNC Chapel Hill.
And what's special about these cells is that lots of different nuclei, many multiple
nuclei share the same cytoplasmic space.
They're called syncycia.
Our typical picture of a cell is one nucleus with DNA, right?
But syncycia actually are not that uncommon.
We have them in our own bodies, muscle cells, for example.
So it's an interesting question to understand how multiple nuclei coexist.
They all have to undergo division like a cell with, there's a cell cycle and all those
cell cycles conflict with each other if the nuclei are too close.
So we are using particle trafficking to try and measure how the cytoplasm is regulated
programmed in order to isolate these nuclei or maybe they cooperate, maybe they compete.
We don't, we, there's a lot of questions that we are interested in answering.
So this is an ongoing project right now.
And we also study mucosal immunology.
So we are interested in how virus and bacteria can penetrate a mucosal barrier which could
potentially lead to an infection.
So we discovered, this is with SAMLI's lab at UNC Chapel Hill in the School of Pharmacy.
We discovered that these mucosal barriers actually trap virus by using antibodies, which
is a potentially therapeutically exploitable avenue of protecting against infection.
Do you already have some areas of further application of machine learning to your work?
Absolutely.
So one of the things I would really like to do is, is move to more of the human scale tracking
world.
And to keep going with object tracking, apply it to scientific problems, but to, to track
say, fish or fruit flies or orbs in controlled laboratory settings where you want three
dimensional information possibly from two or three different observation points.
And there, I would like to be able to, to use mobile hardware to, to process this in
real time, to process and track images in real time.
Oh, really interesting.
Well, Jay, thanks so much for taking the time to chat with us about what you're working
on.
I appreciate you walking us through it.
No problem, thanks for having me.
All right, everyone, that's our show for today for more information on Jay or any of the
topics covered in this episode, visit twimmelai.com slash talk slash 179.
If you're a fan of the podcast, we'd like to encourage you to head to your Apple or
Google podcast app and leave us a five star rating and review.
Your reviews help inspire us to create more and better content and they help new listeners
find the show.
As always, thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.