Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast why interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
In this episode we're joined by Hambiel Zhu, a PhD student in the Robotics Institute
at Carnegie Mellon University.
Han, who's on track to complete his thesis at the end of the year, is working on what is
called the Panoptic Studio, a multi-dimension motion capture studio with over 500 camera
sensors that are used to capture human body behavior and body language.
While robotic and other artificially intelligent systems can interact with humans, Han's
work focuses on understanding how humans interact and behave with one another so that we can
teach AI-based systems to react to humans more naturally.
In our conversation, we discuss his CVPR best student paper award winner, Total Capture,
3D deformation model for tracking faces, hands, and bodies.
Han also shares a complete overview of the Panoptic Studio and we dig into the creation and
performance of the models and much more.
Okay, enjoy the show.
Alright everyone, I am on the line with Hambiel Zhu.
Hambiel is a PhD student in Robotics at Carnegie Mellon University.
Han, welcome to this week in machine learning and AI.
Thank you for having me today.
So you've been a PhD student at CMU since 2012 and a major focus of your work is in and
around an environment that's been built there called the Panoptic Studio.
What is the Panoptic Studio?
Yeah, the Panoptic Studio is basically a multi-b system with more than 500 camera sensors
and the system is also controlled by more than 50 machines.
So this is indeed a giant system using computer vision technique to measure or sense humans
by the behaviors.
So basically we are very interested in the way we are using our bodies for social communication.
For example, all these subtle facial expressions and body gestures and so on.
And we really wanted to make a machine who can understand the body languages we are using
and in the end we want to make a machine which can use these body languages to communicate
with us.
And for the purpose, the first thing we wanted to do is we wanted to collect this kind
of motion capture data of naturally interacting people so that we can use some machine learning
technique on top of that so that we can in the end machine can understand these kind of
signals.
And that was the main motivation of this Panoptic Studio and since we are interested
in multiple people's interaction to avoid all this complicated occlusion kind of problem,
we wanted to make a system with many, many sensors with many viewpoint so that we can
really release these particular occlusion problems.
And this Panoptic Studio goes back quite a ways it sounds like.
Yeah, so CNU has really amazing history on this multi-b system because Professor Dakeo
already started this multi-view system kind of research about, I think, 30 years ago.
And at the moment, the major goal is to reconstruct the 3D world, especially 3D object and
3D human body behavior.
And to do that, obviously, this multi-view system is a really good kind of key to solve all
this depth kind of ambiguity.
At the moment, he already started this project with 15 machines and it was extremely challenging
problem at the moment.
And our Panoptic Studio is kind of third generation and our basic idea is maybe 40 or 50 cameras
I will let it boring.
Let's try to make a system with 1000 cameras, for example, and see what we can solve.
And that was kind of the beginning of our studio and we particularly chose this social
interaction analysis problem because that is indeed a challenging problem and very important
future problems so that the machine can actually have a way to interact with us.
And so how do you frame out this social interaction problem and what are the different research
problems that come out of this broader problem?
So basically, you can easily consider natural language or verbal language problems.
So for example, nowadays, there is a very popular commercial AI system which can understand
human's voice and human's language and use their languages to communicate with humans.
But in that case, the main channel is verbal language, which has sentence and grammar
or just rules.
Basically, we wanted to do the similar thing with non-verbal languages.
And for example, when humans are communicating each other, we use obviously our verbal
languages, but we also use our facial expressions and our body languages.
And all this subtle movement have some specific meaning, which is actually really hard to
define, but humans are really easily understanding.
And so basically, so maybe social signal understanding is something like expanding the dimension
from this verbal channel to non-verbal channel as well.
For example, the input can be, in this case, a verbal voice and also images or motion-catcher
data and machine understand the meaning of each sudden movement and maybe machine can
react to the input signals by using the similar outputs, for example, verbal language or non-verbal
languages.
And so one of the papers that we wanted to talk about is a paper that recently won the
CVPR Best Student Paper Award.
And that was your total capture paper.
And the full headline or the full title is Total Capture, a 3D deformation model for
tracking faces, hands, and bodies, which is right in line with what you've been describing.
Do you want to start kind of jump into that paper or do you want to tell us a little bit
about where that paper fits into kind of the broader scope of research that you're doing
for your PhD in at the studio?
Well, I think by explaining the paper, maybe the concept would be a little bit more clear.
So, yeah, so basically, so let's say we are given a large scale data set and now we have
some consensus that we can solve some problem using machine learning or this fancy deep learning
techniques, right?
So we have seen such kind of success in language part and computer vision or image processing
part or object recognition part.
And let's say we wanted to do the similar thing for body languages.
The problem is the amount of data is extremely rare in this body language.
And maybe the first problem is what kind of data we can use for this purpose, for example.
So machine sees the world maybe using cameras and how can understand the human's behavior.
Maybe machine can use the images and videos directly for the purpose similar to human because
actually we are using our two eyes which captured the scene and we can do some all these visual
kind of understanding part and indeed actually we know the meaning of each other movement
of humans.
But using directly images or videos are extremely challenging because it actually they are actually
nothing to do with humans, but actually they are some pixels and machine need to understand
the meaning of all these pixels so that they can finally infer oh, there is this human
here, there is this human's arm here, arm is moving in such a way, I mean solving all
these problems from the image or video is extremely challenging problem.
So although this is still very popular area in computer vision, using such a data set
for finer output meaning understanding the social interaction is extremely challenging.
So maybe another way to do that is just by collecting a lot of motion capture data because
motion capture is in a 3D space and maybe there can be camera independent, illumination
independent and that each motion capture data like for example 3D skeleton, this already
has some semantic meaning, we know where is the arm, where is the hand, where is, I mean
how they are moving in 3D space.
And this is usually done with the humans are wearing specialized suits with like I've seen
pictures of these things, I don't know if they're balls or lights or sensors or something
like that.
Yeah, exactly.
The area is extremely popular in movie industry and game industry and these are main way to
capture the real world human body signal so that we can put that to the virtual world.
But our idea is to use such data for understanding human behavior using machine learning techniques.
So to do that, we wanted to collect such kind of motion capture data a lot from natural
interacting people.
So the key here is as you mentioned, we really don't want to use any artificial markers
or suit because they may affect the natural motion of humans.
For example, if you are wearing this kind of black suit and say you have all this sensor
or all this kind of markers on your fingers, maybe your motion will be very kind of non-natural.
We really wanted to avoid such kind of cases and we just wanted to capture that in natural
human behavior when they are very naturally interacting.
That means that the method itself should be in necklace.
And this necklace motion capture area is also very popular in computer vision and computer
graphics because if you can do the similar motion capture with a single camera or just multiple
cameras, there can be really great to provide a really reconstruction output or it can
be also used for many main purpose like some action recognition, for example, or all this
movie industry or game industry.
And this itself is a challenging problem and this is especially challenging if there
are multiple people because some part is extremely occluded.
And our idea is, all right, we wanted to collect such data set first so that we can somehow
tackle the final problem we are very interested in.
But solving this problem itself is challenging then why not using a very kind of a good system
which can reduce the challenge of this problem.
So that we can start this project and then if this is really meaningful, then actually
we can expand the project to more challenging environments such as in the wild or maybe
you can try to use some YouTube video for the similar purpose.
So that was kind of the major motivation of our kind of the studio, all right.
This problem itself is too challenging and even obtaining the data is challenging.
So let's solve this problem, the initial data generation problem or human body measurement
problem first so that we can actually tackle the later problem.
And our total capture paper is one of the output of our measurement step.
So here we are interested in interacting multiple people and we are also interested
in measuring all these body signals at the same time, for example, facial expressions,
finger motions and body gestures because when we are using our bodies, these parts are
extremely correlated.
Some specific facial expressions should be very, very correlated to hand signals and we
wanted to make find, we want to find some rules humans are using when they are interacting.
So catching subtle details of entire body part is extremely important, but doing that
is very hard although we are using markers because of all these occlusion, self occlusion
for example, human hands, human have when they're moving their hands, for example.
So yeah, so our total capture paper is person in that direction and it actually showed
some meaningful kind of output in measuring all these parts at the same time.
One question I've got for you about this is are the humans that are in this environment?
Are they just kind of naturally interacting, doing what they're doing and you're capturing
that and then kind of going back and labeling it maybe from video or audio capture or is
there a script that they're kind of working against and well, I'll let you answer then
I may have a follow up question.
Yeah, that's actually a very, very good question because although we have, we collect people
who have no idea about our project, it's very hard to ask them to do some natural motion
right because.
Right.
Because then it's not natural.
Exactly.
So for the purpose, actually we are very closely collaborating with psychologists and they
are actually very careful about that.
What we are doing currently is we build some specific social situation and we actually define
some social game, which is a kind of negotiation game and this negotiation scenario where three
people are negotiating each other and in this game, which we call haggling, there are two
sellers and there is one buyer and the goal of this game is two sellers need to sell some
competitive items to this buyer and if the seller actually successfully sells the product
within a minute of time, we actually gave some bonus for them and because of this bonus,
this monetary bonus, actually they can be really involved in this project because the game
itself is pretty fun and actually they can additionally get this money because of the
region actually we found that the motion became very natural for sure because of the
special system at the very beginning when they first entered the studio, they actually
see the cameras and they can, they usually see the round but we actually spend some time
inside the studio so that they can be fully familiar with the system and because we don't
put any kind of camera in front of their face because cameras are all this cameras are
attached on the surface of the dome.
So it just seems like some kind of special room and after some time, actually the room
is just somehow similar to other kind of room with some special wallpaper.
So we found that their motions are pretty natural and in the end, we actually did some
questionnaire.
It turns out the majority people completely forgot that they are inside the dome and they
can fully kind of involved in this kind of social game.
And so for labeling, have you perhaps in conjunction with your partners on the psychology
side, like have you developed a taxonomy of gestures or some kind of labeling system
or do you have a free, free description of the gestures, which I would imagine would
be pretty difficult to deal with?
Exactly, so that's actually a really big question about this project because let's say we
can obtain all this body motion capture data from this, let's say three people's interaction.
Let's say we have all this facial expression movement and this finger movement and body
movement.
Then what type of problem can we actually tackle given this somehow restrict social situation?
Maybe we can do some type of annotation but actually annotation itself is some big question
in this problem because what kind of label can you annotate in this behavior?
In computer vision, for example, there is just area named action recognition, but different
from object recognition, action is really hard to define because there's starting time
and the time is usually really hard to define, right?
And making the label, the name of each motion is also very challenging because making the
name means we wanted to describe the motion using some language.
The language is in a very discreet space and it's in a very low dimensional space while
the expression, the signals we are using in our social communication is actually really
high dimensional space.
So in that sense, actually, we don't try to do any so-called kind of annotation label.
What we are labeling is kind of more objective thing, for example, who is the winner of this
game, who is the loser of this game, and for example, who is speaking at this moment
so that we can actually be very objective about the label.
And our scenario is something like this.
So how can you maybe make sure that robot detection interesting is a social behavior?
That is another good question we should ask.
And maybe our solution for that problem is something like the following.
Well, if a machine sees the world, sees the human's behavior, and if machine can predict
the future motion of these people, then that can be maybe a way to define that robot has
some understanding about our social behavior.
More statistically, let's say we have all this data and we somehow delete some human's
motion data.
And can we actually predict, can robot predict the person's motion, I mean, this hidden
person's motion by observing the other people's motion?
This is exactly the way we are interacting, for example.
When we are interacting, we observe other people's signal, and we're making some signal
from our body.
And the signal is sent to other people, and the other people are reacting to our signal.
And actually, this is somehow the way we are doing communication.
We just generate some signals using our body, send that, the signal is understood by people,
and that is also, I mean, the reaction is also sent to us, and we are just exchanging
some type of signals.
And we wanted to do the similar thing for the machine, so machine is in the loop and
machine see the world, machine decoded the social behavior with other people, understand
the meaning, and somehow predict the future motion.
So this is a way we define the problem at this moment, and this is exactly what we are
currently working on.
I'm trying to reconcile the idea that you're not doing any kind of annotation with the idea
that you're able to predict motion, but I'm imagining you're not predicting the label
of some motion.
You're trying to predict motion itself, so where is the hand going to be at some future
time based on some set of interactions as opposed to what's the name of the gesture
that the person is going to do?
That's exactly true.
So we just use the motion capture data as the input signal for this machine learning
tool, and output is also the similar types of signals.
But based on the definition of the problem, we can consider different scenarios, but one
kind of scenario we are considering is the input is the other people's body motion,
which is the motion capture itself, the signal itself, and the output is the target person's
future motion.
For example, if somebody is speaking something, maybe our target person can be nodding, which
is synchronized to other people's behavior, or our target person would be maybe laughing,
or moving in a specific way, and actually can we predict such kind of future motion of
the target person given other people's body behavior?
And so does it work?
How?
It sounds like a really interesting problem formulation, and tell us about the system and
how well it performs, and then walk us through kind of how you build it.
Well, so that is something we are currently working on, and for sure to this problem,
we really need a lot of data, because human's behavior would be very different, given the
same situation, right?
That would be maybe very related to our culture or personality, so given the same signal
actually human's behavior would be very different, so basically it's multi-model, very good
is this multi-model issue, and our data set is never sufficient for the purpose.
So we really need to narrow down the scope at this moment, so that we can tackle the initial
problem, and you can consider this simple problem first, for example, unless that we are
always considering three people's behavior interactions, and the input is two sellers'
body behavior.
So we have this skeleton, 3D skeleton kind of motion capture data of two people, two sellers,
and those are the input of our, for example, neural network architecture.
And can we actually guess the gase direction of our buyer?
So you can simply imagine that if somebody is speaking, if all that we don't have any
verbal kind of signals, if somebody is speaking there, if it is some speaking specific kind
of body behavior, and probably the buyer's gaze will be on this speaker, right?
This is some very simple kind of scenario we can imagine.
So this is just one channel, just estimating the gase direction of the target person.
Can we increase the dimension, for example, what about the facial expression?
Facial expression is indeed some 3D face key point, or we can just simply imagine the
mesh itself, so we have all these vertexes moving 3D meshes.
And this itself is the output of the network.
And can you actually predict the target person who is the seller, a buyer in this case,
of the buyer's facial expression based on the other people's kind of behavior?
Or another case is maybe location, where is the location of our target person?
Because basically humans try to have some distance among each other.
And this distance is also somehow trained throughout our life.
And we actually maintain some specific distance when you are communicating.
So actually, machine can predict the distance of the target person and orientation of the
person.
So this is something we can imagine as a very low dimension signal.
And we can actually consider higher, higher dimension signal, for example, can you actually
predict the target person's skeletal movement, or long-term movement, or hand gestures.
And at this moment, all this part is still remains in a very challenging problem, because
we don't have any specific output in this case.
But this is magic focused on our purpose, our motivation.
Got it.
So the big picture is understanding how to predict from these 3D motion capture models,
human behavior in interactions, so that ultimately machines could better understand
human behavior and make predictions based on it.
The longer-term goal to get you there is being able to predict on a, say, pixel-by-pixel
basis what the future state of one of these participants' body position is.
But the intermediate steps or the near-term challenges, and that's really, I think you
sense that that was my, you know, what prompted me to ask, is it working yet?
Yeah, that sounds like a huge problem, and it is.
So the way you're tackling that is these intermediate problems of, can we track the gaze
direction?
Can we track the facial expression?
Can we track hand position, things like that?
Exactly.
So basically, our current kind of problem definition is, we want to make a machine to understand
the human's behavior, and the way to do that is making some system which can predict
the future motion of the target person.
And there, we can imagine some simple good examples and application for this, for example,
let's say we have this AI, which kind of Amazon Alexa or Google Home kind of AI system,
which is nowadays just using verbal language, for example, audio or speaker.
But let's say this small machine has video as well.
So it can capture the scene, the human's behavior using camera, and actually it can display
some behavior using their own display.
I think this can be really interesting because now somehow they can understand the meaning
of our BID behavior, and they can react with that.
You can also consider many interesting AI systems or robot exist, and for example, if there
is a toy robot, which is actually interacting with a child, and if the machine can understand
the meaning of the child's body movement, basically let's say the baby cannot speak at
all, but it can actually make some facial expression and so on and so forth.
But still, the machine can understand this because human can do that, mother and father,
they actually knows the meaning of some specific movement of this child.
So this can be also interesting application.
Also you can imagine some application in medical area, for example, we have all these surveillance
systems, and we need to maybe monitor the elderly people's body behavior so that we can somehow
identify some unusual kind of behavior.
For example, in this case, all this measurement kind of skills and techniques and this understanding
that their behavior would be extremely important kind of techniques for these applications.
And so in the total capture paper you're presenting is a deformation model for tracking
these face-hand and body positions.
What do you mean by deformation model?
So basically we can do some 3D reconstruction without multiple cameras because connect
can do some type of thing or that camera can do some type of 3D reconstruction.
Here deformation model basically means the human's behavior is parameterized by some
limited amount of parameters and this parameter represent body motions.
So body motion means each joint angle is one parameter for each joint.
So we can consider some number of joint and each joint let's say have three-dimensional
rotation vector.
So that is some parameterization for body model.
And also we can do some parameterization for shape deformation.
So we have let's say 10 parameters and by just changing these parameters we can represent
the different size and shape of the people.
So without this parameterization actually reconstructing 3D humans are human is more challenging
because maybe we need to reconstruct all these vertex, all these 3D point of all this
entire body and that dimension is extremely large.
For example let's say we want to reconstruct some mesh model for each individual and
let's say this mesh model has let's say 10,000 vertexes.
The basically we need to estimate the location of these 10,000 vertexes for each time instance.
But the interesting thing is our surface is extremely correlated each other.
So our vertex is not moving arbitrarily.
If we know some location of one part we can easily guess at the location because they
are somehow very, you know, in a low dimensional kind of space in the end.
So this parameterization is basically to parameterize all these variations of human body motions
and body shape in a low dimensional space but still we wanted to have some sufficient
expressive power to express all these body behavior and the shape deformation.
And our total model capture is basically so this deformation model is actually really
popular in computer vision and computer graphics and there it is really popular as deformation
model for body and faces.
Our major contribution of our paper is we build a model which can actually include all
this part together including body deformation, body motion, facial deformation, facial expression
and finger motion and finger deformation and so on.
And when you say you have built a unified model in what way is it unified?
Is it, you know, have you built some ensemble that does each of the things well or have
you kind of abstracted away from the individual parts of the body that you're modeling and
really trained a model that can given any of those inputs, producer and output?
So in this paper actually we defined two different models.
The first model is more related to some independent model.
For example, we have independent facial model and body model and hand model and we somehow
consolidate together by attaching each other explicitly.
So this model is called Frankenstein or Frank because the way we built this system is
similar to this Frankenstein's model.
But yeah, the problem is all part have individual parameterization so sometimes they are not
consistent each other.
The final model we built which we call Adam is actually has single parameter space for
entire shape space.
So if we change one parameter of this space, a phase by the, a phase by the fingers are
changing together and basically defining this low dimensional deformation space means
we want to find out some correlation of different part so that we can reduce the dimension
of this space.
That's the key.
And since we built this model by collecting all this 3D reconstruction of body phase and
hand together, actually when we built this model in a low dimensional space, the model
somehow knows the correlation across bodies.
For example, if somebody has really big maybe face, maybe their hands would be also big
as well.
And by somehow merging this deformation space together, someone we can reduce the space.
So the final model actually has such kind of ability.
So it has some amount of deformation space which can control all this body face hands
together.
And also all this motion on body motion space is in a single skeleton space.
And that means so hand cannot be apart from the body and we know they are somehow linked
together by a skeleton, which is quite important for a computer graphics area, for example,
retargeting zone.
So yeah, that's the meaning of all this total body motion catcher and deformation model
space.
And so is the idea that you were expressing it with the dimensionality reduction with
the atom model that with the Frankenstein model, these parts are, the body parts are more
closely related.
We understand that if as you were describing earlier, if we create a mesh model of the
face, if the vertex and the cheek moves, then the vertex and the eyes are probably going
to move.
Like with these relationships are relatively easy to understand.
But on this atom model, you've got the single parameter space.
And so moving a parameter may have implications in multiple places.
And so it's more challenging and requires a different approach than you might take in
reducing the parameter space on the Frankenstein side or on the ensemble side.
Did I capture that correctly?
Yeah, I am mostly.
So basically the vision why we built this Frankenstein model is actually to build this
atom model.
So for example, for dimension reduction, we simply use, we can simply use PCA kind of method.
But the input of this PCA model is basically the 3D mesh model of many people.
So different shape and different body parts.
So they actually, this PCA can learn the variation space of these humans of deformation
and motion changes.
But generating such input that the mesh data, which include all these details of face by
the enhance, I mean, making such reconstruction is surface challenging, although we use many
many cameras because we are interested in subtle movement of facial expression.
And we are also interested in this subtle movement of fingers.
And at the same time, we are interested in this large movement of bodies.
So how to place the camera is actually a big problem because if we want to capture the
face, the camera should be very close to the face.
If we want to capture the detailed hand, maybe people wanted to use the camera, which is
very close to the finger.
So doing this reconstruction to build the AIDA model, the reconstruction is surface challenging.
So we were only to make some intermediate status by using some already available 3D mesh
model, a deformation model, and that's the main kind of motivation of this Frank model,
which is easier to build without doing any PCA kind of learning.
And after we have this model, actually, we use this model to reconstruct all these details
together.
And then finally, we reconstruct like 100 people's shape deformations, shapes and body motions.
And then we just put all this to this PCA kind of tool so that we can actually learn the
deformation space.
And there are just actually two big regions of doing that.
For example, if we build this deformation model for entire body part, actually we can use
that in the more challenging situation, for example, now let's say we don't have this
motif system.
And now we have this single image or videos from maybe YouTube or Internet.
And let's say our goal is similarly to reconstruct this 3D body behavior by the motion of the
person.
This is obviously extremely challenging problem because we now have single view and we
wanted to get this 3D motion capture data.
But since we now we have some model, which restricts the surface to this low dimensional
space than the original high dimensional space, actually, the problem can be much easier
because now what we need to do is just estimating the parameter of this model, which can express
our measurements, which is the image.
So the major kind of, I mean, the main motivation of research at this total capture is after
we build this model, now we can use this model to do this motion capture face by the enhanced
motion capture in this in the wild situation, so that we can collect more and more data
in this challenge situation.
So that is the major kind of motivation of building this a parametry model.
And another big reason is once we have this parametry model, actually, the data
structure can be very simple.
So instead of having the same mesh structure, which has some arbitrary number of vertices,
now we have some fixed amount of parameter to express the particular motion of the person.
So now we can consider this parameters as the input of our machine learning tools, those
that can be the input.
So other people's motion is abstracted as a parameter.
And then the machine learning tool produces some parameters as the output, which is actually
presenting some motion of the target person.
Can you comment at all about the size of the parameter space relative to the size of
your typical 3D vectorized or mesh type of model?
Well, I don't remember the exact number, but the rough number is we have 21 joint for
the body, and each hand has 21 joint, and each joint has three dimension space.
So 21, 21, and 21, and that is 63, and each joint has three dimensions.
So that is for the motion to represent the body motion.
And we can also have facial expression.
And facial expression is not explained by the sculptor movement that is explained by another
parameterization, which is expressed in the movement of this mesh structure.
And that has 100 dimensions.
So 100 dimension for facial expression, and about 200 dimension for body motion.
And we have about 40 dimension to represent this shape.
So by changing this 40 dimension, the shape, the size, and the shape of the body, bodies
are changing.
But it's more or less I cannot sum them up now, but about 400 to 500 dimension to represent
the human's behavior, including face and body and hands.
But the original dimension can be probably, if we don't have such kind of model, let's
say we wanted to do the similar thing by a mesh structure.
And then the mesh we are using is around maybe 10k of vertexes.
So each vertex has three dimension, and that is more than about 30k dimension.
So we reduced the 30k to this 500 dimension to represent a similar thing.
When you look at the skeletal model, plus the face, you have several 100 or so, 120,
130, then you said you can reduce that down to 40, and then you said, then you started
saying 400, 500, and I didn't catch where the 400, 500 came from.
Okay, let me try to explain this again.
So if we just consider skeletons, which is kind of a stick figure, then we forget about
all this surface movement.
So we can consider the joint location for the body, joint location for the finger, and
some surface key point movement of the face.
So each point is a three dimension space, and we can maybe consider all this number of
3D key point.
So that is our way to represent human body, but let's say now we are more interested
in the subtle details of the surface.
That means we wanted to get the mesh as the input and output of our machine line tool.
And in this case, now instead of just a handful number of stick figure joint location,
now we consider all these vertex locations of the surface.
So that is around, let's say, 40K dimension, because to represent some details, we need
many many vertices.
So the way to reduce this is instead of having independent vertex separately, now we already
learned the correlation of all this vertex movement, and we can reduce the space by using
the motion space and shape deformation space.
So motion space means we just keep the similar motion parameter for each joint, which is
similar to stick figure, and shape deformation space is actually catching the variation of
the surface of the given fixed body motion.
So by changing this deformation space, actually a surface shape can be changing, and by changing
this motion space, human can behave some body motion.
So this deformation, shape deformation space is about 40K, sorry, about 40 dimension,
which is really extremely low dimension, because humans are these are very, very correlated
in this case.
And for motion space, we have three degree of freedom for each joint.
And we have about 60 or 70 joint, so that is about 200 dimension to represent body motion.
And also we have about about 100 kind of dimension to expect facial expressions.
What you're able to represent with this lowest dimension, the lowest dimension of vector
is 40, is not just the stick figure, the body positioning, but also the surface as well.
Is that correct?
Exactly.
So we have a function to convert this parameters to the original mesh space.
The function is somehow fixed function.
So given this parameter space, parameters we obtain, we can convert that to this mesh
space.
So instead of keeping the mesh space, we can just keep the parameters.
The problem obviously here is the expressive power of this model is limited.
So for example, usually in nowadays, this model can express some kind of some body shape
with minimum clothing, because clothing modeling is clothing is extremely challenging,
because of all these variations we have.
So usually when we build this model, the input data is limited to somehow subject with minimum
clothing.
Because of the vision, this model can express only the mesh with minimum clothing.
For example, if you generate any arbitrary body shape and motion from this parameter,
the output is almost always this kind of naked body with minimum clothing.
You've reduced the dimension down to this 40 and then you're able to use this 40 to produce.
You said you refer to it as a fixed function.
Is this a function that's learned through machine learning model or what does that function
come from?
This function is somehow actually a very common function in graphics area.
So actually from the motion capture, if in graphics area, from the motion capture data,
which is basically the three degree of freedom for each joint, we can manipulate, we can
animate the 3D character and actually the 3D character output is mesh, although the
parameter input is this motion parameter.
Similarly, we just use the similar function, which is called linear blending skinning.
So we have some mapping between the vertex movement and the skeleton movement and we are
just manipulating the skeleton.
And then as an output, we can get the location of each vertex of the mesh.
And so you've developed this representation of the body.
How does this tie into the larger goal?
Yeah, exactly.
So first, we wanted to parameterize all this face and body and hands movement in a common
format, a common motion capture format.
That was one of the original building this model.
And as I mentioned, the final goal is actually to use this model to get a similar motion capture
output in the YouTube video.
So actually, we are working on this project and now the goal is instead of having multiple
view, we will just have a single view, single YouTube video, and we wanted to get the motion
capture of the target person.
And motion capture output has all this component facing body and fingers together.
This is ongoing research and we actually get some meaningful result at this moment and
which we plan to submit that to a conference in the end.
So yeah, so basically, we wanted to convert all of our collected data to these types so
that we can actually put this to our understanding part.
That is the current one at this moment.
We are working on.
And is PCA the primary place that machine learning is used in this project or are there
other places where you're building models as well?
Well, actually, this project is a little bit far from the popular machine learning area.
This is more like a three construction.
In this paper, what we show is usually this finger reconstruction and facial of face reconstruction
battery constructions are considered as separate problems.
But we actually somehow demonstrate that we can capture all these components together
without using any markers.
And to do that, maybe one of the key kind of contribution is we use this to the key point
estimation method for each individual camera.
And indeed, we combine them together in this 3D space using a multi-view system.
And in the end, this 3D key point we constructed by using this 2D key point detector.
It turns out they are working extremely well in this challenging problem and we just showed
the result as a total battery reconstruction result.
So in that sense, probably, it would be good to share the 2D detection, post detection
problem our lab is working on.
And that is the open pose work?
Exactly.
Yeah, exactly.
So this 2D body pose detection area is a very popular area.
And one of the most successful areas in computer vision in recent years.
So now we have really great algorithms which can detect this human's body key point, multiple
people's body key point in YouTube video and single image.
And open pose is a version of that.
And one good thing about open pose is this is providing all these facial key point and
body key point and finger to the key point in a single framework in real time.
And multiple papers our lab has been presented is included in this work.
And actually, this is closely related to our panel text studio project because we are
using this detector to reconstruct all the total motion in the end.
And at the same time, we use our system to generate new annotations set to train this
2D detector.
So this is a very interesting idea because usually this multivit system has been used to reconstruct
3D.
But now we believe this multivit system can be a way to generate some 2D annotations for
2D detector because sometimes this generating 2D detector itself can be challenging.
For example, let's say this is one paper we published in last CVPR and the goal is to
make this 2D hand key point detector which is now the part of the open pose.
And the main idea is very simple.
We just wanted to make some data set for 2D hand key point detector.
But just annotating this 2D hand key point is a challenging problem because of all these
side focal illusions.
So at the beginning, we hired some annotators and we asked them to annotate this 2D key point
given some to the image.
But it turns out usually these fingers are glued to each other and just clicking this
finger key point is a challenging problem.
And our idea is if we can capture some data in this multivit system, since we have 500
views, let's say we wanted to capture some finger movement, we wanted to annotate some
key point of some finger movement, then since we have this many views, we can easily
find some good view point to easily annotate the target finger part.
More importantly, if we can have some 3D reconstruction of the target hand, if we can
project this 3D hand to 500 views, each individual view point can have a new annotation by
projecting this 3D hand to this single view.
And we just used this annotation for a neural network architecture to train the 2D detector.
In terms of this, this is extremely successful in making this 2D key point detector and
the key point detector.
So in a way that is, it's kind of a specialized mechanism of data augmentation.
Exactly, exactly.
But in this case, we can use this multi-view supervision so that we can filter out some
noise outputs.
For example, since the original target hand should be in the 3D space, and our image
is just capture of the 3D space in this 2D space, so ideally, if we can generate some
rays from each individual camera, they should intersect in this 3D space, which is the
original 3D joint location.
If they are not, then we can simply say that maybe the detection or 2D measurement is
wrong.
So we can easily filter out all these noisy cases using this multi-view supervision.
And that is a key to make this data augmentation.
Yeah.
Awesome.
Well, Han, thanks so much for taking the time to share this with us.
Are there any final thoughts that you'd like to share to kind of close us out?
Yeah, so currently, we are trying to release entire of our dataset, regenerated from our
panoptic studio.
So people can easily download 500 videos for the same input.
And also, they can get all these 3D annotations regenerated, for example, 3D key point and also
depth information or 3D point cloud for the same target scene, so that we believe people
can use this kind of data to many interesting computer vision and machine learning problem
because people now have some 2D image input.
And they can also have corresponding 3D annotations.
And that can be maybe interestingly trained in many interesting machine learning techniques.
For example, given the single image, can we generate 3D skeleton, given the single
image, can we generate depth data or 3D point cloud because we all captured this all different
sensors output using hardware synchronization and the calibration.
So this can be easily kind of maybe not easy, but this can be in the end used for many interesting
machine learning problems.
Oh, wow.
How many images or videos are you including?
Wow.
Not how many unique kind of scenarios or captures are you including?
So the original data is about 10 hours of many different situations.
So we have captured some musical instruments like playing piano, cello, and so on.
And we also have many social motion capture results, for example, 3D point tracking.
Also we have captured some very simple, example range of motion, which can be easily maybe
useful, much easier kind of problems.
So yeah, and we should collect more and more data and we try to release all of them in
the end.
Awesome.
Well, once again, thank you so much, Tom, for joining us.
Thank you for having me.
Thank you.
All right, everyone, that's our show for today.
For more information on Hambio or any of the topics covered in this episode, visit twimolei.com
slash talk slash 180.
If you're a fan of the podcast, we'd like to encourage you to head over to your Apple
or Google podcast app and leave us a five-star rating and review.
Your reviews help inspire us to create more and better content and they help new listeners
find the show.
As always, thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.