Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast why interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host, Sam Charrington. In this episode of our Deep Learning and Daba series, we're
joined by Airman Kemper, lecturer in the Electrical and Electronics Engineering Department
at Stellan Bosch University in South Africa, and the co-organizer of the endaba.
Airman denied discuss his work on limited and zero resource speech recognition, how those
differ from regular speech recognition and the tension between linguistic and statistical
models in this space. We dive into the specifics of the methods being used and developed in Airman's
lab as well, including how phoneme data is used for segmenting and processing speech.
Before we jump in, I'd like to send a big shout out to our friends at Google AI, which
recently opened up applications for its 2019 residency program.
The Google AI Residency is a one year machine learning research training program with the
goal of helping individuals from all over the world and with a diverse set of educational
and professional backgrounds who come successful machine learning researchers. Find out more
about the program at g.co slash AI Residency. And now on to the show.
Alright everyone, I'm on the line with Airman Kemper. Airman is a lecturer in the Electrical
and Electronics Engineering Department at Stellan Bosch University in South Africa and one
of the organizers for the recent Deep Learning and Daba event. Airman, welcome to this week
in machine learning and AI. Oh, thanks a lot for having me.
I guess we should start with the endaba. The event just finished. I saw an incredible
flow of tweets from the event. It looked amazing from your perspective as an organizer. How
did it go?
I think it went pretty well. I think obviously as the organizers were a lot more aware of
the things that might break behind the scenes but overall it was really successful. I enjoyed
it a lot and from everything I've heard from all the people that was here, I think that's
where we got the biggest encouragement. Just people telling us how much they enjoyed
it and how much they got from the event. So I think it went well.
And the highlights from your perspective?
That's very difficult. I think maybe three things that really stood out for me. It was
two talks. The one was by King Yongchou. He led sessions on basically the fundamentals
of building natural language processing systems and to me was just amazing. The amount of
kind of dense content that he packed into a lecture but then also giving kind of his
high level overview of kind of where the field is going. That was one big thing. The talk
by Jeff Dean at the end, that was just amazing. And then the post decisions which was basically
students from across Africa presenting their work and I've been lucky to be at international
conferences. And this post decision at this African event was just amazing to see the
quality of the work and that the students here are doing.
That's fantastic. Before we dive into some of your research, why don't we have you introduce
yourself to the audience? You are relatively new on the faculty at Stellan Bosch. Tell us
a little bit about your background.
Yeah. So I'm actually a Stellan Bosch boy kind of born and bred. I grew up here. I did
my undergrad and a master's year. And then I also worked for a bit and then I went to
Edinburgh to do my PhD there in the School of Informatics. And that was really amazing in
Scotland. Really struggled with the weather there but other than that, it was an amazing
experience. And then I did a postdoc in Chicago for relatively short time for about a year
at Toyota Technological Institute. And I grew up here. So as soon as I left, I kind of
was campaigning already to come back. I really saw my kind of long-term goals to come back.
And yeah, while I was doing my postdoc, I was very happy to get the appointment here.
Actually, I have a question about TTI Chicago. Is that relatively new? Or is it affiliated
with another school? I lived in Chicago for many years and never heard of it.
Yeah, so it's fairly new. It's really like an institute. It's kind of a lab. It was
funded by Toyota initially, but now it's kind of on its own. And it's a lab that's affiliated
with the University of Chicago. And it's kind of a research-only institution. So you can do
PhD at TTI Chicago. And they do a bit of postgraduate teaching as well. It's actually an amazing
place for specifically machine learning. It's quite a small group, but it's very tight net.
So you have great people in kind of theoretical machine learning, theoretical learning theory,
and then also speech processing, natural language processing, and computer vision.
So Hermann, your research is focused on speech processing. In particular, you're concerned with
how to do speech processing when you don't have a lot of resources. Tell us a little bit more
about what that means. Yeah, so actually this already started while I was doing my masters.
When you want to do, when you want to build speech processing systems, which I think can really
improve people's lives, this works well for English and for German and for Spanish,
because big companies are invested in these languages. And what they do is they collect a lot
and a lot of annotated data. So they get people to say things and then they transcribe it as well.
They give labels to basically the input speech. But there's so many languages on earth that
it's basically impossible to do this for all the languages. So my research focus is really on
very low resource languages, languages for which you just don't have that much data and annotate
the data. So data with labels and actually languages for which you where it might actually be
impossible to get these type of annotated resources. So there's a large proportion of the languages
spoken on the earth that doesn't even have a written form. So you can't write them down.
And if we want to build speech systems for these type of languages, or if you want to maybe kind
of preserve or document these languages, a lot of these languages are dying out. And you want to
build kind of speech processing systems that's able to look at these data sets, then you're in
the setting where you basically don't have any labels at all. You just have a collection of speech
audio. And what you're trying to do is kind of find this structure in the raw audio and to do this
without any form of supervision, any signal. So we call this unsupervised learning. I think a lot
of the listeners might know this. And kind of try to find the raw structure in the audio without
without any guidance. And this really has application. It kind of has this double motivation.
The one motivation is that if we can crack this problem, we can build speech systems in settings
where it was just not possible before for languages that we just can't build systems for at the
moment. And then the second motivation is that a lot of the people that's interested in these
kind of unsupervised model are also interested in how humans learn language. Because human infants
in a sense, they never see any texts labels. They don't get any hard supervision. They're kind of
just bombarded with the stream of audio. And from that, it's kind of a miracle how they then
start to learn language kind of automatically from just this raw sensory input. So people,
they call it zero resource speech processing sometimes. And people that's interested in this
area normally as this double motivation of either building speech systems, practical systems,
or actually using these type of models to investigate language acquisition in humans.
When I think about the trajectory of speech recognition systems over the years, there was this
transition from kind of strongly linguistic based models to more statistical models.
Does the fact that we don't have labeled data kind of push us back towards linguistic
based models or are we still able to operate in the statistical domain? That is an extremely
interesting question. I think a very, very good question because it's something that I think
this unsupervised community, this unsupervised speech community is actually struggling with,
is this question. And I think, so I can kind of say from a practical viewpoint, a lot of the
systems are still very of the, how could it zero resource speech processing systems, although
I might not like the term, but a lot of these zero resource systems still operate in the statistical
domain. So you can think about that is if I give you a ton of data or a collection of data and I
ask you to describe it statistically, then that's basically what it boils down to. At the same time,
I think people in this field are becoming more and more interested in kind of what is the structures
or what is the small things that you need to build into these systems in order for it to actually
learn something. So you might have a statistical system, but you can put in specific cues
that it can, can pick up on. And I think the reason this question is so interesting is,
if we can figure out what type of cues, what type of extract structure, what type of biases
we need to build into our unsupervised models for it to actually learn language, if we can answer
those questions, what are kind of the minimal things that we need to put in, then that might tell
us something about how the type of cues that humans, human infants use to do this. And it's really
interesting because it's also the converse. So people actually are looking, people in this field,
keep a close eye on cognitive studies, cognitive psychologists, who actually try to answer these
questions on infants. So they, we try to read a lot of literature from that side, which tell us
what type of cues do humans use. And in the cognitive literature, there's a lot of studies that
look at what are the cues that infants use. And how can we use some of those ideas and build those
into our systems. I think really what this community is doing is actually seeking the answer to
that question. What are the things that we need to explicitly build in and what should we just
let the model learn? Right. I think it sounds like in, in this field, as in some other areas in
machine learning, there's kind of a pendulum that's swinging that, you know, we started with
these very strongly, you know, physics-based or model-based approaches. And then we kind of swung
hard to statistical-based approaches. And now folks that are kind of on the frontier or, or many,
folks, not all are trying to figure out ways to incorporate the models back into the statistical
approaches to kind of get the best of both worlds. And it sounds like that's what's happening
here as well. Yeah, I think that's right. There's actually a very interesting kind of avenue that
people are starting to explore in this area. And I'm also working on this a little bit.
So infants, they're not just bombarded with raw audio. Of course, infants also have a lot of
other senses, right? Touch and also vision. So there's a group of people, and we're also working
on this, that kind of look at if you have, for example, a speech signal, but it's paired with the
image. So you have a spoken signal. So it's not a written caption, it's a bit of speech, but it
describes an image. Does that image actually allow you to more easily kind of learn the words that
use them in the language? So you might have a picture of people skiing or something, and then
someone describing that image in speech. And then you can kind of use that image to ground the
things that you're discovering. So I think apart from thinking about kind of these linguistic
insights, there's also just this general question of how can we glue different medalities and
different signals together? And that very much operates in a statistical point of view. But again,
we need to figure out what are the specific things that we need to build into these models
for it to actually learn, because it's a very, very hard task if you don't have labels.
It is really interesting how this pendulum actually sues. And I think in the supervised case,
if you have a lot of labeled data, then following a kind of a very pureist, let's just learn from
the raw data approach and learn to predict these labels that we know are important. I think that
makes a lot of sense. But if we're kind of going to this low resource case and generally
machine learning actually, I think there's a lot of evidence that shows that if you don't have
so much labeled data, then building instructors actually helps you in the short term.
You mentioned that the zero resource speech recognition community follows closely what's
happening in the cognitive science community. Are there specific examples of insights from that
community that have advanced the state of the art in your community? That is also a very good
question. And I didn't say, we follow them. I said, we try to follow them. We should follow them
a lot more. Actually, Emmanuel Depou is a researcher in France. And he really is at this intersection
of these two communities. And my supervisor Sharon Goldwater in Edinburgh, she's also very close
to the intersection of these communities. So there's definitely an overlap. I'm trying to think
of concrete examples. I think from, I'll give two quick examples. So actually, and I might not
do it completely justice, but I'll try. There's a lot of evidence that shows that infants can actually
pick up things like syllables. Even before they understand a complete language, they are able to
figure out these puffs, these little bursts of energy, which are syllables. Actually, if you
listen to a language that you don't understand, you would probably, I don't know, maybe you speak
Japanese, but if you listen to Japanese or African, so Tetsonga, you would probably be pretty good
in figuring out where syllables start and end. And human infants are able to do this. So there's
a number of researchers which have tried to explicitly build these things into their models
to explicitly use syllables, or we can kind of use that to guide the systems. And that's one
example. In our own work, what we've been doing is, so there's actually also a lot of evidence
that even before infants can distinguish fine-grained phonemic categories, so this is like the
minimal sound units, you know, vowels and consonants and so on, before they can actually distinguish
these things, or while they're learning to distinguish these sound categories, they can already
identify reoccurring word patterns in speech. So if they keep on hearing specific words,
they can start to identify kind of larger spanning chunks that reoccur. And it's quite interesting
how psychologists test these things in the lab, so they would teach children essentially,
or human infants, like something like Klingon, which obviously the child hasn't heard before,
hopefully. And then they would use eye-tracking experiments to figure out whether the child
has actually learned a specific word. Now, we know from these lab experiments that children are
able to figure out longer spanning word segments. And what we've done in our own work is we've said,
well, okay, if a child can do this, can we actually build that into our model? So maybe you don't know
everything that's going on in the language, but maybe you can run a kind of unsupervised system
that identifies longer spanning words of phrases. You identify these and then you use these as a
signal downstream in building a statistical model or a neural network model to kind of use that
information. And that has proven to be very successful. So when you think about the approaches that
are required to do the zero resource speech recognition, can you walk us through the various
elements of it and how it differs from the way we might approach speech recognition traditionally?
Yeah, that's also a good question. So it's quite of kind of interesting, because this is a
fairly young community. When I started my PhD, there were maybe two groups working on this,
and now all of a sudden, there's like, I don't know, 10, which doesn't sound like a lot, but
in the speech community, that is actually a kind of a big growth. And it's kind of interesting.
I just came back from just before the end of our, we had inter-speech in India, and there
I went to a workshop, spoken language technologies for under-resourced languages. And it was kind of
interesting there, if you look at the type of techniques that the zero resource community is using,
it's a little bit all over the place. And I think it's because we're kind of trying to redefine
the stream that you need to follow, the type of techniques that you need to use, because we're
seeing that a lot of the standard supervised speech processing techniques are just not working.
If you don't have label data, then the trends we're seeing is very different from when you have
label data. To actually answer your question, you've asked just about kind of the little steps
that we take. I think at the moment, it kind of seems like we're converging to maybe two big
important problems that we need to crack first. If I just give you a corpus of audio and Yini's
kind of process there, then the first step you need to do is figure out good what we call features
at the fine grain level. So kind of standard supervised systems will always start in the same way.
They kind of break a speech stream up into these small windows and you hope that the signal
is stationary in that window. And in a supervised system, what we're seeing now is if you break the
speech stream up in this way, and then you feed this into a deep neural network and you tell it that
in this little window, this speech sound occurs, then what the system can do is it can kind of
learn what should it extract from this little chunk of speech to identify a particular sound.
And in the zero resource community, it's very similar. The first step is we need to break it up
into these little overlapping windows. But then our challenge is we need an unsupervised method
to kind of figure out what is it that makes these little speech sounds. And there people are
kind of either using kind of classical echolag Gaussian mixture model based approaches, which
kind of tries to identify these small acoustic units, these kind of sub word units. And then
another group of people are using unsupervised neural networks. And then once you've got features
at this kind of fine grain level, then you need a system on top of that to kind of try and
glue these features together to find structures corresponding to bigger units, things like syllables,
and then words, and then ultimately sentences. And for that, it's also mixed. Some people use
kind of more classical Gaussian mixture based models and unsupervised heat and mark of models.
And I think there's a big push to try and get these neural models, which are working so well
in the supervised case, to also kind of work very well in the zero resource case,
using neural models to discover these word units and sentences ultimately.
Okay, so let me try to recap that to see what I was able to capture. So you've got the speech signals,
and traditionally we'll like window those and try and within a given window, feed that into
a neural network, let's say, along with the label, and then essentially train that neural network
to match those labels to those little segments of speech. And that's more of this right. Yeah.
In this world, we don't have the labels. So we're kind of capturing these windows. And we're using
some number of techniques. Gaussian mixture models are one and the neural networks are another.
But we're trying to identify patterns within these windows, but are we?
So we're kind of comparing across windows in order to do this, is that right?
Yeah, that's right. And I think you're stating three things very carefully. I think that's good.
I think the ideal case what we want is in these kind of short windows,
we want to find a representation which captures something like phonemes, kind of or at least
the small set of units that's used in a particular language. So if I give you a big corpus of
audio, what you want to find is, can I find features that tells me this language uses R,
R, R, R, okay, and in some other language, they might not be the if distinction. And you want a
method to kind of automatically figure out what are the kind of these basic building blocks. So
if I take one window and I get I get a representation for that window and I get another window,
maybe later on and I get a representation for that window, then I want to know that kind of
the fine grain, the sub word unit used in these two windows, although the same or the not.
That's kind of what it boils down to and in the supervised case,
a neural network can kind of figure out exactly what should it look at in the speech stream
to identify the speech sound because I'm telling it what speech sound to look for.
But in the unsupervised case, how do you do this because you don't know?
So you need to start to think about unsupervised models that can do something like
clustering, so a Gaussian mixture model essentially. If I just give you a whole bunch of these
like little windows and I tell you group them according to what you think are phonemes or speech
sounds, then you can start to do that. You can train a Gaussian mixture model in an unsupervised way
and then find these clusters of these groupings of speech sounds that you think are the units
that used in the language. How do you even get the window sizing correct?
I'm imagining that phonemes have different lengths and phonemes over some sample of speech.
You know, maybe one of them is 2x the length of the other and so if you kind of choose a larger
window, you end up with multiple phonemes in the window or at least maybe the end of one in the
start of another. Is it kind of a sliding window approach and you're trying to maximize
something that tells you that you've got a single phonem or are there variable windows?
Like how does that that seems like pretty fundamental to this but also hard?
Yes, it is hard. So actually, supervised systems also have this question like how do you
choose a window? Because you need to, so just to answer your question, we always use a sliding
window. So you kind of have this window that, okay, you need to click a length and then you slide
it across the speech stream. And in the first, the first systems, you take a window and you take
a Fourier transform, which tells you about the spectral content of that window and you just
keep on doing this. So you just slide this across and you look at the spectral content and now
you've got this question of the straight off. If I make the window long, then I've got a lot of
data to kind of tell me what's going on in that window. If I make the window too short, okay,
then I, if I've got a very short window, then I know that it's only going to be one phonem or
part of a phonem, which is kind of fine. If I only get parts of phonemes that's also okay,
I just need to model that. So I might take a very small window, which means that I know that this
is only one speech sound in this window, but then you've got a lot less data to kind of figure
to kind of estimate the content of that window. And this straight off is something that you don't
just see in speech processing. You see it in any type of kind of signal processing task. And
luckily, people in the 80s really fiddled with this and tried to figure out how long should the
window be and how much should I move it. And I mean, I can just tell you the answer now because
people have been trying to do this for 30 years. And so I think the community has a whole,
including the supervised speech community has kind of settled on a relatively specific window
length and then a frame skip. And then so in the supervised community, you kind of you don't
care if it's if if you suite this window across and it's just predicting the same phonem for
multiple windows, then you kind of know that you're in a phoning and then you transition to the
next one. I kind of oversimplify that approach. So what they normally do is they take a window,
you predict the label, then you shift the window, you predict the label, shift the window,
predict the label. And now what you get is kind of the sequence of posteriors over labels.
And that actually goes into another system, a decoder or something that you can train jointly,
which kind of clues these things together and tells you I was in this phoning for this long,
phonemes teach together to form words in this way, words teach together to form sentences in
this way. And in the end, you get a speech recognizer. One question that that raises for me though,
that we've kind of arrived at this answer for the window length and the the stride,
essentially the the step length. But does that suffer from the same asymmetry in terms of
the language that the language is that it's optimized for as speech recognition in general,
like if you're trying to apply these techniques to a language that is under-resourced,
it could be that these values that are traditionally used don't work as well,
are they more properties of human speech than of a given language?
That's a super cool question. Because I think if you read the original papers in the like late
80s and early 90s describing these techniques, a lot of these things were inspired by the human
perceptual system. So they were kind of hand designed initially, they were hand designed to match what
they we know about the human perceptual system. So those papers say that these things are language
universal and I think that's not something that people question a lot. But it is interesting if you
look at supervised system performance on different languages, then if you use the same amount of
data and you compare a English system and you use the same amount of data and you compare that
to a Zulu system, the Zulu system will always perform worse even though it might be trained on
the same amount of data. Now there's a lot of other reasons for that. There can be a lot of other
reasons for that but it's a it's a very interesting question whether we should actually go back to
those first hand engineered question research because they were all evaluated on English,
although the claim was made at their language universe, so they were all evaluated on English
or at least well resource languages. And now we apply these things to Zulu and SOMGA and other languages
and we see that it's just very hard to get these systems to work as well as they do on English,
even if the experiment is controlled. So this was actually I spoke to someone from MIT,
I think it was Jennifer Drexler and she said, ask this question like, are these basic features,
this kind of fundamental questions? Are they overtailer to English because the people that
wrote the papers were English? And I think this euro resource community is starting to ask these
questions or bring that up again because our systems are even more sensitive to these
to these type of decisions. You mentioned that in the case of Zulu, which was the example,
I think you just picked randomly of systems underperforming when trying to recognize that language
that there are some lists of reasons why they do. What are those reasons? That's also difficult
to answer. So I picked Zulu, but I can give you a list of reasons. Very often, so for example,
Afrikans, I think it's SOMGA as well, and I'm not sure about Zulu, are basically languages
that were if we write them down, we often glue words together, they're kind of written as one,
right? So in English, if you have two concepts, then they're written as two separate words,
but in Afrikans, when it's one thing, even though it might be composed of multiple things,
then we write them as one word. Yeah, so it's something like narrow band speech processing,
right? I just said the sentence narrow band speech processing will have a word narrow band speech
processing, okay? But in Afrikans, or in German, you will just write it as one word. It will just
be like one word. And for speech systems, that's something that's very, very tricky to get
right, because you basically don't know when should I split a word and when should it be one.
So that's just one example of a case where it's kind of obvious why the system doesn't perform
as well. Another thing is, so in Sutu, for example, we have tones, which you also have in Mandarin,
and sometimes that's not marked. So you can't see that there's a specific tone being used when
you write something down. Speakers of the language know which tone to use based on the context,
but you can't see it. If you're a non-native speaker, you won't know which tone is being used,
and that might be one other reason why these systems don't perform as well as English. And this
is all apart from the kind of what features do we actually put in that to begin with. Those
were just two examples. Code switching is another big example, specifically in South Africa. So
a lot of the time what we do is we switch between languages in a single sentence. So very often,
you would switch between your native language and English and then switch back. So if you just
look at the output of your speech recognizer, it just got all those words wrong. And a lot of
corpora actually have this code switching in them. It just jumped out at me that even that code
switching alone sounds like an interesting research area for these types of systems. Are there
folks out there specializing in that? Yeah, there are. So actually in the lab downstairs,
there's a whole bunch of people working on this. And there was a special session I think at
Interspeech as well. And in here, just a while ago, focusing specifically on code switching,
because it's something that happens a lot in South Africa because we have a live and official
languages and they're kind of all spoken geographically in overlapping regions. But in other parts
of Africa, it also happens. And then also in a lot of Asian countries and India, this happens a
lot. So people are I think like over the last five years, maybe people have really started to work
on this. And it's not just even in spoken language, also in written language. People, for example,
in tweets would switch between different languages. And that really messes up these NLP systems,
which are kind of tailored for specific language or speech recognition. You kind of build a system
for language. And that really messes up the system. So there's a lot of interesting questions
about how you build these models to kind of handle arbitrary switches between language.
So I think I was trying to recap your representative flow for low resource speech processing.
And I think I got to like the beginning of the first step. Right.
So we talked about this windowing. We talked about this windowing thing and using Gaussian
mixture models to try to determine what phonemes are spoken or in the case of unsupervised,
you're trying to, well, I guess the same thing. You're trying to determine the, like the
universe of phonemes and which ones are represented in an individual sample. And if that's close to
correct, what's next? Yeah. Okay. So now let's say we figure that out. Now what I give you is,
now I can take a bit of speech and then I can kind of pause it through this feature representation
model. And that could just tell me this phonem is present, this phonem is present, this phonem,
and you don't know whether it's a phonem. So it's more like pseudo phonem, or maybe just cluster.
Okay. Now you've got the sequence of clusters or sequence of pseudo phonemes. And okay,
that's helpful. Okay. Maybe you can use that if you're, if you're a language documenting a
language, then that can maybe prove insightful. But if you actually want to build a speech processing
system, you need to go from that to words or some higher level unit. And that in itself is quite
tricky. And it's because of this reason that you already alluded to that one word can be three
phonemes long. Another word can be five phonemes long. Another word can be two phonemes long. So how
do you group these things according to words? And that's very, very difficult. So kind of the
classic approach to doing this is kind of a type of compression model. So what you try and do
is you try to say, okay, if I treat these three units, reoccurring units as a word, how much does
that allow me to kind of compress these sequences? And so you, that's just, that's just one approach.
So but essentially what you need to do is you now need to add a model on top of these unsupervised
discovered phonemes to tell you how you group these clusters together to form words. And there's
maybe I don't know a handful of techniques that you can use to do this. Should I talk through them?
Please. Okay. Yeah. So people at MIT actually, when they started doing this, Jackie Lee and
Jim Gloss, they had a hidden mark of model, which you can kind of train on top of these pseudo phonemes
sequences. And they actually broke down their model. The whole thing is trained in kind of one
go. So at the bottom, you've got a kind of a Gaussian mixture model, which you can interpret as
finding these phone-like units. And then on top of that, now you've got the sequence of phone-like
units. So you feed them into a hidden mark of model, which is kind of like a sequence Gaussian
mixture model. And you treat that hidden mark of model that they are on top of that as syllables.
And then on top of that, now you're getting out the sequence of syllables. And
using the sequence of syllables, now you can train another hidden mark of model. I haven't
had another hidden mark of model layer on top of these syllable layers to model words.
And the whole thing is kind of trained in as one big. They used, I think,
Gibbs sampling to train this whole thing from the bottom up to the top and so on.
And that's one approach. And that seemed to work pretty well if you have single speakers,
because that really messes things up. But if you go to multiple speakers, then that becomes
much harder. I can tell you about our approach if you're interested.
I am, but I guess it just occurred to me that there's...
So, right, we'd ask this question. There's like a fundamental thing missing for me,
and maybe I need to step back and ground out on the goal of this. We're talking about going
from speech to text. Is that correct or no? No. You're basic? Okay. Okay. You're awesome.
I was wondering where there's like a, you know, then the miracle occurs step in here,
and I'm not seeing it. So what you want is impossible, right? So what you want is you want to
ground this in some way. And if you don't have text, you just can't do this. You can't do it.
Okay. So why do you want to do this? I'll give you two reasons, and then I'll ask your question
of what even are we, do we want to do? Yeah. So what you want to do is if I give you a big
corpus of audio, then what I want is I want you to figure out where words start and end in the
speech stream. I want you to snap it up the speech into these things that look like words.
Okay. And then if I, if I tell you, okay, these are the word boundaries, okay, which you've predicted.
Then I want you to tell me this snippet. I don't know what word it is, but this snippet also reoccur
is here and here and here and here and here and here in my speech corpus. So it's this combination
of segmentation breaking it up into things that look like words. And then the second part,
which is clustering, grouping these words together. Now, okay. So that's what we want to do. You
want to know why this is useful? Sure. Okay. So I mean, I'm imagining that it's useful in that I
could take that data and have a prioritized list of words to get someone to transcribe for me and
then start to figure out texts. You know, if that's what I ultimately want, but why else would it be
useful? Exactly. Okay. So that's a great use case that you've just described there. But the years
to two more reasons. Okay. One, if you want, if you're interested in how infants do this,
then having a model that can do this is useful. So then you can fiddle around with the model,
check the type of mistakes that the model makes and see if then you can go and test in a lab if
infants use the same type of cues and whether they make the same type of mistakes. And in that way,
we can actually learn something about how humans learn language. Okay. I'm not a cognitive,
a cognitive modeling person, cognitive scientist. So I probably didn't describe that well, but that
is one motivation. A third motivation is, and this is actually a project that I'm working on
with some of the colleagues here, is the following setting where this project is in Uganda.
It's actually a project within United Nations. And they're really interested in
very, very specific keywords. They have these systems that collect broadcast news.
So it's basically servers that capture radio broadcasts. And then you've got the server full
of speech data, but you don't have a speech recognizer in Uganda, the language that's spoken
there. Okay. But now as the United Nations, you're really interested in figuring out what people
are talking about in these local radio broadcasts. So what you can do is you can get a small number
of people. And you can tell them, listen, I'm really interested in education. I'm really interested
in maybe specific diseases, maybe in specific disasters, things like that. And I can get a small
number of people to give me a bunch of keywords that I'm interested in. Okay. Now I've got my unsupervised
model. I can label these keywords that a small number of people have given me. And then what I can
do is I can go and search this big corpus of audio and find all the radio broadcasts that
contains those keywords. And then maybe I can pass only those broadcasts to an analyst and ask
them, please just translate these ones. I know they're important to me. And then we can, I don't know,
figure out what people are talking about in Uganda. I hope that makes sense. Yeah, no, that does,
that does make, that does make a lot of sense. And so you were about to describe the approach that
you use in your lab to go from the phoning data to the segmenting. Yeah. So I actually want to
answer another question first. Okay. Let me answer this question. And then I'll answer your other
question, which was about grounding. How do you actually know what people are talking about when
you don't have any labels? Okay. So I'll first answer the question about what we use. And this is
really a technique that I developed and my PhD of my supervisors. So we basically argued that
this idea of getting these fine grained units. And then, and then having a syllable layer on top
of that and then a word layer on top of that, that becomes quite here. The whole thing becomes
quite difficult. So what we've been doing is we've been thinking about this idea of something
called acoustic word embeddings. So I think a lot of people know what word embeddings are. It's
these kind of continuous vector representations of written words. And we wanted to take that same
idea to speech. So when you're building these language discovery systems, inevitably what happens
is you end up having to compare two snippets of speech with each other, but they're not of the
same length. Okay. Two words are never the same length. Even if I say Apple and use Sam says Apple
then these two apples will not have the same duration. So inevitably you end up comparing things
that's of different duration, a half a second, one to one second. So what we started to develop
was these acoustic word embeddings. And the idea behind these are basically you'd take a variable
duration segment of any duration and you train them, you have a model that just maps that sequence
that chunk of speech you map that to a single vector. Okay. Now if you could do this,
what you could do is you can just embed basically all the sequences in your language. You can
embed all of them, get vectors for each of them and now you can easily compare the different vectors.
And in very short what we, what I developed in my PhD is something that kind of does this jointly.
It starts by, it basically breaks the speech stream up into things that it thinks are words.
It's random, it doesn't know. It embeds all of these. It classes those things into things that
it now thinks are words and then it goes back and resegments and it has this kind of back and forth
thing. I don't know if that makes sense and there was a 30 second discussion about something
it took me four years to do. Are you kind of iteratively creating this embedding space and then
performing some operations on it to try to determine the segments and then updating the embedding
space and like kind of optimizing the embedding space or were you saying something else about this,
I kind of picked up on an iterative cycle in there but I'm not sure what the, the iterations are.
Yeah, you should have, you should have written the abstract for my thesis. So what you just said
is exactly right. So you start with like a random segmentation of your input corpus and then
on that random segmentation you build an embedding space. Now if I actually have an embedding space,
okay, initially it's, it's going to be pretty bad, okay, but I have an embedding space.
Then what you can do is you can say, given this embedding space, how should I split up my input
stream to kind of have a higher score if you want under this embedding space? Okay, so you go back,
you resegment. Let me pause you there. So yeah, you've got this embedding space and are you doing
some kind of clustering within the embedding space? Exactly right. So I actually use a Gaussian
mixture model. I also played a, a Bayesian Gaussian mixture model and I've also played around with
some non parametric like infinite Gaussian mixture models to do that. So the idea behind these
embeddings are that if you say Apple and I say Apple, then we're going to have two embeddings
and we want all the instances of specific words that are acoustically the same
to end up in similar regions in this embedding space. So that's really the goal.
But when you start out, you don't know where words, whether words start an end, so you kind of
start randomly. And then what you do is so you start randomly, you get all these embeddings
and now you group them, okay, and you cluster them, I usually Gaussian mixture model to do the clustering.
And the idea is that every cluster in the Gaussian mixture model should be hypothesized word.
It should be something that you think or the model at the moment think that this thing,
this group of embeddings, they all correspond to the same type of word, the same word, okay,
initially that's wrong, but that's what you kind of hope where the model ends up.
So you cluster, you start, you snap off your speech, you embed, you get this embedding space,
you cluster in that embedding space using a Gaussian mixture model.
Now, under this Gaussian mixture model, I can now say, go back to my inputs,
pretend I don't know where the words came from. And under this Gaussian mixture model, how should
I split up the speech stream so that I get a higher score under my current Gaussian mixture model
or the embeddings that I would get if I split it up, okay. So then you break it up and then you
re-embed and then you build your Gaussian mixture model again. Under that model, you go back and say,
even these groupings of words, how should I chunk up my speech to get a higher score? And you just
kind of iterate through this thing. Now, I describe it as this iterative process, but actually,
it's implemented this one, Gibbs sampler. So it's this one model that kind of does things in one go.
The projecting backwards step there where you are asking the question, given a set of groupings,
how could you change the segmentation to improve the groupings? Is that a difficult piece in this
or is that a pretty straightforward element? No, that is a difficult piece. So that's where I spend
a lot of my time. Okay, also, there's two answers. It is a difficult piece, but it is also something
that people have been looking at for a relatively long time. Meaning in the context of an embedding
space or in other contexts and it carries over? No, in other contexts, kind of in computer science
in general, but specifically in, actually, it came from the NLP literature. So it actually
comes from a different part of literature. So in Chinese, you have this problem that we don't know
where words start like Chinese than the way it's written. It's written with outward boundaries.
So in that literature, people have started to look at, if I kind of know the words in my language,
or I think I know the words in my language, how can I figure out where all the word boundaries
in Chinese? And using that silent type of ideas, that's exactly what we used here, except that now
we're doing it on this kind of continuous embedding space, but the mathematics for that is very,
very similar to this question of, if I give you an unsegmented Chinese corpus, how do you figure
out where there's words? So it ends up being like a dynamic programming procedure where you
basically ask, okay, I'm going to start at the end of my sentence, and then what I'm going to do
is I'm going to say, okay, words can be between 200 milliseconds and one second. Okay, so you're
built in that constraint. And then what you do is you basically say, okay, I'll start at the end
of my sentence. If the last word in my sentence is 200 milliseconds long, what's the score?
If it's 250 milliseconds long, what's my score? If it's 300 milliseconds long, what's my score? Okay,
and then you basically looking for all the possible word segmentations in this range,
and then you kind of get an overall score using a dynamic programming method for figuring out where
words started in the speech stream. And the score in this case is what? Yeah, so the score, if we're
just looking at a single question of should I put a word boundary year or not, then the score is
basically, if I chunked up this chunk of speech and I treated that as a word, how likely will that
be? How close would that be to a cluster mean under my current plus string? Does that make sense?
You're trying to set your segments up so that as many of the segments as possible are words
basically? That's right. You can think about that. It's not really as many as possible. It's kind of like
if I gave you, if I gave you an utterance, a whole sentence, and I told you big places that you
want to put boundaries, big places that you want to put boundaries, that if I look at the overall
okay, so now you put boundaries, now you have a whole bunch of different embeddings, right?
And you want to look at the overall score for that utterance. Each of the embeddings gets a score
and what you want to maximize is kind of the overall score for that specific utterance.
One last piece you mentioned that as opposed to the multiple phases, you do everything in kind of
one pass with Gibbs sampling. Can you give us kind of the high level overview of Gibbs sampling and
how you apply it here? Yeah. Okay, so Gibbs sampling is this very cool technique where
you basically try to get samples from a distribution and in general that's tricky, especially if your
model is quite complicated. So what Gibbs sampling does is it basically keeps everything fixed
and you want to know, you want to get a sample for a latent variable. So in our case, the latent
variable might be something like which clause does this embedding get assigned to? Okay, so
so in Gibbs sampling, how it works is you pick a specific latent variable and you keep all your
other latent variables, you keep that fixed at previous samples. Okay, and then what you say is
given that all the others are fixed, sample this thing from my distribution, this one that I'm
interested in. Okay, after you sample that one, now you keep this guy fixed and you go to the next
latent variable. Okay, you keep all the others fixed and now you sample from this guy,
then you go on to the next latent variable and so forth. Does that make sense? Okay, so in our case,
what we do is we basically say given we've got this entire corpus, the whole corpus have been
segmented and they've been clustered already. Okay, everything is fixed and we pretend we know where
words start and end and we know we pretend we know which clusters they should belong to.
Okay, then what you do is you take one utterance in your dataset and you say now I'm going to
take this utterance and I'm going to remove that from my model and I'm going to pretend that
this is the only utterance that I don't know the segmentation and the clustering of.
So you remove that utterance and then you say given the model which is now defined by all the
rest of the utterances for which I know the word boundaries and the clusters, what is the best
segmentation for this utterance? Okay, and then what you do is you segment the utterance according to
all of the rest of the data that's been fixed and you clustered that utterance and then what you do
is you fix the segmentation and the clustering for that utterance and you go to the next utterance
and so basically your this utterance procedure that I kind of said was like segment cluster segment
cluster and I kind of described it at the corpus level, it's really happening at kind of a per utterance
level. Interesting. And I want to answer one question that you asked really early on or just a while
ago, you asked if you're just going to do this right, you're never going to get to text, you're
never going to figure out exactly what is the meaning in this utterance right, you're going to
segment that and that that's exactly what's going to happen. I don't know if you saw this movie
arrival. Yes. Yeah, some people loved it, some people hated it, I really liked it, but there's
the scene where they go to her and they ask her, I mean they play her the snippet of audio,
right? And she's a linguist, a linguist that documents languages, so they play her the snippet
of audio and then asks her, listen, what is being said in this language? And she looks at them and
tells them in a very, it's probably very unholy word, but tells them, I can't help you, right?
I have no idea what this snippet of audio means because I don't have any context, I haven't seen
the people that speak these things, I haven't seen when they use it, when they do not use it.
And a lot of the research into the zero processing models is exactly like that. We just want to see
how can you learn something from the raw audio and infants can do this to some extent and our
models can do this to some extent and then there are these good use cases for these models,
but ultimately you can never figure out what does this word actually mean. And this is why a lot
of people in this space are moving to the setting where you have other signals that goes with the
speech. So if you have a chunk of unlabeled speech but you have an image describing the context in
which the speech is used, because if you can do that then you can segment your words hopefully
and then figure out, okay, this word, I don't know what it is, but I can ground it because I have
an image and I can try and figure out what is it in the image that calls this word to being said.
So that's a very, very interesting avenue for feature work that a lot of people are looking at.
Well, I was going to ask you, if you had some words on where you see this going, but that sounds
like you anticipated that question there. Maybe final thoughts, again, circling back to
where we started all this on the endaba and you know what you see for that community and more
broadly machine learning and AI in Africa. Yeah, so this I think it's a super exciting time for
machine learning and AI in Africa and the endaba is one part of that and that has really started
I think to both communities and kind of bring people together and in Africa and kind of
helped people to see that the stuff we're doing here is very, very relevant also at the broader
scale. I was quite a broad question so I'll give a whole bunch of small answers.
One thing that I'm very excited about is that in Africa we have very unique challenges
and unique opportunities and so taking language as an example there's so many languages spoken
here in the same geographical area and that's very, very unique and I think what's going to happen
if we start to push this community forward and if people actually believe that they can do this
because we can then what I think is going to start to happen and I hope for this is that we're going
to start to develop unique solutions for our unique problems and I think if that happens it's
not just going to be like we are users of machine learning tools that's being developed in Europe
of course we need to be that as well we need to solve our problems using the tools that's being
developed in Europe and in the US but I think if we start to solve the problems here then we
are actually going to start to contribute to the global scene and we're going to start to say
this and this is a unique solution and actually you guys can also use this in some other problem
areas in machine learning so I think it's going to be a combination of developing exciting
applications but then also contributing to foundational research in machine learning and AI
and that's I think that's really what I hope will happen. Being Dava is growing a lot it's going
to Kenya next year which is super exciting and then in Dava has this kind of dual motivation the
one is to strengthen machine learning and AI in Africa but then also to fix the problems of
diversity in ML and I hope that that is something that Africa can also contribute to because
I mean Google can just start to hire a lot more African researchers right and from across the world
I think that would be very exciting. For me personally the thing that excites me most is actually
the in Dava spin-offs I'm very passionate about developing local communities because I think
so in the Cape area for example there's a lot of people working on ML and we can learn a lot
from each other but up until fairly recently a lot of people have worked in isolation so I'm very
very passionate about building local things at universities and in regions and the in Dava X is
a spin-off of the in Dava kind of funding these local regional little in Davas and I think that's
that's really where we're going to see some some interesting things happening people starting to
collaborate and and and working together and I'm very excited to see what will happen there.
Fantastic fantastic well Erman thank you so much for taking the time to chat with us this
morning it's really really interesting research you're doing and I enjoyed learning about it.
Cool thanks so much for having me.
All right everyone that's our show for today. For more information on Erman or any of the topics
covered in this show visit twimmelai.com slash talk slash 191. For more information on the deep
learning in Dava podcast series visit twimmelai.com slash in Dava 2018. Thanks again to Google
for their sponsorship of this series be sure to check out the 2019 AI residency program at g.co
slash AI residency as always thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.