Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast why interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
For those challenged with promoting the use of machine learning in an organization and
making it more accessible, one key to success is to support data scientists and machine
learning engineers with modern processes, tooling and platforms.
This is a topic that we're excited to address here on the podcast with this AI Platforms
Podcast series as well as a series of eBooks that we'll be publishing on this topic.
The first of these eBooks takes a bottoms up look at AI Platforms and is focused on the
open source Kubernetes project, which is used to deliver scalable machine learning infrastructure
at places like Airbnb, booking.com and open AI.
The second book in the series looks at scaling data science and ML engineering from the top
down, exploring the internal platforms that companies like Airbnb, Facebook and Uber
have built and what enterprises can learn from them.
If these are topics you're interested in and especially if part of your job involves
making machine learning more accessible, I'd encourage you to visit Twimbleai.com slash
AI Platforms and sign up to be notified as soon as these books are published.
Alright, in this episode of our AI Platforms Podcast series, we're joined by Bicheng Chen,
principal staff engineer and applied researcher at LinkedIn.
Bicheng and I caught up to discuss LinkedIn's internal AI automation platform ProML, which
was built with the hopes of providing a single platform for the entire life cycle of developing
training, deploying and testing machine learning models at the company.
In our conversation, Bicheng details ProML, breaking down some of its major components including
its feature marketplace, model creation tooling and training management system to name just
a few.
We also discussed LinkedIn's experience bringing ProML to the company's developers and the
role of the company's AI Academy has played getting them up to speed.
We're excited to have LinkedIn as a sponsor and supporter of the show and to include their
story in this series.
And now on to the show.
Alright everyone, I am on the line with Bicheng Chen.
Bicheng is a principal staff engineer and applied researcher at LinkedIn.
Bicheng, welcome to this week in machine learning and AI.
Yeah, it's very nice to be here.
I'm excited to have you on and to learn more about what LinkedIn is doing to support its
AI efforts.
But before we dive into that, you currently lead machine learning algorithms and tooling
at LinkedIn.
Can you tell us a little bit more about your role and your background, how you got to where
you are?
My current responsibility is to ensure LinkedIn has the right machine learning and AI technology
and also ensure our developers are productive using this technology.
I have been always interested in machine learning since college.
I still remember that probably 20 years ago, I'm doing neural network for face detection.
Then in my PhD study, I was in a database group, but my research is always on how to apply
machine learning to database systems to make data systems more intelligent.
And after I graduated, I joined Yahoo Research and started my career in recommender systems.
So in addition to publishing papers and also a book on statistical methods for recommender
system, we also designed the recommending algorithms for the Yahoo homepage, Yahoo News
and some other applications.
And something we find to be very interesting is that for recommendation system to work
very well, human and algorithm combination is very, very important.
So human being are very good at selecting good candidate articles for recommendation.
And that algorithms are very powerful to identify the user's interest and do depersonization
and quickly react to changes in the user behavior.
And after that, I joined LinkedIn about six years ago.
I started by working on news recommendation and also feed ranking algorithms.
And I'm amazed that LinkedIn has a very unique and a very rich data sets.
So we have a pretty large member base like more than 500 million members and more than
30 million companies and also a lot of like open jobs that people can apply to you.
And another unique aspect is for every member, LinkedIn has very good profiles of those
members, which are difficult to find other places for web companies.
And in addition to those profiles, we have people's connection, we have people's interaction,
we have users activity, people are seeking jobs, people are consuming content on LinkedIn
and also learning courses on LinkedIn.
And each member also have different roles.
Some people are seeking jobs, some people are hiring people, some people are consuming
content, some people are using LinkedIn as a platform to publish content.
So there's a lot of connections we want to make between users so that everyone has the
best opportunities.
After around probably two years ago, I started to lead a group which designs the algorithms
and also tools to help LinkedIn to be able to use machine learning and AI technology in
all of our products.
So you've talked about some of the unique assets that LinkedIn has in terms of its members
and the profiles and the connections between those members.
What are some of the machine learning and AI applications that are in place at LinkedIn?
Yeah.
So machine learning is used almost in every product in LinkedIn.
So just give a few examples.
If you open LinkedIn homepage, you see a feed of updates from your connections.
So those are articles shared by your connections and also their professional change.
For example, they change a job or they have a job anniversary.
So we use machine learning to rank these different types of items so that we can maximize
users engagement.
And also in the feed, we also have sponsored updates.
So company, they are paying thing to put updates in the feed so that they can get attention.
And we use machine learning to predict the click rates of these different more like
device advertisements and so that we can maximize the revenue and also the optimizer's value.
And also we recommend people to people.
So for social network, growing a person's network is very important.
So we look at people's connection structure and try to identify the connection strength
between two users and then make recommendations that you may be interested in connecting
to these people.
And we also use machine learning in different search problems.
So for example, recruiters come to LinkedIn to search for potential candidates.
And we use machine learning to help recruiters to find the best candidate that can feed their
need.
And also in addition to recruiting product, we also have a sales solution product to help
sales people to find leads that can lead to potential like sales opportunity.
And this is also using machine learning to find the right connection between the people.
Can you talk a little bit about the evolution of tooling for machine learning at LinkedIn?
So we started by developing machine learning algorithms on Hadoop.
And I think several years ago, we find that using Hadoop may not be the best or the most
efficient way of doing machine learning computation.
So we start to develop algorithms on Spark.
And we find that the ML leap coming from the Spark package is not efficient enough.
So we develop our own training algorithm called PhotonConnect PHOTON Photon ML.
And we open source that so that like everyone can also use that.
And in addition to algorithms, we also look at how people can deploy model into our production
systems.
And in the past, deploying model into product systems has been pinpoint.
There's a lot of co-development that people need to do.
And our current effort is to make this whole process as automatic as possible.
OK, and is Photon ML is that a replacement for ML lib that also runs within Spark or
does that?
Is there another engine for that?
That is another engine.
And internally, we basically mainly use Photon ML for our model training purpose.
And we are not using ML leap because ML leap, at least in our experience, doesn't really
scale to the amount of data that we need to process.
And so it's Photon ML replacement for Spark or just the ML lib piece.
And do you still run within Spark?
Yeah, that's correct, right?
Just a replacement for ML leap.
We are still running using Spark.
Maybe before we dig deeper into kind of the tooling and platform side, can you talk a
little bit about the developer audience for your tooling efforts at LinkedIn or you targeting
primarily kind of applied researchers or how diverse is the audience that you're supporting
with the various tools that you're building?
The initial audience that we support are the machine learning developers, right?
So those are the people who design algorithms for our application, use machine learning
to make the best decision for a different LinkedIn product.
That's our initial focus.
But at the same time, we also recognize that we really need to scale machine learning development
and LinkedIn.
We made an effort to educate our self-engineers to be able to apply machine learning.
We call that AI Academy LinkedIn, so that is a five week training program that our engineer
can participate to learn about machine learning and later, they can also apply machine learning
to their application area.
So gradually, the tooling that we're building will also support those people who graduate
from AI Academy.
They don't have a lot of past machine learning background, but they are learning to use machine
learning and apply machine learning to our applications.
Before we kind of dug into the question about the developer audience, you walked us through
this evolution from Hadoop to Spark ML Lib to Photon ML.
LinkedIn also has a machine learning platform that you call ProML.
That's correct.
Tell us about ProML and the relationship between it and these other tools that you've
mentioned.
Okay.
So ProML is an initiative to double productivity for ML developer, and this platform provides
functionalities for the entire machine learning life cycle.
So starting from a feature marquee place, in which people can share and find potentially
useful features and manage features for their machine learning model.
And the second is model creation tooling.
So this involves all the tools we use to train machine learning model and also specify
the computation logic of machine learning model.
So Photon ML belongs to this category.
So Photon ML is one of the tools in ProML ecosystem.
And we also develop algorithms to automatically select features and also automatically selecting
hyper parameters for your machine learning models.
And a third area is model deployment in which we develop tools to manage all the previously
trend models and allow users, like LinkedIn internal users, to click on a button to publish
the model and then deploy the model into various places in our production systems.
And a third, the fourth area is model inference engine in which we provide the runtime environment
to run the model and to serve user traffic.
And the fifth area is what we call health assurance.
So in which we provide tools to automatically monitor the model performance and also data
quality to ensure that our models are performing well.
And we also provide anomaly detection capability so that when something goes wrong, we can quickly
identify them.
And after we identify issues, we also provide debug and explain tooling so that people can
investigate and find the reason that caused the issue.
OK, it sounds like there's a ton for us to dig into the air.
Maybe let's start at the beginning and talk about the feature marketplace.
What's the motivation for the feature marketplace?
So I think feature marketplace is also, I think, one of the quite unique area that we are
looking at.
So the reason that we start this feature marketplace effort is that in the past, different teams,
they have different pipelines to produce features.
And what we observe is that there are different teams.
They develop very similar features.
There's a very little leverage across the teams.
And also the pipeline that generate features over time get very complicated, right?
So we get into a pipeline jungle that at some point, for some application, become very
difficult to manage.
So the effort of feature marketplace is to simplify all these so that we provide a
abstraction layer. In this abstraction layer, the feature producers, they use simple configuration
to set up features by defining the location of the feature and the extraction logic of
the feature.
After that, the feature users, they can just use a unique name to refer to the feature.
And the system will automatically figure out where to get the feature and how to extract
the feature.
And when you say the feature location, what are you referring to there?
Is that like a source system or is it, what are we referring to?
Yep. So location refers to the source of the features of example.
We need features for model training offline, for example, Hadoop.
So then the location will be a path on HDFS.
And when we do online serving, the features may come from, for example, a key value store.
So in that case, the location will be the address of that particular service.
So you've got kind of the source of the feature data.
And then it sounds like you're also providing a way to declaratively specify some sequence
of feature transformations.
Is that right?
Is that part of it?
Yeah, that is correct.
So there are a few common logic that people use to produce useful feature.
One is sliding window aggregation. So basically, you look at a user's past activity and aggregate
the activity to identify their interest.
So for example, if we saw that a user's frequently clicked on an article that mentioned a particular
company.
So then we know that the user probably is interested in that company.
So one of the concepts that comes up in some of my conversations around features and
repeatable pipelines is the notion of a DAG or a graph for applying these different transformations
are you using some kind of metaphor like that?
Yes, that's correct.
There are two kind of DAGs in our system.
So one DAG is for this feature computation.
Another DAG is for the model computation logic.
So in the feature computation DAG, that can include, for example, aggregation and also join.
So from a key, we can look up.
So for example, if we look at a feature for a member, so from the member, we know the
indenting, right?
We know the job title of the member and from the job title, we can look up for more information
about the job title that in term can become a feature for the member.
So such a join look up are all in the DAG that process the feature.
Do you run into the issue of kind of the leaky abstraction problem around features where
a team will define a feature?
And it has kind of very specific semantics to the problem that they're trying to solve
and someone else might find it in a marketplace or catalog and want to use it, but it doesn't
quite fit.
And if you do run into that, how do you address that?
Yes, I think different teams, always, right, may define some feature that is very specific
to their application.
And in that case, while those features probably won't be that shareable, however, there
are a large number of features that can be shared across different applications, especially
on the features that capture a user's interest, right?
So for example, users' interest in different kinds of jobs can be used to, for example,
rank the content like articles for the user also, right?
So for example, you look at job activity that a particular user is interested in jobs
from a particular company, then when we rank articles, then we can potentially rank
articles about that company higher, right, so that user can get a value.
And are the features that groups define and publish out to this marketplace, are they?
I'm thinking of like different version control metaphors, like forkable and I guess mainly
that's the one I'm thinking of.
Like can you fork these things and extend them to make them more, to tailor them to specific
use cases or are they kind of more static?
So the way that we are managing the features is the following, we try to reduce the dependencies
of features on other features, because I think when we have more and more dependency, then
it becomes something that would be difficult to manage.
So we tend to treat each feature as a independent unit, and if you need to modify the feature,
to some extent you fork or you copy and then you make all the changes and become another
like independent features.
I'm curious, what are the, it's just kind of wrapping up the feature marketplace component.
What are the key things that you've learned in kind of producing and supporting this
particular component in terms of the way folks use features and the most important
things to consider when you're thinking about creating some kind of reusability for
features?
I think something that we learn is that a abstraction layer for feature access is very
important.
This abstraction layer gives the user a very simple view of how you can use a feature,
basically you just refer to a user by its name, right?
And then the system basically just automatically figured out where to find the feature and
how to extract feature.
I think this greatly simplify the way that people use feature.
And when you refer to features here, it sounds like you're referring to kind of a higher
level concept that is analogous to a pipeline as opposed to a low level, you know, I've
heard it, you know, sometimes referred to as like a snapshot in time of data, right?
And so you've got these features, you've got features, then you can kind of fast forward
or kind of go back in time and kind of access features at different time points and things
like that.
Are you addressing, does your model address that as well?
I think that that is a great question.
We are currently building that capability, I think yeah, so the ability of looking at
the feature at different time point is a very important functionality.
The next part of the promo that you mentioned was kind of the interface for kind of building
new models.
What does that look like from a user perspective?
Just make sure I understand this correctly, when you say user, you mean the user of machine
learning tooling.
Right.
The developer.
Yes.
Over the year, right?
We found that there are three types model that are very useful for LinkedIn application.
One is the tree models, usually that is a set of trees like a gradient boosted trees.
And a certain type of model we find to be very useful is like deep learning models, right?
Those are the neural networks.
And a third type of model that we find to be also very useful is a deep personalization
model.
Those models try to learn a set of model parameters for each individual user.
And the tool we provide is a method to allow people to connect or combine different type
of model together, right, into a deck structure.
Right.
So for example, you can first apply tree models to learn the interactions right between
users and for example, jobs, right, if we are talking about like job recommendation.
And then after that, you may have another model neural network, right, that try to learn
the representation of the member and also learn the representation of jobs, right?
Through a neural network, we generate a vector that represent the behavior of the user and
that behavior of job, and we can combine all these together into features into our deep
personalization model and the tooling will building basically give people the flexibility
of peak and choose different type of model and then combine them together into a deck.
And then we do model training to train all these models together is the implication there
that the feature marketplace and these DAGs has some kind of first class notion of the
type of a feature or the type of features inputs or outputs that can be used to validate
this DAG.
Yes.
So at the type of features, what we are currently developing is, well, tensor, right, so
which is pretty much the same as other tools.
However, we want the tensors to also carry semantic meanings, right?
So if you look at say tensor flow, each tensor basically just a numeric array of multiple
dimensions, but to be able to like validate the features and also help the developer to
understand the feature, we want to add semantic to the dimensions, right?
So for example, one dimension of the tensor may represent, for example, skills of the
user.
But another dimension may represent, for example, companies of a job, for example, right?
So we won't be able to capture all these semantic meaning and so that our tensor type, when
user look at the tensor, they can understand the tensor better.
And that can also be used in our later validation.
And now that I'm envisioning this, you know, almost kind of a wizzy wig drag and drop kind
of thing, is that the direction you're headed or using more of a Jupiter notebook or kind
of a code based way of constructing these graphs?
Yeah, we are using code based approach rather than imagine that would be your, yeah, I
think yeah, drag and drop is easy to create some small DAG, right?
But if you manage a large DAG, I think that code based is important.
Are notebooks a paradigm of choice at LinkedIn?
Yes, we use notebook mainly for data analysis and also the first stage of modeling.
Usually people do like portal typing, but I want to try out different ways of specifying
your model, we use notebook for that.
But for our production model training workload, we are not using Jupiter notebook.
Okay.
And so it sounds like there's not particularly any effort or interest in integrating the
notebooks, like automating the notebook to production pipeline.
It's a kind of ad hoc analysis tool and then if someone's going to produce something
that eventually is targeting production, they're starting from, you know, they're starting
in an IDE more often than not.
Yeah, that's correct.
That's the current usage, however, we are also evaluating the potential of using notebook
for manage production training, but that's still in the exploration phase.
So you've got these, you've got models that are developed in notebooks and in code connected
via these graphs.
I think the next component of Fremel is a component that manages the training environments
and training clusters, is that right?
Yes, the way that we manage training is mainly through Hadoop and the Spark.
Our data all stored on Hadoop cluster and we use Spark to coordinate training of different
types of models.
And after training, we need to deploy the models into our production environment.
There's another workflow management to take the model we trained and the data available
on Hadoop, the model available on Hadoop and deploy that into different places in our
production environment.
And I think that is actually quite challenging problem in our system.
The reason is that our models are usually very large, right?
In order to be able to model each individual user's behavior, in the model training process,
we generate model parameters for each individual user, right?
So if you look at the size of a machine learning model, usually that's in the order of tens
of billions of parameters.
That amount of model parameters usually cannot fit into a single container.
So in reality, we need to deploy parts of the model into, for example, key value store,
parts of the model into the scoring service and also part of the model into the index
that provide all the items.
So that's the complexity that we are dealing with for the model deployment tooling.
Okay.
And the model, is there kind of an automated pipeline to kind of overuse the term between
the training tooling and the deployment tooling?
Yeah, that's right.
So we are building a web interface, we call that model explorer.
People can go to this interface and look at all the previously trained model and you can
publish a model from the interface.
And after that, we start the deployment process and we have a centralized release tool which
monitor the deployment process and this process usually start with validating the model in
a test environment and then deploy that in one instance in the production service and
to validate that it works well in that one instance and then deploy to all the instances
right after we validate that it works well for a single instance.
So yeah, so this is a tooling we are currently building.
I remember seeing a while ago, some work that I think was done at LinkedIn around distributed
TensorFlow training on Hadoop.
That's correct.
I think you open sourced a project, is that still in use there?
Yes.
Yeah.
So in when we train deep learning models, we are mainly use TensorFlow and in the past,
we evaluated using Spark to manage a cluster for TensorFlow model training.
However, that framework didn't work very well.
So we develop TensorFlow on Yang, which we call like Tony, T, Stanford TensorFlow, ON,
Y, Yang, which is a Hadoop cluster management system.
And that helped us to effectively manage a cluster of machines that we can run distributed
TensorFlow.
Yesterday, I talked to colleague in Spark, apparently with a new release for Spark, Spark 2.4,
they provide better support for TensorFlow.
I think that's also something interesting to look at.
There are a lot of folks working on different ways to do distributed TensorFlow.
There's the horror vod stuff, there's the distributed TensorFlow that's kind of baked
in the TensorFlow.
It seems like just based on the level of activity that there are either a lot of kind of decisions
that don't work well for everyone or the current solutions aren't, folks aren't very
happy with what's currently available.
Do you have a perspective on that?
I think this is still a quite active area.
I think probably after half a year, we will probably start to see like clear winners.
And in terms of the actual computation, TensorFlow itself provide distributed training.
However, I think most of the effort is on how to set up a cluster for machines such that
we can start TensorFlow distributed training.
And the key is how to enable developer to very easily set up these set of machines.
And the set up mechanism also interact with TensorFlow very well.
We've talked about training and deployment.
And you also have an aspect of ProML that's focused on what you call health assurance.
And I'm taking to be model evaluation and performance assessment.
Can you talk a little bit about that?
Yes.
I think after we deploy the model into production and we start to serve user traffic, it is
very important to make sure that the model continues to run properly.
There are many things that we want to monitor.
One is that the data quality, especially the feature data quality, we want to make sure
that in the online service, the feature data we receive is consistent with the feature
data we observe in our offline training process.
And we also want to continue to continuously monitor our feature data distribution.
So whenever we see a distribution change, then we want to be able to react to that quickly.
Usually, distribution change may indicate some problem in our feature generation or
feature serving systems.
And after people received alert, people need to be able to investigate the problems in
our production system and also the model.
So in that area, it's important that we provide a user interface.
People can go and look at to be able to explain for a particular recommendation.
Why we are making this recommendation, people should be able to see all the features and
also the model decisions based on these features.
How is the distribution even specified?
Are you assuming kind of simple Gaussian types of distributions and just looking at means
and variances, or is it agnostic to the distribution of the actual data?
We start by looking at basic statistics, right?
So like, meaning variance, those are like first, old and second, older moments.
And we also look at some higher older moments.
And we also look at the cumulative distribution and compare the difference between the two.
And you find that there's been a shift in distribution and or a model has degrade and
predictive performance.
Are you doing anything where you're kind of automatically triggering retrains or things
like that?
Or is it more about notifying whoever owns that particular model to take the right action?
So now we start with notification and we are building methods which can also trigger
this retrain.
But we have not yet gone there.
But that's an important next direction.
And are you also doing things like canary models or AB testing, where you're kind of varying
the amount of traffic that you're sending to a model on the fly?
Yeah, AB testing is a very, very important aspect.
And for all of our machine learning development, we use AB testing to verify and quantify
the improvement of a new model that we launched in production.
And a LinkedIn, we have a AB testing platform that is widely used in all the products.
It's not only for machine learning, but for any product feature change, we are also doing
AB testing because we want to make decision based on measurable results.
You're able to use the existing AB testing platform that I imagine was in place for switching
out copy and images and things like that on web pages with models as well.
Did it require a lot of retooling to be able to support the use with the machine learning
models?
The way it works is pretty much the same.
So basically, we have different treatments, and we allocate user traffic to different
treatment.
And each treatment has a key, and that key basically depends on how we interpret that
key.
So for experimenting with product feature, then in our product, we use that key to design,
which experience we want to show to a user.
And for machine learning experiment, we use that key pretty much to decide which model
ID we want to pick up to serve the user.
So at the infrastructure level, it's pretty similar.
One thing that we didn't talk about earlier on in the relating more to model developments
and training to some extent is experiment management.
Does ProML provide a feature set for data scientists to help them manage the various experiments
that they're running?
So this is an area that we will be looking into in the future.
So currently, our AB test platform provides reasonably support for managing the experiment
that we run.
But these are mostly user-facing experiments, right?
Those are running online.
For offline experiments, that is an area that we are currently building to be able to
allow a user to see all the past experiments and enable them to compare different models
in terms of their performance and also the difference in their features and also the difference
in their type of models are using.
This is one of the next steps that we are looking into.
And that ties to hyperparameter optimization, which is something that you mentioned earlier.
It sounds like you do offer via the platform some capability there.
That's correct.
So to train a machine learning model, usually we need to set up different like tuning
parameters.
For example, if you do a regression model, then usually you have regularization terms,
then you need to specify the regularization weights.
And also when you do neural net models, there are also many hyperparameters you need to
decide.
What we do is that we develop a Bayesian optimization method that sequentially try out different
hyperparameter settings and based on that, where we learn the distribution of a potential
best parameter setting and then based on that, we pick the next step.
And through this iterative process, we find that better and better parameter settings.
Sounds like ProML as one would expect is kind of in constant evolution.
That's been the experience in bringing these features to the users of the system, the
developers.
Do you have, I'm curious really about observations in terms of, you know, for folks that have
some community of machine learning engineers or data scientists that they're supporting.
And it wants to bring platform features to them to make them more efficient.
Do you have any advice as to, you know, where to start or how to proceed or the best way
to work with that community to give them the tools that they really need?
I think when for people to start using machine learning, I would recommend to start from
simple methods and then gradually build complexity.
And I think currently many cloud platforms provide capability of building and managing simple
models.
By simple, I mean that the model size is not very large and also the size of data is
not very large, right?
And then gradually you can add more complexity and by and for those simple models, I think
Jupiter notebook is a perfect place to get started.
And then when you add more complexity, then you may need to train your model on a large
amount of data.
And for that, I would probably recommend the listeners to take a look at the photon ML,
which is a LinkedIn open source project, which can enable you to train your models on a
large amount of data using Spark and do very good and deep personalization.
And then after that, when you have those complex and large models, you need to start to
worry about how to deploy model into your production systems.
I think currently that is still a challenge.
I think after we solve the problem, and we can share more of the fact that things.
Watch this space is definitely a quickly evolving area.
That's right.
So you started this and describing a goal of increasing developer productivity and in fact
ProML stands for productive machine learning.
Have you kind of benchmarked productivity gains of the developer community as they've
used this platform?
We start to measure productivity in our LinkedIn machine learning applications.
We just get started and what we look at is the number of successful experiments per engineer.
So we want to improve or increase the value that a single machine learning engineer can
produce.
And the way that we measure the value is by looking at how many successful experiments
that a single engineer can do by using the tooling.
I think over time, we will be able to quantify the gain of the tooling we are building.
And this is still a process that we are going through.
Awesome.
Well, Bichong, thank you so much for taking the time to chat with us about what you're
up to.
It is really interesting stuff and I learned a ton.
Cool.
Thank you so much.
All right, everyone, that's our show for today.
For more information on Bichong or any of the topics covered in this episode, visit
twimmalai.com slash talk slash 200.
To learn more about our AI platform series or to download our eBooks, visit twimmalai.com
slash AI platforms.
As always, thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.