Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast why interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington to close out 2018 and open the new year we're excited
to present to you our first ever AI rewind series.
In this series I interview friends of the show for their perspectives on the key developments
of 2018 as well as a look ahead at the year to come.
We'll cover a few key categories this year, namely computer vision, natural language
processing, deep learning, machine learning and reinforcement learning.
Of course we realize that there are many more possible categories than these, that there's
a ton of overlap between these topics and that no single interview could hope to cover
everything important in any of these areas.
Nonetheless we're pleased to present these talks and invite you to share your own perspectives
by commenting on the series page at twimbleai.com slash rewind 18.
In this episode of our AI rewind series we introduce a new friend of the show Simon Ocindero,
staff research scientist at DeepMind to discuss trends in deep reinforcement learning in 2018
and beyond.
We've packed a bunch into the show as Simon walks us through many of the important papers
and developments seen this year in areas like imitation learning unsupervised RL, meta-learning
and more.
Enjoy.
Alright everyone, I'm on the line with Simon Ocindero.
Simon is staff research scientist at Google Monde.
Simon, welcome to this week in machine learning and AI.
Hi, sir.
Good to see you.
Awesome.
It is great to have you on the show.
You are joining us for our end of 2018 beginning of 2019 kind of reflections and predictions
series and you're unique in this series and that the other guests that we've featured
in this series are all kind of guests that are returning back to the podcast, but you
are our new guests in this series.
We wanted to catch up with you because we've been trying to get you on the show for a while.
We just saw one another at Nourips and this seemed like a great opportunity.
For our project here, we're going to talk through some of the interesting developments
in your particular area of focus which is deep reinforcement learning.
But you've identified a bunch of papers that caught your eye as being significant this
year.
Yeah, that's right, I guess when you asked me this, I was kind of trying to think of what
was interesting and just the rate of publications at the moment is so high that given that and
the number of subfields that I see developing in deeper all these days, it was kind of
hard to come up with a short list.
So I figured maybe what we do is touch on a couple of high level topic areas and I'll
try and pull out from each of them a couple of the papers that I thought were interesting
or that caught my eye.
Actually, even doing that, there's probably going to be some focus areas that we could touch
on that I don't know if we'll have time to but maybe we'll do that in another show.
Awesome.
So what's the first area you have for us?
So the first step is what I'm going to call grouping together, sort of imitation learning,
learning from demonstration, warm starts and curricula, so kind of this idea that we don't
always need to learn from scratch without any information and in fact, doing that when
rewards are very sparse is kind of difficult and so we can leverage other types of knowledge.
So in particular, maybe demonstrations, a small number of demonstrations from other agents,
some of those might be humans, another way of thinking about this problem is to think
about curricula, so either over problems or model complexity and essentially starting
off doing something simple and then bootstrapping from the solution to a similar problem to a
more complicated one.
With regards to imitation learning, I typically see this in the context of reinforcement
learning, are they linked inseparably or can you do one without the other?
Yeah, I mean, for sure you can do reinforcement learning without imitation and actually I guess
depending on what you mean by imitation, you don't necessarily have to do it in a reinforcement
context.
Are there examples that come to mind of imitation learning outside of the reinforcement learning
context?
I mean, I guess depending on how you think about it, you can actually imagine even some of
the way in which we train some language models is essentially being imitation learning,
the kind of teacher forcing aspect of sequence model learning, you can kind of do that as
a kind of imitation.
All right, so the first paper on your list of important papers in this space comes out
of deep mind is the playing exploration games by watching YouTube paper and actually by
the time this interview is published, my interview with Nando to Freitas, one of the authors
of that paper from Nureps, will have been published.
So folks can take a listen to that one.
Great.
Yeah, what were the highlights of that paper for you?
I guess a couple of things, and Nando's already said about this, I'll be relatively brief,
but it's kind of nice that we have observational demonstration data rather than necessarily
providing.
So I guess there's a couple of ways that you could give an agent demonstrations, one is
just letting it watch another agent and observing the world, the other is literally telling
it action sequences that another agent have done that have been successful.
So this is a kind of nice example in that it's purely observational, and so the hope is
that by generalizing this technique, we really could take it from, in this case, it was
looking at a video game that you can imagine wanting to scale this up and just having an
agent watch, people doing stuff in YouTube and learn to do stuff in the real world.
So it's kind of got a lot of potential in that direction.
Okay.
Cool.
How about the next paper on your list?
So the other one was another deep mind paper and similar kind of idea, so this is the
observant look further, achieving consistent performance on Atari.
And again, it's using demonstration, in this case, they do get to see the actions, but
they basically learn to get good performance on some of these hard-expression gains with
just a single demonstration trajectory.
And the kind of idea there is that you basically, in your replay buffer, you have the experience
of the agents generated, but you also get to populate that with experience that a demonstrators
provided, and it turns out that if you do that and a couple of other tricks in terms of
how you do the training, you can also get extremely good results from a very limited amount
of demonstration data.
So when you say a single demonstration trajectory?
Yeah, so imagine a video game just kind of playing through it once, and that's all you
get to see.
So the reason that's kind of interesting is that, you know, a single, I mean, I guess it
depends on the game, but a single playthrough wouldn't necessarily capture all the variability
that you get when you're playing the game, you know, if you start to do the things a little
differently at the beginning, then things can kind of diverge, but in this game, and I
guess it's true of a lot of environments, you know, if you're starting from scratch and
you don't know anything, then there's lots and lots of things that you could end up doing.
And so even just seeing one demonstration of roughly the right thing to do can be extremely
helpful.
How is the imitation part of this paper approached?
Yeah, so like I said, they're using the building known as Technica DQFD, and so DQ learning
from demonstration.
And so the idea there is you have this replay buffer, which is basically transitions that
you've seen in the world.
So you have your current state, the action you did, where you ended up next, and associated
with rewards, and in regular Q learning, or you would essentially populate that buffer
just with your own experience.
And so when you're starting out, you maybe don't really know how the world works.
And so it's put part of the reason that this is interesting and kind of why highlighting
this as an area is, there's a lot of problems where just getting the agent off the ground
and starting to do something simple, can actually end up being the hardest part, but once
you're starting to see rewards and figuring out how the world works, then learning tends
to progress reasonably.
So in terms of learning curves, a lot of the time on some of these tough environments,
you'll basically see flat lining for a very long time, because the agent is essentially
just randomly exploring until it figures out something interesting, and then it starts
to get a signal that it can learn from.
And so I think that's another reason why just a very small amount of demonstration data
or instruction or just something to kind of kick learning off the ground and end up accelerating
learning and help us learn on problems that otherwise would be very hard to do from scratch.
Were there other papers in the scatigory?
Yeah, I guess there was another one that we had in Europe, so I was actually, so this
was kickstarting deep reinforcement learning.
And that's a slightly different approach, so it's not using demonstrations per se anymore.
The idea is we have a free-training teacher agent, so you could imagine getting that in
a couple of different ways, so maybe that would be a simple, easy-to-train agent that
doesn't necessarily get the best performance, but it's easy to train in a reasonable time
or maybe you have lots of different tasks in an environment you want to do, and you might
be able to have a teacher that specializes on a single task, which is typically easier
than learning a whole bunch of things, but you have a student who wants to be able to learn
to do many different things, and the kind of, the approach we have there is we are able
to have the student experience in the world, and we can also query the teacher in a sense
he asks, what would you do if you were in the situation?
So here we have access to the actions, and the idea is we'd like the student to match
the teacher's behaviour, but we don't just want to end up completely copying the teacher
because there can be no point in that, so we also have a mechanism that essentially
over time allows the student to figure out how much attention it should pay to its teacher
and how much attention it should pay to its own experience, so over time the student
trusts its own experience more and more, listens to the teacher less and less, so you
can end up with a student rather exceeding the performance of the teacher, and we kind
of see this as being useful in a couple of different ways, so particularly right now
in terms of the kind of nuts and bolts of experimental cycles, you often want to try out
a lot of different ideas and architectures, and if for each one of those you are having
to start from scratch each time that can be costly in terms of computation, but also can
just be slow, so we kind of see this as a nice way to shorten experimental cycles if
you're wanting to iterate through different aging architectures pretty quickly, another
benefit that we see is, sometimes if you have a really big agent it's just a lot of
parameters to train, so getting that off the ground initially can be kind of hard, and
so we've actually seen really nice progress taking very simple agents that are quick
to train, but they flatline it, not great performance, but by having that as a teacher
we can then get one of these much, much bigger agents off the ground that then ultimately
gives us much better performance, so it's, yes, as a technique it's something that we're
using quite a lot internally.
One of the contexts that you explained this in is in terms of like multi-task, or at least
an agent trying to learn multi-task, I don't know if it's formerly multi-task learning,
but what's the role of the teacher in that multi-multiple task scenario?
Yes, so in that scenario it would be, often what we'd like is a single agent that can
do lots and lots of things, and that training that transcript can be kind of challenging,
what's often more manageable is you kind of subdivide the problem space into smaller
and smaller chunks, so you are learning to do just one of those tasks, maybe even breaking
a single task into smaller chunks, so learning to do a small part of the overall problem,
you can get a teacher agent that specializes on that little bit of the overall problem
space, and if you then have many different teachers that specialize in different parts between
them that able to do most of the things you care about, but like I say what you'd really
like is a single agent that has competency to do everything in the domain, and so in a
situation like that you could build these simple agents that kind of specialize in parts
of the problem space, and then use those different teachers to then transfer their knowledge
to a student that is learning from all of them, and as I say over time it can figure out
how much attention to pay to the different teachers and get good performance, so in the
paper we have a set of different tasks that we want to do in the 3D DM lab environment,
and so you know they can like navigation kind of tasks, avoidance kind of tasks, gathering
tasks, all sorts of things like that, and we have teacher agents that are specialized
for each one of those, and then we can build, but what we're really interested in, and
this is kind of moving towards general intelligence, we really want one agent that can do lots and
lots of things and can also learn to do new things, and so one way of getting that off
the ground is to have these simpler, less general agents that specialize in particular parts
of the problem space, and then distill their knowledge into the student to get the student
off the ground.
To be clear, so maybe an example, if you say you have, you're trying to train an agent,
and you've got four kind of things that you want it to learn, and you create three of
these teacher agents, are the teacher agents increasing performance in the three categories
for which you have teacher agents, or is the lack of teacher agent allowing the agent
to learn more about the one where you don't have a teacher agent?
In this setting, I guess it's a little orthogonal to that, so in terms of, the teacher should
never be too limiting in the sense that we have this mechanism, in the people are using
population-based training, but you could imagine doing other things that essentially tries
to meta-learn how much attention the page of the teacher.
If the teacher is useful, if it's giving you learning progress on the thing that you
care about, great, as that becomes less and less useful, you pay less and less attention
to the teacher.
So far, in these conversations, what's been interesting is that I could spend the entire
time talking about one thing that kind of pulls me in that direction, but we'll try not
to do that here, and so where there are other papers in this category, do you want to move
on to the next one?
So we had another paper mix and match agent curricula for reinforcement learning, and
there, rather than having a teacher that's kind of pre-trained, it's kind of as if you
have a companion agent that is trained jointly with the one you really care about, so in practice
how we implement that, we have a mixed-your-policy, which is two different policies that we kind
of blend together, and the idea there is maybe a much simpler policy would be easier to train
to imagine something that has far fewer possible actions that it could take, and so often
that's similar to learn, but what we'd really like is an agent that has access to many,
many actions.
One thing you could do is initially train an agent with few actions and then use the behavior
of that agent to train the one that has many, many actions, and in this particular setup,
we do that in a continuous way where the learning is shared between both different types
of policy, and we have a term that essentially encourages the information to flow in a sense
the simpler and faster learning agent to the complex, more solely learning agent, and again,
we have that processes orchestrated, is done automatically with this method population-based
training, which essentially tries a whole bunch of different values for how strongly we're
coupling behavior and preferentially follows the ones that are giving the best empirical
performance.
So the next category that you identified was what?
So this one is, I guess what I call unsupervised RRR, or you could think of it as self-supervision
or different kinds of interesting auxiliary tasks, so I think this is sort of a general
direction that lots of people are interested in, which is the information in a reward signal
probably isn't enough to train the scale of agents that we're interested in in a reasonable
amount of experience.
It's not very information rich, but there actually is a ton of other stuff in the environment
that we can learn from.
And so leveraging that along with a reward signal is something that I think we're going
to see a lot more.
So you've probably heard Jan Lecun talk about the cherry analogy with a cake, so it's kind
of getting at that, but the point is that there's all sorts of things that we can learn
from in the reinforcement learning context.
And so examples of this, not from this year, but previously, would be the unreal paper
where you're essentially doing a whole bunch of auxiliary prediction tasks in addition to
trying to learn the policy and value.
One of the papers from this year that I thought was particularly interesting in that sense
is this one unsupervised control through non-parametric discrimination rewards.
And the basic idea is wanting to kind of learn to discover and achieve goals without
any supervision.
So it appears to be similar to what happens if you have a young kid, you're essentially
just learning what you can control in the world, learning what you can do.
But no one's, you do have some supervision, but a lot of learning is just figuring out,
what can I affect, what can I control in the world, can I set myself arbitrary goals
and then achieve them?
And so it's kind of taking a shot at that problem.
Does that kind of exist?
Yeah, how did they kind of encode that knowledge that they're making not relative to the
loss function?
Yeah, that's a great question, actually.
So they let's learn a loss function, so there's a couple of clever tricks that they do.
So you start out behaving, let's say, randomly, and you know that states that you visited
in that random paper are achievable, or you know, something closer that should be achievable
because you've achieved that before.
So this is drawing on some of the ideas from, there's a paper last year on hindsight experience
replay, which essentially is, you know, maybe I was trying to do one thing.
I didn't necessarily do that, but I did a whole bunch of things.
And so you can learn about the count of factuals.
When you're acting, you do something.
And so learning about what you did is an alternative to learning about what you wanted to do.
So that's kind of one element.
The other element is how you figure out how well you achieve those goals, and they use
an approach that's a little similar to the discriminator in again, so that the basic
idea is, well, yeah, okay, the three components, you have a goal condition policy.
So you have a policy that gets to see its current state, and it also gets given a goal state
that it's trying to achieve.
And under ideal conditions, you kind of plug both those in, and it will get you to the
goal.
But then there's the question that I think, well, you're saying initially, how do you figure
out if you achieve your goal or not?
And that's where this sort of bootstrap teacher comes in.
So the idea is, imagine the goal that I'm trying to achieve, and imagine a whole bunch of
other possible states that I could be in.
So there's the kind of, there's the target and a whole bunch of distractors.
What I'm going to do is try and learn a classifier that distinguishes between those distractors
and the goal that I was trying to achieve.
And the way that that's trained, it's a little subtle.
So there's two things that we can plug in there, because if you've told what I was saying,
you might worry there's a bit of a secularity.
So one of them is to plug in some of those hindsight goals, so given some initial state
and just a random trajectory, there'll be states that I go through.
And so I could, after the fact, say, hey, that state that I ended up passing through,
that wasn't my goal.
And so the nice thing about that is you know that you achieved it because you were literally
in that state, you can use that to kind of get this classifier a little off the ground.
Now other data, the situation between that goal that you reached and these distractors,
but then it's also bootstrapped a little bit, and there you essentially end up saying,
wherever you've got to, when you were following this particular goal, I'm going to treat
that from the point of view of the classifier as if that was the ground truth.
Which sounds like it might be a little unstable, because initially you're not going to be
achieving those goals, but what that ends up doing is it sort of gives you a scoring
function that is kind of smooth in the sort of meaningful space of task achievement over
time.
So, you know, I don't necessarily want to need to be pixel perfect to say that I've achieved
that goal and there might be different ways of achieving the same thing.
And so by plugging the agent's behavior in it in that way, they're able to learn an
intrinsic reward function that is effective at kind of critiquing how well they achieve
these arbitrary self-derived goals.
Yeah, yeah.
So, I think that this kind of area of self-supervision or unsupervised RL is going to be something
we're going to see a lot more of figuring out good ways of how we can set prediction
or control tasks for ourselves in order to expand the knowledge and capabilities of an
agent in a particular environment.
And so, is this general category is it trying to help us overcome the difficulty of creating
loss functions for RL?
Yeah, you could do it.
It's doing that in one way.
So in terms of a lot of problems that we might be interested in, so imagine you know,
a kind of robotic and control problem, we're sort of trying to move away from hand-engineering
reward function.
So, in that setting, you might, what you really care about is the task done or not.
But just training on that is very sparse, so you basically get to know if you've done
the task or not pretty much at the end.
And there might be lots of different ways of achieving that and to the extent that you
try and hand design or reward function, you're also in some sense hand designing a solution
which were kind of trying to get away from it.
If it was easy for us to design solution, then maybe we wouldn't need to learn it in
the first place.
Right.
So, yeah, this is kind of heading in this direction of how can I build a system that can
learn to control the environment in lots of different interesting ways?
Because if I can do that, then when you give me your problem, if I know how to do all
sorts of things, then essentially when you give me your problem, I just need to figure
out all the many things that I'm capable of, which one is the one that fits your particular
problem?
And so that then becomes a lot easier.
So what's the next category?
So, the next category, learning to learn or meta-learning.
So, this idea of how do we use learning to improve the process of learning itself?
And I'd sort of, this kind of blends in a little bit, especially in the RL setting with
how do we learn to acquire experience that is useful for learning, or to us to be care
about, which is, you know, more or less exploration.
So, I had three papers from this topic that I thought would be good to highlight.
So, the first one is called Meta-Reenforcement Learning Exploration Strategies.
And there's a couple of elements to it.
So, it builds on some meta-learning ideas from previous papers.
So, there's a paper model-agnostic meta-learning, mammal that folks went ahead of where the
idea there is, you're trying to find model parameters such that, given arbitrary new problems,
you can rapidly adapt to solve them.
This one is building on top of that, and you have a policy that has latent variables.
And in this case, those latent variables are going to add, so, episode scale, noise
or stochasticity to your behavior.
But there's other ways you could do that conditioning, the kind of the point is, there's a latent
variable that different settings of that cause your model to, cause your agent to behave differently.
And so, by setting those parameters, you effectively can get different types of exploratory
behavior.
So, they essentially try to learn an initial distribution of these latent variables, such
that for new problems from the domain of interest, if you sampled on that, you quickly produce
behaviors that allow you to gain experience, that allow you to solve those new problems
rapidly.
So, rather than having to have stochasticity at each time step, you get to explore in
a structured way across the scale of an episode.
Okay.
So, that was one of the ones.
Another one, this paper, Evolved Policy Gradients, and there, it's a very similar metal learning
flavor, there the idea is, can we evolve a reward functions or an intrinsic reward functions
such that if I optimize, according to that reward function, I get good performance on the
task that I care about.
So, again, imagine one of these settings where you basically, all I care about is, did
you do the thing that I wanted you to do or not?
Did you complete the task successfully?
And, you know, as I was saying before, hand designing, excuse me, a dancer reward function
that tells you, you know, for each state action transition, how good was that?
It's kind of hard, but maybe that's a function rather than specifying it, maybe we can learn
that function.
And that's what this paper is trying to do, and it's using evolutionary methods to do
that.
So, basically, you have an in-loop where you're using regular policy gradient learning,
an absolute where you're using evolutionary search to figure out what a good function would
be.
So, I plug in a function, you get to train with that function, I see how well you did
training with that reward function, and I'm slowly shifting my search space of functions
towards ones that when I optimize them, give me good performance on the thing that I
really care about.
The evolved policy gradients paper is out of OpenAI and the Meta-reinforcement learning paper
that I remember correctly is out of Berkeley.
That's it, yeah.
Okay.
Yeah, I should think both of them, they might be both the OpenAI Berkeley collaborations,
but.
Oh, really?
Okay.
Yeah.
Okay, interesting.
This, the meta-learning space is a really interesting one that I'm starting to hear a lot
about.
Yeah, yeah, I think there's a ton of interesting potential there.
The other paper I was going to mention in that topic real quick was this one is another
deep-mine paper, Meta-gradient reinforcement learning, and yes, similar themes again in
terms of having two scales of optimization.
Here we're asking ourselves that there are parameters that essentially influence the
return that we're learning on that can affect the learning dynamics, so the discount, how
much I discount rewards into the far future is a property of the algorithm that affects
the learning dynamics.
So even if there is a horizon that I truly care about, it might be the case that I get
better empirical performance by using something that's different from that.
And so this paper is combining regular policy gradient with essentially a second set of
rollouts that try to, again, ask the question, if these meta-parameters of my learning were
different, would I be making better learning progress?
And so it's a way, for instance, of automatically and dynamically tuning things like the lambda
or your discount, moving on, and I'll try and condense this section a little bit since
we're probably going to get tied on time if we kind of go into a lot of detail.
But we've been trying to hold back my many questions.
So yeah, another kind of interesting area is exploration, learning to explore, and dealing
with different types of uncertainty, so I guess this, you can think of two types of uncertainty.
And so, folks like you've been talking a lot about, sort of, epistemic versus alliotoric
uncertainty.
So epistemic uncertainty is basically represents your lack of knowledge or data about
the world.
So it's like uncertainty in your model parameters.
So whereas alliotoric, you can kind of think of that as like fundamental randomness in
the world, so stuff that you just can't predict no matter how much data you see.
And maybe that's because it's too many random, or I guess other people might argue that there's
the things that are just kind of outside the capability of a model class, but it kind
of boils down to the same thing.
So yeah, there's a couple of papers that are closely related, actually, that touch
on this.
So there's a really nice paper at New York's in Osborne, John Aslanneeds and Albon Kissiro,
customized prior functions for the DBRL.
And there's a couple of really nice tricks in what they're doing.
This is also kind of building a prior work that I've seen reused in a couple of different
places.
So this notion that we can use a sort of bootstrap ensemble of functions to try and represent
uncertainty.
So that's basically just rather than having a single function, if I train lots of copies
of a function with different visualizations, and with, in this case, different prize,
which I'll touch on briefly in a second, I can then look at to what degree the different
models in the ensemble agree or disagree.
So if there's a lot of variance in the models predictions, then in some sense that's a reflection
of uncertainty.
And it turns out you can kind of make that connection tight on the certain conditions
and in general, it seems like a good heuristic.
So the idea here is we're going to do that with our Q functions and then build on top
of that for learning the notion of the randomised prior, essentially boils down to, I'm going
to have a prior distribution over the parameters of our function class.
And for each member of the ensemble, I'm going to sample from that prior and instead
of effectively doing weight decay towards zero as a kind of regularization, I'm going
to do weight decay towards those initially sampled parameters.
You can kind of think about as starting off with some random function from your prior
beliefs, and then learning a correction function top of that to model what you actually
see in the world.
And so it turns out, if you do that and you don't look the right way, you can basically
sample when you're acting, you can sample a function from your ensemble, act according
to that gather experience, participants in a buffer, bootstrap, update all the different
members of the ensemble.
And it deals with that uncertainty about the world in the right way that leads to good
exploratory behaviour.
So yeah, I thought that was a really cool paper.
There was another paper, I think OpenAI and you'd most of Edinburgh folks, so Yoruba,
Harrison Edward, David Storky, and all the claim of exploration by random network distillation
that take a similar sort or the, you can actually draw a fairly tight connection between what
they do and the paper I just described, although it's maybe not so obvious immediately.
What they're doing is they're coming up with a function that, so you have a random
function, and what you're going to try and do is predict the outputs of that random
function, using a function that you're learning, and you're going to use your prediction error
as a sign of unfamiliarity, and then you get to plug that in as an intrinsic award.
So the idea being, you know, if you're in discrete states, then you can use some kind
of account-based measure of how unfamiliar you are in a certain part of the world, and
kind of give bonuses for exploring new places, that gets harder in much bigger statespaces
where you can't enumerate everything.
And so this is another way of approaching that.
How do I measure how uncertain I am about this part of state space?
And so yeah, essentially what you do, you have this random function, you're trying to
learn something that predicts the outputs of that random function when applied to the
state, and your prediction error, you're going to use as an intrinsic award.
So places that you've visited lots and lots, you kind of know what the random function
is going to behave there, and so you should have relatively low prediction error, places
that you haven't visited that much, and you're going to have a higher prediction error,
and so you'll be incentivized to go find those and explore those more.
And so they use that approach on Montezuma, which is this hard expression game, and they
get some really nice results using that.
Is Montezuma still considered to be, you know, unplayable, you know, with high performance
by RL agents, or have we kind of cracked that with this and other recent agents?
Yeah, I mean, it's still pretty challenging.
Yeah, with a person like this and other recent agents, I think in this paper, they get super
human performance.
Okay.
Yeah.
Okay, interesting.
So these are always to kind of structure the structure, the exploration space, and
kind of create different types of ensembles and train across those ensembles.
That's right.
Okay, very cool.
And then the other one that I guess I'll just mention briefly that is sort of in the category,
but as long as this is dealing with the other type of uncertainty, was a paper implicit
quantile networks for distribution RL that was, will that be Geogos Grobski, David Silver
and Ren Yunus, and it's sort of building on some of these previous ideas in distribution
RL were the kind of the ideas, rather than just predicting the expected return, I'm going
to try and predict the distribution of possible returns.
And so that could happen.
So if there is sort of intrinsic uncertainty in the environment, then even if I'm following
the same policy, how the world turns out could end up having variability in it, and rather
than just kind of model the mean of that, you can also try and capture properties of the
distribution.
That's potentially interesting for two different reasons, one, it's a richer prediction problem,
so you can sort of think of predicting that distribution as helping in the same way
that auxiliary tasks do.
And then the other is having those sorts of estimates are themselves useful in some
cases.
So, you know, if you want to be risk sensitive for instance, then you might prefer something
that even though the mean might be higher, you might prefer a policy that has a lower
mean, but also a lower variance, so you kind of avoid worse but rare outcomes.
So, that was the one for that one.
The other area that I thought I'd mention briefly, and again, I think this is an area
that we'll see more and more interesting developments over the coming years, is in model-based
reinforcement learning, so this was another one from New York's this month, sample-efficient
reinforcement learning with stochastic ensemble value expansion, and they have an algorithmic
approach that they get the acronym Steve out of.
And that was, I think, mostly Google brain folk, so Jake and Bookmoon don't know, I have
to Joyce Chalker, Eugene Bervdo, and Holly Lakeley, and it's another one actually where
they're using this trick of using a bootstrapped ensemble to help us capture model uncertainty.
And here, they're actually using it in a model of the environment.
So, in addition to learning our policy and value, we're also going to be trying to learn
about how the world works, so given a particular state in an action, what is going to be my,
what state will I transition into, and what will be the associated award?
And if you have a really good model of the environment, then you can learn much more quickly
because you can not only use the experience that you gather in the world, but you can also
essentially simulate in your model what would happen if you did different things.
But the problem, or one of the problems with that, is that if your model is inaccurate,
then you can run into all sorts of trouble, and so what they do in this paper, they,
because they're learning this model with an uncertainty estimate, they essentially
are able to use the measure of model certainty to figure out how far to trust a model, their
environment model.
So, you essentially roll out your internal environment model to the point where you're essentially
waiting how much you trust your model at different prediction depths into the future by how
much uncertainty there is associated with that, and then at some point you end up bootstrapping.
So, it's kind of a neat way of combining model based and model free RL.
So, the other thing that, or one other area, and this is probably the last one that we'll
touch on for today, I'll maybe just kind of be shout out to some of the other ones that
we probably wouldn't have as much time to talk about.
And that's this kind of trend of seeing sort of, ways in which DPRRL are being scaled
up, so moving to kind of like these very large models, lots and lots of data distributed
training systems.
So, there's a couple of papers from this year that are doing that, so there was three,
or there was a comment to mind as a three from demide and one from OpenAI, so we had this
paper importance weighted at learner architectures in Paula, and so the set up there is, you
have lots and lots of actors gathering experience, they send that experience to a smaller collection
of learners, but even the learners can be distributed, and one of the kind of subtleties
of that is, in that kind of set up, the experience that comes from the actors might be a little
allowed of data, so there's a little bit of op-policy correction, but it essentially
allows you to use extremely large batches and very big models, and still kind of get
through a reasonable number of model updates in a short space of time, so that's kind
of one direction for scaling.
The others, I'll just mention these, I guess briefly, so there was a paper distributed
prioritized experience replay, and that's essentially a kind of value learning analog of the
impulsify I just mentioned, so again lots of active generating experience coming into
a shared experience, a replay, and then learners pulling off on top of that.
Another similar paper had an approach, D4PG, so there was all demide, and then the OpenAI
data, I think there's not a paper on it, I'm not sure, but they kind of detail it in
their blog post.
They have a similar scheme, I think, to Impala where they have essentially lots of distributed
workers generating experience, and then a small number of beefy large batch learners pulling
from experience from the actors and generating parameter updates, and there's a couple of
things there, as I said one, it sort of like allows you to kind of crunch through a lot
more experience, and in some ways it's kind of just by scaling up in that way, it's able
to address some of the inefficiencies of RL, so earlier we were talking a little bit
about wanting to kind of pull as many different learning signals as we can out of the environment,
particularly if reward is sparse or explosion is difficult, and there's sort of lots of
different ways of tackling that, some are kind of more algorithmic, but also just by
scaling things up and pushing a lot more data through, that's another way we're addressing
that, and it also helps some of the kind of stability issues from the variants of the
learning signals that you get a lot of these environments, so again I think that's another
trend that we'll see just kind of being built on more and more, and you know, so it's
somehow in computer vision kind of things have been scaling up and up over the past like
five or six years.
So yeah, maybe if I'll just mention some kind of other interesting areas that we work
up time to dive into, but there's been some kind of interesting developments in hierarchy
car, RL, multi-agent, there's been some neat work on sort of leveraging different types
of memories in agents, and also just the kind of folding in of the sort of broader advances
from machine learning in general in terms of better ways of doing representation learning,
kind of some modeling, all those other kind of techniques, kind of feeding into DPRL.
So just a quick review of the topics that we did cover here, imitation learning, unsupervised
RL, meta-learning, exploration, model-based RL, and scaling up, and those are just a
few of the ones that you were able to think of.
So what would you say about the kind of the rate of growth of RL as a field?
Yeah, super exciting.
I mean, there's a lot of difficult problems that we don't yet have good ways to solve,
but there's a ton of creative solutions coming out.
Beyond papers, did you, did any other kind of broader developments in open source or on
the commercial side, anything jump out at you?
Yeah, couple.
So I guess the commercial side, I've tracked a little less of late in terms of open source.
There's a kind of background in terms of like the kind of continued development, both sort
of like the TensorFlow and PyTorch frameworks in the sporting ecosystems.
There've been a couple of things that there that I thought were pretty nice.
So these like TF Hub, kind of having a kind of repository for models, and now they're
kind of similar efforts.
So there's a couple of frameworks that I saw at Neuros that I like.
So there's dopamine, which is out of, I think, Google Brain Montreal, lucid, such a dopamine
is a kind of a nice way of making some of these, yeah, with, with definitely lucid, and
then there's also something from Uber Model 2, the kind of combination of those, it's kind
of nice and that I think it'll maybe open up some opportunities to kind of play with
deep RL with a lower entry bar.
So with the model zoo they essentially have, I think, three or four different flavors
of agent, pre-trained on all the games in the Atari Suite that you can just essentially
download, and lucid is this kind of visualization framework.
And so with the two of those, you can start to play with some of these pre-trained agents
without necessarily having to have the resources to train them yourselves, which I think
is probably something that will be helpful for new people wanting to get into the field,
to kind of get a bit of a warm start, and then also, I think in general releasing pre-trained
agents that people can build off of and poke is a nice trend, similar to some of the stuff
we saw, again, sort of looking back at computer vision with making some of the pre-trained models
on the ImageNet available that helped a lot of folks kind of get a foothold there, and
then also then accelerated the progress in that field.
With these tools and with RL models in general are the same kinds of things possible, like
kind of taking off the last few layers of a network and fine-tuning, that same kind
of transfer learning.
I guess it would depend on the agent, not so much in what's available right now, the
transfer between different Atari games, for instance, isn't huge, but just in terms of
having something that can get you started.
For instance, the kickstarting stuff that we were talking about earlier in the conversation,
if you have pre-trained agents that have some decent behavior that can dramatically shorten
your experience cycle time if you want to play with your own modifications of those architectures,
eventually you might end up wanting to not use that pre-training to kind of get a clear
look at innovations that you're looking at, but if you don't necessarily have access
to a ton of compute resources, then leveraging things that are pre-trained is a really nice
way of making it more accessible.
Okay.
So, no direct transfer in the way we might see with CNNs, but you can use these agents
to kind of get things kicked off.
Yeah, I think so, I guess, transfer in RL is an interesting conversation that we could
have on the side, but yeah, it would depend on what task you want to transfer to, and
there's a lot of subtleties there, so even things like training and simulation and deploying
in the real world, you see some transfer there, so I guess that's one place where you could
kind of think of that as being pre-training and fine-tuning, but yeah, I kind of think
of that as a little differently than like I said, or at least in its current state, the
model zero is just focused on Atari, so it's more kind of entry level, but I think that's
probably still something that folks entering the field will find useful.
Okay.
Cool.
And so, given all that we've seen happen in 2018, what are your kind of thoughts and
predictions on what we'll see in 2019 and the near future beyond that?
Yeah, prediction that was tough.
I think a lot of the areas that I highlighted to me feel like they're particularly active
frontiers, so yeah, I think we'll see more folks trying to come up with different ways
of doing agent-based RL with more self-supervision, I think the kind of trend, sort of meta-learning,
learning to learn, transfer learning, continual learning, so one agent learnings to do many,
many different things through a lifetime.
I trends will see, yeah, likewise, model-based RL, I feel like models have probably been a
little less prominent in recent years, sorry, like in very models, definitely have been
some papers that look to that, but I feel like that's an interesting area for growth,
so yeah, those are a couple that come to mind.
Any final thoughts before we wrap up?
Yeah, I think a super exciting time in the field is kind of tons of groups, both from
academia and industry that are doing really great work, and so yeah, it's a super exciting
time to be doing research in the field, and then also, I guess, through the broader machine
learning community, there's a lot of great efforts in terms of just working to expand
that the pool of folks who can participate in AI research and who can kind of contribute
to some of these problems that we're looking at, so yeah, I'm super optimistic for the
future.
Well Simon, thanks so much for taking the time to chat with us about RL, there's a ton
of stuff here, and we'll try to get links to the various papers that you mentioned in
the show notes, but thank you.
All right, everyone, that's our show for today.
For more information on Simon or any of the topics covered in this show, visit twimlai.com
slash talk slash 217.
You can also follow along with our AI rewind 2018 series at twimlai.com slash rewind 18.
As always, thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.
Happy Holidays.