So what's your name?
My name is Harov Suckman.
I'm the CEO and founder of Kepler Vision Technologies.
We are a spin-off company from the University of Amsterdam.
We bring to the market body language recognition software.
Whether I tell you a story looking like this,
or looking like this, or looking like this,
I may be able to, I may be saying the same thing,
but my body tells a different story.
Many possible applications for it,
they are sort of blindfolded looking at the market.
Because self-driving cars will need body language recognition,
security, but people focus on elderly care.
We can also recognize that people are drinking or eating,
if people have fallen, if they are laying on the floor,
or laying on the couch, or laying on the bed,
or if people get upset, and that's what we do.
And how does it work?
Based on post-estimation, or I think the figures
that look like post-emptimation.
Skeleton, combined with raw pixel data,
because with just a skeleton,
you cannot distinguish a person eating or drinking.
And what's the origin of the technology?
The technology.
We build it from scratch.
So we use the available open source,
deep neural networks, but we train it with our own data.
We annotate it, we annotate the data also ourselves.
And how do you collect the data?
From partners.
We have potential clients that we build proof of concepts projects with.
Okay, and is there a demo?
No.