Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast why interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
While at last year's NERP's conference, in December, I attended the second annual black
NAI workshop, which gathered participants from all over the world to showcase their research,
share experiences and support one another.
Today, we conclude our black NAI series with this interview with Sikle Lukwandazwane,
a master student at the University of Vithwatersrand, and graduate research assistant at South
Africa's Council for Scientific and Industrial Research, or CSIR.
At the workshop, Sikle Lukwandaz presented on safer exploration and deep reinforcement
learning using action priors, which explores transferring action priors between robotic
tasks to reduce the exploration space, which in turn reduces sample complexity.
In our conversation, we discuss what exactly safer exploration means in this sense, the
difference between this work and other techniques like imitation learning, and how this fits
in with the broader goal of lifelong learning.
Enjoy.
Alright, everyone, I am on the line with Sikle Lukwandazwane.
He's a master student at the University of Vithwatersrand, and a graduate research assistant
at the Council for Scientific and Industrial Research, or CSIR in South Africa.
Sikle Lukwandazwane, welcome to this week in machine learning and AI.
Thanks a lot, Sam.
Thank you for having me.
So I will just let everyone know that you were very, very gracious in practicing the pronunciation
of your name with me, and I am still butchering it, but thank you so much.
We had a long practice session before, and I am going to work on these, Koza, was it
Koza?
It's a Zulu.
Sorry, sorry.
Yeah, it tends to be very similar to a Kosa.
Okay, so I am going to work on this, and the next time we have you on the show, we're
going to get it.
We're going to get it.
But thanks so much for your patience with that.
Why don't we get started by having you share a little bit about your background and how
you got started working in machine learning and artificial intelligence?
So I got into machine learning because of the problems that I found when back when I was
in this interest group in 2nd year, where we were at this robotics interest group at
VITS, and we were giving these quadcopters to fly around, and my friend and I decided
we want to fly hours in like a rectangular shape, and we found that we couldn't do that.
Like we had issues with things like wind and momentum.
You could never actually get the drone to be in one particular position.
But nonetheless, even though we did fly in some type of kite shape, like I found myself
fascinated by the fact that I basically wrote some code, and I had to sit back and relax
and watch my code basically fly this machine around, right?
So actually I became interested in the field of robotics and continued my studies and tried
to pick subjects even in honors that would basically give me a good start in my career
as a roboticist in South Africa.
Then I think during my honors year, one of the subjects that I picked was reinforcement
learning, and there I learned that the big challenge in trying to get machines that can
think and act like human beings is not so much the actual machinery and trying to create
something that is anatomically similar to a human being.
But the bigger challenge was trying to get these machines to perform like these complex
behaviors, things like that we take so much for granted, something as simple as picking
a pen or picking a cup up and putting it down is something that is still a difficult
task when you want to achieve it with a robot, or rather the bigger challenge was this
thing, generalization, we want to have, we want to want these machines to be able to
perform general behaviors, if I say pick something up, you shouldn't care what the object
looks like, your code shouldn't rely on the actual position of the hand when it does
it, it needs to generalize to all these weird scenarios, for example, if someone has a
bigger cup, if someone has a mug, if someone has a pen, it turns out that machine learning,
or I found out that machine learning was one of the tools that could actually help achieve
this goal through machine learning, we can actually learn more general behaviors to
get more interesting robotic applications, or more useful, actually useful is the word
I was looking for there, that is literally how I got into the field, just by wanting
to see a robot perform some simple task, and then realizing that having the robot perform
that task is not something that is simple to say, it wasn't trivial, one alternative
or as a third year computer science student, I think my skill set would have probably pointed
me towards trying to hard code, okay maybe tilt the robot hand by 45 degrees and then move
it forward a few centimeters and then go down and then open the gripper, close the gripper
and then pick it up and then, but you realize that you just, you created like this behavior
is only specific to this particular scenario, like you leave your robot overnight at the
lab and someone comes and they move the cup by a few centimeters and now your whole system
doesn't work, so the reason why I'm interested in machine learning, or the reason why I'm
in machine learning is to be able to learn more general behaviors, you know, more useful
behaviors for robots and other applications, because machine learning is not only useful
for robotics, just that, that is my, yeah, interest.
One of the things that I can really relate to is that initial inspiration, you know, I find
I really enjoy, I don't code a lot, but I do enjoy it, but when you're writing code
and then that is affecting the physical world through motors and other actuators, you
know, basically robotics, whether in like small form, you know, making light splink, all
that kind of stuff, I find it super rewarding and so I can see how that would like it you
kind of pulled into wanting to explore more and have more, kind of be able to build these
more robust interactions.
Yeah, now, yeah, that's precisely the point, right, there's so much, it is actually very
rewarding to say something that you created actually become something physical that you
can see.
At the Black and AI workshop, you presented on some of your research, titled safer exploration
and deep reinforcement learning using action priors.
Tell us a little bit about the motivation for this project.
Okay, the motivation is not really a straightforward thing for me.
But motivated me to go with this particular topic is my, mainly my experience with using
deep reinforcement learning and trying to apply it to the robotics domain, right?
So I have access to this mobile manipulator, it's basically just a powerbot, AGV platform
with that baritwem, seven dog robot arm on top, and we would like to basically, the dream
is to have this platform performing complicated tasks such as making someone coffee or making
a sandwich and things like that, but it's really hard to specify rewards and it's very
hard to produce those kind of behaviors.
If you are trying to manually specify what is supposed to happen, ideally, would like
the system to actually learn to perform these behaviors on its own.
So what I'm kind of hearing here is like you kind of started out as an undergrad, like
trying to get robots to do things and at that stage in your experience, the natural way
to do things was to build these big rule sets.
And then else kind of programming and you went on to explore doing this with deep reinforcement
learning, but then you ran it to this challenge of how do we create the reward functions to
get a robot to grip something?
That's historically one of the hard, you know, the hard parts about using deep reinforcement
learning.
Yes, that is correct.
So I found it very hard to specify a reward function for picking something up, you know.
My first task as a master student was, okay, I want to use deep reinforcement learning
to perform multitask learning on this particular robot platform that we have at the CSR, right?
Then when I'm thinking about doing that, I realize, okay, this is basically one of the
few robots that we have and reinforcement learning is known to be random in nature, right?
You rely on maybe executing random actions to kind of discover rewarding states and stuff
like that and you can't really afford to be performing these random actions and these
jerky movements when you're actually working with actual machinery or the physical platform.
So my first task was, let me just build a simulated environment and as I was doing that, I spent
some time trying to basically find the right meshes that would kind of correspond in shape
and size to the actual physical platform and I was using this thing called gazebo where
you can basically have like a physical environment, you know, with all the physics and collisions
and things and then gazebo is a gazebo is like a physics simulator that's used quite a
bit in robotics, is that right?
Yes, yes, yes.
So yeah, when I say both is that I built basically some packages for this particular platform that
would allow me to use reinforcement learning with the actual joint configurations of the robot,
you know, so things like I need to be able to publish actions to the robot and have it perform
those actions and then observe some change and then have something that's going to decide
if this was good or bad, which is basically my reward function, right?
So yeah, but the whole thing was just I want to have this particular robot platform being
able to perform multiple tasks and on my way there towards performing multiple tasks,
I realized that okay, there's actually a lot of challenges with getting a standard
dipping reinforcement learning algorithm to to work properly on, you know, like any environment
that you have, right?
So when I think about a deep enforcement learning, I'm going to be thinking about okay, firstly
you have this, this exploration phase where you start with random policies, right?
And you're going to be trying to find, I guess, would be executing random actions.
I found out that it was really hard to specify reward functions for these complicated
behaviors, like for example, in wanting to pick something up, right?
You need to somehow reward the agent for what's this thing re-reaching towards the object
and then actually picking it up, you know, which is there's actually two stages you need
something that's going to encode moving towards the object and something that's going to encode
basically you closing your gripper around the object and then still having the object
and moving that your hand up and having the object remain in the hand, you know, so things
like that.
You presented a project called safer exploration and deep reinforcement learning using action
priors.
First off, when you say safer exploration, you know, what does that mean and why is that
important?
Yeah, so when I'm talking about safer exploration, right?
I'm trying to improve the safety of the exploration policy in a standard deep reinforcement learning
algorithm, right?
So being in the robotics domain, I can't very much about the physical well-being of my
platform, right?
So it's very important to me that I won't be, if for example, I need to learn to perform
some task using a deep reinforcement learning algorithm, I need some form of insurance that
my platform won't be basically performing the worst possible thing.
It won't hurt itself in any way.
For example, if I have like a Rumba and basically having it sweep my roof for some reason, right?
I need to know that this thing won't drive off the roof, you know, like things like that,
like it should be able to learn, right?
In this scenario or in an environment where there are still states that are deemed very
unsafe or like very undesirable, right?
So when I talk about safer exploration, I'm just trying to
I guess improve the safety of your standard deep reinforcement learning algorithm, I mean.
That paradigm is based on, so you understand the standard paradigm in reinforcement learning
in general is that you, or one of the more popular exploration techniques is this
epsilon greedy thing where you're going to decide, okay, I'm going to execute some random
actions or actions from random policy, right?
Some epsilon probability of the time and then with probability one minus epsilon, you're
going to be basically exploiting or you're going to be executing actions that come from
your from the policy that you're training, right?
Which is also quite random initially, but you do this so that like you can actually discover,
you know, like potentially useful actions to perform in any state in the state that you're
currently occupying.
So my work is to trying to kind of relax this very random nature, right?
When you're exploring and what I'm saying is that instead of trying to explore randomly,
right, or executing random actions, why don't we execute actions that were performed
by experts in these like states that were in, you know, so you'd have maybe something
like you tried to first build some notion of account, right, to maintain, you'd maintain
some notion of accounts to see how many times a particular action has been performed
in a state, right?
And then you're going to explore according to these counts, you convert these counts to
a probability distribution and then you sample from the from from this distribution and
that is the action that you're going to apply, right?
Like a more intuitive example is something like if I gave you the task of opening a door,
right?
The first thing, if if you're an enforcement agent and you've never opened a door in
your life, the first thing you do when you're in front of a door is that you're going to
try every possible action, right?
And you're going to try a very random things.
So now in your action space, you have the action of licking the door handle, which is,
you know, could not lead to you opening the door, you can you can try kicking the door,
you can try, there's so many things you can try.
But if you have the opportunity, maybe to sit on a chair next to the door and watch how
other people do it and then try what they're trying to do, like these people may be trying
to do other things with the door.
But the hope is that by trying what other expert agents have tried in this particular state,
you know, you may be doing, you may avoid this, this, this, this, this, this random nature
like that, that may lead you to undesirable states, like it kind of grounds your, your search
for good actions.
And also, you know, like because these agents that you're watching expert agents, you can
assume that they're behaving optimally or in a way that they're not trying to harm themselves
in any way.
So when I hear you describe it like that, the thing that comes to mind for me is imitation
learning.
How was that related to what you've done here?
So how I understand imitation learning is that you're going to be observing.
I think you're going to have access to some expert trajectories.
And I think the task today is to try and follow those, right?
You're basically trying to make those trajectories more general in any way.
You want to kind of imitate the expert, right?
Whereas here, what we're trying to do is that we're not really performing the same task
as the expert that we're watching, right?
So the action process framework has the flexibility that the different experts can be performing
different tasks, right?
And by different tasks, I mean, tasks that have different reward functions, right?
Meaning that it doesn't matter what the action that the experts are doing, as long as the
action spaces are the same between the agent that is learning and these experts here, right?
You may find some benefit in basically trying what the experts tried, like if that makes
sense.
You're trying to act according to this body of advice, like I think advice kind of makes
more sense, right?
So if I can recap what you're saying to make sure I understand when an imitation learning,
if you've got our scenario with the robot sitting in a chair, observing an expert interacting
with the door and imitation learning as it's classically defined, what you're really trying
to do is have the robot, you know, look at someone performing a very specific task like
rotating the door handle thousands of times or however many times and you're trying to
teach it that very specific action.
And any other actions would be noise and that kind of model, whereas in what you're doing,
you're presenting, it's kind of not random observations, but observations of a bunch
of different things, reaching for the door, turning the knob, opening the door.
It's more unconstrained and you're trying to use all of these observations to kind of
condition the exploration process.
Yes.
That's exactly what I'm trying to do.
Okay.
So, yeah, it's just as you put it in unconstrained, I guess, version where you're trying to,
you have all these multiple demonstrations, you're not exactly trying to follow any particular
trajectory, but what you're interested in is what these experts are kind of doing in any
particular state.
So, if you visit a state, you can always ask the question, what did experts do, right?
And maybe there'll be some arbiter or some Oracle that will tell you, hey, 63% of experts
took this action, maybe 23% of experts took this action and then, you know, other experts
took this particular action and no expert took this particular action, right?
So then I want to, in that case, basically try the actions that were more popular as opposed
to the one that the experts didn't try because you can imagine that in a model like that,
you're kind of implicitly representing in this case, I guess, the state space in the environment
and maybe the experts in this particular state are not moving for, are not taking the action
for going forward because this is a cliff, right?
So as they were training, they found that, okay, when they went forward, this led to a
very bad reward.
So they decided, okay, I'm not going to take that action.
I'm just going to do this and that.
You know, so it's basically you treat it as this party of advice that you can, like,
you know, kind of query at every step in your exploration process.
One question I'm curious about is how you define the state space and if you're doing
anything to generalize it and I realize there's a lot of loaded language there.
What I mean is kind of going back to this example of the robot observing the expert.
If the expert is reaching for the door handle, you could learn a lot about that action.
But if you're only able to access what that expert has done, if the robot is in the exact,
you know, if all of the dimensions of the robot, you know, it's all of its positions
are in the exact same point, then you kind of miss out on a lot of advice from, you
know, experts who were, you know, their hand was doing the same thing, but it was shifted
over a centimeter or something like that.
Yeah, yeah.
That's a question of portability, right?
So, so this in the original paper, right, the way the authors basically tackle this
problem is by introducing a second version of the action prior framework, which was conditioned
on observations instead of the state, right?
So obviously, if you're trying to learn this distribution over actions given a state,
right, basically asking, okay, what action should I take at this particular state?
You are only going to, that model is only going to be useful, should like in an environment
where the state space doesn't change, you know, so essentially if there's an obstacle
here, that obstacle should not move at all, right?
And they'll also stay the same place and stuff like that.
But as soon as you move like an obstacle or something that was not like, for example,
if you were training in an environment way, let's say the obstacle is in one particular
position, right?
And then now you take demonstrations from that setting and you try to move it into a setting
where the agent is training, where these obstacles have been moved around now.
What's going to happen is that that information is not going to be portable, right?
So to try and fix that problem or to fix the problem, what the authors did, this is Benjamin
Rosman and Subramarine Ramamothi, I think, remember correctly.
What they did is that they conditioned the action prior distribution over observations,
meaning that I guess if you can imagine if all the obstacles were blue and your agent
can be like, oh, your body of advice could be something that says, okay, if I see a
blue thing, I want to do this or this, you know, so basically whenever I see an obstacle,
I want to do one of the following deterministic things, you know, so you can increase the
possibility of this action prior framework by just conditioning on observations instead
of this state.
I guess I'm trying to visualize how you represent the state for a given problem.
How do you figure out, is it, is the representation, like, I'm, you know, I'm imagining it's a
vector of some sort, but is it a vector of, like, if it's a robot, like all of the stepper
motor angles and that kind of thing, or is it something else?
Is it more abstract?
No, no, it's exactly that.
So if you have a robot, like a robot arm, then it will be your joint angles and stuff
like that.
It's literally, so how I think of reinforcement learning in general is that you're going
to have some target environment and then you can have a state, right?
I defined in the framework of often a Markov decision process, you can have a state and
then you have access to actions and the transition function and then you have a reward function
I guess in some gamma discount factor thing, but yeah, like a state can mean anything that
you wanted to mean as far as, as long as you have formulated the problem you're trying
to solve as a reinforcement learning problem, like that's how I think about it.
So in my case, so then the question that I was trying to get at in this case is let's
say that your state vector is all of your angles and you've got this.
You're basically able to consult the Oracle, so to speak, to see if it knows anything
about what to do in a given state.
I guess the question that I'm asking is like, when you consult the Oracle and you say like
these are my, you know, angles out to the second decimal point, the second decimal place,
will it return what it knows even if it's not exactly that, but kind of close or do
you have to kind of generalize it around it before you consult the Oracle or will you
only know about things that happen at the very exact places?
Does that make sense?
Yeah, it does.
So that's a very good question, right, so that is precisely the challenge with trying
to move.
Okay, let me just first say this action prior framework was defined, the thing for it to
work very well in the discrete setting, which is true for most deep reinforcement learning
and reinforcement learning algorithms, right.
And moving into a continuous setting where you don't really have any guarantee that you'll
ever see the same state again, there's, there's a need for models that can generalize,
you know, like in some region and say, okay, for this particular region of state space,
this is what the action distribution looks like, you know, and stuff like that.
And I think that is what motivated my choice in what model to use to represent the action
prior.
That was a Gaussian process, which has a very nice, a smoothing effect, you know, like
as far as data is concerned.
Okay, okay.
Yeah, now that you've said it, all of the language that I should have been using to ask
the question is obvious, like discrete versus continuous and so just maybe to take a step
back to make sure I understand the question I'm curious about now is how your specific research
fits into the broader landscape of research in this area?
Okay, so how I thought about it, right, was basically if you want to have a robot that
can perform multiple tasks and things like that, right, you, okay, if you want a robot
that is going to be useful in any particular scenario, then you need to think about, I think
the field is called lifelong learning, right, and lifelong learning is basically trying
to get these systems that can basically learn tasks as they are presented either, you know,
in parallel or sequentially and then retain their ability to perform those tasks and then
somehow use the knowledge that they've gained in learning the previous tasks to what's
a thing to improve the learning of concurrent tasks.
And I think that's almost how humans do this learning thing, right?
So if I then think about the challenges that you get there, the first one is just trying
to perform successful, you know, transfer learning in my case in continuous settings,
you know, so I would, I can imagine that the action-price framework kind of fits somewhere
in between, in between having like a very full or rather, it's one component that you
would need to have a lifelong learning system or a lifelong learning robot, you know.
So for example, my whole pipeline would be something like you train some expert agents
in some target environment, right, and then these expert agents or these tasks, right,
you're actually trying to learn can be, you know, all basically learned by the same robot,
so to speak.
And then this particular robot would use or sample trajectories or like keep a data set
of trajectories from these learned tasks, right?
And it would fit this model, this action prior distribution over those trajectories.
And then for every task that it wants to learn, it can basically explore according to this
action prior distribution, and after it has learned this new policy, it can then sample
trajectories from there augmenting its data set, and then, you know, fitting the distribution
again, you know, and then when learning a new task, it then going to use the exploration
policy again, and then that just keeps going on until you have this machine or the system
that can perform, you know, multiple tasks and things like that, you know, so I like
to think of it as, I guess, a step towards lifelong learning, and one of the problems we
have there in lifelong learning is we need to, I guess, solve the problem of transfer,
as well as, you know, if you're talking about deep reinforcement learning, you need to
kind of worry, or at least dedicate some time towards how to do exploration more efficiently
and more safely.
Before this explanation, when we were talking about experts, I was thinking in terms of
observations, so your system would have some set of observations and those represent
the experts, but you just introduced this concept of training expert models.
How is that done, and kind of how is that different from the ultimate model that you're
trying to train with reinforcement learning?
So you please read the question.
So it's you asking if how different is having this whole notion of an expert model compared
to having what?
Reinforcement learning, like the expert model is presumably the expert model is simpler and
more readily trainable than a DRL model, is that true, or are the experts also trained
using reinforcement learning?
So in this case, I think my notion of expert, or how I think of expert, of what an expert
is, it could be a deeply enforcement learning agent that was learning a task in the same
environment, and now I just sample trajectories from the policy that I get from there, and
then I use those samples to train the agent that I'm going to train next on a different
task.
It could also, expert can also mean, you know, just some, I guess in the context of video
games, you can find that maybe a human player can kind of demonstrate what the correct actions
or the correct policy is by playing the game and giving the reinforcement learning agent
this trajectory that goes to the game in some sort of optimal way.
And yeah, so it's basically either your expert is either agents that you were training in
the same environment, or it could be just some human demonstrations and things like that,
you know.
In the context of getting learning from demonstration, when you're talking about robot manipulators,
you can have someone who's trying to teach a robot how to wave by actually performing
the action themselves and then recording that trajectory, you know.
So my, I think the notion of expert in this case is just a bit more general.
You know, say we're back at the door, and is the idea that we would have separate expert
models for reaching and turning and pulling and that kind of thing?
Or is there one expert that knows how to open a door?
So I want to say maybe in training and expert how to open a door, right, you'd use information
from these other experts, right.
So reaching a door and turning the handle could all be actually useful actions.
Okay.
Yeah, in that case, this task is, it feels like it's arranged in a sort of like a hierarchical
way way, turning the door could be considered as some kind of, I guess, opening the door
could be considered as some kind of macro action that is composed of these smaller policies,
such as reaching for the door handle, turning the handle and then pulling, you know.
So yeah.
And the action priors framework I'd like to think is more primitive in the sense that it's
not hierarchical in any sense.
It doesn't really, although you can kind of make it hierarchical by using options and
other stuff like that, but my particular use case is using action priors or rather the
action priors rely on actions that are kind of primitive, you know.
So as long as my experts have the same action space and state space, then I can be able
to use trajectories from other expert models or trained models and use them to train one
particular target task faster and safer.
So in other words, if you're trying to train an agent to open the door, you don't really
care.
You may have access to these experts that were trained on these sub tasks, but you don't
really care about that implicit hierarchy.
You're just looking, you're asking the question, hey, the arm is here.
What do people use?
What do experts usually do when the arm is here?
And then kind of sample from a distribution of that answers that question and use that
to inform your next step.
I'm trying to move or rather trying to think independent of or rather I'd like my model
to kind of not consider the reward functions or what task was being performed by any particular
expert.
Right.
Okay.
Because it makes sense for me to use data from an expert that was performing a very similar
task.
And now when I say similar task, I have to in my pipeline somewhere consider, how am I
going to compare task similarity?
Like how do I know that this robot is performing a task that is similar to this one before deciding
to sample trajectories from the policy that I got from this one?
Right.
So it's something like if I have this library of policies that do multiple things, the
first task is to first maybe traverse through all these trained policies, checking to see
how similar these tasks that they're performing to my tasks to the task that I'm interested
in.
And then after finding the one that is most similar, then I can now perform transfer.
But I guess what I'm trying to do here is trying to perform multi task transfer, which
is basically you just have this library of tasks, tasks and you're trying to extract some
common knowledge from them and then use whatever body of common knowledge to kind of speed
up or improve the learning of some tasks that you're interested in.
You're not looking at test similarity at all.
You're just looking at, you know, what do we know about what these experts do when we're
in this state?
Yes, yes.
So I'd like to think of transfer as like falling into two categories, right?
And the first one would be aggregate transfer, right?
We're trying to transfer from like I guess all the tasks that I have.
And then the other version of transfer would be kind of more selective to say, okay, in
this library of tasks that I've learned, these maybe three tasks are very similar to the
task that I'm trying to learn.
And I'm going to take these three and transfer only from those, right?
So yeah.
And then when transferring, we also need to be careful of things like negative transfer
because you can imagine that not all that knowledge is going to be used for some is actually
going to be very bad for like it's going to hurt the learning of this target task if
you're not careful, you know, and you can imagine that's one challenge that I kind of have
to worry about here.
So again, taking a step back to understanding the specific focus and contribution of your
research relative to the broader landscape, it sounds like action priors is already
out there, epsilon greedy exploration policy, we know is already out there is what you're
adding here, the idea of this multitask transfer from multiple action priors, or is it something
else?
It's essentially the extension of the framework to continuous settings, you know, okay.
So yeah, so just trying to understand how you can still maintain a notion of account
in a continuous setting, because if you think about having a discrete space like, for
example, and maze with with tiles as as as states, it's easy to basically keep some table
where you're like, okay, this particular action has been performed this many times and this
action has been performed this many times.
And then you build a decision over that, you sample over like from that categorical distribution
you get an action outright, but now how do you do that for for for for the case where
you you don't really have the ability to to to even kind of maintain account, because
you essentially have as soon as things become continuous, you kind of have infinitely many
states, right?
And and the other thing is that you get this effect off of multi modality where at the
same state, you need a model that can kind of represent these different action preferences
like these action preferences from from this this data that that you have these trajectories
from the experts that you have like for for example, if if we're talking about maybe
let me see.
So you have an action space where actions can range from minus one to one, right?
And you can imagine that maybe in this particular setting, experts, most experts prefer an action
of 0.2 or around they prefer an action that has a mean of 0.2 and other other experts can
have a preference around maybe off of minus 0.7 and things like that, but then there should
be this places where if if you were to put a mean around there like that would result
in a very, very bad kind of policy, you know, so it's kind of like you have a one to many
mapping, right?
At every point in the state space, right?
And that is not really in my experience.
It hasn't been very trivial to kind of learn, you know, cause I think neural networks are
kind of the more for kind of one to one type of mapping, you know, where you have like
input and, oh, no, they call this the more for many to one type of scenarios where you
can have multiple inputs and then you have like one kind of output in the end.
But what happens when you have like a single input, which is like your state and then you
have all these like possible wild values that you have to get out, you know, so my experience
with using just like a standard neural network is that you get this averaging effect and
you have noticed that the the average of of of expert actions in a particular state is
not an expert action or is not an optimal action.
Yeah.
So in the scenario of I guess a self driving car, you can imagine that you're driving into
like a kind of fork, right?
And then in the middle of the fork, there's something like a tree or something like that.
And then your experts would be going either, you know, a steering have a steering angle of
like minus 0.5 at the decision point.
And then other other experts have have like, I guess, 0.5.
And then what happens in that case is that if you try to learn your guess action prior
distribution or action preference distribution at the decision point, you might just average
over the two and you get like a steering angle of zero and that says, you know, drive straight
into the tree.
And then that's not useful at all, especially if you care about your cause.
Yeah.
And so how does this model compensate for that?
The framework does compensate for that.
But I have been looking at models that try to to look at how to represent a multimodal
policy.
Like for example, especially since I'm talking about probability distributions or it's kind
of like I'm working with mixed Gaussian mixture models, right?
So I need something that will basically take in a state and then give me a mixture, a
Gaussian mixture model of sorts over the action space.
And recently I've been playing with things like, um, I'm playing with things like mixture
and city networks.
And those have been giving me promising results.
And then there's still like some ammo of models that I have, I guess I heard about, um,
I think it's overlapping mixtures of Gaussian processes.
And basically it's just, um, models that have, uh, support for, uh, models that can give
you, um, multiple outputs given a single input, you know?
So yeah, that's kind of, uh, the challenge here.
So is the idea that kind of referring back to your self-driving car example that you,
you know, given your state, you know, one of these mixture models would be able to tell
you that there are two distributions that, uh, are likely one is centered at minus 0.5
and the other centered at 0.5 and then based on, you know, based on that information, you
would know to choose one of those as opposed to choosing the zero or averaging out to zero.
Yes.
So that's exactly what I'm trying to do.
And, and actually you highlighted another problem there, right?
Which is how do you choose how many modes they are, you know, like, um, no one is going
to tell you that, um, the good kind of behaviors here, uh, like, there's only two of them,
meaning that you have like, uh, two kernels or two, two modes, like in, in your mixture
model, right?
Meaning, um, you got your goal left and then go, right?
Um, that kind of thing can, can change, um, um, at, at different points in, in, in, in
the state space.
Maybe some states have got like an action preference distribution way, like experts
are doing kind of three optimal, uh, uh, things and then like in other cases, it may kind
of change.
So like learning this kind of model has been, uh, a bit challenging, um, when it comes
to, like, continuous environments.
And I feel like this is typically, typically the case when you're moving some, I guess,
reinforcement learning algorithm from a discrete setting, uh, towards continuous settings.
Because I'd like to think that the real world is, is made of continuous contact, continuous
quantities and, and, and stuff like that.
And there should be some, um, care taken as to how, or what kind of model you're going
to choose to, to represent that, like for, for example, going from, um, standard reinforcement
to deep reinforcement learning, we need to care about how we represent our policy.
So, you know, um, um, going to use maybe some, uh, deep neural network and, and this
is going to, I guess parameterize my policy.
I also need to represent my action prior, uh, distribution.
It's just, there's so many, you know, things that you, you need to kind of like, uh, tweak
and, and work with for you to have a fully working, working system.
Maybe as a way to start to wrap up, can you give me a list of kind of the top three things
that you've learned about doing about a, I guess, about deep reinforcement learning in
general as applied to robotics, but with a particular emphasis on taking, uh, existing
research results from the discrete domain into continuous environments.
Uh, firstly, just moving from discrete environments to, to, um, for, from, from discrete environments
to continuous environments.
I think one challenge, uh, with doing that is, uh, just representing, uh, I think your
policy, right?
So, for example, uh, I think, I think the first paper that I came across, um, that kind
of did like a good job with that was, was DDPG, it made me very interested in, in trying
to apply, uh, reinforcement learning, um, towards, um, it, it basically, like, allowed me
to believe that, okay, reinforcement learning will work in, in, in the robotics domain,
right?
Um, but then the paper again, uh, I think it's, it's, it's deep deterministic, uh, policy,
policy gradients.
Okay.
Right.
There's a, a newer version, I think D4 PG, um, not sure, but yeah, but, uh, essentially,
um, it's like an, uh, it's a critic method and that it has all these, um, okay, let me
just say, like, it is one of the, the first papers that, that kind of worked in, in, in,
uh, deep, in, in robotics, right?
So to apply DDPG reinforcement learning in, like, with continuous environments, right?
Um, I think, I think besides trying to learn, like, a, a good policy, you need to kind
of think of, uh, exploration, like, how you're going to handle, um, exploring this very,
like, uh, the, your, your, your, your, your, your state space, given the fact that it's
continuous and there's like infinitely many, uh, states that you can, uh, occupy there.
And, um, the, the other thing is data in robotics is very, like, it's, it's, it's very,
it's very hard to come by, like, you, um, you kind of need to, or rather, the ideal case
is to not have a lot of, um, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's to not have to train
your, your model for a long time, right?
You'd like to maybe train, um, your model, like, for, for a very short period of time,
but, like, in reality, if you're using, like, these model free methods, um, you find
yourself training for a very, very long time.
And that makes it difficult to kind of apply, um, um, existing work in the sense that
maybe you have, like, uh, you're working on your laptop and you can't run these models
because it's going to take a long time to converge.
And the other thing in reinforcement learning is that, uh, I realized it very late, um, um,
in my master's project where, like, I realized the fact that, uh, your random seed is, is
quite a very, it's a very important thing, you know, like, so you can, you can blame the
model all you want to, like, you get, maybe you get, like, a very good, uh, kind of learning
curve and you feel like, okay, this thing is working and you run it again.
Um, and what happens now, it basically gives you, like, a very flat thing and shows you
that it doesn't work.
So it fluctuates a lot, there's like all these variants.
So I learned that, okay, for you to actually, for people to be able to trust your results,
you need to be able to kind of average them over multiple runs and multiple runs means
that you're going to be running your, you, I guess, you'll algorithm for like a long time
and, um, that is just more compute time.
So like, you can't, you need like, uh, I guess compute, compute is a very important thing,
you know, so I'm fortunate enough to have, um, access to a cluster, like, um, we have,
I think something with, with 60 blades, like, at the university, um, and I can basically
run multiple experiments in parallel and, um, I can get my results within, uh, two
hours or so, you know, but the one challenge is just, you know, um, you, firstly looking
for environments, you're looking for, um, things that won't take too long, you know, um,
and then also, yeah, exploration has been like a very, uh, a big thing, you know, so, yeah,
I don't know if that answers your question, but, um, yeah, those were like, in my experience,
things that I found very difficult about trying to apply, uh, deep enforcement learning
in, in, in the robotics domain, just data and having very accurate simulations.
Like, for example, you start out very, very ambitious, um, for example, we have a physical
robot, uh, in house here, um, like this mobile manipulator and I'm like, I want to apply
deep enforcement learning, maybe learn to pick up a cup, and maybe the cup will have water
and stuff like that.
And as you kind of traverse through the literature, you start checking things off from this
checklist or like from these ambitions, you know, it's like, okay, maybe there shouldn't
be water, you know, like in the cup, and then maybe the cup should be like a ball, you
know, something that's, I don't know, easier to, to, to, to hold.
And then you're like, okay, maybe instead of having a ball, I'll just have, I'll be moving
the manipulator just along like this, you know, and then you keep going and then you
find yourself, okay, maybe you have instead of having a physical robot, I'm going to
build a simulated version.
And then when you're there, you're like, okay, instead of building a physical simulated
version of the robot, I'm just going to build a simple 2D thing just to see if like these
models work.
And then you go all the way down to like a simple navigation domain, like a 2D thing where
you can kind of easily prototype ideas and, you know, so it's, it's a very humbling
experience.
You start out very, you know, big and then like you kind of, you kind of get to narrow
down into these like particular problems and you need something that's going to allow
you to evaluate your ideas like quickly and, and, and, and very, you know, very efficiently
and things like that.
So yeah, like that has been my experience, I think with, with deep, deep RL in robotics
and I think other applications that have been trying to use it in.
Yeah, and I think your experience is very much in line with, with the experiences of
others and it has, you know, that kind of experience I think has led a lot of people
to kind of, you know, leave deep RL in frustration and move on to simpler things.
But it's, you know, certainly a, a space that I find fascinating and thank you for kind
of walking us through the way you're approaching it.
Yeah, thank you.
Thank you.
Like I really, really relate to like that, that last part, you know, I understand people's
frustration and understand the reasons if they end up leaving deep RL, you know, like
I think what has helped me stay here is the, the communities that have been exposed to
like, for example, I've met other people deep learning in Daba who are using deep RL
for the, for the unique applications and we get to kind of, you know, talk and if you're
having a problem, you can ask this particular person.
Same thing is happening at Black and AI and like in some cases, you know, I guess through
Black and AI, you get to meet the leading researchers in the field of the people who wrote
the paper that's giving you sleepless nights and headaches and you get to ask them directly
like, yo, what is this ex like, how did you make this work and what was, what motivated
you, your decisions like for, I guess, choosing this particular thing.
So yeah, I really, really understand, I guess the frustration and why people would be frustrated
with the field, but hopefully going forward with this whole movement of trying to get people
to release their code more like this whole thing of reproducibility, problems like that
will tend to die out.
Awesome.
Thank you so much for taking the time to chat with me.
Thank you, Sam.
And I think you're having me.
All right, everyone.
That's our show for today for more information on secret, or any of the topics covered in
this episode, visit twimmelai.com slash talk slash 235.
For more information on the black and AI series, visit twimmelai.com slash black and AI 19.
As always, thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.