Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast why interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
Today we're joined by Andrew Goldman, vice president of product engineering and research
and development at Fluid.
Andrew and I caught up a while back to discuss Fluid XPS, a user experience built to help
the casual shopper decide on the best product choices during online retail interactions.
The XPS has expanded since we recorded this interview, we specifically discuss its origins
as a product to assist out-of-wear retailer the North Face.
In our conversation, we discussed their use of heat sink algorithms and graph databases,
their use of chat and other interfaces, and the challenges associated with staying on
top of a constantly changing technology landscape.
This was a fun interview.
Before we jump into the episode, I'd like to join Pegasystems, this episode's sponsor
and inviting you to meet me this June at Pegasworld, the company's annual digital transformation
conference, so that it optimizes every customer touchpoint on every channel in real time.
That way each interaction is relevant and timely to each individual customer, no matter
if it's a sales call, a digital marketing campaign, or a customer service chat, either
online or in-store, and the system is always learning in real time to make the next interaction
better.
Pegas Customers are the real stars at Pegasworld.
There, you'll hear great stories of AI applied to the customer experience at real Pegas
Customers.
The event is a great way to learn from a who's who of the Fortune 500, and of course, I'll
be there and speaking as well.
To register, visit Pegasworld.com and enter the promo code Twimble19 when you sign up.
Again, that's Twimble19, it's as easy as that.
Hope to see you there, and now on to the show.
All right, everyone.
I am on the line with Andrew Goldman.
Andrew is VP of Product Engineering and R&D at Fluid.
Andrew, welcome to this weekend machine learning and AI.
Thank you very much.
Great to be here.
So you've been at Fluid for about 18 years, not counting a brief hiatus that you can
describe, but why don't you tell us about Fluid and the kind of work that you've done
there over the past 18 years?
Great.
Thank you.
So in general, Fluid focuses on providing excellent user experience for online retail,
and Fluid has agency and software as a service divisions, and within both of those addressed
engineering design, user experience and strategy, Fluid's clients include the North Face,
and we'll be talking about shortly, Puma, Vans, Benefit, Cosmetics, and many, many others
with offices in New York and in Oakland.
So that's Fluid as a whole.
My particular role at Fluid has been focused on engineering leadership, so I've worked
in both the agency and software as a service side of the business.
For the last several years, I've worked primarily on two big projects.
One of them, Fluid Configure, online product configuration platform, and the other XPS,
which we'll talk about in more detail.
XPS stands for Expert Personal Shopper, applying AI technology to online retail.
And XPS was a product or XPS was a project that Fluid created for and with the North Face.
Is that right?
Initially, yeah, they were our first customer with XPS.
It's expanded a little beyond that, but they were the initial focus, yeah.
Let's jump into that.
Tell us about the general problem that you're trying to help these retailers solve.
Sure, sure.
Absolutely.
We'll first just really brief encapsulation of the North Face in case people are unfamiliar
with them.
They provide top quality gear that's really designed and targeted towards climbers, runners
and skiers.
And of course, a good jacket for runners is also great for hikers and is also good for
lifestyle and so on, but they're really targeted towards technical high quality gear.
So what we were trying to do for the North Face, the genesis of XPS, was to help the more
casual users figure out what to get from the North Face, you know, the really technical
like the expert climber would probably know what they need in a jacket.
But somebody who's going back backing for the first time might not really know quite
what to get.
And so we wanted to help them sort of help them sort of emulate the experience of working
with a knowledgeable sales associate in a scalable online venue.
I can relate very personally to that need right now.
I am in the process of planning my first bike packing trip, which is basically camping,
but kind of carrying your gear on a bike that's going to be later this month.
And the array of stuff that the lists say that I need is immense and then kind of sorting
through all of the different options for each of the various components is just, there's
a lot of work that one needs to do to at least if you're like me and you want to kind of
get the right thing, it's a lot of work.
So I can definitely see why an online tool in particular one that's powered by some
element of AI would be super helpful to folks.
But exactly, so you're trying to build this tool, what is the, what is XPS provide?
How does it kind of emulate this assistant?
How does it emulate like a sales person at a store?
In format, we adhere fairly closely to what would happen with the sales associate.
You have a conversation, you know, there's questions and answers going back and forth.
And through that conversation, the sales associate is accumulating important information, you
know.
And then as that information accumulates, that sales person's recommendation gets better
and better.
So what that means in the more technical world of XPS is that we have, we actually used
graph database technology to represent the, we called them facts, just to be a fairly generic
term that could be used across, to me, in different things at different times, you know,
but like, you'd have this directed acyclic graph of facts that could be hierarchical that
eventually connected to products and the edges in the graph had weight associated with
them.
So as a session with XPS proceeds, you're parsing XPS would parse the responses from the user
if they came in via free text, or it could also work with button clicks if the answers
were a little more directed.
But either however they came in, it would result in weight being placed on nodes in the
graph and then the directed graph, we used a heat sink algorithm to accumulate weight
on the products and thereby derive the recommendations.
What specifically is a heat sink algorithm?
So a heat sink algorithm, if you have, you know, a directional graph where things, an
acyclic graph where things point in a direction, just to look at a simple example without getting
into hierarchy, you can consider product characteristics.
So we're looking at North Face Jackets and you could say, okay, this jacket has color,
right?
So it can be red or it can be blue or it can be green or whatever.
So you'd have an association sometimes people would have color preferences so you'd have
an association, directed association from green to this particular jacket.
So then if it comes out that I'm looking for a green jacket, I'd put weight on the green
node in my session specifically and then that weight traverses the edge of the graph and
ends up on, well, the multiple jackets that could be green, right?
So green would be associated with an array of different jackets, all of which would receive
weight from green.
Then simultaneously, I'm looking for a waterproof jacket.
So I put weight on waterproof.
Waterproof is similarly associated with a collection of jackets.
The weight derives from, or it travels from waterproof to all of those waterproof jackets.
So we have some jackets that have accumulated heat or weight from green and others that
have accumulated heat from waterproof.
And so some jackets are hotter than others.
The jackets that are both green and waterproof are the hottest ones.
And so you have like multiple sources of heat, you know, the nodes that have been activated
and then that heat accumulates on products.
Where does AI come in in this project?
What requirements did you have for artificial intelligence as you were building us out?
Well, the artificial intelligence requirements were pretty high level.
The initial genesis of the product was a partnership between IBM and Fluid for the benefit of
the North Face.
So the original idea was to use Watson to create this technology.
But that's pretty broad, right?
So as we dug in to implementing what I was describing there, the first attempt was just
to use Watson as is.
At the time though, this is way back at the beginning of Watson.
This was, you know, a little bit after Watson had been used in the Jeopardy game show.
Okay.
And we have a lot of notoriety there.
Right.
But at the time it was a single API, it was this question and answer API that was really
targeted towards the Jeopardy use case where it didn't, it didn't have the idea of context
like I was describing where you accumulate knowledge through a conversation that really
wasn't part of the game.
And it also was designed to come back with a single answer, you know, because in Jeopardy,
you don't say, oh, well, it could be this or that or that or that, it's just one answer.
Right.
So the question answer API didn't really fit our use case.
So that was when we started getting into this graph database business.
So in the context of the solution I was describing, we initially used AI technology for natural
language processing to try to make sense out of the utterances that users would provide
to us.
That was the initial piece.
You know, what I was describing with the graph and everything was basically a content
based recommendation engine that really doesn't use a lot of sophisticated AI techniques.
We'd always had in mind to get to machine learning sort of collaborative filtering type
techniques to improve the recommendations.
But you know, as of now we're still, we're still waiting to get there.
So it's been a little more focused on content based recommendations.
The interface for XPS, is it a chat, I'm assuming it's a chatbot type of interface?
And if so, are you using a platform technology to manage the chat interactions, you know,
parse out the intents and all that kind of stuff, are you doing that manually?
So at the highest level it is a chat interface and it's super compatible with things like
Facebook Messenger and we have implemented it on Facebook Messenger, but it doesn't
require a dedicated chat platform like that.
It runs just fine in a standard browser as well.
So it's pretty flexible in how it can be deployed.
We initially, when we were building this out, the supporting technology to manage the
conversation for us was not super satisfactory.
So we sort of built our own deal.
In the meantime, since then, we've evaluated other technologies like IDM Assistant, which
do a lot of the same things that we've been doing and have a lot of advantages, just
the training capabilities they have, the ability to understand intents as well as entities,
the ability to impact the behavior of the conversation, you know, to change the flow,
the conversation, have it work better without having to do any coding, it was really attractive.
So what we're sort of in the process now of incorporating watts and Assistant into
XPS, sort of as complimentary pieces, if you want to go into a little more detail about
how XPS guides a conversation relative to how watts and Assistant does, they have fundamentally
different approaches, which can work well together.
Sure.
Had that direction?
All right.
No, that's interesting, because you mentioned using them in conjunction with one another
and I was starting to form a question around how that's going to work, so to start with
watts and Assistant, I mean, that's fairly, there's a whole sort of family of technologies
that operate in fairly similar ways.
And they parse intents based on the intent that's been identified, can parse out entities,
and so you can do things, you know, a customer service, it can understand that you're trying
to track and order to be your intent, for example, and then it can know that in order
to track and order, it needs to have an order number, right?
And so it can try to parse the order number from what you've said, or if it doesn't get
it, it can solicit the order number, once it has that, then it can move forward.
And so you've got this sort of structure of intents with related entities, and it can
guide a conversation that way, it can solicit what it needs based on what the intent is.
So that's kind of the watts and Assistant approach.
XPS, on the other hand, is much more, is intended to be much more sort of directive and focused
and purposeful and flexible in what it's doing, like its sole purpose is to recommend products.
So you've got a potentially confusing collection of products, you know, like all these jackets,
so many jackets, there's like 20 kinds of ski jackets, what the hell, you know, right?
So there's all these products with the intention of recommending the right ones.
And the watts and Assistant approach tends to lead the order in which information is solicited,
is somewhat fixed.
You know, if you're looking for an order, you get the order number.
Whereas within the jacket recommendation world, there's a lot of different things that
you could be soliciting.
You know, there's how it behaves in certain types of weather, you know, how it does relative
to wind and rain and temperature, there's color, there's breathability, you know, on and
on and on, like the number of questions that could potentially be asked is big.
And if you ask them in the wrong order, it doesn't appear very intelligent.
So our one of probably our core challenges of XPS was guiding the dialogue in a way that
would allow it to make the best recommendations the quickest.
So we incorporated kind of a taking that heat sink idea that I was talking about earlier
where you figure out what price recommend based on the information, you know, we kind
of flip that on its head and use like a complementary idea of hypothetically saying, well, if we
knew this, how helpful would it be?
If we knew that, how helpful would it be?
Combining that with the natural collections, you know, natural groupings of these facts,
you know, like if you're saying like, is it, is it good in mild wind or high wind or calm
or whatever, if you're looking at the wind speed collection of facts, well, that condenses
nicely to a single question.
You don't have to ask three separate questions, you know, it's like, how windy is it going
to be?
And perhaps your answers are buttons if you want or it could be free text, whatever, whatever
you want, right?
But if we've decided based on analyzing all of these different facts and running them
through these scenarios, we decide we care about wind is the most important thing to
influence our recommendation.
And we ask about wind, you know, if we get to another point in a different conversation
with a different user, maybe based on what they've told us, it's more important to ask
about color to differentiate the candidate product set.
The way I would describe the algorithm that you're describing is along the lines of it's
trying to maximize information gain per question asked or something like that.
Basically, I mean, the way that we phrase it is differentiating the candidate product
set, you know, like we have based on what we currently know, we know that there's a set
of products that are suitable.
And what we really want to do with the next question is chop that set in half and be more
confident about half of it.
You know what I mean?
We kind of simplified the challenge to try to make it more consistent.
We found that taking that approach worked pretty well.
So that's how we scored each one of these potential questions to ask, did how much does
it split the results set in half and how much does it increase the confidence of one
of those halves?
How complex is the algorithm excited that is there a pre-existing algorithm that's known
to solve that kind of problem or did you have to kind of invent something from scratch?
We invented stuff.
We were working.
This was logic that ran in the graph database.
We were using TinkerPop APIs.
It's TinkerPop APIs.
Yes.
Yeah, I don't know where they came up with that name.
It's standardizing the way that you can interact with graph databases.
It's sort of like JDBC is to relational databases.
TinkerPop is to graph databases.
So it's a set of standardized APIs.
We were initially working with Neo4j and we moved over to Titan.
The graph database space is quite volatile.
It was nice to have this sort of standard API to work with.
We were writing Java code that used TinkerPop APIs to interact with the graph.
It was sort of like streaming APIs.
If you work with Java collections and you start streaming them and then you do one thing
to them and then you get a stream back and you do another thing to them and you kind
of chain these calls together.
It's just sort of typical sort of a Lambda type flow within Java.
So you do things like you get your set of facts and then you filter it based on the ones
that have weight and then you see where they point and what the edge weights are and you
calculate the accumulated weight and you filter again.
Anyway, all these sort of traversals and streaming stuff in Java.
So yeah, we had to write this code.
We basically would look at the, you take the original set of recommended products, then
you'd apply hypothetical weight to a single fact and then you'd see what the result of
that was in this new result set and then you'd just repeat that process for any of the facts
that you could consider asking about and then you'd just compare the sort of the weighting
of the results, the recommended products and see which one had the profile that most
closely matched, chopping the original set in half and increasing its confidence.
And so was your product catalog space or there are the intersection of your product catalog
space and the characteristic space such that you could do that calculation all in real time
or did you have to pre-compute some of it or could you pre-compute some of it?
It was all real time, yeah, the graph database ran quickly, I mean that was one of the reasons
we chose that technology.
The traversals are really, really fast and the accumulation of calculations as you navigate
as you traverse through the graph could happen really, really quickly too.
You build this algorithm that allows you to direct questioning in a way that helps a
user kind of iterate as quickly as possible to a single product or a small set of products
that they're interested in but you still see their opportunities to use that in parallel
with the Watson platform, how would those work together?
Yeah, yeah, good, yeah, that was what I was supposed to be describing before, right?
I was describing these different mechanisms for driving a conversation with Watson Assistant
having this intent and entities approach versus what I was describing with XPS and so
the way they fit together nicely is that if you have, if the utterance can be, if Watson
Assistant can get some traction with the user's utterance, then you let it do its thing.
So if it says, oh, this is customer service, I got this, then XPS isn't going to be able
to handle that, no, that's not what XPS does.
And so if Watson Assistant was able to figure out that it could do some with it, then it
does some with it.
So Watson Assistant is kind of the initial recipient of the request.
And then if Watson Assistant either identifies that it's not an XPS could deal with or it
just doesn't know what the heck is going on, then XPS takes a cut at it.
Yeah, it sounds like if you walk into a store, there's a greeter there that greeter is
Watson Assistant.
If you have a customer service question, they'll walk you over to the CS desk and kind of figure
that out.
But if you want to buy something, they'll kind of direct you to a salesperson and that's
XPS.
Exactly, exactly.
Because what we found, I mean, this is pretty obvious if you think about it really, but
you know, when people come into like a chatbot experience, they don't all want to do
what you want them to do, you know, they're like, they're checking it out.
They're like, oh, what is this thing?
And XPS was really not very good at handling this broad array of things that were coming
up.
People just chatting.
People were like, hi, you know, an XPS didn't really know what to do with hi, you know.
Right.
I'm curious about the software development process and specifically the idea of incorporating
in these, you know, external AI-centric APIs and any ways that maybe you had to think differently
about the development process, you know, relative to other kinds of projects.
Well, I think the big difference is that the, you know, the AI technologies we were using
like Watson Assistant and to a lesser extent some of the NLP stuff we were using, it's
not like, you know, talking to weather underground and getting back the weather, you know what
I mean?
You have to train them, you have to prep them up, you know.
So there was this body of work that typically is best handled by experts to get the corpus,
get the service ready to do what we needed it to do.
And just needing that different skill set definitely presented challenges for us.
You know, our team was really a team of software engineers and the idea of using APIs at runtime
was super comfortable, but the idea of needing to train a service so that it would recognize
certain intents was pretty foreign.
And just because of staffing challenges, the engineers typically had to kind of step into
that role of training these systems.
And so did you have to build out specific processes and tooling to enable that to be done
successfully?
Um, I mean, I don't know if it was really that formal, it was basically like people were
obligated to do it and so they did it and as they did it, they got better at it.
You know, the tooling was already present, you know, like there's Watson Knowledge Studio
comes as part of the package, which is, you know, great tooling sophisticated at this
point.
It's mature works really well.
So we fortunately didn't didn't have to address that part of a puzzle.
I mean, we were looking, we played around at different times with just manually using
Watson Knowledge Studio to do the training versus trying to do it via APIs.
You know, and we hit our heads on walls every once in a while when we would try to do our
own automation is generally work better to like do it the way they sort of want you to
do it, which is more manually or less or yeah, exactly a little bit more manually.
In the case of WKS Watson Knowledge Studio, it was easier to just go into their UI, do
their thing.
I mean, that's continually progressing, which actually I think is another way that this
type of work was a little different than the work that we were accustomed to doing.
What's that?
Well, like just this exact thing you were talking about, like trying to script, trying to
interact programmatically with some of these services would change, it would change way
more quickly than we were accustomed to.
There'd be new vendors offering things that were better from one week to the next, you
know, WKS would have a big iteration and things would change around and things that weren't
possible previously were now possible.
There'd be discontinued practice like, like Watson Assistant went from being Watson dialogue
to Watson conversation to Watson Assistant and if through each step of that, there were
major changes.
So it's just such a like booming in a live field, sometimes it's just like ground is constantly
shifting under us.
And so we had to incorporate into our normal development process.
This idea of sort of continually having spikes where we were doing research about things
that we had already researched, you know, there had to be kind of a lot more time and energy
put into staying abreast with the current technologies.
And we also incorporated short, really short sprints.
We're on a weekly sprint cycle on this project throughout throughout its whole life cycle.
At the beginning, we thought it was going to be a temporarily short sprint cycle, but
we found that we continuously were needing to like adjust course, you know, we'd learn
something new, we get some new feedbacks, there'd be some new technology and we're continually
just kind of let's say zigzagging because we were generally playing in the same direction
of the significant, you know, adjustments to the approach on a almost on a weekly basis.
Yeah, but at the same time, it sounds like you were able to successfully get this done
with a traditional engineering team, whereas if you were, you know, needing to build all
of the AI and LP conversational bits from scratch, it may have been a bit harder.
Yeah, absolutely, absolutely.
Yeah.
And the degree of maturation in the space that we saw in the, you know, couple of years
we spent building it was just amazing, you know, it would have been awesome if it could
have been at the place it is now two years ago, it made our lives a lot easier, but we
you know, perhaps gained a deeper appreciation of the advances.
How did you address like the testing part of the development cycle and understanding, you
know, did you try to create some kind of regression testing for the training process?
So you knew if you kind of broke something in training, that kind of thing.
Right.
Great question.
Kind of mapping this, you know, traditional dev process to this, you know, AI enhanced,
let's say, dev process.
Yeah.
You know, I'm afraid my answer is going to be a little bit of a cop out here.
We were looking at this, finding the right balance between delivering stuff quickly for
a small number of customers in this constantly shifting space versus having a solution that
was really solid and scalable and we'd be able to use for 50 customers, you know, there
was this real tension between that.
And as you say, it's directly attributable to applying sort of traditional web software
development, multi tenant software as a service practices to this AI space.
So, you know, we, we just kind of did the best we could, we had thorough regression tests
around the more traditional parts of our code base.
You know, we had thorough unit tests, test coverage metrics and all that kind of stuff
around the express application and around our react front ends and stuff like that.
And it came to the Watson assistant pieces and the NLP training, it was a little softer.
It was a little softer.
We were intending to button that up a little better as we move forward.
And we're expecting, you know, given the pace of evolution of the tools, we're expecting
that it's going to be easier to do that going forward.
You know, it was like Watson knowledge studio advance, we're expecting to be able to script
the training more thoroughly and tie that scripted training to testing the results of it
more thoroughly.
But it's really tricky because not only is potentially our training set changing, but
also, you know, like Watson assistant is a service we're relying on that's constantly
evolving.
So it could be that our training data stays the same.
But the results change, even though we can't change anything.
And so we didn't get too obsessed with buttoning that up at this point in the process.
Right.
Embrace the chaos to a certain extent.
You know, and I think an important sort of corollary to that is that, you know, we're
not sending rockets into space, right?
And we're not automating million dollars trading, right?
We're recommending jackets.
And so we, we kind of leveled the appropriate appetite for risk with the domain.
You know, if something goes awry with the training of Watson assistant and it's not quite
right, well, you know, we can tolerate that.
So, you know, we, we do our best.
Where did the training data come from?
We have thorough analytics built into XPS so that we keep track of every step of every user's
interaction with the service.
And we're able to use the utterances that we captured from users throughout the process.
So there's, there's a manual step to it in that the taking the data from our analytics
system and feeding it in to Watson knowledge studio.
There were some manual processing involved with it, especially around the ground truth.
You know, like we could have automated feeding in all the utterances, but it would have
been a little trickier to say what the correct responses should have been.
But we did have the advantage of accumulating a large amount of real data and being able
to use that throughout the process.
And from the perspective of the engineers that were working on this, what was their experience
like did they feel like they had to become data scientists in order to be successful
with this project?
Or, you know, was there a good balance between the APIs taking care of, you know, the deep
algorithmic bits in them, you know, doing the higher level training stuff, the integration
and the traditional engineering tasks?
Yeah, a good question.
You know, there was a, on the one hand, the engineering team were, were somewhat generalists
who really enjoyed being exposed to new ideas and new technologies.
You know, so like in the course of this project, some of the people on the team were learning
react and redux for the first time, for example.
Okay.
But the entire team was learning about the Watts and APIs for the first time.
And so being exposed to new technologies like that was awesome.
And I think there's just the idea of understanding and being exposed to the role of a data scientist
and how that compares to software engineering and being in a situation where they were forced
to kind of be a little bit more immersed in that data science role than they ordinarily
would have been.
I think that was, that broadened horizons and was welcomed.
At the same time, I think there were kind of, you know, they reached kind of a saturation
point where like having to deal with the fact that it wasn't, you know, recognizing,
you know, the difference between, you know, there are some examples of these things, you
know, there are certain utterances that just cause problems like, yeah, just like negation
is a simple one.
You know, I want a jacket that's not green or you could say that anything but green,
you know, and recognizing these negations correctly can involve some extensive training.
Some of the language around that is fairly ambiguous to the untrained NLP system.
And so like having to go back in and like, oh, anything but green, why isn't that working?
How are we going to train that?
Like that wasn't generally the developer's favorite part of the job, you know, yeah, so
I think at the abstract level, the idea of understanding data science and how that fits
into the process and how these AI technologies really work was awesome and they loved it,
but they kind of had enough after a while.
And kind of end of the day, how was the project received from the North Face's perspective,
customer perspective?
Well, it was certainly understood from the get go that this was kind of bleeding edge
stuff, you know, that we were figuring this out on the fly and giving it a go.
So the like the format and the vision of it, I think, was awesome, you know, they really
like that.
One of the challenges that we met with the North Face that honestly surprised me was
the product attribution turned out to be surprisingly challenging.
I had assumed that the North Face would have really thorough, like facets, faceted characteristics
of their jackets that would provide us with all the raw material that we would need
in order to differentiate them through a conversation, but we found two challenges in
that.
One is that the the existing faceted search capability that you see, you know, basically
across the commerce landscape is really good, you know, like if, if you want to just sort
of check boxes and say, I need a jacket that's waterproof, I need a jacket that's green,
like you don't need this conversational interface to do that.
You can just click, click, see it, you know, that's like, so that is so surprised you said
is really good because in my head, as you were saying that I was thinking is really horrible
I guess in some places it's implemented better than others is probably the best way to
say that.
I mean, I think of like kayak.com, you know, when you're searching for flights or
hotels or something, you know, I'm like, to me, that's awesome, you know, just it's
really nice, like, but you're absolutely, of course, you're right.
I mean, it's not implemented well across the board, but the idea has been articulated
successfully in certain cases.
So we deliberately did not want this conversational experience to be perceived as like a watered
down version of a faceted search.
Right.
And so part of that sort of necessitated that we have facets, you know, we have product
attributes that are different, you know, there's kind of qualitatively different.
And so we started looking, you know, experimented around with different things, you know, like
more emotional type attributes where you'd say, like, I want an adventurous jacket.
Well, like, what does that even mean on one, you know, but if you could, if you could
somehow capture that and kind of represent that or, you know, like, like the personality
of the shopper can translate into like finding jackets that match that personality, whether
it's adventurous or studious or whatever it may be, you know, so we spent some time kind
of exploring that in order to really maximize the conversational benefits.
And that proved to be difficult.
I can't say we hit, hit it out of a park with that piece.
So there's, there's clearly room for more progress, like identifying what, how to make
this more satisfyingly conversational and how to obtain the product attribution necessary
to do that.
All right.
The challenges that you had with regard to the product attributes specific to these more
emotional attributes that you were looking for or even some of the traditional attributes
as well, like the kind of the, did you deal with challenges and just having the basic kinds
of information you'd want to help customers make decisions?
Yes, for sure, for sure.
Take, take waterproofness, for example, like if you don't think about it too much, it seems
really straightforward.
The jacket's waterproof, it's not, right?
But it's, no, it's not that simple.
And there are some barely formally defined standards of waterproofness.
You have water resistance versus waterproofness.
And so you have the one challenge of like the interface with the human being, you know,
with the person who's by this thing, right?
And like trying to avoid jargon, but it was surprisingly difficult to avoid jargon.
Same thing with windproofness, wind resistance and all that.
So you've got kind of this sort of impedance mismatch between the technical characteristics
of the jackets and the way a user might perceive them.
And then sometimes too, there were just missing data, you know, you just, you would think
that they would just all be there, but it's not, you know, like the systems that they
use, sometimes all the dots don't connect all the way up to where we got the data.
So it got to be sometimes a bit of a bottleneck, just getting data that they just must have,
but it wasn't flowing to us.
And how did you address that?
Well, the scale that we were looking at with, that we were looking at with the North Face
is relatively small, you know, we got a few hundred jackets.
So we would just work, we were just working with the North Face product team and just working
with people there and they help us resolve things that are missing.
That's sort of a simple part.
It's cumbersome, you know, it's not super ideal.
And it raises questions around scalability, you know, like it's working okay, because
we got, you know, 300 some jackets, but if we were to expand, that would be more problematic.
With other customers, we've worked with, we've had larger numbers of products, which has
made those problems more, more real, and we've had to resort to, well, not resort to,
we've leveraged, there's actually another place where machine learning has come in, where
you get information, the information that you have about a product, you know, things
like its description and so on, can be used via machine learning to perform classifications
and determine some of its attributes, limited, you know, it depends on what kind of description
you have for that product, as to how well that will work, or if you're able to tap into
supplementary sources like product reviews, but it's really helpful, but it doesn't
truly solve the problem.
We've also looked at crowd sourcing to help with it too, but it's just definitely a
challenge.
It really kind of opened my eyes to like a whole industry.
I didn't really quite realize that there's like a whole industry around product attribution
and it's tricky.
Yeah, it's amazing.
So you've some years back or some, at some point someone used some attributes to come
up with a description, but you've lost connection to the attributes themselves and have to
like infer them using ML from the descriptions that they wrote, basically, that's sort of
what it seemed like, yeah, yeah, wow, wow, yep.
And so this, the system is like, it's up on the northface.com slash XPS.
How do you see it evolving over time?
You've talked a little bit about, you know, some, some areas, but where does it go from
here?
What's the budget?
I think that probably the most interesting place for it to go is machine learning.
So we've got that whole heatsink business I was talking about to provide content based
recommendations, but providing using machine, I see using machine learning in two ways
to benefit system one is to help figure out which question to ask next.
So you could be seeing based on the characteristics of a session in XPS, you could see which questions
not based on this predictive stuff we've been doing, but you could just see based on like
actual results of prior sessions, which questions delivered the most value.
Right, right.
And then, of course, you could also be using it to actually provide product recommendations.
You could see, okay, based on how this session is progressing, you know, what products
received positive feedback from similar sessions in the past and then bump those recommendations
up.
And like I had mentioned, the analytics tracking that we've been doing, you know, came up when
we were talking about like, training the NLP system, well, that NLX system also will
provide us with training data for both of those applications of machine learning.
So we're positioned to make that happen, but all you have to do is listen to a couple
of episodes of Twimmel to understand that it's a piece of work, you know, that's, you
know, that, but I think that would be a great place for XPS to expand.
Andrew, thanks so much for taking the time to chat with us about this project.
It sounds like a ton of fun, and I'm looking forward to playing around with it and maybe
seeing if I can find a jacket.
Yeah.
Hopefully we can expand to give you advice about bike paniers and tents and stuff.
Thanks a lot, Jim.
Thanks, Andrew.
All right, everyone, that's our show for today for more information on Andrew or any of
the topics covered in this show, visit twimmelai.com slash talk slash 239.
As always, thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.