Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast why interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
Today we're joined by Dan Schreider, Assistant Professor in the Department of Genetics at
the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.
My discussion with Dan starts with an overview of population genomics and from there, digs
into his application of machine learning in the field, allowing us to, for example, better
understand population size changes and gene flow from DNA sequences.
We then dig into Dan's recent paper, the unreasonable effectiveness of convolutional neural networks
in population genetic inference, which was published in the molecular biology and evolution
journal.
The paper examines the idea that CNNs are capable of outperforming expert derived statistical
methods for some key problems in the field.
Before we dive in, a quick thanks to our friends at Pegasystems, sponsors of today's show.
Pegaworld, the company's annual digital transformation conference, which will be held
at the MGM Grand in Las Vegas from June 2nd to 5th, is just a couple of months away now.
I'll be attending the event as I did last year and will once again be presenting.
In addition to hearing from me, the event is a great opportunity to learn how AI has
applied to the customer experience at real-pecker customers.
As a Twimble listener, you can use the promo code Twimble19 for $200 off of your registration.
Again, that code is Twimble19.
Hope to see you there.
And now on to the show.
Alright, everyone.
I am on the line with Dan Schreider.
Dan is an assistant professor in the Department of Genetics at the University of North Carolina
at Chapel Hill.
Dan, welcome to this week in Machine Learning and AI.
Hi, Sam.
Thanks for having me.
Awesome.
It's great to have you on the show.
So you have an undergraduate degree in computer science, but you are now an evolutionary
biologist.
Can you tell us about that transition and how it led you to work in machine learning?
Sure.
Yeah.
So it's actually sort of a series of transitions.
And it started when I was in undergrad, I was studying computer science.
I got into that field because I liked to write code in high school.
I didn't really know what I was going to do with it.
And during, I believe, my sophomore year, I started going to seminars about sort of
various topics in computational research.
And I heard about this thing called bioinformatics.
And it turned out that you could write code to do research in biology.
And I thought that sounded amazing.
I always sort of liked the idea of being a scientist, though I didn't know much about
biology at the time.
And the night after that seminar, I immediately started looking into taking biology courses
and sort of shifting focus.
And from that moment forward, I was training to become a biological researcher as well as
a, you know, someone with computer programming skills.
I was not sort of keen on the idea of being a software engineer.
And yeah, when I heard that, oh, someone like me can, you know, be a biologist.
I thought that was really cool.
So I started doing that.
And when I wrapped up my degree, I decided to stay at Indiana University and started working
there with Matthew Hahn, who is my PhD advisor there.
And our area of research was population genetics, which is a subfield of evolutionary biology
where you're sort of looking at the evolutionary dynamics of gene sequences, especially in
the recent evolutionary history.
And you do this by looking at sort of the patterns of genetic variation that are present
within a population.
So you go out to nature, sample a bunch of individuals, sequence their genomes, and see
what sense you can make of all the variation there.
Started that at the beginning of grad school, fell in love with it, and haven't really looked
away since now you might be gathering that this involves a lot of data analysis, a lot
of sequence analysis.
And we're interested in population genetics with trying to tease apart the different
evolutionary forces that are shaping patterns of genetic variation, things like natural
selection or demographic events such as population size changes, like population crashes
or expansions, and all of these things sort of leave their footprints in patterns of genetic
variation within species.
So we're sort of interested in going backwards, taking these patterns of variation and making
inferences about the evolutionary forces at play.
And it turns out that machine learning is a great way to go about doing this because
you have a lot of high dimensional data and we're trying to sort of, you know, churn out
as much information from it as we can.
Very cool.
One question that just jumps out at me is you mentioned that your study or maybe evolutionary
biology in general is focused on recent changes in genomes.
What does that mean in this concept?
Yeah, certainly clarify.
Population genetics, my sort of subfueled within evolutionary allergies, is often more
concerned with recent changes because the recent evolutionary events, because those are
the things that shape present-day patterns of genetic variation.
And so how recent is that in this context?
Yeah, so it depends on the organism and, you know, there's sort of theoretical expectations
for sort of how far back in time you can see based on present-day patterns of variation
and without going into the theory, the idea is essentially that if you take one, we'll
start with one human individual, so humans have two copies of each chromosome, one from
mom, one from dad, and if you compare those two copies, you'll see a bunch of differences,
and that is because these two chromosomes, at some point in the past, were derived from
the same ancestor, but enough time has passed since then that mutations have occurred and
everything, and therefore you see differences between the two.
So we expect that those two chromosomes will have been separated, you know, on separate
sort of evolutionary trajectories for the last two end generations, wherein is the population
size, so that's sort of the expectations.
For humans that turns into something like a scale of hundreds of thousands of years,
and using populations, genetic approaches, you have more resolution to say something about
kind of the more medium, the intermediate and recent subset of that range, so up until
the last 50,000 years or so, we have a lot more power to see what's going on, and once
you get back sort of half a million years ago, you're sort of running out of information
there with that, that's sort of the time range that we're talking about.
And to put that in some context, half a million years in humans, you know, they can compare
that to the time since our split with chimpanzees, which was about five to six million years
ago.
Maybe walk us through some of the biological concepts that might be handy in kind of
exploring what you do and how you apply machine learning.
Sure, so I think sort of the key concept is that we're dealing with a sample of genomes,
so it's not cost effective to sequence every genome in the population, so we draw some
random subset and sample them, and then what we get is a string of letters, A, C, G, and
T is for for each of the individuals that we've sequenced, and then we're sort of putting
that together into this matrix where each row in the matrix is one genome sequence, and
each column in the matrix is one site along that genome as we're moving along.
So that the human genome, for example, is about three billion of these sites.
Now not every one of those sites will exhibit variations.
There's not always useful information there that we're going to look at, but you know,
there's a lot of columns in this matrix.
So that's sort of the data that we're dealing with, then there are a number of questions
that we're interested in answering with that data, one area of research that has been
a major focus of mind for the last several years is looking for the signatures of natural
selection.
So if a new mutation shows up in a population and is harmful, then it will be rapidly
removed by natural selection because individuals bearing that mutation will be less likely
to reproduce.
And therefore in that region of the genome, you might expect to see a deficit of diversity.
If on the other hand, a new mutation appears and it's beneficial, then it will rapidly increase
in frequency because individuals harboring it are more likely to survive reproduce and
leave offspring. So after some number of generations, this mutation has increased in frequency
to the point where it has replaced the ancestral version of that site in the genome.
And this will also create a sort of distinct characteristic signature of selection that
we can try to uncover by using some of these computational techniques.
So yeah, there are a whole number of other interesting areas in population genetics that
are doing similar types of research.
We're taking this sort of input matrix and trying to infer what is going on there.
But the natural selection question has been one that's especially near and dear to my
heart over the last few years.
Does that depend on or assume that you are doing a complete sequence of the genome for the
samples that you're working with or are you able to make inferences based on partial
sequences as well?
You can use partial sequences.
In fact, population genetics as an empirical discipline has existed for quite some time
long before we were able to sequence entire genomes, especially if organisms like humans
where we have this large complex genome.
Yeah, there's sort of, we refer to this as kind of a shift from population genetics to
population genomics because for much of the field's history, we were interested in what's
going on at say one gene rather than looking at patterns of variation across an entire genome.
But now with increases and the speed and cost effectiveness of DNA sequencing technologies
were now able to look at variation at genome-wide scale.
So yeah, you're not limited to cases where you have whole genome data, but it's getting
to the point now where anybody can sequence a gene, anybody who has a lab and modest research
funding can sequence a fairly large sample of genomes.
And when you're doing the type of experiments that you describe or you're trying to understand
natural selection, is the implication of what you describe that you're kind of fundamentally
looking at stable sections of the genome as opposed to those sections of the genome that
tend to exhibit a lot of variation, or are you looking at those as well for different
things?
Yeah, so in my work, a lot of what I do is I'm sort of trying to walk along the genome
and look at how sort of the landscape of variation changes.
So you'll have some areas where there's a lot of variation, somewhere there is not.
And we try to make sense of that by sort of segmenting the genome into these different
classes or evolutionary models.
So this chunk of the genome looks like it's being shaped by positive selection, which
is that scenario where beneficial mutation has recently increased in frequency, or this
region of the genome seems to be experiencing negative or purifying selection where harmful
mutations are being removed.
And this region of the genome seems to be evolving relatively free from selection.
So mutations don't really affect fitness.
They're just kind of drifting around randomly over time.
So their frequencies are fluctuating, but it does nothing to do with any sort of selective
benefit or harm caused by the mutation.
So yeah, basically I'm trying to figure out how much of the genome is evolving under
one particular model of evolution versus another, and so on and mentioned in the landscape
as you move across chromosomes.
And so you recently published a paper called the unreasonable effectiveness of convolutional
neuron networks in population genetic inference, actually they came out earlier this month.
We're speaking at middle of February.
And that was published in molecular biology and evolution.
Can you talk a little bit about that particular paper and what it is trying to convey?
Yeah, so this paper is purely methodological and focused and that we're sort of interested
in the different statistical and computational methods that population geneticists have been
using over the years.
And a major focus of my work over the last five years has been to try to incorporate
machine learning techniques into population genetic inference.
And I should probably start there before I get into this paper because this is kind of
the culmination of a lot of that.
I was wondering just that if it was a culmination of a trajectory of things that you tried
in machine learning applied to population genetics or if you, you know, I also talk to scientists
that kind of, you know, just luck into hearing about her finding out about CNNs and deep
learning and apply it to their problem and damage as works and they kind of start there.
So how did that evolve for you?
Though, the way this evolved for me was around the time that I was finishing up in grad
school and getting started with my postdoctoral research.
I was becoming increasingly interested in this question of, you know, how much can we
learn about natural selection from looking at genomic data and the methods for doing this
in population genetics I found were, to me, they seemed a little bit antiquated in
that they were often focused on taking your alignments, you know, this matrix that I'm
talking about, this matrix of genome sequences and sort of boiling it down to a single number.
So describing your sequence data by a single statistic, which is descriptive, it tells
you something about how much variation is there in this alignment or what are the frequencies
of mutations in this alignment are some of them very common within the population or
they're very rare, to what extent are two mutations correlated?
That is, if an individual has a mutation at site one, how does that tell you something
about whether he also has a mutation at site two, there are a large number of statistics
that all sort of captured different somewhat redundant but somewhat complementary patterns
of a variation and there's kind of this cottage industry and population genetics of coming
up with a new statistic that you think is the best one for answering the question that
you're looking at and sort of describing the theoretical expectations for the statistic
under various evolutionary models and, you know, applying this to some data and seeing
what you can learn.
Well, that's all great, but, you know, you can imagine that if you take this large matrix
of genome sequence data and boil it down to a single number, you're probably throwing
out a lot of useful information, right?
So the work that I was doing during my postdoc and there's some other labs that are doing
this too, I'm not the only one doing this, but it was sort of a small group of population
geneticists doing this and we were just trying to incorporate as much of this information
as we could into a method and one way to do that is to, instead of using one of these
statistics, use a large vector of them, throw them all in to a vector and try something
like support vector machine or random forest so you can use a support vector machine and
train it to distinguish between natural selection or no natural selection.
Yeah, if I can jump in just to make sure I understand what you're doing, you've got kind
of this underlying set of data, which is essentially these alignments, you've got genomes or
genome samples that are aligned with one another and the first thing you did was you took the
traditional metrics that have been applied to these alignments and you kind of calculated
all of them, put those into a vector and then use machine learning to, for example, identify
clusters within the vector space that you created of these summary statistics.
Is that correct?
Yeah, that's right.
So the idea is rather than arguing over which one of these summary statistics is best,
we should see how well we can do if we use all of them at once and machine learning
is one way for you to do that because you can use it for higher dimensional data.
So when you say how well you do, what was the specific problem or what are the types of
problems that you're trying to solve?
Is it just clustering them together or are there other problems that you apply this
technique to?
Yeah, so a lot of population genetic inference is about discriminating between different
evolutionary models.
So let's go back to this question of can we find whether there has been a recent beneficial
mutation that has increased in frequency and become what we call fixed or ubiquitous
within the population?
So a little bit of terminology, we call this a selective sweep because this mutation is
selected and it sweeps through the population.
So this problem of finding selective sweeps is a very difficult one, but it's one that's
sort of central to pop general research because we're interested in how much recent
adaptation, you know, particular species might be having whether it's humans or anything
else, you know, how are we responding to the selective environment that we're in?
So you can use this information to tell you something about how much adaptation is there,
which parts of the genome are responsible for this adaptation, but it all boils down
to this model selection thing.
Can I discriminate between regions of the genome that are experiencing a sweep and those
that are not?
So the way that I have gone about this model selection is by treating a classifier to
do it.
Is the data just the sequences, at least at this point in your application of machine
learning, is it just the sequences or is it the sequences, for example, and I guess
I'm curious about if there's some element of time that's captured like the, you know,
birth or death or eight, you know, the timestamp of the sequence or something like that.
And you're looking at these sequences over a long period of time.
Is it like a time series thing or are you able to infer these sweeps just by looking
at t equals zero set of samples and the way that they're distributed?
Sure.
Yeah, that's a great question.
So generally we do, you know, think about the scenario where you only have sampling from
one time point.
So, you know, you've randomly sampled from some population, you know, last year and
you have this data set and you're trying to use it to make these inferences about, you
know, recent evolutionary history.
And a large reason for that, I mean there are two reasons for that.
One is the practical cost of accumulating sequence data and that cost has gone down.
I'll come back to that in a second.
And the other is that if you want to do this sort of time series thing, you need to say
you want to sample every generation.
Well, if you're doing that in humans, then, you know, each generation, you know, might
be 25, 30 years or so.
So to sort of capture any interesting patterns or you have to be accumulating data over a long
period of time.
Now, some organisms have much more rapid generation times.
They also work on fruit flies and mosquitoes and, you know, these things rather than having
one generation every few dozen years they'll have a, you know, a dozen or so generations
in one year.
So over the course of a few years, you're going to accumulate a large number of generations
and create time series data.
And this is something that's becoming feasible now with improvements in sequencing technology.
So I would say that that's kind of a small subset of the kind of landscape of pop chin research
right now, but you're going to be seeing that changing very rapidly.
I think so.
So you'll see a lot of this time series analysis, but right now it's mostly just looking at
this one snapshot.
So at this stage where you're creating a classifier, you've got this data as we discussed, it tends
to be from a single period of time or a period of time I'm assuming that where you can
kind of, they're close enough that you can kind of ignore time as a big factor.
And you've collected this data, can you talk a little bit about the data collection process?
So in, this is where it gets a little bit tricky because in sort of more traditional applications
of machine learning, you want to collect training data.
And here we can't do that, you know, we collect data that we can apply something to, right,
we can sequence a bunch of human genomes that we want to run our classifier on.
But how do we get a data set where we know what the ground truth is?
And you know, that can be tricky and evolutionary biology because, you know, while we are doing
our best to make evolutionary inferences, it's difficult to nail down with absolute certainty,
right?
What is the evolutionary history of, you know, this species, this population or this gene?
So what we do is we simulate.
So there are these nice idealized models of evolution that allow you to simulate an
evolving population and sequences within this population.
So you can produce synthetic data that one can then use to train a classifier.
And then the tricky part is, you know, how do we simulate this thing?
How do we parameterize these simulations and, you know, you have to be careful to sort
of try to make these simulations match your data as best as you can.
But if you knew exactly how your data, you know, how your organism of interest was evolving,
then you wouldn't be needing to do the research anyway, right, because you already know everything.
So it's kind of analogous to doing some sort of Bayesian inference where you've got, you
know, these priors.
And, you know, here we're simulating onto those priors to generate training data.
And you have to examine what is the robustness of this classifier to model a specification.
What if I'm wrong about the, you know, the parameters of the simulation?
What if I, you know, I thought the population size of this organism was 1 million, but
actually it's half a million, how does that affect the accuracy of my downstream analysis?
So you have to take all these things into account.
Is there some like prototypical human genome that you use as the starting place for your
simulation or some kind of standard human, how does that work?
Yeah.
So, yeah, there is.
That's a great question.
So we typically refer to these as reference genomes.
So for the way that sequencing started out like this approach was that you would go and
create one very high quality genome sequence for your species.
So we did this in humans and it took over a decade and a billion dollars to sequence
the first human genome, which we call the reference genome, but it's this very high quality
sequence and you can use that by using these cheap and fast DNA sequencing technologies,
which produce a bunch of very tiny chunks of DNA sequence that you then search against
that reference genome.
So that's this, that's how you create these alignments that I was referring to by doing
sequence searches and figuring out, okay, this tiny little chunk here that goes to this
part on chromosome one, I can figure that out by searching it against the reference genome.
So there are sort of these two different tiers of genome sequences, are these very high
quality reference genomes and then there are these genomes produced from these rapid sequencing
technologies that are mapped against the reference genome in order to reveal variation
because you take this tiny chunk from this individual sequence, you map it to the reference
and you see, okay, this little chunk or read, we call it, it's identical to this portion
of the reference genome except for this one difference.
And if you accumulate enough evidence for those differences, then you know, okay, that
is a mutation that's present in my population.
And then you referenced needing to make sure you get the population size right.
In the case of humans, for example, where does the complexity come in there and is it
correct relative to this reference genome and the specifics of the population you're sampling
or what kind of resolution do you need there?
Yeah, I mean, that's a good question and it's still a very open area of research.
So you can go get the census population size of humans today or pretty good approximation
of it, but that has not been the size of our population over much of our history.
There's been dramatic changes, of course, growth most recently, but in many populations
there were contractions, especially with those populations that migrated out of Africa.
That migration was associated with a large population bottleneck.
So the population size history in humans is, it's messy, it's non-monotonic and it concludes
with this very rapid, super-exponential explosion that's been going on for the last
few hundred years now.
So to what extent can we accurately model these population size changes, that's another
area of research that actually touch upon a little bit in the CNN paper that we'll be
talking about.
Yeah.
I don't know if I answered your question.
No, I think you did.
I think my takeaway was it's complicated.
Yeah, okay, then I think I did a good job.
Yeah.
So you're doing this simulation, you're applying kind of Bayesian types of methods, you're
trying to apply probability distributions at different points in the simulation process.
I guess the question is, are you doing that per read or SNP or something like that?
Are you doing that on a sequence level like do you, are we at the point where we're modeling,
variability and distributions on a kind of subsequent level or is it kind of a more
coarse-grained model today?
Yeah.
So for the most part, Rich, and sort of zooming in and looking at relatively small regions
of the GNOME, so that's kind of what we're simulating, yeah, to sort of come up with
expectations for patterns of variation within, you know, say a size of the genome that's
spanning, you know, a few dozen genes, something like that or less, sometimes something on
the order of a single gene.
So yeah, typically we're looking at smaller regions, but for some questions, especially
this question of trying to infer demographic changes like population size changes, we
want to be looking at patterns of variation across the whole genome because if there's
a population crash, that affects the amount of genetic variation across the entire genome.
So we want to use as much of that data as possible.
So yeah, another development in our field in recent years has become feasible to simulate
larger and larger genomes.
So we can sort of capture the expected dynamics genome-wide, not just, you know, at a gene
or a few genes.
So we do the whole gamut, I guess.
Okay.
And so this approach to training a classifier based on the sequences and simulated results
to provide your ground truth was one of your first steps in the direction of applying machine
learning to pop-gen, you know, the CNN, the next step, or did you have a few more steps
to get there?
Yeah.
So I played around with this approach on, I guess, a few different problems.
You know, I was mostly interested in this natural selection question, but I branched out
to a few different areas.
You know, I kind of got a little bit caught up in trying to push along a cultural change
in our field in population genetics.
I was trying to make the point to people that these machine learning methods are not scary.
We should consider trying to use them for, you know, every question where it is appropriate
and then see how well they compare to our more traditional methods.
So another question that I was looking into was this question of finding gene flow.
So this is the scenario where you have two different populations.
They diverge to some time ago, you know, say African and non-African humans, you know,
they split some time ago when non-Africans migrated out of the African continent and,
you know, colonized your Asia.
And we want to know, after that split, did these populations come back into contact at
a certain time point and exchanged genetic material?
And if so, can we find like the genomic regions where there has been this gene flow?
So yeah, probably the African non-African question is the best example of this because
that the genetic exchange is across the entire genome in cases where there has been the
secondary contact like African-Americans, for example, have European ancestry across
the entire genome, as well as African ancestry.
A better example is probably Neanderthals, so you may have heard it's been reported in
the news that we now know that Neanderthals have donated genetic material to Eurasian
Asians and Europeans, humans. So a typical European individual has maybe two to four percent
of their DNA tracing its ancestry back to Neanderthals.
So after the split between, you know, the ancestral population that gave rise to modern humans
and also Neanderthals, these two species eventually found themselves in the same location,
and there was interbreeding there, and we can sort of see the genetic remnants of that
in certain parts of the human genome.
So I got into this question of detecting regions where there has been regions of the
genome, where there has been the flow of genetic material from one population into another.
And of course, here there have been a large number of statistical approaches devised
over the years to detect these patterns, and I took the same approach of creating a machine
learning classifier that uses a vector of these statistics to discriminate between these
different models of, so here are three models where there is no gene flow between these two
populations, or within this genomic window there is gene flow from population one to population
two and vice versa. And of course, it works much better than any method that is using
just one statistic because you're throwing out all that information, so if you incorporate
as much information as you can, the feature vector you produce more accurate inferences.
So I was going around talking about that work, going to conferences, trying to sell this
stuff to people, say this machine learning stuff works, which here is the evidence.
And somebody in the audience of that talk was interested and went and looked at my code,
and thought, well, what happens if I get rid of this part that calculates all the statistics
and just replace it with a convolutional neural network? So let a neural net come up with
its own statistics and see how well it can answer this question. And this person was
Lex Flagel who was the first author on that paper published in MBE, and Lex sent me an
email one day, and yet the day I opened up this email was the most exciting day of my professional
life. He opened this up and said, hey, I got this result. I was playing around with the
convolutional neural net, and thought I'd see how it did. And here are the results. Is
this good? So I pull up my data and I'm comparing and I'm like, huh, this is better than mine.
So, yeah, so there had been a few conversations I'd had in the years leading up to this
about this idea of maybe using deep learning or some approach to say, well, act directly
on the alignment rather than pre-digesting it into a bunch of features or summary statistics.
But I never had a chance to get around to it. And then suddenly there on my screen was
the evidence that not only can you do this, but it works really well better than what
I was trying at the time. So we knew right away, or I knew right away that we had to try
this out on a bunch of different problems in population genetics to see if this approach
would work in general. And that was the work that led to the MBE paper.
In the paper you're doing just that, you're trying CNNs out on a bunch of these different
problems. Do each of these problems represent one of the statistics that you were kind
of aggregating together in your previous work? Or are the problems kind of at a higher level
and the statistics, you know, informed approaches to the problems?
Yeah, so these problems have been major areas of research and pension for quite some
time. So the different problems we touch on in the paper are this problem of finding
selective sweeps, this problem of finding gene flow. We try to infer population size changes
and the other is inferring the rate of our combination. So our combination is when
during myosis you're two different chromosome copies, exchange, genetic material, one
another. So it sort of breaks up the association between mutations along a chromosome. So you
would think that if you're looking at say chromosome one in the human genome, like if you take
one of your copies of chromosome one as you're going back in time, that whole chromosome
should have the same evolutionary history, you know, as you trace it back through ancestor
to ancestor, but recombination breaks that up. Different chunks of the chromosome have different
ancestors. And it's a longstanding problem in population genetics trying to infer how
much of this recombination happens in different parts of the genome. So can you infer the
recombination rate landscape across the genome? And you can try to do this using population
genetic data. So a bunch of methods exist for doing that. All of these problems have gotten
a lot of attention from researchers over the years. So there's not just one statistic for
each of them. There are dozens for many of them. So we were comparing our approach of just
throwing it all into a CNN and then seeing what answer comes out to many of these statistics
that have been used or vectors of those statistics, you know, like the approach I had been using
up to that point of throwing them all into a classifier and using something like a random
forest. Can you talk a little bit about the approach to making your data fit well within
the paradigm of CNNs? Did you need to do anything special there?
Yeah, you certainly do. And because we wanted this to sort of be a proof of principle,
we were focusing on simulated data in this paper just to show that this can work in principle,
and it can work better than some of the best methods that we have at our disposal right
now. We didn't want to get too deep into the rabbit hole of all the things that you have
to do when you're working with real data that can be messy. So yeah, one problem with,
so we kind of skipped a lot of this stuff or just pointed out that these are issues that
won't have to deal with. But I think that the deep learning approach is probably better suited
for dealing with a lot of these problems than some of the more traditional approaches.
Because what are some of those problems? Yeah, so a common problem is that there can be
piece parts of the genome where you just don't have a lot of information where, you know,
you've mapped these reads, but you're not exactly sure where they go or the reads are of
localities, so you're not exactly sure what nucleotide is there with the bases. So there's
low confidence data or missing data, and you have to sort of mask these out. So dealing with this,
I think, is actually pretty straightforward. In this machine learning framework, you take a look
at your actual data and see like sort of what's the distribution of missing data along my genome,
and then just adjust your simulations accordingly, synthetically mask some portion of your training
data and your simulated test data, and then train. It's a lot more easy to do this when your input
is just the sequence matrix rather than some statistic that has been calculated across the matrix,
and it might not be designed to deal with missing data. You know, we don't really have to deal
with that. We just have to supply training data that we think kind of matches what the input
data look like. You know, we think of CNS, we most frequently think of image data that has kind of
you know, often square or two dimensional or two three dimensional channels kind of structure.
How did your sequence data map to that? Yeah, so we were using two dimensional data where each
row in your matrix is a genome sequence in each column is one site. Yeah, the shape of this matrix
is different from what you might find in like a typical image or something like, you know,
the image database because you might have something like 50 rows, you know, 50 is a fairly
small number of pixels, but you may have thousands of columns, you know, maybe 10,000. So,
you know, you get these very oblong matrices that you're that you're shoving in there. So,
yeah, we're actually using primarily one D convolutions within the paper kind of treating these
more as time series data than as image data. And myself have also played around with applying
different flavors of RNNs. And I know some other researchers that are doing that as well now.
So they don't look exactly, you know, in terms of their shape, like a typical image that you'd
be throwing a CNN app. This is kind of a, a net, I guess, but did you, I'm curious if you
did like a one-hot encoding on your proteins or your gene, individual genes?
The way that we encode the sequence data is basically zeros and ones. In a lot of population
genetics, we are only concern ourselves of what we call biolilic sites. Those sites where there
are two different variants. So, you know, maybe I have an A and, you know, you have a G at this site.
You know, we'll just think of those two different alleles as zero and one. So, just a matrix
of zeros and ones. And, you know, if we are trying to use that information to find selective sweeps,
then we'll have different classes. You know, there are a few different types of selective sweeps.
So, you know, like say zero for one particular type of sweep, one for another and, you know, two for
a neutrally evolving region of the genome. Those are our class labels and it'll make a one-hot
and coded vector of those classes. But yeah, the input matrix is just a 2D matrix of zeros and ones.
Okay. For now. But I mean, there's a lot of, you know, other different ways of encoding that one
could try out here. And I think it's important to stress here. And I'm sure a lot of listeners
of your podcast will gather that we are very far behind the machine learning field, the deep learning
field. When it comes to population genetics, we're, you know, just sort of trying things out right
now and we're trying out neural nets that, you know, are at least five years or more behind the
state of the art. So, there's a lot of catching up to do and a lot of experimentation with
different network architectures, different input encodings and things like that that we have to try out.
So, can you give us a summary of the results you saw for these four different types of problems?
Yeah. Yeah. So, that's basically deep learning. If trained carefully, it can, it can at least match
the current state of the art methods. If not, handle the outperform them for most of the problems
that we've looked at. So, the one case where I think there's a lot more work to be done that we just
sort of gave a simple first attempt at was this question of trying to infer population size histories.
You know, it's the method we came up with worked fairly well there, but we want to be able to scale
up to genome scale data and you know, a simple CNN approach where you have an image that encompasses
an entire genome of billions of base fares is at least beyond our capabilities at the moment
computationally and it's probably not the appropriate method for that anyway. Something like a
recurrent neural net of some kind might be more appropriate, but for, you know, these questions of
finding gene flow, finding selective sweeps, inferring or combination rates, the results were
pretty stunningly amazing. And, you know, that's why we gave it the title, you know,
in reference to the, you know, the popular unreasonable effectiveness meme in statistics.
Yeah, I mean, we were certainly blown away about how well this stuff works and,
yeah, we wanted to share that enthusiasm with the field and get people to consider these types
of methods in the future for their own work. Awesome. Awesome. And so where do you go from here?
Yeah, so I have started my lab here at UNC almost a year ago and we're continuing some work along
these lines. So I have a postdoc right now who's very interested in trying to dive deeper into
this question of population size changes and try out a variety of methods, including deep learning
methods to to answer these and other demographic questions. So yeah, the deep learning is definitely
still a part of it. I have another postdoc who is working on phylogenomic questions. So here,
phylogenomics is different field of ocean biology where you're looking at sequences from
different species rather than sequences within one population within one species and try to make
inferences like just inferring the species tree that, you know, connects them. So figuring out the
relationship among species, you know, trying to fill out the tree of life. And he's also trying out
deep learning methods there. Yeah, it's not my plan to have a lab that's entirely based on
machine learning and deep learning, but when you've had some success using these methods and,
you know, they've got the cool buzzwords. So it attracts talent and, you know, I have people,
the people who want to join are interested in doing deep learning. So I guess that's what I'm
going to do, right? You're limited by who you can recruit. So, but no, we're enjoying it a lot,
sort of trying to push the envelope to see how much we can learn by applying these methods to
genomic data. Yeah, there's other stuff that I am interested in doing that it's not at all
related to machine learning, but yeah, that's probably a topic for a different conversation.
Well, Dan, thanks so much for taking the time to chat with us about your work. It's really
exciting to see how deep learning and machine learning in general is applied to these types of
problems in population genetics. Yeah, my pleasure. Thanks for having me, Sam. And I'm looking
forward to seeing how this stuff evolves over the next few years because, you know, I want to be clear,
there are some other labs working on this as well. And I want to see where they where they take it.
Thank you. Thanks.
All right, everyone. That's our show for today for more information on Dan or any of the topics
covered in today's episode. Visit twimmelai.com slash talks slash 249. Be sure to register for
Peggo World using the code twimmel19 for $200 off of registration. As always, thanks so much
for listening and catch you next time.