Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast why interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
If you love this podcast, you definitely don't want to miss the very first Twimble Con,
which is coming up soon.
The two day conference will focus on topics like overcoming the barriers to getting machine
and deep learning models into production, how to apply MLops and DevOps to the machine
learning workflow in your company, the latest approaches to platform technologies for accelerating
and scaling machine learning and deep learning, experiences and lesson learns and delivering
platforms and infrastructure support for data management, experiment management and model
deployment.
Platform deployment stories from leading companies like Facebook, Google, Airbnb and more,
and organizational and cultural best practices for success.
Be sure to register today at twimblecon.com.
If you've got a great story to tell in this area, there's still time to submit a proposal
for our call for presenters, which has been extended until July 19th.
Accepted talks will be notified no later than August 15th.
Head over to twimblecon.com slash CFP to submit your presentation.
Looking forward to seeing you there.
All right, everyone. I am here with Michael Levin.
Michael is a professor of biology and director of the Allen Discovery Center at Tufts University.
Michael, welcome to this week in machine learning and AI.
Thank you so much, pleasure to be here.
So you gave a talk just this afternoon to a gigantic room here at the Neurops conference.
Your talk was on a couple of themes that I have found fascinating just from the summary
of it, developmental bioelectricity and some of the implications for machine learning.
Why don't we have you get started by telling us a little bit about your background and
then we'll dive into the topic of your talk.
Sure.
My background originally was computer science.
I did software engineering for a number of years.
I got an undergrad degree in computer science.
I then went to graduate school for biology.
So I have a PhD in genetics and then I did postdoctoral training in cell biology and my lab
does a number of things in developmental biology and regenerative biology and computer science
all around the theme of information processing and computation in living systems.
So we are interested in how living biological systems process information and compute at
all scales, molecular tissue level, cell level, behavioral and so on.
Maybe you can give us kind of a broad survey of what the current thinking is around biological
computation.
It's not something that I've had a lot of exposure to.
No, and this is very much an emerging field and in fact there are lots of divergent opinions
and approaches at this point in this area.
It's a very exciting time.
My particular area comes in trying to understand how cells and tissues interact to revise the
anatomical plan of the body.
So we all start life as a single cell.
The fertilized egg gives rise to a bunch of early embryonic cells and these have to arrange
themselves into a particular anatomical structure.
So it might be a tree or a snake or an elephant or a human or whatever.
But all of these cells have to figure out what to do to make this appropriate structure and
in fact it's much more than simply creating that structure.
Some animals are highly regenerative which means that you can for example if certain body
parts are amputated they will regrow those parts, so salamanders will regrow legs and
eyes and jaws and portions of the brain.
And these kind of examples and many others that I show today illustrate a remarkable capability
of biological systems to do flexible dynamic remodeling that is they don't simply create
a structure as some sort of a pre-written set of instructions but they can modify on
the fly to repair towards a particular goal state, a coherent organism.
So when a salamander regenerates its limb for example, it stops exactly when the limb
reaches its correct size and shape.
And so the question then for regenerative medicine is not only to try to trigger this
kind of regenerative ability, we certainly work on this in our lab is to try to kickstart
regeneration in human patients down the line but also to understand how the whole system
knows when to stop and for us regeneration is primarily a computational problem, the
tissues need to know that they've been damaged, they need to know what to do to repair and
they need to know when it's done.
And these are all questions that really are very much not understood today.
This is kind of blowing my mind I think for those of us outside of the field of biology
like we know that bodies do these things and you know the answer is just oh it's DNA right
the DNA controls all of this stuff but to think of it as a computational process that's
a totally new way of thinking about it for me.
Yeah so this is very common and in fact so I gave a version of this talk to a bunch
of middle school kids last year and I asked them I showed them a picture of an egg and I asked
them what actually determines what comes out of this egg it could be a snake, a turtle,
a dinosaur or whatever and even the nine year olds all said DNA it's DNA.
Well in a certain sense it is DNA but the thing to realize is that if in this age of genomics
if you actually sequence the genome understand the genome says has information about proteins
there is nothing directly that you could read out of a genome that would tell you how
many limbs and the creature was going to have or what type of a body symmetry it was going
to have whether it was going to be regenerative or not or any of these other things there
none of this is directly encoded in the DNA what you see in the DNA is just the proteins.
How do we know like have we cracked the code to I mean we know we can sequence the genome
and know the protein sequence but how do we know that that isn't somehow encoding
you know some of these more discrete properties.
Well it's a subtle thing so what the DNA I'll jump right into the kind of the middle
of the talk so what I did at the beginning of the talk was to try to set up a couple
of things that may be surprising to people so one is this amazing ability of bodies to
repair themselves.
I showed one for example this creature known as the planarion flatworm and these flatworms
are able to regenerate any part of their body so they can be chopped into pieces.
Every piece knows what a complete planarion looks like it regrows exactly what's necessary
no more no less.
I also showed unicellular organisms that have one cell that are just a no brain just one
cell but that are incredibly adept at behavior at changing their body changing their structure
in order to fit their environment and so on so I tried to get across the importance of
understanding this kind of decision making in biological tissues.
Now the DNA code has been cracked we know we know exactly what the DNA actually encodes
the DNA actually encodes proteins.
Now down the line of course in an important sense the DNA produces everything you need
for the hardware of the body so the proteins that are in the genome that's what your
body is going to be made of okay so so hardware is critical without hardware you get nothing
however hardware is only half the story so the hardware that is produced by the DNA some
of these proteins are electrical conduits known as ion channels and the thing about these
ion channels is they can operate as little transistors they can some of them are voltage
gated current conductances just like transistors and this means that the hardware produced
by that genome is electrically active and it's not only electrically active but the circuits
that are present in these cells produce some very complex behaviors that allow symmetry
breaking self-organization and decision making in terms of pattern control at the large
scale so whole tissues whole organs whole appendages of bodies so so yes the DNA is critical
in that it establishes the hardware but the software that runs on this hardware is
not directly encoded anywhere in the DNA it is the result of the electrical activity another
way the DNA establishes the hardware which creates the software that controls all these things
essentially there's a there's a default software that will run on this hardware if it's
unperturbed but the cool thing about the software is that it's very it's very plastic and
it's written and and it operates in such a way that it's it makes it very easy for us
to rewrite it and so that means that we can intervene and I show numerous examples of
of us learning to intervene in the software to make the to make the body into shapes that
are entirely not what the genome default is so for talking about things like crisper or not
at all no so no genomic and once again no not whatsoever so the interesting thing about this
approach what makes it different is that another point I tried to make in the talk is that
computer science the reason the reason computer science was able to drive this incredible
revolution in information technology is that we moved from having to program at the level of
hardware which is where we were in the 40s you know if you wanted to program a computer you had
to get in there and shift wires around that was how we program but now because of the appreciation
of the hardware software distinction we are able to work at these in these high level programming
formalisms where you can think about the information flow the algorithm and you're not worried about
what the underlying hardware is because if the hardware is good enough it can run lots of different
kinds of software and at that point you can forget about the hardware and really focus on the algorithm
our biological hardware is good enough it is it is complex enough that it is able to run all
sorts of interesting physiological software there is some default that comes with if you don't touch
it this is what it's going to do but it is also a label such that we can rewrite it and so what I've
shown is rewriting the software without touching the hardware meaning control what happens by input
and experience rather than by changing the circuitry the there are two analogies that I will put
in forward one is at this point we program the compute we program our computers not by getting
in there and melting bits of silicon here and there but we have a keyboard we have a way of
entering information not re not rewiring the the physical hardware so everybody understands
that the same piece of hardware if it's if it's decent can run lots of different types of software
and the way you change it is by providing inputs that shift the electrical dynamics of the system
without having to change the structure of it the other analogies with the brain so the DNA certainly
includes all of the proteins instructions for all of the proteins that are required to make up your
brain but the information content of your brain is nowhere in the genome and you couldn't dream of
reading out the content of a person's memories and their mind or animals by looking at the genome
what you may recover from the genome is some default instinctual behavior so for example
let's say some insects wasps you know they're born knowing how to build a you know a thing to catch
prey and all this so the genome certainly gives rise to a neural network whose default behavior
includes these kinds of interesting things that insects do but other animals are also able to
learn and this means that you can have experiential inputs information that they get through the
visual through other senses that radically change what their behavior is going to be down the line
many circuits in the body have this kind of interesting plastic property so some of the things
that I've shown today for example one of the one of the examples was we can take a flatworm
that has a very particular shaped head and we can very transiently briefly alter the electrical
properties of that of that animal such that when it regenerates a new head it will make heads
appropriate to other species of flatworms other species 150 million years different so the shape
of the head is different the shape of the brain is different the stem cell distribution is
appropriate to a completely different animal 150 million years distant the genome is untouched
there's that we did not touch the genomic sequence because what the genomic sequence encodes
is a body that can build a number of different types of structures one of those structures is this
other type of plenary and head I've shown other examples where we can induce different parts of
the body so for example we can make a chunk of the gut of a frog embryo become an eye and again
this is this is the same thing because one of the things these electrical as it turns out
one of the things these electrical networks do is they specify large scale anatomical
decisions for the body and so the decision of what organ shall I make at any given space in
the any given location in the body is dictated by the outcome of a complex electrical circuit
downstream of that electrical circuit are all the familiar things people have heard about so
transcriptional cascades genes turning on and off physical forces tension stresses between cells
cells moving around chromatin states so all of these kinds of things but many of these important
decisions are made upstream by an electrical circuit and we have the opportunity to intervene
and I've shown I showed a number of examples of this where we can repair things that for example
animals in which defects have been induced in genes that are required for brain development for
example so we showed a is a bioelectrical fix which is a strategy that repairs their brain so
basically by forcing the appropriate electrical states in that region of the body they will build
a correct brain with the correct structure correct function and even correct behavior so
these animals get their IQs back despite the fact that they've had a genetic mutation that
normally takes out the brain completely or that they've been exposed to a variety of
horrible toeratogens that normally cause really terrible defects so there's the genome there's
the default set of things that happen normally but that layer is very rich and we get to intervene
and make a number of changes this is incredible this kind of suggests that at least at some point
you know there's a possibility of bioelectric medicine or we have any you know for humans do we
have any you know early indications of that being possible yeah very much so so so we're working
exactly on this we're working on applications like limb regeneration tumor reprogramming repair
of birth defects all of these things I think are going to be part of human medicine and one of
the important things is that something like 20% of all drugs are ion channels blockers or activators
so this means that there's a huge kind of already of starting to do this well not so so they're
all used for things like cardiac arrhythmias epilepsy so so people use them to target neurons
but my big message today was that neurons are simply a sped up a sort of accelerated version
of much more primitive ancient cells so cells were were were processing information in networks
long before brains and neurons came on the scene and while all of these drugs right now are being
are being developed for problems in in cardiac and neural and neural kinds of syndromes they form
this amazing toolkit of electrosuticals that we've begun to apply them towards problems in tumor
reprogramming regenerative induction repair and so on and so I absolutely think this is going
to be part of human medicine yeah one of the things that you were talking about in your talk
was this notion of right rewriting pattern memories is that you know this general concept that
we've been discussing or is there is more specific meaning to that well I can give you a specific
example but it's part of that same that same idea one of the things that we we we know is that
even our unicellular ancestors so single cells before they became multicellular already had
a lot of the machinery that we associate with decision making and cognition so synaptic proteins
eye on channels um neuro transmitters these things are extremely ancient and cells and tissues
were processing this information before we had brains uh this is um the the the the way that they
that they do this is by storing a bioelectric prepatterns that are um guideposts for what they're
going to do if they're damaged so we I show today an example where we can take a flower and in an
intact flower you can actually see we've developed techniques to visualize some of these electrical
memories we can see these as stable electrical states and tissues and we can go in and rewrite them
and when we rewrite them what happens is initially nothing because that that memory is latent
it's not being used but if that animal gets injured in the future so let's say we cut its head
and its tail off that middle fragment with a rewritten pattern memory will then go on to
regenerate two heads one at each end so no tail two heads at each end and this is because we gave
it a false memory we gave it a false now this is a different kind of memory it's not the kind of
memory that lives in the brain about behavior this is a memory that's distributed across the whole
body that determines the behavior of the cells as they will try to recreate what they think a worm
looks like and this representation of the fact that a worm is supposed to have one head and one
tail is not set in stone we can rewrite it and that's what we've done it also calls to mind the
whole idea of biological memory systems like the you know the human brain from a kind of storage
perspective is a way more efficient memory store than DRAM you know that we use in computers is
are there clear implications to that yes I absolutely so there are a number of applications of
this work to machine learning into AI in general certainly living tissue is an incredibly dense
information medium there are networks made of cells within with inside of each cell there are
incredibly complex molecular and also some some cellular networks things like the cytoskeleton
which process information in a distributed fashion in an incredibly dense and rich way so so I
think as as new media as new excitable unconventional media for computation biological tissues have
a lot to teach us I think that's that's absolutely true the other the is some of the other
implications are that biological systems are very very good at adaptively altering their behavior
and function in light of novel stressors so the the the problem that we a or a problem that we
currently have in machine learning where some of these applications are really brittle the very
good at doing one thing you shift them to a slightly different problem and everything falls apart
living things are the exact opposite of that we have many examples of living structures that can
adaptively respond to novel stressors in in a very kind of efficient way and and this is
something that we badly need in in robotics and machine learning and I think we're going to be able
to get that by observing how cells and tissues make decisions in the kinds of experiments that we
deal with a lot of the mechanisms of machine learning are you know the manipulation of probability
distributions do these kinds of bioelectric systems and signals within within the body or other
organisms do they exhibit the same kind same kind of probabilistic nature they do they do so so
we've we've we've characterized several kinds of stochastic decision making but pretty much we
have a we have an interesting review on this on this whole question pretty much every major concept
in neuroscience and cognitive science that we've been able to find has an analog in somatic
decision making so everything you can think of from from memories to optical illusions to false
memories to forgetting to inference to making mistakes to calculating forward do for expectations
in terms of anticipation all of these concepts and many more have exact analogs outside the body
and I think one outside the brain rather and I think one of the major implications of all this
is that in developing new AI and machine learning technologies we should not be trying to mimic
the human brain I think that a focus on architectures that try to mimic specific regions of the brain
or specific processes in the brain or or specific architectures really looking at one very narrow
and and fairly recent evolutionary development the the kinds of things that we really want which
is robust distributed highly plastic performance and decision making these were things that were
invented long before brains came on the scene and those those basic mechanisms still remain to be
investigated and implemented in in machine learning. Are there any kind of concrete examples of
the intersection of machine learning and developmental bio electricity to date or are you projecting
into the future into a direction we need to go? There's two I think there's two branches of this
on the one hand it's the question of what can machine learning do for regenerative medicine
and we have begun to develop and we need a lot more help with this and a lot more progress is
available this is a hugely exciting frontier area of using machine learning technology and
strategies to help developmental biologists solve the problem of of pattern control what we what
biologists are very very good at is characterizing the molecular details of the hardware we are
basically where computer science was in the 40s all we do is try to interface with the hardware
we try to push push around single molecules you know whether the the the fanciest papers in nature
are all about how somebody can do something at single molecule resolution this is what we're very
good at or terrible at is solving the inverse problem of asking what do we need to tweak at the
low level to get a desired systems level outcome so if somebody's if if we have a fetus that's
going to have three fingers instead of five the question of what exactly do we need to tweak at
the lowest level to get a particular outcome or to fix a certain organ or the shape of the face
or something like this we're actually really really bad at that and so using meanwhile the data
on these low level pathways grows exponentially so so people keep sequencing things the the this
kind of deep data is just increasing in an incredible fashion but but this is already exceeded
the human ability to synthesize all of these data into some sort of model that can be that can
be reversed so that we can ask what would we have to do to get a particular anatomical outcome
so machine learning tools to help us with this problem are absolutely essential for regenerative
medicine to move forward in and we've had a little bit of success with us we've developed some
some genetic algorithm based machine learning platforms that have actually helped us discover
models of how some of these things work it's it's kind of amazing we we made what I think is the
first is a couple years ago what I think is the first example of a model in developmental biology
that was discovered by a non-human intelligence so basically of a platform that was able to
derive a model not just crunch the numbers but actually come up with a theory of what was going
on what was going on inside that plenary and flatworm that was better able to explain all the
experiments than existing models that humans have come up with so I think this is the tip of the
iceberg we have to do do better with this and give people tools to help extract wisdom from
this mountain of data that we have going in the opposite direction this is really just starting
and I don't have anything specific to point to other than people have started to look at things
like slime molds like ant colonies like bacterial biofilms as models for computation and there are
people like Andrew Ratamatsky and others who are using some of these kinds of unconventional media
as a very simple computers with the idea of understanding how they do what they do and trying to
implement some of these advantages in robotics and and we're doing this too we have collaborations
with people like Josh Bondgard at University of Vermont who make robots and trying to really
squeeze some some insights out of these biological systems for much better technology.
Really fascinating work Michael thanks so much for taking the time to share with us any kind of
final thoughts or suggestions for folks that want to dig into this in a little bit more detail.
Yeah the biggest thing I can I can suggest is to drop me an email because we are always very
interested in collaborating with people from the machine learning community I think there are
huge opportunities in both directions for enriching the progress and so you can reach me at
michael.leaven at tufts.edu and if you drop me an email I will get back to you and you can see
all of the all of the data we have there's a lot of code that we've written and I would love to
talk to experts in this field for working together. Fantastic thanks so much Michael thank you very
much. All right everyone that's our show for today. For more information on today's show visit
twomolai.com slash shows. Be sure to get those submissions in for the twomolcancfp at twomolcan.com slash
cfp. As always thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.