Welcome to the Twimal AI Podcast. I'm your host, Sam Charrington.
Before we get going, I'd like to send a huge thanks to LinkedIn for sponsoring today's show.
LinkedIn Engineering solves complex challenges at scale to create economic
opportunity for every member of the global workforce. AI and ML are integral aspects of almost
every product the company builds for its members and customers. LinkedIn's highly structured
dataset gives their data scientists and researchers the ability to conduct applied research to
improve member experiences. To learn more about the work of LinkedIn Engineering, visit
engineering.linkedin.com slash blog and now on to the show.
All right, everybody. I am here in Santa Clara at the first O'Reilly TensorFlow World conference.
And I've got the pleasure of being seated with Jonathan Hong. Jonathan is a senior software
engineer at LinkedIn and he is presenting here at the conference tomorrow. Is that right, Jonathan?
Oh, yep. That's correct. On your experiences, scale,
link TensorFlow at LinkedIn. Welcome to the Twimal AI Podcast. Thank you. Before we jump into
your talk and your project, I'd love to learn a little bit about your background and how you came
to work on machine learning infrastructure at LinkedIn. Yeah. So back in 2014, I joined LinkedIn
as an intern on what was then called the Hadoop development team. So we handled the Hadoop
infrastructure at LinkedIn for storage and compute and compute orchestration. So I rejoined LinkedIn
the next year in 2015 on the same team. When I joined, I was working on the compute
infrastructure at LinkedIn, which is yarn in the Hadoop project. So we were building some
enhancements around compute efficiency, making sure we were getting good ROI on the hardware
that our jobs were running on. So I worked on that for a few years. Was this the Tony project or
was that separate? No, so this is separate. This was yarn specific. So nothing related to machine
learning yet. Just making sure we have Hadoop clusters at LinkedIn that we manage a couple
of thousands of nodes and making sure that things are running efficiently. So I worked on that
for a few years. And then in late 2017, I'd say there was a lot of interest in using deep learning
to improve the insights that we were giving our members. So we started exploring using
TensorFlow as our deep learning framework. And so we were kind of experimenting with various
existing frameworks in the open source world for running TensorFlow on Hadoop cluster.
So we explored some projects and none of them really fit our needs exactly. So that's when we
started to build this project called Tony, which stands for TensorFlow on yarn. And so this is our
in-house solution for running distributed TensorFlow on our Hadoop clusters. I'm curious,
what were some of the things that you looked at that didn't quite work for you? Yeah, so we looked
at a few options. The first one was a project called TensorFlow on Spark. So this was open-sourced
by Yahoo. I don't know the exact date. So the concept there is pretty similar. Instead of running your
TensorFlow training and modeling code directly on your yarn cluster, you would run it on a
Spark cluster, which usually runs on a yarn cluster. And so that worked reasonably well, but there
were some feature gaps that we couldn't overcome. So at the time, there wasn't great support for
fault tolerance in that project. I know since then it's improved. But at the time, this was a
big blocker for us. And then a couple of other things that are related to kind of the
Spark execution model. So one of them was that Spark didn't have support for
GPU requesting and scheduling. And so a lot of our AI engineers, they were interested in running
their distributed TensorFlow training on GPU hardware to accelerate the speed at which they can
iterate. And so since Spark didn't have support for this, this was one of the big reasons we
decided to build something else that we could integrate that GPU support with. And then the last
thing was more related to Spark itself. So kind of the Spark execution model is, you know, you have
a driver and a bunch of executors in your job. And the problem here is that all of your executors
need to share the same resource profile, essentially. And this didn't really mix well with the
TensorFlow execution model where you have various job types such as your like your perimeter servers
or your workers and things like that. And each of these job types may require different resource
profiles. And so if you're running TensorFlow on Spark, this won't really work. And then you end
up with a lot of resource wastage. Yeah. And so maybe taking a step back, what's the overarching
motivation for running TensorFlow on the Hadoop clusters? Is it that you have them in there there?
And you want to use the machines? Is it that, you know, you like yarn as a general kind of workload
orchestration system? And maybe kind of an adjacent question, you know, if you didn't have that
existing investment, would you do the same thing? Would you stand up with the Hadoop cluster and
then run TensorFlow on it? Or would you be going in a totally different direction? Yeah. So
I think our biggest motivation for building Tony was because we had these Hadoop clusters.
So LinkedIn has invested in Hadoop as our de facto data processing platform for many years now.
You know, even before I joined the company. Sure. And so, you know, teams across our company are
running very diverse workloads at scale on our Hadoop clusters. And so the Hadoop ecosystem at
LinkedIn is very mature. And so we're running these clusters with thousands of nodes, you know,
petabytes of compute. And so we wanted to use our infrastructure and our expertise in Hadoop and
build a way to run TensorFlow on this infrastructure. And historically, you know, Hadoop offered
this advantage of, you know, in the context of MapReduce, this kind of locality between your
compute and your data. Does that have any relevance in the machine learning model training world?
Yeah. So ideally, the model training would be bounded by your compute speed. And so hopefully,
IO doesn't become a concern. Yeah. We have found in the past that IO was a big limiter for us. But
we don't think it was related to locality reasons. You're just a bad model or training or something
like that. Okay. Okay. I've had Beechan on the show before talking about ProML. What's the
relationship between Tony and ProML? Yeah. So the idea behind ProML was to give our AI engineers a
better experience for building and machine learning pipelines. So you know, you have your data
pre-processing phase. You may be doing some feature extraction, things like that. And then
you have your model training and then you can save your model and then go onto the serving phase.
And so the Tony part is kind of fills the model training part of this pipeline. And then we have
some internal libraries to link all these systems together. Okay. So ProML is kind of a layer of
abstraction that sits on top of a bunch of things. Tony being one of those on the training side.
Yeah, exactly. Cool. So tell us about your presentation. How's your presentation structured?
Yeah. So it's kind of a mix of the things that we've talked about kind of the
hoodie ecosystem at LinkedIn, what that looks like. And then kind of going into the story of
why we were looking at TensorFlow as our deep learning framework and kind of what the experience
was like for our AI engineers in running either single node or distributed TensorFlow back in 2017
when our deep learning infrastructure was not very mature. So talking about what that experience
was like some of the gaps that we saw. But maybe pause here. It sounds like you have some interesting
stories there. What's the kind of what what what what did that world look like and how does that
contrast to how it looks today? Yeah. So I think the biggest gaps there were
users would have to like AI engineers would have to set up their own training environment either
locally or on machines that we provided them. And so there wasn't really like a set of managed
compute hardware that people could run on. So it was it was kind of like a free for all wild west
situation. You know, you have all this compute hardware sitting there, but there's nothing to
manage it. So it kind of ends up being the user who has to figure out which machines are available
when you run into like race conditions where I see this machine is available, but so on
else does and then you end up kind of butting heads. Yeah. So that was the biggest issue. And you
know, especially with like GPU hardware, this becomes an even bigger issue because you only have
so many GPUs on a single machine. And you end up running into, you know, multi-tenancy issues
a lot, which is what we experienced. Yeah, the race condition, race condition issue is that's
an interesting one I hadn't thought about that particular example of you've got some shared
resource and two people see it and want to take advantage of it and then they spend something
up and now they're colliding. Yeah, exactly. The ones wins, but you know, the other person loses.
Right. That's the really bad experience. Yeah. And so today, obviously, it's more of a you've
got a set of shared services that developers can take advantage of and TensorFlow is a big part of
of that. And why TensorFlow? Any, you know, particular thoughts on why TensorFlow is a framework,
you know, was the right direction for you? I can't really speak to why we decided to make
TensorFlow the official deep learning platform. But maybe the more interesting question is,
you know, one of the big decisions that folks that are trying to provide platform services need
to face is whether they are offering, you know, whether they're trying to be framework agnostic
and support everything or whether they're focusing on a particular thing. Is it correct to infer
that there's a strong focus on TensorFlow for LinkedIn to the exclusion of other frameworks? So do
you also have ways of supporting, you know, you're just here talking about TensorFlow, but you also have,
you know, PyTorch on yarn or something. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So this is actually something.
It's kind of interesting. When we first developed Tony, it was for TensorFlow specific support.
Okay. And this was mostly guided by our AI teams who were most interested in using TensorFlow.
There was certainly a period in time in which TensorFlow was the only choice that made sense.
Right. Right. Yeah. And so, you know, I think right now we are not really platform agnostic.
We, as a policy, I'd say, we only support certain frameworks. And I think that's maybe
an easier way to scale our deep learning infrastructure. You know, we only have so many
infra engineers on our team that can support these frameworks. So we kind of need to
limit what kind of the support we provide to the engineers at our company. Yeah. Yeah.
It's interesting. We earlier this month had a conference, Twomelcon focused on Twomelcon AI
platforms to be precise focused on the platforms and technologies that folks are standing up to
accelerate machine learning. And you hear a lot of people kind of advocating for you got to support,
you know, in platform roles, you have to support everything that the engineers want to use.
And it's, I think, worthy of pointing out that if an organization, you know, with an engineering
culture like a LinkedIn and, you know, the size and scale of LinkedIn, both in terms of
engineering team and problem, you know, can say, well, you know, we're going to focus on this.
Yeah. Then there are probably a lot of other organizations that are smaller that can also do
that and probably get as much advantage, you know, of focusing on something, whether it's
TensorFlow or PyTorch or whatever. Yeah. Exactly. I feel like, you know, if you have a team of
hundreds of engineers that are working just for deep learning at your company, that might be
something that's possible. Maybe just on your platform team. Yeah. Yeah. Not developing. No,
you know, right. Yeah. But, you know, we only have so many people on our team that can only do so
much. Right. And so I think this is the best way for us to do it. Yeah. Okay. So you were talking
about the motivation for this investment and the experience that engineers had before this project.
What's next in your kind of agenda or your story on this with the presentation?
Yeah. So, you know, after we go into kind of the gaps that we saw in distributed
TensorFlow training, we'll talk a little bit about how Tony works behind the hood.
So kind of what features we support, how it's implemented on top of yarn,
and then kind of how AI engineers at LinkedIn would use it.
Yeah. And so that part will kind of go into like coming back to the pitfalls that we saw,
how Tony addresses them, basically, to walk us through that. Yeah. So do you want like a walk
through of how Tony works? Yeah. Yeah. Absolutely. Absolutely. Yeah. So sort of for any yarn
application, there's a few main components. There is a client component that is submitting jobs
to your hudu cluster. And then there's what yarn calls an application master. So you can think of
this as essentially a driver that handles all of the subtasks in your hudu job.
And then you have what Tony calls a task executor. These are essentially the tasks that are doing
the heavy lifting in your job. And so for us, we have implementations of all three of these
components. And then we package them all into this Tony library. And so some of the things that
we've built into the design of Tony, most of this is happening in the application master of the
driver. So some of the things that we need to support are like fall tolerance, which we talked
a little bit about earlier. So you know, as our engineers are running on more and more training
data, their training may be running on more workers running for longer. You know, there's this idea
that any machine can fail at any time, which will cause the tasks running on that machine to fail.
And so we needed good support for fall tolerance in the Tony framework to make sure that if we run
into these transient issues such as hardware failure, that Tony can transparently continue training
and make sure that the job succeeds to completion. Yeah. In the Hadoop world, there's,
you know, people will say fault tolerance and mean lots of different things, right? They can
mean that they can mean that a node fails, but there's been checkpointing happening during the,
you know, the training or the job. And so some other node is able to access that state and start
or continue and not have to start back to the beginning, you know, or you said kind of
continuous, you know, fault tolerance. Whereas, or such that there's no interruption at all.
There's no checkpointing that needs to happen. Those are maybe the spectra of different, you know,
ways that people use fault tolerance. You know, what level of fault tolerance are you providing?
And how are you providing that? Yeah. So I think for, you know, for frameworks like MapReduce
or Spark, it will follow this model of you, you may need to recompute some things. And then the
framework will handle exactly what you need to recompute. Yeah. So in Tony's case, it's a little
different. So since TensorFlow already has this capability of checkpointing, checkpointing status
to some durable storage essentially. In our case, we're using HDFS since it's running on our
HD cluster. Yeah. So for us, we're like checkpointing the status of our Tony jobs every, every few
minutes to our HDFS clusters. And then in Tony's case, if it detects that some worker has failed
for whatever reason, it can tear down the the Tony application of all the workers associated
with it and then re-request resources from the HD cluster, spin up the same job, but read from
the checkpoints that were saved from the previous attempt. We spoke earlier about this race condition
issue. Does Tony kind of inherently solve that race condition problem, or is it just that it
organizes everything in some higher level abstraction like ProML, like a scheduler of some sort with
the user interface can handle, can better handle that race condition. Yeah. So the, I think the core
problem with having these unmanaged machines and, you know, that's the race condition. Yeah.
Is that there is no layer that is that is aware of which machines have how many resources and
how many are being used. Right. And so we kind of got this for free, so to say, when we move to
manage infrastructure like yarn. So, you know, when we want to build end-to-end GPU support for
our users, we need to make sure that every layer in our stack is aware of these GPU resources,
so that we don't have this race condition. So for us, that meant, you know, in the yarn layer,
yarn needs to know, you know, you have all of these machines in your cluster. How many GPUs are on
each machine? When a user runs a task on one of these machines, how many GPUs is it using? And so
yarn is aware of all of these things. And then so we can leverage that in Tony. And Tony can say,
you know, this user requested 2GPUs. I'm going to ask the yarn cluster for 2GPUs. And then the yarn
layer can handle the scheduling part for that. And so that was the kind of how it works
element. And we covered some of the problems that it fixes are there others that you highlight in
presentation. So the fault tolerance issue and the GPU issue, those are the two that we cover.
There are a few that we decided not to get into. So after that, we kind of start to go into,
you know, this is useful for scaling up TensorFlow training at LinkedIn. But we also have this
orthogonal issue of if AI engineers want to experiment on new libraries that came out in the
open source world, how can they easily experiment on that? And, you know, if you've ever worked with
Hadoop, it doesn't lend itself very well to experimentation, I think. And so one thing that we were
exploring was building a Kubernetes research cluster that our engineers could use to do various
experimentation. And so one of the powerful things about Kubernetes is that there's very good
support for containerization. So if our engineers want to use some library, they can easily
build the image themselves and run it on the Kubernetes cluster. And so the later part of the talk
we'll get into kind of how we built that out. Some of the gaps that we saw when we were building
out our Kubernetes cluster and some use cases. Okay. And just to be clear, the Kubernetes cluster is
independent of the Hadoop cluster, or you somehow running Kubernetes on top of Hadoop?
Yeah. Yeah, I know there have been some attempts to do. Yeah. We decided not to go that
route. So essentially the Kubernetes compute part is a separate cluster. And this is something
we'll get into in the talk as well. We already have this vast data lake on HDFS with all of our
training data. And so even while we have this separate compute cluster for Kubernetes, we want
a way to access this data lake. So this is one of the gaps that we saw when building out this
Kubernetes cluster, how if people run these Kubernetes jobs in this cluster, how do they access
this data? You know, since we're running a secure Hadoop, it's kind of non-trivial to instrument
this. So that's something we also get into in the talk. And so the main challenges there are
kind of integrating in with the kind of your access controls and entitlements on the Hadoop side
between the kind of the file system driver infrastructure on the Kubernetes side, or is it
something else? Yeah, that's basically what it does. Okay. You know, there's built-in support
for accessing a secure cluster. How do you like authenticate things like that when you're running
your tests on the Hadoop cluster. But then when you have some external cluster on Kubernetes,
how do you do the same thing? And so that gap is something we have to bridge.
Well, before we dive a little bit deeper into the Kubernetes side of things,
does Tony take advantage of or draw from any of the other distributed training
approaches for TensorFlow, the, you know, the built-in distributed training, or a horrified,
or any of those kinds of things, or is it, you know, as part of what you did kind of build your own
version of that stuff? Yeah. So the layer at which Tony operates that is kind of on top of the
TensorFlow distributed training part. So when the AI, when an AI engineer wants to run distributed
training, they are writing like the model creation and the training logic themselves. So if they
are interested in running some distributed training strategy, they can do that. And then Tony is
kind of a thin layer on top of that, which will handle the resource acquisition and task launch
essentially. And then once that part is complete, then the user, the AI engineers distributed
TensorFlow job will proceed as it normally would. Got it. Yeah. And so some portion of your user
community is coming in, you know, their jobs are being submitted via ProML. But I'm imagining
some are using Tony directly. And if that's the case, I'm curious what the user experience is.
Are they creating Tony Yamal files? Yeah. Yeah. So kind of the bare bones Tony experience is
you need to create your configuration files. Yeah. And then package all of your source code
and everything yourself. Like jar files or something. Right. Exactly. So if you're running Tony
from like the command line, for example, that's something we would expect the user to do. But
at LinkedIn, we have this this ProML ecosystem. And the objective there is to provide a higher
level abstraction to our engineers. And so a lot of these nuts and bolts are kind of handled
for them. Cool. Well, maybe let's take a few minutes and talk about how you're approaching
Kubernetes. I guess first of all, are you, you know, is there an official position? Like, you
know, this is the future of the future direction for, you know, distributed compute for ML and AI
at LinkedIn? Or do you see Kubernetes and Tony coexisting long term? Yeah. That's a difficult
question for me to answer. I don't think we I think we are the Kubernetes work we're doing is
still pretty early phase. And so I think as we onboard more and more use cases, we'll see
what the gaps there are. And then I think at that point, we'll have a better idea of what the
long term distributed TensorFlow story will be at LinkedIn. But as of now, the state of Kubernetes
at LinkedIn is, you know, we're we're still building out the infrastructure. And we don't really
have a solid idea of how that plays into our long term solution. Beyond the challenge of
the security challenges that we talked about integrating at that level, these two
disparate systems, what are some of the other challenges that, well, challenges are what are some
of the other, you know, focus areas that you're doing to kind of make the Kubernetes cluster accessible
to folks? Yeah. So I think that the HDFS access thing is was the biggest thing for us.
And then for experimentation, we're still kind of experimenting with it within the infrastructure
team. And so a lot of the issues are related to building out the actual cluster and making sure
that it operates as a production cluster should. So for example, making sure that the nodes in
our cluster are up most of the time and making sure that we have appropriate metrics and monitoring
to accurately assess the state of our cluster. Yeah. So it's kind of core
Kubernetes operability stage that a lot of people, frankly, are at as opposed to how do we build
some higher level abstraction on top of Kubernetes that is ML focused or creates the user experience.
You're trying to offer to your ML engineers. Right. Exactly. Yeah. I think once we solidify
the Kubernetes infrastructure, then we can start onboarding more and more users and then
hopefully it will take off from there. And it's not like you have a few research focused teams
running on Kubernetes now, are they doing, are they kind of experimenting? Well, I guess they're,
yeah, experimenting is overloaded, but are they like running real use cases and workloads on this?
But maybe not time-critical ones or like what's how do you characterize how you've started,
you know, in terms of a workload perspective on the Kubernetes side?
Yeah. For now, it's mostly kind of on an ad hoc basis. So people aren't really running
critical jobs there. Yeah. And we've kind of played with some use cases such as running
horrified on Kubernetes or running Qflow, for example. But yeah, those are still very experimental.
So did you cover anything beyond the Kubernetes stuff? Or is that where you left it?
I think that's the last thing that we cover. Yeah. Okay. You know, I asked a little bit about the
kind of the feature of all this at LinkedIn with respect to Kubernetes and Hadoop. But more broadly,
you know, what are some of the things that your group is looking at going forward?
Yeah. I think right now, it's really important for us to give our engineers a really good user
experience. A lot of our work so far has been making sure our clusters can scale well as we add
more machines and, you know, hundreds of users are onboarding their deep learning jobs. But
we're all just trying to improve our user experience. And so that's something we'll be addressing in the
next few months. And other specific aspects of that that you can talk about? I'm not sure how much
I can say. A lot of it is related to, for example, like internal tooling or the way our clusters are
built out, for example. So even if you could say it wouldn't mean much to anyone. Yeah. Cool. And
I'm curious if you have any kind of going back to kind of core TensorFlow, any kind of interesting
lessons learned or, you know, things that you would share with folks that are, you know, starting to
think about, you know, building out platform support around TensorFlow key, key things that it
was important for your team to learn. Yeah. So far, I think just using what the open source
TensorFlow community has provided has worked reasonably well for us. And I think when we cover,
for example, Tony and talk, it kind of sits on a different layer from TensorFlow. So up to now,
we haven't really had to delve into the TensorFlow internals. But in the future, I think as we optimize
model training more and more, that's something we're going to look into, you know, how can we
better optimize the actual TensorFlow layer rather than the layers that sit on top of it?
Well, Jonathan, thanks so much for taking the time to chat with me. Yeah. Thank you. It was a pleasure.
All right, everyone. That's our show for today. To learn more about today's show, including our
guests, visit twomalai.com. If you missed Twomalcon or want to share what you learned with your team,
be sure to visit twomalcon.com slash videos for more information about Twomalcon video packages.
Thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.