Welcome to the Twomo AI Podcast.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
Hey everyone, producer Amari here.
As we mentioned on the podcast last week, we've got some exciting new additions to our
Twomo community programs, including the IBM AI Enterprise Workflow Specialization
Study Group, which will be hosted by Sam, and the causal modeling in machine learning
study group hosted by Robert Osa-Zua-Ness, who you heard from earlier this week on the
topic of causality.
Today, I want to remind you that Sam and Robert are hosting a course and study group overview
session this Saturday, February 1st, at 8 a.m. pacific time.
To get signed up for this course, or to learn more about the other upcoming and ongoing
Twomo community programs, visit TwomoAI.com slash community.
And now on to the show.
Alright everyone, I am here with Heitem Abul Fatou and Katen Umare from Lift, Heitem
and Katen, welcome to the TwomoAI podcast.
Thank you.
So, we're here in once again, sunny San Diego.
We got the two days of like horrible, miserable rainy weather, you know, earlier in this
week.
And we're here to talk about some of what you're doing in Lift, namely the flight project
that you just presented on yesterday, it's open sourced.
And it's open sourced.
We're going to dig deep into this, but before we do, I'd love to have each of you kind
of introduce yourself, share a little bit about your background, how you got to work
on ML and Fra and, you know, what's your story?
Talk to us.
Katen?
Yeah.
Hey, my name is Katen.
I lead the flight team and probably one of the founding person of the flight at Lift.
So my background is I work across different industries from hedge funds to retail, to logistics,
to cloud.
I'm mapping and now finally back in sort of transportation area.
And one of the things I've been interested in is just large scale data processing and
solving business problems where data and computation comes together and machine learning is
a place where, you know, that's really, really important.
I started Lift in 2016, but I started on flight close to the end of 2016.
And it was mostly like, you know, I started working on this team.
We were trying to get ETAs, which are, I'll explain what an ETA is.
So when you open up and lift up and you see, hey, three minutes to get your driver or if
you are in a car and you see like it will take 15 minutes to reach the airport, sometimes
it's accurate.
And it's accurate mostly because of a ton of machine learning models that go in the
background and including understanding how the road traffic is and understanding all
kinds of things that are happening on in the current conditions on the road.
So using, so I was leading the team and which I joined the team, there was another engineer
on it.
He used to run the models all on his laptop and he was like, how are you running this?
And he's like, I have this script, I've just run this and it just runs and it figures
out.
And you know, then I run this other script and then I run this other script and I do that's
crazy.
Yeah.
So, and we, I'm trying to decide whether to interrupt you and just like dive deep into
that.
That sounds crazy.
It is crazy.
Like running a model that's doing like live prediction of ETAs on a platform, like training
training the model, training the model or collecting the data for the model aren't
things like that, right?
And still reproducibility issues and stuff like that.
A lot of issues.
Yeah.
But you wouldn't be surprised how many times this happens in the industry, right?
It's just like the, and this is actually how we lead into it because this is the current
state of the infrastructure for machine learning and especially productionizing models is,
it didn't exist.
We didn't think about retraining these models at that time and quickly we wanted to retrain
them and then I'm the laptop's not going to scale.
Now, the other story that happened, so this is just leading into flight, right?
And the other story that happened is there was a research scientist on my team.
He created a model and that model is pretty cool.
It served live for many years.
But he left the company and the model went with him probably, so we lost it.
Like we had no idea where the model was and as leader, they told me, hey, let's recreate
this model and I, I don't know how to and I, we knew the algorithm.
So we just rewrote it and we got everything done.
It would not give the same results.
And it, like it literally took us three months to get like to the same level of accuracy.
Wow.
And we were like, okay, so he had done all of this extra work that we really kind of lost.
We didn't waste too much effort on it because we knew the algorithm, we knew some of the
tricks.
But still, it's like wasted effort in trying something out and then going and trying
out the accuracy and you're like, oh, it's time to say.
Yeah.
It's not like one person spending all the three months, but it's still like, it's like,
it's wasted effort.
So at that time, I decided that this needs to be, this needs to change.
And delivering new models became slower and slower.
So that was the birth of flight.
At that point, we used to call it a bad name.
I'm not even going to put it on the podcast, but I used to, and we wrote, like I wrote
like a first draft proposal internally and everybody was like, you are crazy.
This thing is not, never going to work.
But somehow in like a couple months, we erected a V zero, V one of this thing.
And we got a team to try it out and this team was also struggling a lot with delivering
their models.
And the intersection where flight really fits in is when you have a lot of data and you
want to reproduce, reproduce your models again and again, like maybe every day, every week
or every hour.
And you want like the trace of what happened and the lineage between everything.
And this team actually fit the bill.
And they, for the first time, they were able to deliver a model in like six months.
And this was a gigantic model.
It affected the bottom line of lift and it was really, really meaningful.
And it was not without a lot of, you know, stress and working hard through the night.
But that was the starting of flight and that was in 2017.
And then we didn't stop like the use of the company just skyrocketed.
And we at that point, we are like, hey, we should open source this thing because it's
such a big problem to solve that a small team at lift can probably never solve it on
their own.
And if you open sources, we should be able to work with the community here, more ideas
and improve it all the time.
So we actually rewrote everything from scratch, made it Kubernetes native, took, took like
the primitives that we understood from looking at all the various use cases.
And that's the amazing part of lift, like it's a rich ground of amazing use cases.
And we used all of that and put like basically distilled that information into flight.
And that's our first cut into the world.
Hi, Tom.
Tell us about your background and what you do at lift.
Sure.
Yes.
So my name is Haytan Abouhtou.
I have worked previously at Microsoft, Google, and I had a journey up and down the stack.
I worked in like enterprise, create applications in low-level storage, like Azure storage.
And I, you know, at some point, wanted to try out ML and I kind of found this sweet spot
in ML Infra to fit the bill kind of thing for me.
I joined lift two years ago, January, and at that time, it was that we're still stabilizing
the prior incarnation of flight, the unnamed product.
It was great and teams loved it.
As Keeta was saying, at that point, I joined in the midst of this discussion about what
do we do next.
So I got to be part of the decision-bidening, going Kubernetes native, and all the very
I see as critical design decisions.
We took in flight to virtual decisions, all the, like going with a very strong type system
and very strong language specifications through Protobov, like there is a lot of things
we view, we are like very opinionated about in flight, and a lot of things we are not.
We like explicitly decided to leave open.
Based on the experience we had, we think we found a good path for where we give you the
learnings, like enforce the learnings we have had before, in how we ask you to write
your code or deliver your models or did the processing tasks or whatever.
At the same time, leave it open for a variety of different workloads that can run the system.
And there we are, I'm very proud with how the product turned out to be in the launch and
the reception we have had during the conference.
And just a shout out to the team, we wouldn't have been possible, because our like just crazy
amounts of effort with the team.
It's an amazing team at Live.
And we are proud of all our users also at Live, just they have stayed with us through
bad times, good times, and thank you for all the support.
That's awesome.
So, Kate, then you've given us a little bit of an overview of flight.
Maybe take a step back, and what's the core value proposition that flight is offering
and how do you mention that it's Kubernetes native, like how does it relate to Qflow?
Yeah, for example.
Good question.
Let me start with the motivation of like, or what is it that we think is missing and
what we were trying to address?
One of the things, as I said, we started in 2017, so the landscape was very different
at that point, right?
So we evolved from that point.
And this is a V2, even though actually I think this is the real V1, but this is a V2,
so that means we went through a process of like actually making something and failing
and then redoing it, that has a lot of learnings with it.
So one of the learnings is that we feel that there is this artificial divide that's happening
between ML and data, but actually they go hand in hand, like you, it's not that these
companies have amazing data systems, they're not the Google's Facebooks or the Amazon's
of the world, right?
They are smaller companies, nimble, and they want, they are basically building their data
stack too.
So, and the other thing that we realize is there are teams cross-collaborate quite a bit.
Learning models are built, let's say, by A team, but the team B probably provides the
data that builds that machine learning model.
And actually the fallacy of separating them is that many times in production, we use machine
learning models to predict, and that creates data that becomes a fact in the fact tables
in the data world.
And then many times you use machine learning models to convert that fact to a dimension,
which trains other models.
So there is this cyclic nature that's happening, and this needs to be captured at that granularity
of saying that there is data and processing and machine learning all interacting together.
So, that was the motivation behind flight that we need a single tool and a platform that
allows for collaborating, sharing, and MLOPS along with definite focus on orchestration,
and that's why the core of flight is a workflow engine that actually runs all of these pipelines.
But from the idea point of view, it was built for collaboration and sharing across the
company various aspects, as well as processing and machine learning on the same tool.
And so maybe to make that more concrete, we can kind of compare contrast to what Q flow
is trying to do.
Right.
Are they orthogonal, are they complementary, does flight use Q flow?
That's a great question.
So Q flow started a while ago, started as one thing, initially they had just the TensorFlow
operator.
And as the product started maturing, it became not just a product, it became a collection
of products under the name Q flow, Q flow serving, Q flow pipelines, TensorFlow became its
own thing, you can use it from its own and so on and so forth.
So we don't see the comparison between flight and Q flow as a collection of tools or products
that the fear comparison I would say is between flight and Q flow pipelines, which is like
one segment of Q flow that sits on its own, in a way, and underlying engine, the workflow
engine under Q flow pipelines is not actually a reason why Google, it's an open source
product, a different product, right.
So it's also swapable that way, as it's, you can think of it as like a puzzle kind
of thing and these are just a few pieces of that puzzle.
And flight does things slightly differently for those few pieces that are comparable, if
that makes sense.
So then, like saying that flight might be a swapable alternative to Argo under Q flow
pipelines.
Actually, yeah, we might, it might be more vertical than that, but I'll give you an example
like a Q flow that is PyTarge and TensorFlow to absolutely opinionated distributed or
not distributed or deep learning frameworks, they both exist, right.
And it should be the user's choice of what they want to use.
And that's how I feel about how flight and let's take you flow pipelines work.
They might, they could interrelate and that absolutely, it's the number best interest
to make all of these tools play very well with each other, but they could be like completely
vertically available as two alternatives.
And you could use Q flow serving to serve your models, but build those models on flight.
This flight offers a great abstraction on, on compute and it gives you big data with
it, right.
So that's essentially our differentiator where we think like Q flow pipelines doesn't even
try to do that.
And then the lineage and the cataloging that we do is further on built on top of it, which
is also the other bit that we should talk about, I guess later.
Well, you mentioned that one of the aspects of flight is that it's strongly typed, makes
me think most immediately to like FB learner and kind of its approach to typing and you're
nodding your heads, maybe they think, yeah, can you talk a little bit about that kind
of design decision and implications?
I can actually tell you the first time I saw the FB learner blog.
It's uncanny, but it's also unbelievable at some level, so we looked at it and I shared
it with the team.
I'm like, did you see this?
This looks exactly like R. And this was around the same, about 2017, 2016, that time.
And we had the same like the annotation decorators in Python and I'm like, is it like they're
people thinking about like us, but I think that yeah, that helped us, you know, they
were earlier than us.
I'm not saying that, but it's just that that kind of helped us believe like more in that
we were probably on the right path, and so, yeah, so we, in the version one of flight,
we did not have a very, we had a type system, but the type system only existed on the SDK,
because we call it in the Python, where you, maybe take a step back for folks that, you
know, here type system, or some only type, and there's no context for that.
What does that mean from the perspective of the user experience for flight?
Yeah, so let's tell you right, a function in any language, you, you have some inputs
and outputs to that function.
There are languages like Python, where you do specify inputs and outputs, but you don't
know what those types are, barring the new typing.
Whether they're strings, or integers, or fields, or whatever, or more complex things.
Could be typing in there, and so on.
But if you go to a language like Go, or Jow, or C++, it's a really strong type, you have
to say this is an int, and this is a string, and that's the order and whatever, right?
There are benefits of having types in the system, and that's why people love them to
use them in programming languages, because you get compiled time safety.
When you build the function, if you pass in an int, and try to use it like a string, you
get an error at compile time, so you don't have to wait for it to run for 10 days, and
then figure out, oh shit, but in Python, actually, there was a, there's more of a movement
to add these kind of typing, compile time type safety.
We think that that is the same thing that should be done for, why not do it for all functions.
Like in our RPC systems today, like services, microservices, and people are using, we have
types, and we have APIs, and people talk to them, and then they receive outputs.
In flight, that's how we've designed, every single function is a task, we call them,
and these have inputs and outputs, and by strong typing, I mean, these inputs and outputs
have a known set of types, but what are the known set of types that you need to use with
machine learning?
So we had to come up with a type system that allows you to specify the various types of
types that users use when they are pilling models, like an example could be a structured
schema, which is like a row vector, or could be a tensor, could be a blob, which could
be a serialized model, and it could be various formats, could be on X, could be, and those
could be annotations on top of that blob saying that this is a serialized with the TensorFlow
serialization format.
So that's the type system that we are referring to.
So when you declare a task, if it's a model building task, and you use joblib to serialize
it, you can output a model that says it is joblib.dat, and then the next task that actually
consumes it knows that this is a type joblib, so I can just load it into using joblib.
And if you try to now put these two tasks together, they will work, but if you try to
put a task that does not understand joblib, only uses TensorFlow, it will fail at compile
time.
And that's what we wanted to achieve in a pipeline, try to fail earlier if possible.
And one of the things that that enables for FB Learner cases that they can take all of
these tasks that are strongly typed, kind of created dependency graph, and then execute
them in parallel, like as one completes spin off its descendants, are you doing some more
things?
Exactly.
I just remember something you wanted to add to the timing system, so one of the decisions
we made there was using Protobov to declare the, to specify the types, and then that might
be one of the distinctions between the existing systems you might see, even like FB Learner
and others, and flight.
And that makes it not, like takes it one step further, it doesn't only allow you to put
Python tasks together, because after you declare the task in whatever language you choose to,
using our spec, you can, you know, let's say right go, function becomes one step in your
graph, the next step might be a Python task in a different container or, you know, what
you have you.
Because at the end of the day, they would compile to this standard spec that has standard
set of types that are compatible with, you know, our SDK in any language.
And yes, I guess back to your question, it does allow us to, we once you declare the graph
in this spec, we have a compiler that looks at the graph and figures out dependency graph,
and we can go as parallel as we, as the system would want, you know, pairing the dependencies
and all of that into accounts.
Yeah.
And there are other advantages, like what I think, I just wanted to add one more thing is
the reason why we did this is because we saw use cases within Lyft, where users were
writing models in Scala for spark processing, right, like they just want to do spark processing
Scala.
They don't want to write this in Python.
They do sometimes, but sometimes they want to use Scala for higher performance.
And we are like, how do we move the data between these two different languages?
And so that's why we came up with, so we also using arrow underneath, this is an open
search project.
But like we wanted to create a layer on top of it, so that it's easy to construct these
polyglot pipelines, if I may.
So we're talking about stuff like type systems and protobuffs and arrow and not language
that the typical data scientist is about a lot, yeah, is it, you know, have you built
abstractions that make it more acceptable to data scientists or do you just have a different
audience?
I think that's a very good question.
And actually sometimes we do debate amongst ourselves, what's our audience, right?
But we do want to appear in the beginning, at least, to the savvy engineer like us who
wants to get his hands a little dirty.
But as we are progressing, we are creating layers on top of them.
So think about it, we are like, we built the foundation and now building layers on top
is much easier.
So for example, like we're just about to merge full notebook support, so you can write
tasks in notebooks.
So like we're just going to add like support for Jupyter notebooks.
The way and the way we are thinking about Jupyter notebooks is users like data scientists
and researchers love to use Jupyter notebooks.
They write code in Jupyter notebooks in a very different way than how engineers write
code on like using IDs, right?
It's very different.
And we want to keep and preserve that semantic of writing code.
So we actually found a project called Paper Mill, which is pretty cool.
We like that.
That's pretty cool.
There's only out of Netflix now in a background independent company.
Yes.
And so we decided to adopt it.
And we take that and we convert a notebook into a function into our system with the
same inputs and output.
We do the magic of like passing the inputs and outputs.
You just write your code as if you're writing a regular notebook.
You can try it out to whatever, drop it into a container, give it to flight.
And then it'll take care and execute it and actually record the output notebook and
store it for you.
So you can go back in time and look at it even if you want to.
So yes, our audience is was engineers in the beginning because we do have that sort of
audience at lift, but we are, we also have like data scientists and research scientists
using more and more and we are improving every day for them.
So if you start today, you might look at the Python flight kit and see that it's a little
more suited for people who write with IDs, but with the notebook introduction and our demo
we showed like how to use everything with the notebook.
We are going more towards research scientists.
And they will not even see some of the things that we do, like for example, I'll give an
example, in a task, you can return a data frame, a pandas data frame and we understand
that a pandas data frame is actually the throw vector that we do underneath which is converted
to a prototype and arrow and it's just sent through.
You don't even have to think about it.
You just work with pandas data frame and hopefully we are thinking we're not yet implemented
this, but that goes into spark data frame and the other side.
So we created the abstraction layer for that.
Does that introduce a lot of latency?
I was having a conversation with someone who was talking about reason why they don't
use TF serving is because they're primarily doing inferencing on images and it requires
that you have to put everything into a data frame and there's a bunch of latency that
that introduces.
Do you run into these kinds of issues where your abstraction hides kind of some nimbleness
and what the underlying data format is and you're doing conversions underneath the covers?
So actually, arrow in that case is an extremely interesting project, according to me, aim
is to make zero copy abstractions from one format to pandas data frame, to spark data
frames and I think the founder is, I think it's Wes, who the guy who has been following
that project and I think that's more of that is required, where we just should stop wasting
CPU cycles on transforming data from one format or one language to another and more use
the zero copy abstractions that we can create and that just makes the open source ecosystem
much nicer.
And that's why we chose arrow, but you don't have to, for example, if you're emitting
out images, you don't have to have a data frame for it in flight.
You can just say, I am emitting a directory of million images and we will take the million
images and upload them and download them onto the other machines and use them.
So yeah, so there is, you can use data frames, but you don't have to, and that's where
the type system comes in.
It needs to be more granular then.
Okay.
So we've talked a bunch about the type system and the workflow that that enables and kind
of some of the user experience in introducing flight you mentioned.
This important idea of kind of connecting back to the data and, you know, enabling things
like end-to-end data providence and this, you know, kind of loop that you pointed out
where your inference actually is, you know, data for your next train or a future train
at least, talk more about kind of how that works like I'm thinking, the thing that comes
to mind as I'm hearing that is Airbnb has a project that's kind of an adjacent project
to their big head platform that is focused on, like doing, you know, point in time feature,
mapping and management and feature repository, that kind of thing, is that the kind of thing
we're talking about?
That could be one of the things, but it's not like exactly what we're talking about,
but like I think your, it's feature service is, well, let's call it like a generic name,
feature service.
Features as a service, right?
What is an implementation on top of this potentially that allows you to pass the, like,
consume the data back into the model and also build and send it to feature service.
What we are referring to is the causal dependencies between the compute and the actual production
of that data and then further consumption of data by the next compute layer and production.
So now let's take an example.
You get a map from OSM, OpenTreatMaps, if we consume it and you build a graph, the road
network out of it, then some other team actually analyzes the road network in real time that's
happening and creates the traffic pattern that's that are happening at the moment on the
road and annotates the road network with some speed profiles, that's what we call them.
And then the third team actually consumes these two things and creates the final road network
that's deployed to production.
So when we did a prediction on ETA, we would want to know which version of the map did
I use and what was the speed profile at that point in time and what were the traffic
conditions that were led to that speed profile?
That's the type of question that we want to answer.
So to go to that, you need to have a full trace in the system of how the data was generated,
when did it get generated, when did it get passed under the next bit and then so we call
this typically lineage or prominence as you said.
And the way we track this is our type system was the other reason why we had our type system
is to have the central engine automatically publish all of this data as it's generated
by every single task execution to a central service that actually just records a unique
signature of the execution and what did it generate with the inputs and the outputs.
So now you have a relationship between what got generated by what and now you can create
a graph because you know the graph that ran like flight knows intrinsically that how what
was the computation graph.
So you can go in and create the causal dependency structure across these data sets.
We do this today, the exposed thing that you get in open source is not the full, we don't
show the dependency tree that will come out soon at some point, but we are using this
for memorization. So if you recompute the same data set, let's say you took some data set
and you transformed it and it produced an output.
Some other user goes in and takes the same data set and transforms it and produces the
same output potentially because the code really has not changed.
In the past people were like we would spend money.
So then the solution would be let's create a intermediate high table or whatever, right?
Things like that.
But that's not really what it was for many artifacts that are like images, right?
If you did luminon sampling on some set of images and you're not going to store them
in high.
I think we can do that, but we don't.
But what we do is because we can identify the compute process and the set of inputs that
were given, we create a unique signature of that.
And so next time when we observe that the same thing is being run, flight just smartly
replaces it with the existing outputs.
Now you have to tell flight that this process is reproducible because if it has side effects
or it is like, you know, if you're using random number, the generator or something, that
might not work.
So we, you have to tell us, but if you tell us then we just go and replace any execution
of that on the platform across the company.
So that saves money and time because the iteration time now, like if you're running something
that's 10 steps, like a 10 step pipeline and you fail on the 10th step, you just fix
the 10th step and rerun it.
Right.
And the 9 steps just are cached.
So you just automatically fright will fast forward you to the 10 step and go, go, let's
run that guy again.
And so this is what we call it, memorization.
So flight.
I think you've described it as kind of a workflow engine, it's not a data store or something
that is like creating snapshots or anything, it's more like, you can think of it more
like metadata and pointers to, you know, existing training data and interim data, transform
data, output data, et cetera.
Exactly.
Yeah.
And or presumably you're also kind of tracking model versions as they're trained.
Yes.
Yeah, we have, that's one of the things we are a bit opinionated about flight is every
artifact in the system, all the data produced, all the definitions, all the tasks and workflows
are immutable.
So we have versions, strict versions, versioning scheme that you can use your own versioning
scheme, but it has to be strict as in you can't mutate something and try to register it
or produce it with the same version again.
So we, when we produce any metadata about tasks, outputs or whatnot, they are always unique
and like the signature is always unique.
And that allows us throughout the system to always refer to very consistently to like
executions, past executions in the history and the produced artifacts and produced models
and, you know, anything that went through the system with very confidence that, you know,
we know exactly which even like piece of code produced that.
So yeah.
Yeah.
And you should be able to fully re-run, re-produce it, but it'll cause a new version.
We don't even have one single update API in the entire code list, because you have like
a functional system.
What's the smallest kind of use case that you can envision someone using this for?
Does it make sense and is it kind of approachable enough for kind of a, you know, a single person,
a kind of clone or repo and like actually get some value out of it or do you need a team
of, you know, 10 MLN for people or that's a great question, great question, yes.
We, and I will say like our work there is not done, but we have put a lot of effort to
make the first time experience and the maintenance for small projects, as you mentioned, very
approachable.
We have written, we have written docs that, like I would say maybe most of the time, like
the efforts we put in the docs, we're in the docs that tell people how to get started.
So it's like me that easy, even sometimes we went back to like our architecture and what
not to try to, you know, make that easy when like we looked at the docs and it's like that's
a lot of steps.
This is not okay.
Let's go back and redo things, right?
So that's one part of it.
I would say the other part I think is we have seen that in a lot of cases, people when
they get started in developing a model or even doing some transformation or whatnot, they
don't think initially, unless they have done that before, they don't think that they will
need a workflow for it.
They think you know, we'll spawn off a notebook and do my thing and be happy, right?
Which usually is the case in the beginning, right?
Until you know, somebody leaves the company or you started, like you want to go back to
a model that worked, but you don't know which version of the code produced that and so
on and then you start realizing the problems and the need for such systems.
But by trying to make it as easy to get started as approachable, we hope that at one point
it becomes like a standard given that you always start there and the system, like the friction
between I have nothing to the first task or the first execution is almost not there.
Like more people would get into the happy love doing this as the first step before I think
your first piece of code and it sets you up for success, leader.
We are basically saying that every company should grow and become great and you know, start
with what we think is like the bare minimum and it will evolve with you, right?
So it's an evolveable system.
The other bit that I want to add to that is that I think that one of the reasons why we
move to Kubernetes is to make that first case experience and for small company experience
really, really good.
Kubernetes is great to get.
You can go to any of the clouds and get one Kubernetes cluster and we use customized,
I don't know if you know of that project, but that's a pretty interesting project.
All of flight is really one YAMO and you can say, CUP, CTO, apply minus F, that YAMO
and boom, you get a flying cluster, including all of the things that we just talked about.
Wow.
Okay.
Yeah, you can even do that on the Docker for this top or Kubernetes.
Like on your machine, you don't even have to go to a CUP provider to get started and
set it up even with menu for storage.
So you will get the full experience, your manual tasks and once you're ready to take it
to the next level, run on in AWS or GCP or whatnot, that you don't have to change how you
were doing things or how you wrote your tasks.
They will just seamlessly run on the bigger cloud within lift and we talked about this
in the presentation yesterday.
We run a multi cluster set of flights, a single cluster, but of course you will not start
there.
Right?
And we did not start there.
We started with single cluster.
We soon outgrew that and started, you know, deploying multiple cluster to flight.
And the user's multi cluster.
What's the multi tenancy models like a single user has stuff running on multi clusters
or you just have multi clusters and you have some users among cluster and some on another.
We have multiple clusters and we for the user though, it's one cluster.
So we abstract that entire thing behind the service and the way we spun off the work
depends on the load of the system or priority classes or things like that.
Is that all stuff that's happening in the open source or this way that you're operating
it?
No, it's all open source.
Interesting.
Yeah, you don't need to do this.
You don't have to use multi cluster, but let's see your company grows further beyond
that single cluster.
Yes, flight will evolve with you.
Yeah.
Yeah, we basically open source everything that we do at lift.
Some other thing that I just talked about like the lineage or whatever, it will come soon.
Yeah.
But most of the things.
What's exciting about this for me is that there are many, many companies that are doing
this kind of thing internally.
We talked about Facebook, Airbnb, Uber, obviously with Michelangelo.
Some have talked about open sourcing, but I'm not sure I can think of any name brand
company that is open source their internal platform outside of like TFX if you consider
that Google open sourcing their internal platform.
Yeah.
So this.
The TFX doesn't come with an execution portion of it, right?
It's just basically the library at the moment.
Right.
And so this is the library that does all the type stuff.
There's the execution piece, workflow engine, you know, after the step after the CUBE
CTL, like is it spinning up a web front end that I can see stuff?
Yeah.
Our web front end is pretty snappy too.
We show like errors in the UI and graphs and things like that.
You can click you get log links in the UI and like inputs and outputs and the artifacts
produced.
All of that is in the UI too.
Yep.
And then the CLI too, of course.
And tell me a little bit about the like the process of open sourcing it.
Like, was that the size of it all?
Yeah.
All right.
So I had a baby five months ago, five months ago, and I had another baby in a flight.
So they think having literally having two babies at the same time.
It's a twin, a twin, and I have not slept almost for five months probably.
And so as the team, like, been a fantastic job.
So yeah, that's why we took this long, actually.
We started the process last year.
We could have been.
I mean, let's start with why?
Very good question.
They have to like, why?
And we did debate that a lot, didn't they?
We did a lot, right?
Yeah.
Especially that, right?
The previous system wasn't going to be open sourced, was sift only.
So like, when this came, this, when the new, when you started deciding to redo it, I
remember, even hit them giant and when I was one of the question, why do you want to open
sourcing?
And I think what happened is there was interest from outside was one of the reasons, I don't
need to name, like who, where it was, but there was some interest.
The other thing is we realized this is such a big, like, big problem to solve.
And I said this in the, I think, before, but a small 9 or 10 people team cannot do this.
It needs to be an industry wide effort, hopefully, if not, at least like a few, few tens
of people working on this.
And, and all with like, if we do set the right primitives, then we can let it evolve into
the, into the piece that it needs to be, right?
And that gets great stuff for life, like if we, we get, for example, we don't, we currently
only have a Python SDK, but I know there are other companies are saying that we want
to add a scala SDK for this and we're like, awesome, we will use it, right?
There is demand for this at least, but we don't have the time to build this.
So that's one, a definite biggest reason that get, basically, leverage.
Second is lift open source on why it was a foundational technology for lift two.
And it's been, it's been, you know, amazing success, right?
We're in this community.
So we're not saying we are going to be even 10% of that weight, that's just much.
But from that we learned that people actually, like, it's a great hiring tool.
You are not working on a technology in the company that's, that now you have to hire
engineers and teach them.
You are going to work on a technology that they have probably used at their previous jobs
and that's great for lift.
So, and, yeah, answer and just wait for the team potential, right?
So, and I would like to just add to all of this.
I think we, as we talked throughout the conversation today, there are a few things we strongly believe
in.
And we wanted to have that debate in the open, because I think it will not only influence
like this product or similar products, it will influence like the entire ecosystem,
how it, how it interacts with each other, how, how you do serving even after like the
all of that, even if you don't build these pieces, the concepts, like the underlying concepts.
And I think it, like, we, we see that it does bring something to the table that isn't there
yet.
So, we wanted to make sure that, you know, we have that conversation, like it, it will,
we think, advance like the entire, like the email, link for a community overall, to hopefully
a slightly better place.
Well, hi, Thom Ketan, thanks so much for taking the time to chat with us.
Thank you, Sam.
Thanks for having us.
Yeah.
All right, everyone.
That's our show for today to learn more about today's guests or the topics mentioned
in the interview, visit twomelai.com slash shows.
For more information on either of our new study group offerings, causal modeling and machine
learning or the IBM Enterprise AI workflow, visit twomelai.com slash learn 2020.
Of course, if you like what you hear on the podcast, be sure to subscribe, rate, and review
the show on your favorite pod catcher.
Thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.