All right everyone, I am here in Vancouver at NURPS 2019 and I've got the pleasure of being
seated with Josh Tobin. Josh here is a former research scientist at OpenAI and a co-organizer
of full-stack deep learning. Josh, welcome to the Trauma AI podcast. Thanks, happy to be here.
Awesome, so let's maybe jump into a little bit of your background. Do you spend some time at OpenAI
and you did your PhD at Berkeley advised by Peter Abil, who's been on the podcast before?
Great, yeah. So I got into the field about four years ago. Okay. Really I started at Berkeley
in the applied math program and then you know kind of on a whim took a class with Professor Abil
who ended up becoming my advisor and I was just kind of blown away by the potential of AI to
make robotics work better and so you know through that I ended up working with Peter and spending
a bunch of time at OpenAI and so what are you currently up to? Yeah so I left OpenAI a few months
ago and I'm in the process of exploring kind of what to dive into next. Figuring out what's next.
Yeah exactly. Nice, nice. And so your talk here actually later this afternoon is on geometry
aware neural rendering. What's that? Is that something you worked on at OpenAI or kind of personal
interest? Yeah that's something I worked on at OpenAI also through like during my PhD at Berkeley
kind of while I was spending time in both places. Okay and so the kind of the core problem that I'm
working on there is you know how do we like in robotics you know in order to to act robots need
to first understand what's happening in the world and so typically the way that you'll do that in
robotics is you'll kind of take your sensor observations about the world and you'll map them to
some way of representing the state of the world right so where are all the objects what poses are
they in you know what configuration is the robot in etc but the challenge is that as you move to
more and more complex scenes then it becomes hard to write down a concrete representation of
the state of the world and so the kind of the focus of this work is on implicit scene understanding
so can we can we take some sensor observations about a scene and then use that to create a
representation of the world that kind of implicitly has an understanding of what's happening in the scene
and so what's can you be more concrete than that or is there an example that that you use to
describe that? Yeah absolutely so that concretely the way that you formulate the problem is you take
one or more observations of the scene so think about like cameras imaging the same scene from
different viewpoints and then you train a model and the goal of that model is to
give in some arbitrary other viewpoint that could be you know any other viewpoint of the scene
the model's goal is to render what it thinks the scene looks like from that viewpoint
and so the and thus if it can do that then it has an accurate kind of implied or implicit
representation of what's happening in the scene yeah that's the intuition right it's if the model
can do that task well it has to have some sort of representation internally that understands what's
going on in the scene practically when you do this a how many cameras are we talking about yeah
it's a handful I mean it's the formulation can really extent any number in practice I usually
use three cameras to image the scene and then and so then the fourth viewpoint is the one that the
the model is trying to predict that is the the neural rendering part of the the talk geometry
aware implies that it's kind of a model-based approach in some sense yeah I mean so the geometry
of where part is so the kind of the the inspiration for the work that I did and what I built on was
this paper from DeepMind called GQN generative query networks okay and so the the extension that
I added to that is the geometry of where part and so what it refers to is you know if you
if you know the geometry of the scene so where the cameras are relative to one another then that
allows you to constrain the process of of searching what pixels are most relevant to rendering a
particular pixel so you know if you're rendering a particular viewpoint and you want to know you
know okay what should I image in this pixel somewhere somewhere in the image that I'm rendering
then what you want to do is you want to go back and look at all the images that you've been given
as context and sort of search over those images for relevant information and it turns out if you
use the geometry of the scene this thing from classical computer vision called the epipolar geometry
then you can constrain that search to align in each of the context viewpoints and so maybe as context
kind of walk us through GQN and what that paper is talking about yeah so in GQN they're taking this
problem of neural rendering right so looking at a looking at a scene for multiple viewpoints and
rendering from an arbitrary other viewpoint and then they set up a model structure and the way
that model structure works is it's basically an encoder decoder architecture so the encoder
takes each of the viewpoints and maps them through a convolutional neural network independently
and so then you get a representation for each of those viewpoints those representations are summed
and then you get sort of one representation for the entire scene so that's kind of the encoder part
so like element-wise or concatenated more yeah some element-wise okay yeah so then you take that
that representation for the scene and you pass that to the decoder and then the decoder's job is to
take that representation and sort of go through this multi-step process of turning it into the
what it thinks the image from that viewpoint should look like okay and is there any particular
intuition for the element-wise sum versus keeping everything around you know I think the main
intuition is that you want it to be you don't want it to depend on the order that you present the
camera's in so if you can coordinate then order matters some then it doesn't okay and so they
their results were kind of purely based on this just the camera angles and the kind of encoder
decoder architecture and so that what you added was a constraint to the search base that is based
on what we know about the geometry epipolar geometry epipolar geometry yeah so so basically the
the contribution of our paper is you know there's this this sort of bottleneck in the GQN formulation
where you know you've taken the encoder and that's given you representation of the scene and then
you pass that to a decoder but what we do instead is instead of having this representation of the
scene instead we have an attention mechanism so that attention mechanism allows you to when
you're generating a new image to attend over all the information in the in the representations
of the context images that you've been given and the way that attention mechanism works is by
taking advantage of this you know this sort of fact of 3D geometry called the the the epipolar
geometry is calling it an attention mechanism is it is it like attention like or is it
implemented the way attention is often implemented in these kinds of networks yeah so it's
implemented exactly like like kind of like a scaled dot product attention mechanism but the way
that you have to do that is you know you have for every pixel you know you're searching over a line
so you need to create you need to sort of construct the right representation so that you can do
attention in the normal way okay so you're you're kind of constructing a vector that represents
this line that you're doing the dot product and your dot producting that with everything yeah okay
so for each pixel we're constructing this vector that represents a line and so when you aggregate
all of those right so you have two spatial dimensions for the image and then you have this line
and so you get this sort of 3D tensor and then your dot producting the image that you're trying to
render the current representation of that with this 3D tensor and then that's kind of the attention
mechanism cool cool and so tell us a little bit about the results of the paper is it kind of
trying to get at you know better accuracy in rendering the scene or computational efficiency all
of the above yeah so it's nice to me that both of the above would be would follow from what you're
doing sure yeah I mean there's definitely data efficiency gains but really the main goal was
sort of coming back to the motivation for working on this I you know I primarily work in robotics
and so the you know the reason I started working on this was to construct better representations
for robotic scenes and so the thing I really wanted to do was to extend GQN to you know more complex
more realistic scenes so higher dimensional images more like higher dimensional sort of robot
morphologies and more complex objects and so the the kind of main result of the paper is we
introduced a few new data sets that capture some of those properties and then we showed that our
attention mechanism produces like kind of qualitatively and quantitatively much better results on
those sort of newer more complex data sets there also the results are also better on the
old data sets as well but you know I think really the interesting thing is how much better they work
on on these newer data sets so tell us a little about the newer data sets and how they were
constructed yeah so there's three new data sets one is a data set that's based on the
in-hand block manipulation work from open AI and so it's you know related to the Rubik's Cube
yeah so the precursor to the Rubik's Cube works so before the Rubik's Cube work there was the
block manipulation work that was you know I guess a little more than a year ago at this point
and so yeah we hadn't we hadn't released the Rubik's Cube work yet at the time I was working on
this so I worked on the older data set okay and yeah so you know you have a bunch of cameras looking
at a robot hand that's holding a block and the sort of colors of the cube in the background
and the hand are randomized and the hand and the cube can be in any pose so that's one of the
data sets okay and so that's kind of meant to capture sort of a like what a quite realistic sort of
robotic task could look like right the second data set is what I call disco humanoid and so this
is like you know the he the classic mojoco humanoid model but the poses of all the joints are
completely randomized and the colors of everything are randomized as well the lighting so what it
looks like is this sort of humanoid model that's like doing this like crazy jumping in the air dance
moves okay and so that's kind of the second data set and that's meant to capture you know whether
you can model robots that have complex internal states right so this high-dimensional robot
needing to model it in any pose now is this the starting position randomized or is it kind of
randomized in time at every time step or yeah so just one time step okay it's just a single frame
yeah a single frame a single scene and then multiple viewpoints of that scene right got it okay
but then each each each scene has different parameters for randomizing everything about the scene
so the the humanoid is in a different pose the colors and lighting are all different okay and so
the third data set the third data set the third data set is I think the most challenging one so
it's basically a room and then in that room are placed a few objects but those objects are sampled
from the shape net object data set okay so there's something like 60,000 possible object models
and so each in each of the kind of million scenes that we generated there's a different set of
objects that are placed in that scene and so it's really challenging because you know the
the model needs to understand how to render sort of you know essentially any type of object
interesting at least in the the first couple of those examples maybe in the third
what kind of jumped out at me is not so much the like the complexity of the scene you know of
course that that that's there but also the attempts to you know randomize colors and things like
that I often refer back to one of Peter's videos of like the robot doing rope tying and like it
can figure it out on a green table but then if you change the table to red it like totally fails
yeah so now you know it's a part of what you're doing explicitly trying to make the model more
generalizable or yeah I mean so we didn't explore how generalizable the model could be in this work
okay but I think you know a lot of my earlier work was on like this idea of domain randomization
right so if you want to train a model in simulation that generalizes the real world kind of the
one of the most effective ways of doing that is to sort of massively randomize every aspect of
the simulator so there's some background that you brought into this task exactly okay so I'm
interested in realistic robotics tasks and so to me if you're working on realistic robotics tasks
in simulation you need to randomize everything okay and you know I think exciting future work
could be to see how well these models transfer from simulation to the real world uh-huh and so
when you're evaluating the performance of these models are you is it kind of like pixel wise
differences or distortions and an error rate that you're kind of looking at or what's what are
the metrics that you're looking at yeah so the way that these I sort of gloss over how the models
are trained but it's essentially like the the easiest thing to compare to is to a VAE
okay so you have a lower bound on the log likelihood and that's a variational autoencoder that's
right yeah and so that's kind of the main way that you can compare the differences is by is by
comparing the number of that lower bound and then you can also look at things we also look at
things like you know L1 and L2 pixel wise differences between the images and so that's where our
quantitative results come from it sounds like you have not applied this to a real world you didn't
uh apply it to the Rubik's cube uh robot or any uh robots uh not not yet not yet yeah okay okay
so what are some of the other things that you're working on or have worked on or are interested in
yeah um so I think as I mentioned a lot like the sort of big chunk of my the early part of my
PhD was working on demand randomization so you know really the sort of core question I got
interested in early on when I started working robotics is if we believe that reinforcement learning
is going to have a big impact in robotics then um sort of the the main challenge is that most
reinforcement learning methods are super data and efficient right and so there's you know
different ways that you could think about dealing with that you know one is just to make reinforcement
learning methods themselves more data efficient um so that's like a lot of work from uh surgae
Levine's group at Berkeley um pushes in that direction um but I kind of became interested in this
question of you know can we just assume that our algorithms are always going to be data inefficient
and then figure out how to generate data much more efficiently so that that kind of led me to work
on simulation the thing that I've realized recently is that I think domain randomization and um
you know other simple real techniques work actually surprisingly well other what techniques um
other uh simple real techniques okay some transferring simulation in the real world domain
adaptation and things like that um but so I I think are still like very um under explored
techniques in robotics but the challenge if you want to apply those techniques has become that
it's actually quite difficult to build physics simulators and so in practice that often becomes
the bottleneck is you have some new robotics task you want to solve maybe you want to use Sim to
real to solve it but um then you have to go and do this manual process of um you know constructing
and uh randomizing the simulator that you use to generate the training data um and so that's
kind of what started to get me interested in 3d scene understanding is thinking about the question
of is it possible to automate part of that process um or at least to augment augment people
in um the process of creating synthetic training datasets does that goal tie to the work we just
talked about what's the connection there yeah or are you not trying to say that I think uh
I think it loosely ties to that goal okay right so I think um you know that like in my mind
sort of the end state for Sim to real is um you know is you have like real to Sim to real right so
you have you collect some data in the real world you use that data to generate a simulation
mm-hmm and that simulation is sort of richer than the real world it's highly randomized
um you train a model in that simulation and you transfer that model back to the real world um
use that model to collect more data in the real world and then feed it back into the simulation
mm-hmm right so I think and then I think you iterate over that process and I think that um
if you have the right algorithms for that then I think that process or that um those types of
algorithms will be really powerful um and so you know that the the main sort of missing piece
there is um going from you know a small amount of data about the real world right so a small number
of observations about you know the scene that the robot is going to be interacting with
and then turning that into a simulation mm-hmm right and so um the this work on neural rendering is
um kind of I think like a conceptual cause of that because um we're not directly trying to create
a simulation but we're trying to create a um like sort of an implicit version of a simulation
mm-hmm um and so right now it only captures 3d structure it doesn't capture um
semantics or dynamics or anything like that but I think it's kind of like an early step along that path
mm-hmm what's the the state of research in the real to sim
part of that flow like how far along are we yeah I think it's I think it's pretty early there's
been a number of papers that have come out on it you know 2018 2019 what what are the main things
the way that researchers are approaching the the problem right now yeah I think um so I think
like the general problem is very challenging and this is the general problem is inverse graphics
which um it's super super hard to do mm-hmm and so I think the main way that people are
approaching the problem right now is to sort of create a frame in first graphics being like I've
got some set of images create the representation yeah create the um create a world that would generate
those images right and so I think like the main way that I've seen people approach this right
now is um instead of trying to solve the entire inverse graphics problem mm-hmm um instead sort of
manually create a parameterized simulator so a simulator that kind of in principle should capture
the things about the real world that you care about mm-hmm and then using the real data to optimize
the parameters of that simulator yeah yeah um and so then you you know the hope would be at least
you can use the real data to choose the distribution of parameters that allows you to best transfer
your model from simulation to the real world um and so there's a bunch of work in that direction
so for example in the case of trying to use Grand Theft Auto as a simulator take a picture of a
road and try to generate something that looks like that road within the constraints of GT Auto
exactly yeah yeah yeah and so it sounds like folks are starting the kind of poke at that
direction how far you know what do you do you have a sense or do you know off the top of your
head kind of some of the results that folks have seen there yeah I think uh I don't want to point
to any specific results because I don't want to get them wrong but um yeah let's see we're
even going to find this qualitatively like are we at doing this with Grand Theft Auto or are we
more doing this with like simple rooms with shape library pictures like how sophisticated are the
simulation environments that we're even able to do this kind of thing with yeah I mean so there
are some results doing this kind of thing um I think like the primary results come out of
Nvidia um doing this kind of thing with self driving car data okay um and uh the results there
seem to be promising um I think um it's not clear to me how much effort still goes into the manual
sort of creation of the parameterized simulation yeah um versus that being more automated um that's
kind of the big question mark I think also although I'm not going to remember the the specific papers
off the top of my head um I wrote kind of a a guide to some seem to real um transfer for robotics
and I cited a bunch of the kind of relevant work in this direction there um so I'm happy to
share a link to that yeah please do and we'll include it in the show notes you mentioned a few times
domain randomization as a way to drive kind of generalizability and the the you know more
effective seem to real are you or are there folks looking at more of it maybe kind of stretching
the term too far but like active learning type of approaches like should the domains actually be
randomized or should they be you know more carefully constructed so as to drive generalization
yeah it's a great question um I think there's not really a simple answer to it I think in a lot of
cases what I've found is that the simplest thing that you can do which is just randomizing your
simulation as much as possible um tends to give you like closed optimal results um so you might
as well just do a simple thing but for a lot of problems that's not that's not true I think like
one of the main cases where that's not true is where um randomizing your simulator too much
actually hurts performance in simulation right so and if your performance in simulation gets worse
than your performance in real gets worse as well um and so I think in those types of cases
so that's like a lot of the dynamics randomization type stuff as an example of where where that happens
okay and so in a lot of those cases you know choosing not just randomizing everything but
choosing the right randomizations become super important and so there's also some work in that
direction there's a there's a paper from an Nvidia for example where they kind of do an iterative
process um where they you know at each step in the iteration they um take real data and then they
use that real data to optimize the parameters of the simulator so that the the distribution of
simulations is as similar as possible to the real data um they go back and collect more real data
and then continue to iterate between those two things um so there's some work in that direction
yeah you describe so you describe the the scenario where the simulator you over-randomize and you
drop performance in your sim um that seems like the easier of the you know problems relative to
over-randomize your simulator does great but you drop performance in real does that happen also
I've not really seen that happen okay usually more randomization tends to help generalization
okay yeah yeah unless it hurts performance on the original task it's in principle possible
that that could happen but it's not something I've seen much in practice so I described earlier
the geometric aware approach that you presented is kind of a model based on model aware approach
do you have ideas or other types of models that you might want to combine with a neural
rendering that you know would help it yeah it's a good question um an interesting
direction for this type of work is um we right now model static scenes so we you know um
we're taking like we're freezing a single time frame of a robotic task and we're saying
you know can we understand what this what the scene would look like from another angle um but
also super relevant is to um is to look at entire tasks and try to you know compress those
and understand those um and so um what that would require you you to do is also understand
things like how um objects interact with one another how robots interact with objects how physics
works um and I think there you can I think there are certainly other kind of concepts from physics
that you could encode into a neural network architecture that would allow you to um to do those
tasks more data efficiently cool well it sounds like really interesting uh really interesting work
and best of luck in the presentation thanks a lot yeah you know do you want to kind of
give a pitch for your next job or something like that well uh no I don't think so um I think
people just have to wait and see yeah yeah so it sounds like you've got something something brewing
uh yeah we could call it that yeah yeah nice nice awesome well Josh thanks so much for
taking some time uh chat with us about what you're up to yeah thanks so much for having me thanks