Welcome to the Twimal AI Podcast.
I'm your host, Sam Charrington.
Hey, what's up everyone?
Happy Memorial Day to those of you in the States.
Although we might not be able to celebrate holidays like we once would, I encourage
you to find a way to enjoy yourself this weekend, connect with family and friends and enjoy
some good food and fun as best as you can.
I am super excited to be hosting tomorrow's live panel discussion on advancing your data
science career during the pandemic.
This is going to be a great one featuring an amazing lineup and I encourage you to join
us.
You can check out twimalai.com slash DS careers for more information and to register.
I also want to give you a heads up regarding my upcoming webinar with Algorithmia CTO
Kenny Daniel.
The hot topic at last year's TwimalCon on conference was a discussion on whether you
should build or buy an ML or data science platform.
Well, we'll be tackling this topic head on in our upcoming session.
We'll discuss what goes into building a machine learning management platform, how to make
the business case for ML ops at your company and how to evaluate off the shelf machine
learning management solutions.
Be sure to mark your calendar for 10 a.m. Pacific on June 9th and visit twimalai.com slash
Algorithmia to register.
That's twimalai.com slash ALGORITHMIA.
All right, enjoy the show and enjoy the holiday.
All right, everyone.
I am on the line with Joey Gonzalez.
Joey is an assistant professor at UC Berkeley in the EECS department.
Joey, welcome to the Twimalai podcast.
Thank you for having me.
I'm really looking forward to diving into this conversation.
And in particular, talking about ML systems and your recent paper on train large then
compress, but before we do that, please share a little bit about your background and how
you came to work in ML and AI.
Yeah, excellent.
So my story's a bit funny.
I started my PhD at Carnegie Mellon with an interest in actually flipping helicopters
because that was a trendy thing to do back in 2006, a while back.
Flipping helicopters.
Colleague of mine, Peter Beale, now at Berkeley, when he was finishing up his thesis work,
he was looking at how to do interesting control for helicopters.
I thought that was really cool.
And at CMU, I went to my thesis advice and you've worked on control as well.
I'm kind of interested in flipping helicopters.
I think that's really neat research and you know, I didn't know that was the thing.
Well, it was.
And it actually was some of the pioneering work to what we see today in reinforcement
learning.
But what's kind of cool about the story is my advisor at that time being a real machine
learning researcher.
I was like, you know what, flipping helicopters, that's exciting, but there's something
more important, like we can actually help the world with sensors.
We can build sensor networks to monitor fires and we can use kind of principled machine
learning techniques.
I should add that when I was looking at the flipping helicopters, like, you know what,
we should flip them with neural networks.
And the other thing my advisor said, which was good advice at the time, was neural networks
aren't really serious research.
We use more statistical methods, graphical models, things that have formal foundations
that we can reason about and write kind of detailed analysis and understand what our models
are doing.
And that was good advice.
And so I went down this path of how to build Gaussian processes, Bayesian on parametric
methods to reason about link quality and sensor networks.
And in that process of doing that, I kind of stumbled into a problem.
I was writing a lot of MATLAB code to compute big matrix inverses and then approximations
to that to make it run faster.
And one of the things I enjoyed doing in the process of, you know, exploring these more
efficient MATLAB programs was trying to make them more parallel.
And I think my advisor included is a good advisor is like, you know what, maybe you enjoy
that more.
So maybe instead of focusing on the non-permetrics and the sensor networks, let's start
to think about how to make machine learning more efficient.
And in particular, at that point in time, Hadoop was taking off and said, you know what,
MapReduce, that's going to change machine learning.
And we were thinking, well, we're working on graphs and they just don't fit the MapReduce
pattern.
And the kinds of computation we were doing just, it wasn't, it didn't actually fit the
technology that people were building.
So we started to explore a different design of systems.
So design of systems for computation on graphs, which took us down the design of graph processing
systems.
System that I ended up writing is kind of the end of my thesis was a graph lab for doing
very large analysis of graphs.
And so by the time I finished my PhD, I was actually writing systems papers, not machine
learning papers.
And the field was changing very, very rapidly too.
This around 2012, if anyone's been following the history of machine learning around 2012,
everyone started to realize maybe actually the neural nets were a good idea.
The deep learning, these ideas actually really dated back the 1980s.
They're actually really starting to work.
And they were changing the field of machine learning.
And graphs were also taking off, so we built actually a company around the systems that
I was developing as a graduate student, it was graph lab, that evolved into a company
for building tools for data scientists to do interesting machine learning at scale.
That was ultimately acquired by Apple.
And around that time, I also joined the UC Berkeley Amplab as a postdoc.
And there was, you know, a chance to come out to California and it was a really exciting
opportunity to do research in a different system, a system called Spark, which eventually
became Apache Spark.
And there we started to develop the graph processing foundation for the Apache Spark
system.
And again, as I started to explore more and more into the field, I learned more about
research in data systems and transaction processing and how those connect back to machine learning.
And so after finishing my postdoc, I came to Berkeley.
In fact, I chose not to follow the much more lucrative path of the startup.
It was going to ask about that.
Yeah, I made a terrible financial decision.
But I'm happy because I have a chance to work with students.
I'm a little less happy because I'm not as wealthy as one could have been.
But now I am teaching students that do research at the intersection of machine learning and
systems.
And so we have a pretty broad agenda around how to build better technologies for delivering
models to manage machine learning life cycle, not just training, but prediction, how to
prioritize training experiments on the cloud to use serverless computing to make machine
learning more cost effective and easier to deploy.
We have a big agenda around autonomous driving, building the actual platform that supports
autonomous driving, not necessarily the models, but how they are connected together to make
a reliable car.
And we have work in natural language processing and computer vision.
And one of those papers, one that I'm hoping to talk a bit about today, which is our work
on making a vert models easier to train.
And it, too, has a kind of funny story how we came to actually a realization that what
we were thinking was entirely wrong.
And that's what that paper talks a bit about.
Well, let's get to that funny story in a second.
There's so much interesting stuff that you just mentioned.
It's there, there are at least three or four interesting podcasts in here.
I'd love to dig into some of the stuff you're doing with serverless at some point and how
that intersects with ML and AI, something I've looked at a little bit as well.
But before we jump into even more of that, I'm curious.
Your co-founder at GraphLab and Tury Carlos Gastron was one of my very first guests on
this show.
Tumel talk number seven, in fact.
And I'm curious how you came to know and found the company with Carlos.
Yeah, Carlos is awesome.
So he was my thesis author.
Oh, okay.
When I came to CMU, Carlos was the guy who said, let's not flip helicopters, let's do
something that could make an impact in the world.
He was a great advisor.
He pushed me down the right path in my PhD, the thing that reflected what I was interested
in.
And he was one of the pioneers in the modern field of machine learning and systems.
Yeah.
So that's how I came to know.
He did go to Apple.
He did.
He saw him recently at Nurebs, most recently in Vancouver.
It seems to be really having a good time there.
Yeah, he's had a chance to have a lot of impact doing really cool stuff.
You kind of laid out this broad space of research.
It sounds very broad, actually, tied together by systems.
I'm curious how you kind of, you know, is it rationalized by, hey, you've got a bunch
of, you know, students and you're letting them flip helicopters in the way that they want
to flip helicopters more so than you were, you know, and so it's you or it's challenging
as faculty to decide what is your research agenda.
One likes to imagine you sit there and go, here are the three two things.
I want to study, usually not one, because you have to have enough for a couple of students
to build, you know, their thesis around.
The reality is that students pull you and I actually, I think sort of like artists, it's
hard to compel people to follow the research agenda that you ultimately want.
My advisor did a great job.
It's not about telling you what to do.
It's about showing you the exciting opportunities you can explore.
And so with my students, I've pushed them in directions to think about how we make models
more efficient to not just train, but to serve, how we support new emerging applications
of machine learning that might require innovation both in the system and the modeling techniques.
And actually what's kind of neat about the field of systems and machine learning is, again,
when I started, it wasn't really a thing.
In fact, some of my colleagues at CMU were like, you're just hacking, you're not actually
doing research, you're not proving anything fundamental about machine learning, you're
writing software, a little bit of that was true.
We were definitely writing a lot of software.
We were trying to prove some stuff too, but I think the impact might have actually been
more on the software side.
And one of the funny things about the broader field of systems and machine learning is
that it actually has been kind of the undercurrent of a lot of the recent progress in AI.
When we look at this revolution in deep learning, we can go back to the 2012, the Alex Net paper.
That's actually not the beginning, it goes way back to the 1980s.
In fact, the techniques are from the 1980s, the architectures, the models, even the algorithms
that we're using are from the 1980s.
If you actually read the Alex Net paper, more than half the papers devoted to how they got
it to run on a GPU, how they got it to run on a very large image data set, and some of
the optimizations they made to the training process to make it run at scale.
So it is the movement to scale that really helped launch the revolution that we are on
today.
Now there's the other factor, which I think people overlook, and it's sort of when I was
doing my PhD, we were writing the foretran of machine learning, we were writing MATLAB
code to implement algorithms and debugging gradient procedures, and that's absurd.
Today, it's just too easy.
So a graduate student can pick up PyTorch, TensorFlow, MX Net, one of these packages,
and very easily architect a new model, and train it on TPUs, GPUs, how do they barely
understand, and get it to run at scale on data sets that they don't have to collect.
So that is an enormous jump forward.
And if you look really carefully and a little bit depressingly, the models didn't change
that radically.
The algorithms didn't change that radically.
What changed was it became a lot easier.
We developed the languages, the tools to make machine learning practical, and it really
boiled down to getting the right abstractions.
And maybe if you roll all the way back when Alex Net came out, they didn't quite have
that.
Alex Net came out.
Theanos started to really take off, cafe at Berkeley started to take off, and it became
so much easier to build that next model and the next model, and so on.
And today we're stuck into a flood of archive papers because basically anyone can download
one of these packages and start building state-of-the-art machine learning models.
There's some learning that you go into the process, but the fundamental principles are
to find your objective, to find your decision process, and then tune your decision process
optimize it for that objective.
That's it, and the undercurrent that drive all of this has been a lot of the innovation
in the systems front, not necessarily the machine learning.
And so my research is trying to find those right abstractions, and especially as we look
at new frontiers, not just training models, but how we deliver them, how we support them
and autonomous driving, and how we adjust the architectures of the models themselves
to make them more efficient in these new kinds of applications.
At when I first started doing these interviews, one of my favorite questions was looking
to explore the way folks came up with new models and trying to find the science behind
it, and I think that the takeaways where a lot of it was, the answer was like graduate
student descent.
We would just throw a graduate student at this, and they tweak something that pre-existed,
but there wasn't necessarily a hard science behind how to come up with a new model architecture.
But so we've seen a lot of innovation like and around, you know, Bert and the kinds
of transformer models that we're seeing here, you know, has that, has, you know, would
your answer to that be kind of similar, has it, you know, it changed a lot, or how do
you think of, you know, beyond kind of that high level process, you just laid out?
How do you think of the process for coming up with these new types of architectures?
Yeah, so that's been a struggle for me.
So remember, I start with this religion, this Bayesian philosophy of model development,
they have these principles of priors and likelihoods that gave us at least the basic foundations
of what to think about when building a model.
That's all, that's not gone, but that's, you know, effectively gone for a lot of the
machine learning world.
And so we're left with a lot of the new, though, actually, right?
Like the concept of modeling is on the rise, I think.
So I should say it's not gone, and it's very important to note that a lot of the world
actually runs on these more traditional techniques. It's the research community where we're writing
these new papers for language modeling or speech or driving where there's very specific
cases that have been kind of dominated by deep learning techniques.
But the Bayesian methods are still, you know, fully alive and medicine and even traditional
advertising algorithms.
But with that in mind, so when I start to look at the deep learning work, how do I find
those principles?
And actually, they actually exist. They're a little smaller.
And sadly, we start to embody the model with personality, like the model is trying to
do X, which is sad because that's not how we like to, you know, formally think of things.
But these building blocks, convolution, recurrence, attention, each of these becomes tools that
we can use to architect our models.
When students go, how deep should we make it while we try to go a little deeper?
They start to look at how it affects convergence rates, variation in batch size and its relation
to batch form.
So we have little rules of thumb.
And unfortunately, there's no great, like, my PhD students like two or three years to get
up to speed with the rules of thumb in the area that they're working in.
And once they have that, I hope they teach the next PhD students and so on because it's
hard to really grasp what those are. It's more like, it comes from experience working with
these models and going, ah, right?
So like the transformer, in this particular piece of work that we've been exploring, like
how to make it more efficient, we're like, should we make it deeper, should we make it
wider?
Who knows?
So we start to measure each of these things.
And that's one of the jokes that we make is that machine learnings become more like
a biological science.
It's driven by laboratory experiments, ah, by using compute to understand better the
models that we're building, ah, as opposed to the more, ah, principled approach we might
have had in the past.
We tried to, to frame it in some probabilistic architecture.
You mentioned that there was a story behind the, the work that led to train large than
compress.
Yeah.
So I'm happy to go into that story.
Sure.
Yeah.
So the story behind that the train large and compress work, ah, it starts in the following.
So, ah, we've been doing a lot of work in how to make, ah, computer vision models more
efficient, ah, in particular, not for training, but for inference.
Ah, and so we have these skip net architectures, ways of making things more dynamic.
And some of my colleagues go, you know what, maybe we should start thinking about language
models.
They seem to be eating up a lot of cycles.
The, the transformer, the BERT model that's become a kind of a foundation for reason about
text and context.
Well, so that, that model is pretty expensive to run.
Ah, and so we said, all right, maybe we'll explore what we can do in, in the context of
making these BERT models more efficient.
Now, I should say a lot of people are starting to think about that because BERT is, you know,
incredibly expensive to run, ah, on, on text feeds and text is a pretty large, ah, you
know, body of data that we might want to process.
Yeah, I'll mention that, ah, for folks that want to dig into that particular point, I
did an interview with Emma Strubel, ah, who has, um, you know, in, in fair amount of
detail, kind of characterized the, both the cost and kind of environmental impact of
training some of these large scale NLP models.
And it is crazy.
It's, it's crazy, actually, the, the CO2, ah, as narrative was one of the things that
got me, especially, like, I was, ah, maybe we don't touch language, that's, that's
there's plenty of people thinking about it, and then I, I saw Emma's papers, like, wow,
ah, I'm here trying to make autonomous cars so that, you know, a little bit more environmentally
friendly when it comes to driving, when I could go fix a, you know, fundamental prime
right in my field, ah, and so, yeah, so we look at these language models and go, how
can we make these better, ah, and the first step to doing that is we got to understand
them.
So we need to run some experiments, ah, and, and my students go, well, we're going
to need a lot of machines, like, I can't afford a lot of machines.
So if I look at Google at Facebook, they can throw a lot of compute and trying to understand
something, and that's actually one of their, their tools that, that we don't really have
access to, ah, we've actually, ah, started a collaboration with Google so we could get access
to TPUs.
We can't do it at the scale that they're going to run their experiments.
So we had to get lean.
So how can we rapidly iterate on variations in our architectures, ah, we want to look
at different types of, of attention, different architecture sizes, understand the effects
of these hyper parameters, and so my students go, ah, here's what we'll do, we'll make the
models really small and we run a training run every day with different configurations
and we've got a good picture of what's going on, ah, and they did that and so they made
the model really small because that would, in theory, make it really fast to train, ah,
but they also run really small in terms of, ah, good parameters or, yeah, so they made
the model smaller in terms of both the height, ah, the number of layers and the width, the
number of these hidden, ah, hidden layers, hidden parameters inside of each of the attention
heads.
So basically they tried to make the model so it would, ah, it would train faster because
it had less to compute, ah, less to, to update, ah, this is more of a classic way of thinking,
how I would approach a problem too, if it's too big, make the problem smaller, ah, it
should go faster, right, it's less to do, ah, so they did that and it was working, but
one of them was like, well, what if we make it a little bigger just, you know, to get
a point of comparison and they applied the point of comparison on top of the, you know,
the, the smaller models they were training and, and the point of comparison seemed to go
down pretty quickly and I say, well, let's put it in time and you put it in time and
actually the bigger model, the point of comparison was actually getting to a better accuracy quicker
than the smaller models that we were supposed to be running because they're faster to train,
ah, and then we started to wonder, hm, maybe it's the other way around, maybe we had
this backwards all along and if we want to go faster we have to make the problem bigger,
ah, which is really counterintuitive, but it actually turns out to be a really neat intersection
between, ah, how these models converge and how they can take advantage of parallel resources
in the GPUs and TPUs, ah, to get good scaling as you make them bigger, ah, and that sort
of forms the foundation of, of this work that sort of went against what we thought would
be the case, ah, and actually presents a neat way to approach training, ah, these expensive
models.
It is the idea related to the, kind of the rate of change of, ah, of kind of accuracy
for these models and, you know, taking advantage of the idea that the larger models learn
quicker, ah, but the, you know, I guess the, the area under that learning curve is proportional
to your compute cost and you cannot kind of optimize that.
Yeah, so there's a bunch of trade-offs.
Let me, I try to walk through them because they were counterintuitive to me at first
too.
So the first trade-off to think about is, ah, actually let's talk about compute.
So as I make my model bigger, I'm going to compute more, so it's more work and it should
run slower.
But the neat thing is that when I make these models wider at least, ah, I actually expose
more parallelism, and if we look at the execution of these models, it's a little surprising.
We've optimized those, those GPUs and TPUs to have a substantial amount of compute, often
for computer vision models, ah, and so now we have an opportunity when we run a transformer.
If we don't crank the batch, batch size up incredibly high, we actually have a fair amount
of leftover compute that we can use.
So making the model bigger doesn't necessarily translate to a linear increase in runtime.
So we can afford to make the models bigger without, ah, linearly increasing execution.
Parallelism and runtime don't correlate to cost because you're just running more compute
at the same time.
Yeah.
So, ah, this is looking at a single CPU.
Or carbon for that matter.
Yeah.
So, all right.
This is, you're getting to the interesting stuff.
So, so first, let's, ah, in the paper, we actually tried to control for this, because
I was like, ah, on a second, you're, you're just going to increase the cost of compute.
So we looked at one GPU, and what happens is you're not using all the cores on one
GPU when we were looking at the smaller models.
So as we make the models bigger, ah, for a fixed batch size, ah, we can get, ah, an increase
in the utilization of the GPU.
Um, and right now it's not easy to turn off those cores, and you're also paying a fixed
overhead to power the, the actual box that the cores are living in, plus cooling.
So trying to power throttle individual cores on GPUs, generally not a great idea, ah, especially
if we can get better utilization of the cores that we have, ah, now you could say I should,
I should have more GPUs.
We did.
We're going to burn more resources as we turn on more GPUs, ah, but the hope is that
we can get to a solution quicker.
And if, and if those GPUs are already attached to our box, which they often are, there's
usually some incentive to go ahead and try to use those as efficiently as possible.
Um, and so that brings us to the second question, which is if I make my model bigger, is it
really improving any efficiency, which is what we'd like to think of as the improvement
in our, our perplexity, our reduction in perplexity as we, ah, train.
And so we'd like to, to reduce our errors quickly as possible, um, in, in walk clock time
because we have to pay for the power of the building and so on.
Um, so we want to, to train as fast as possible in time, the simpler way to look at that
first is how is it, ah, how is he perplexing or error decreasing as a function of the amount
of data that we touch?
Um, and so there are two knobs there.
So now we're getting to the, the weeds, but there's the batch size, which determines how
much data we look at per step of our algorithm, um, the more data we look at, the better of
an estimate of the direction that minimizes the loss, uh, which in principle should give
us faster convergence, um, it also increases GPU utilization.
So we can use that as another mechanism to get better, uh, utilization out of each of
our piece of hardware, um, but it also has diminishing returns.
So as we increase the batch size, our, our speed at which we're able to converge as a function
of samples we look at, um, doesn't necessarily increase linearly, uh, and one of the other
sort of side effects of this, which if you work in computer vision, you're like, oh,
no, there's a problem, um, that as we increase the batch size, there's some risk of overfitting.
Um, and this is a fact that shows up more in computer vision models where, where it's somewhat
data poor, where in, uh, NLP, it seems at this point, at least that we have opportunities
to, uh, overfit more before we actually are properly overfitting.
So, uh, there's this question of the generalization gap, the gap between how well your models
fitting the training data and the test data.
And in NLP tasks, we're not at a point where we're, that generalization gap is disappearing,
which means that we can increase the batch size quite a bit more, um, without overfitting,
but it also means we can increase the model size quite a bit more.
And so what this paper then does is tries to play off, uh, compare this trade off between
model size and batch size to find the best combination.
And one of the neat results we find is it actually cranking up the model size and a batch
size, uh, to a certain extent as well, kind of gives us the best outcome, uh, it gets
us to a, a model that's more sample efficient, the more samples it sees, the faster it reduces
the, the test air, uh, and it also lets us better utilize our hardware, so we're actually
getting, uh, a gain from parallelism.
And those two forces interact to give us a faster in terms of walk lock time, um, reduction
in the test perplexity or the, the, the air metric that we care about.
In terms of this, uh, generalization gap and the, the differences between it, what you
see in computer vision and, uh, what you see in NLP tasks is that related to the way
the problems are formulated in terms of, uh, supervised versus self-supervised semi-supervised
and the kind of availability of data and labels and that kind of thing.
Absolutely.
So, uh, you're hitting a key point.
So in computer vision, we are largely still focused on supervised tasks.
We need labeled data sets, which, uh, are big, but they're not, uh, as big as we want
them to be.
Uh, whereas in NLP, we can go to really large, uh, unlabeled data sets, uh, cause we're
essentially predicting missing words.
So we've created this self-supervised task, um, and that means that we have so much more
data, we can support bigger models and bigger batch sizes without having this, this generalization
gap disappear.
Uh, we're able to, uh, sorry, without, uh, eliminating, uh, or causing our, our training
error to, um, go to zero and our test error to, to, you know, dominate, uh, so, so there
is, uh, this, this opening created by this, uh, self-supervised training that, that we're
able to take advantage of.
Now, in our experiments, we test both the self-supervised training task as well as the
downstream, uh, translation or, or classification tasks.
It would be applied to actual language modeling, you know, supervised training tasks, but that's
typically done as a small fine tuning step on top of, uh, this extensive pre-training,
which is where all the, the CO2 is going, uh, to pre-training these models.
Uh, and then in, in your description of the, the train large, it, it sounded a little
bit like you're ultimately saying, uh, you know, fully utilized whatever box you're
training on, but there's a lot more nuance there.
I am, yeah, elaborate on, on that.
So this has been a big question in data center design, generally, as a systems person,
like, should I turn off my GPUs, should I turn off my CPUs, uh, or should I try to utilize
them better?
Um, and the general consensus when we think about data centers, uh, is that we really
do want to try to maximize our utilization.
Part because we bought the data center, it's expensive, we should use it, uh, we have
to keep it cool, we have to staff it.
There's a lot of other factors that go into play, uh, and so we want to be able to use
that hardware as much as possible and as efficiently as possible.
Um, and part of the reason we might want to use it as efficiently as possible, you think
of things like serverless, uh, if I'm not using the hardware, I can put something else
there, uh, and we're creating markets for filling in the excess capacity.
So the idea that I would turn off a GPU is sort of silly, I should always have something
running.
Um, now the question is, can I make that thing running on the GPU as efficient as possible?
Uh, and so in our work, we're focusing on trying to maximize that efficiency, uh, in
my lab, for example, students are competing for the GPUs, we, the one GPU experiment is
definitely easier to run because they're not fighting for the entire box.
Um, and so the other GPUs are being used for other experiments, uh, and then when we
go to, to, you know, a GPUs, we're going to again use the whole box.
So the general consensus or at least the thought process today, when we think about the data
centers to really maximize our utilization and not try to, uh, power throttle, um, or
limit the performance of each of the, the course.
So it could be in the future and new kinds of hardware might change that trade off, um,
but the underlying economics would sort of suggest that if you bought the device, you should
really try to find ways to maximize its usage.
And given machine learning has an infinite supply of things that we'd like to train, um,
it's not hard to imagine that I can always fill my excess capacity with more training.
So is the paper fundamentally an economics paper in the sense of, you know, you're trying
to maximize utilization and those kind of things, or do you also get to results that talk
about performance given a set of constraints, like your traditional computer science,
he kinds of papers?
Yeah.
So it's, it's funny.
We hadn't gone down the economics route.
So it's, it's a funny.
I mean, very loosely.
Yeah.
Well, so we, we are actually very much thinking about the economics of computing.
When we look at serverless, that is going to fundamentally change our economics computing
in a way that I think will make things more efficient, more cost effective, um, and
actually easier.
So it's, it's a win for everyone and we actually have a, uh, upcoming paper, um, on
this at a hot cloud about, you know, the economics of serverless are going to generally be favorable
for everyone, um, assuming we get some of the systems problems, uh, you know, ironed
out, uh, this paper was really our students as in, you know, a first effort to really make
progress in the BERT-P training space to find mechanisms that we in academia can use to
go fast.
Uh, and part of that is finding better ways to be more efficient about training.
Um, it allows us to run experiments more quickly and so we can now innovate on BERT.
And one of the things we're actually looking at is, uh, trying to make these models more
non-parametric so they can leverage other data sources.
One of the side consequences of this paper is sort of, uh, you know, if you're out there
thinking about, oh, I should, that's really cool.
I want to play, uh, to play that, but hey, wait a second.
You made the model four or five X bigger, six, seven X bigger.
That's six.
Bensive for inference.
Uh, what am I going to do about that?
Um, and in fact, when we got this result, that was like my first conclusion, yay, we went
on the training front, but we just made inference, which is actually the more expensive
problem, uh, worse by seven, 10 X, uh, and if you think about it, training should only
be a small part of the use of these models, uh, inference is where it really the cost
should be.
And it is when you look at a practical application, we might train it, but we're going to
run that model 24 seven at every single tweet, every single web page that we encounter.
That's a lot of inference.
Um, and if you 100, so you're doing what a thousand, uh, when batch, the optimized, a thousand
sentences per second, uh, which sounds good.
But then you think of the amount of text in the web, that's a lot of expensive GPU hardware.
Um, so making the models smaller after training was one of the questions that we had to solve.
And so this is the second half of this paper comes back and goes, wait a second, so even
the model is bigger to train faster, but now we need a way to squeeze them down.
And maybe actually the bigger insight, which is also maybe a little less counterintuitive,
is that the bigger models, we could actually make smaller more efficiently and actually,
uh, with, with less of a degradation in accuracy.
So we make a, we train a really large model and then we chop it up.
So we, we both explored weight pruning, so eliminating weights, making the model more
sparse, uh, and quantization, reducing the bit precision of each of the, uh, the weights.
And so we are able to take our much larger models and then apply these, these, uh, compression
techniques to make them smaller.
And the, the effect of that is we can make the model actually smaller than the small models,
uh, while retaining higher accuracy.
And so that's something that we're still.
So were you able to use the compression techniques off the shelf, or did you have to adapt
them to this kind of model or, um, the specifics of the way you train them?
Yeah.
So, uh, getting close to the deadline, realizing our models are now 10x bigger, we're like,
right, so how do we quickly figure out a compressed these?
Good news.
One of the students, Shen, uh, who's, uh, working on this project had just finished
to work on quantization, uh, and so we're like, right, Shen, can we use your quantization
technique?
I don't know, maybe.
We started playing math and it turns out that, it worked really well, uh, and so we looked
at the standard quantization and standard pruning.
So we tried not to innovate extensively in each of these pieces, more of an exploration
how they interact with this kind of counter intuitive hypothesis that bigger models might
actually be better, both for training and it turns out for inference as well, if we compress
it.
Got it, got it.
So not that you have any of these numbers like right at your fingertips, but can you give
us a sense for when you say train large, like what large means in this case and how that
compares to what a Google might do typically?
Yeah.
So I think we were looking at like six X seven X bigger than was normally, was normally
published.
Uh, I'm guessing Google actually goes much larger still and they might already be benefiting
from these ideas.
And what, what order of magnitude is that in terms of number of, you know, servers or
CPUs or GPUs or so we were at eight, uh, GPUs, we actually also ran experiments on a
GPU, uh, V three TPU as well, uh, I'm trying to remember the exact sizes, I have a paper
in front of me if I can find it.
Many tabs.
Uh, yeah.
So I think we were at, we were up to like 20 hidden layers or so, uh, our 24 went up
24 layers, um, and we tried, uh, hidden sizes of, you know, like the order of, uh, 15,
36, so 1,536 hidden units, uh, for each of the layers.
So we, we tried a pretty reasonable space, um, we, we built off off the Roberto work,
which is actually if people haven't looked at, it's kind of neat, uh, sort of revisiting
what Bert did, uh, and in some ways, Bert really had the right answer, just this broader
experimentation of the, the trade off space makes a big difference.
Um, so we built off of that and tried different variations on the sizes described in that paper.
Yeah.
The kind of rough magnitudes that I remember reading about and I don't remember if this
was, you know, Bert or Almore, some of the different variations or, or, but there was,
you know, on the order of like 64, you know, tens of GPUs for, you know, yeah, or more.
Yeah.
No, so, so we went, uh, we used a TPU cluster for our big experiments.
So we actually tried to reproduce the Roberta setup, uh, so our, our comparisons are compared
to these standard baselines.
Uh, so we had to use a TPU cluster for several weeks, it's expensive to run the full experiment
for the baselines.
Um, but what was needed is by making the model bigger, we could get comparable results
quicker.
Yeah.
Mm-hmm.
And, um, so we've, we've kind of characterized bigger, now characterized quicker.
What did, what did that mean in practice?
So, uh, we used them, uh, I guess at about a hundred thousand, uh, seconds, are we able
to get fairly competitive accuracy?
Um, you should see the, the final number.
So it sort of depends also on, on which tasks we, we also accounted for the, uh, downstream
fine tuning that you'd need to do as well.
I don't actually remember I'll top my head, uh, uh, uh, well, we'll leave it as an exercise
to the listener to pull up the paper.
So you've increased the size of the model and the number of resources, the CPU resource,
or GPU rather resources that the model is running on and in turn decrease the, the training
time of the model and the aggregate compute cost, right?
Did you need to do anything special to accomplish that or was, is the paper primarily observing
the fact that, you know, the, you know, the, in aggregate, you get the, the preferable
approaches to increase the, uh, the model size.
So, uh, we did small changes to where we placed the batch normalization, uh, we did pre-normalization,
but it's like negligible changes in the underlying architecture.
Most of it is really exploring this, this trade-off space, uh, these different parameters.
So, uh, in some sense, it's a first step towards a bigger agenda.
It wasn't intended to be like a ground, uh, changing work, but what's kind of neat is it
does really make us at least rethink how we approach training of these models.
Well, it's, you know, it's important stuff like, I think a lot of people, uh, will think,
well, you know, if Berkeley's worrying about the cost of training these models, what,
what hope is there for, you know, my lab in, you know, um, a non-Berkeley institution,
you know, that has such close ties to Silicon Valley and, and relatively, awash and resources.
Uh, and so if you can figure out how to make training these models more efficient, then,
um, that's potentially a huge impact for a lot of people.
There's a, an important, uh, sub narrative here, which is that, uh, training, the pre-training
isn't something that everyone needs to do, um, and so, uh, Google has done a great job
of offering these pre-trained models.
So this really expensive part isn't something that every, you know, group in the world has
to address, uh, and that's a good thing.
Um, but if we want to innovate on that pre-training process, if you want to do research in it,
or we want to, in fact, the data suggests that adding more data, uh, that's specialized
to your domain can improve the quality of the model.
So if we want to be able to push pre-training research forward, we do need to find ways
to make it more efficient, uh, and I should say we started out with thinking, oh, we're
going to invent a new bird, um, and discovered in the process and maybe, we don't necessarily
need a new bird yet, but maybe approaches to how we do the training, how we choose our
hyper parameters can make a really big difference.
Your comment just prompted a thought to what degree has the, uh, kind of the, uh, I don't
know, theoretical trade-off space around pre-training versus fine-tuning been explored.
So that, you know, if I know that I have a unique domain, you know, and some, you know,
corpus, uh, of documents or data available to me, you know, is there a, is there any kind
of concrete research I can look to to help me understand, you know, if I should be pre-training
from scratch versus fine-tuning and, or do I just need to try everything and see what
works?
Uh, the try everything is, is not terrible advice, but here's what I would tell my students,
uh, so pre-training is expensive.
So maybe start with fine-tuning, understand what, what is your prediction task, and this
is what, you know, the, the practical world will do, um, so take your, your, your, uh, your
prediction task, whether or not a translation or sentiment tagging, or maybe it's like, which
call center, which call person should this, this, you know, message be forwarded to, um,
focus on, on fine-tuning for that task first, um, there's a little bit of art in choosing
learning rights and stuff to get your fine-tuning to work, so go through that process, uh, understand
how well you can do, uh, by fine-tuning to your, your domain.
And then if you have, and you might, you know, billions of call records from the past,
you think you could really better improve the underlying representation, um, you could
then try to go back to this mass-language model, uh, training, the, the pre-training process,
uh, and then the work that we've done and, and, you know, other work that's, it's, it's
going on around us, um, can help to make that process more efficient so that you can, in
a matter of, of weeks or a week, in our case, um, take your V100 box and really make substantial
progress, uh, towards, uh, pre-trained model that's now pre-trained on, on your domain
as well.
Um, and so where do you see this line of research leading?
Yeah.
So I asked my students this every year, so as we said in this group, like, what's next,
guys?
So we figured the original goal was to, like, be able to develop a new bird.
So now we have the tools to start testing pre-training.
What should we do next?
Um, one of the things that I'm kind of excited about, uh, is, uh, well, the realization
that we're trying to cram a lot of knowledge in the weights of our model, uh, and making
the models bigger certainly helps with that, uh, another way to deal with knowledge is to
not put it in the model at all.
I, I actually have to look up stuff most of the time when I want to remember facts and
terrible remembering facts.
So I use the internet, um, I have a neural net in my head.
It doesn't have to memorize the internet because I have the internet.
So having access to a knowledge base can make a big difference, uh, and how much we need
to encode in our model, make our model perhaps smaller, um, the ability to, uh, synthesize,
uh, decisions or to apply logic on top of knowledge base.
It seems like a really big opportunity for language modeling for, uh, for NLP broadly.
And maybe even for these, these basic representations like Bert.
And so we've been looking at, and starting to look at, and some of their groups actually
have got some early published work on how to bring in a non-parametric or semi-parametric
lens on, on these models so that, uh, we can reference into a large knowledge base, uh,
in, in the construction of our embeddings themselves.
Uh, and that has, you know, the advantage of maybe being more efficient, uh, allowing
us to grow the knowledge base without having to retrain the model, uh, we could get more
data, our model just gets better without having to adjust the model itself.
Um, and maybe even giving us some explainability.
So when we go to make a prediction about, like, how we embedded the sentence or how we represent
this, you know, this decision for, you know, which called a route to, we can now actually
point back at historical data and say, here's the data we use in our embedding to reason
about that.
And you know, that's terrible data.
I don't want that in my data set or, you know, that actually, that makes sense.
And so that, that connection to the data could actually also help with the explainability.
So that's sort of the vision that I, that, that my students and, and I are pretty excited
about right now.
Does that pull from or kind of lead you to like memory based networks or like information
retrieval types of problems or?
Yeah.
So memory nets, I are all of these, these kind of, I say, I are more classic memory nets
that also increase any more classic.
Um, so, so those are our tools.
Uh, one of the things we're looking at right now is something as simple as like, can
we use embeddings from other piece of text and simple text similarity to, to recall those
embeddings?
Um, and, and there's some other work exploring this now.
Uh, ultimately things like, uh, memory nets or pointer, mechanisms to point into a knowledge
base and attend to an entire corpus would be really exciting and, and we're just starting
to explore this.
Uh, so there, there's a lot more to do.
Uh, it does push us in the direction of IR, uh, imagine a neural net that can Google
stuff for you, uh, to answer questions.
So it's certainly, there's a, a well studied area that, that we'll have to build on.
You touched on explainability in there as a possible, uh, benefit here.
Uh, I'm, I'm curious about, uh, you know, maybe you're elaborating on that a little bit
more and then also you've been doing some work on explainability as applied to reinforcement
learning.
Um, um, maybe a little, if you can share a little bit about that work as well.
Yeah, so I'm the co-director of the UC Berkeley RISE lab, which stands for real time working
on that intelligent working on that secure.
So we have an interesting agenda on security, which is another time, um, and then the E.
And then for a long time, I'm like, what does the E really, what, what, what should it
mean?
Uh, we were initially thinking execution, we're going to execute things securely, but
that, that's actually some bad connotations.
So, uh, maybe there's another agenda, which actually came out of our, our exploration
lineage, uh, how we, we track relationship between data and the model development process,
explainable, uh, decisions would be a good thing to be able to support.
Um, and so we had an agenda around how to do X, or we have actually on going agenda,
I had to, uh, explainable machine learning by connecting our training process to our data.
But what's actually pretty exciting is, is pulling in some of the recent work and explainable
AI.
Actually, my, this advisor, Carlos has an exciting work, uh, line, which provides a black
box mechanism for explaining, uh, model's decisions.
Uh, so my students have been also exploring, uh, tremendous staying power.
This is, you know, one of the things we talked about three plus years ago, and that, uh,
went that early twinal episode and Lyme comes up all the time still.
Yeah.
So I, I run the risk of a, of a, another tangent, but the, the world of explainability
is, it's, it's kind of rich and it is created by this need to, to make sense of models
that no longer make sense, uh, and so this idea that I can inspect my model and go,
hey, I like how that makes decisions, uh, that's gone, or at least, you know, to a first
approximation.
So we're left with justify the decision you made.
Let's go back and at least connect it to the data, to even the input.
Uh, so, so my group had started looking at that, and one of the things that we started
to ask is, why can't we have some interpretability?
Uh, and so one of the agendas that, uh, I'm exploring that's actually not in the language
domain, but more in the, the vision domain, um, is how to apply decision trees to connect
decision trees back with our, our, our deep learning models so that we can get the accuracy
we want, but we can also go and interrogate our model and go, well, it's going to call
this a cat, but in order to do that, it has to first identify that it's an animal and
it has to cluster it in animals with, with legs, uh, and then, you know, with fur and
then it gets us to cat.
Um, so there is an opportunity to actually understand what the model is going to do at
the high level, each of these decisions is governed by a neural net, so understanding
that is sort of off the table, uh, but at least we now have an idea of the decision process
the model will go through to make a decision.
So this is our recent work on neural back decision trees, uh, when we look at language, it's
been an interesting question of what, what would an explanation look like in the language
domain?
So there are techniques like grad cam that have been pretty popular in vision that would
give us, you know, highlighting parts of an image that say, you know, this is the part
of the image you're attending to.
We could do that in their explorations of that in the language domain, but one of the
neat things going back to our very beginning narrative is, can I connect my decisions back
to data?
Um, in many cases, that is sort of the ideal explanations.
Like here's the data that informed my decision about what you've given me now.
Um, and so, so that explanation is what we're exploring.
One of the hopes in doing that is you can not only connect it, but you can even fix
it.
Uh, so one of the kind of ideal outcomes of an explainable model is when it gets it
wrong, you go, that's wrong.
Here's what is wrong about it.
And that extra signal could be way more valuable than just some more labeled data.
Uh, and so that's our hope and maybe being able to correct our knowledge base if we are
referencing data so that we don't use that reference data in the future.
That would be one mechanism in the case of decision tree changing the path.
So, you know, cats can't be attached to the thing that are, you know, they're under
water.
That doesn't make sense.
So I want to move my cat class somewhere else in my tree.
So the opportunity to intervene in a model is something that I'm excited about when
we look at explanations at do you draw a hard line between explanations and interpretability
just when you're speaking about them casually?
I do a little bit because at least classically to me, I was again, background being more
in the traditional machine learning, uh, we really cared a lot about interpretal models
and that meant that I could look at the individual pieces of the model and start to reason
about, uh, conditional probabilities, what they would say about the, the priors that I'm
trying to impose on my data.
Um, so interpretability to me means something that is sort of independent of the kind of
intrinsically.
Yeah.
It's intrinsic to the model.
Whereas an explanation could also be called a justification, sort of looks retroactively.
Here's a decision I made, provide an explanation.
If we look at humans, humans are not interpretable, you can't look at their brain well.
Most people can't look at the brain and go, okay, yeah, I know what you're going to do.
But they provide meaningful explanations and that's maybe all we can hope for and we learn
to work with that.
And I hope with the work and explainability that we're explain is to sort of provide a
little bit more of the interpretability, uh, and I think that's important one because
it, you know, if I'm going to deploy a model, I'd like to be able to, in general, understand
how it's going to behave, uh, not just on, on a, you know, candidate piece of data.
The other lens that we're bringing is, be able to adjust the model when I get it, when
it gets it wrong, I wouldn't be able to, to correct it.
So this work with the decision trees is the set up such that the decision tree is, uh,
is an intrinsic part of, like, when you refer to the model there is the model, a superset
that includes the decision tree or is the decision tree a kind of a surrogate model that's
used when you're asking, uh, explainability kinds of questions.
No, so the challenge here was to, to make the decision tree the model.
Uh, and so what we're doing, uh, we don't do really crazy complicated things.
So in this set up, we're taking a standard ResNet 101 to find an embedding of our, our
input.
And then we're using the decision tree as a, a decision tree on top of that embedding.
Um, and so that's allowing us to route our decision process based on that embedding from
ResNet 101.
So there's a part of the model that I can make no sense of that there's no deep, uh, interpretable
or even explainable component of that little piece.
Um, but there is now structure in how decisions are made.
Right.
So the ResNet is basically, um, kind of learning this space of relationships between
the things that it's seeing, at least in a computer vision sense.
And then the decision tree is on top, making decisions about what is what based on the
space that the ResNet has locked.
Yeah.
So it is a funny recipe.
And a lot of vision now, it's take a ResNet like architecture as a backbone and it's
role is to embodying the things, you know, it wants to, but it's role is to extract, um,
pixel information to extract texture, shape, things, image attributes that would be then
used to make a decision.
And it places them in a fairly high dimensional space and then the, the decision tree is, is
constructed in a way that tries to, uh, use that, that space to make decisions.
Now, that actually alone doesn't work.
So you need to take that decision tree and fine tune the neural net, the ResNet backbone
so that it's, uh, compatible with the decision tree we build.
Um, so it's a, you know, a small twist that's needed, but that small twist now allows us
to get competitive accuracy to the original model, we're still using the model, uh, but
now have an interpretable path where like, uh, one of the fun examples is, uh, if we
give it a picture of a zebra, it's a class we've never seen before, it'll route it down
to near the horse, but then it doesn't know what, you know, it'll classify something
in that one of the horse categories.
Um, and so it, it does try to extract some structure to the classes, uh, that is
semantically meaningful, but also a picture, uh, uh, in the, in the image domain meaningful.
So, uh, things that look similar, yeah.
Can you provide a, uh, kind of a quick intuition for why a fix is needed in the neural network
domain, um, as opposed to just throwing the existing decision tree against the existing
embeddings and what the kind of intuition of that fix is?
Yeah.
So, uh, the simple answer is we tried, uh, throwing the simple embedding into the decision
tree and it didn't work, uh, the, the deeper answer is that, uh, it's, the decision tree
wasn't up, sorry, the, the neural that wasn't optimized to give features that have some,
uh, coherent structure that we can build this, this class hierarchy on top of.
And so adding this extra decision tree loss, we can actually force a decision tree to cluster
things using semantically similar structure, like we want horses to be nearby dogs and
farther, like share less common ancestors to fish.
Um, so, so we can impose some structure in our tree, uh, and then we can force the neural
nets and embeddings to reflect that structure.
So that, that is why we need to adjust the neural net to deal, to compensate or to be
able to work in the context of the tree.
So in the, and you're changing your loss function and the decision tree to accentuate kind
of like maybe, you know, I'm envisioning kind of spreading out the embedding space or
something like that so that the decision tree can, so we're more meaningful for the
semantics of the decision tree.
Cool.
Awesome.
Well, Joey, uh, this has been wonderful, uh, learning a little bit about what you're
up to there.
We still never got very deep into serverless, so we're going to have to put a pin in
that one for, uh, next time, but very cool stuff.
And thanks for taking the time to, uh, share it with us.
Thank you.
It's been fun.
Awesome.
Thanks.
All right, everyone, that's our show for today.
For more information on today's show, visit twomolai.com slash shows.
As always, thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.