All right, everyone. I am here with Pavan Taraga. Pavan is jointly appointed in the schools
of electrical engineering and arts, media, and engineering at Arizona State University.
Pavan, welcome to the Twomo AI podcast. Thank you, Sam. It's a pleasure and an honor
to be here. Thank you. It is my pleasure to host you here. I'm looking forward to digging
into your paper that will be presented at CVPR, revisiting invariance with geometry
and deep learning. But before we do that, I'd love for you to share a little bit about your
background and how you came to work in computer vision and ML. Sounds great. So my beginnings
in this area started as a senior in my undergraduate years. I was looking at problems like
face recognition, face tracking from video, track to do a senior design project really. And
as I started digging more, this was in the early or yeah, early 2000s. And it was a very exciting
time to be in the field of computer vision because the problem statement in those days would
be presented as giving a computer the ability to see and that felt like wow, that's a frontier
topic, right? Yeah. And I said, you know, looks like I'm sufficiently invested in this, looks
like it intersects with things like neuroscience, perception that is interesting mathematics,
that is interesting computing happening, very highly interdisciplinary and it felt like there
was much work to be done. So I decided to go to school in 2000, I mean grad school in 2004
to the University of Maryland studying with Professor Ramachalappa who is a pioneer in this field
and very well known for face recognition techniques and a lot of interesting things in vision at the
time. And as I started my work in the lab, I broadened from just face recognition to other things
like understanding video, understanding time series, understanding the role of light, you know,
geometry, elimination, reflectance, all these physics-based concepts and how they interface with
pattern recognition methods or machine learning methods. And as I went deeper and deeper into it,
I felt like there was a big disconnect between the methods of physics of image formation
and the methods that are used in machine learning where it's just purely a driven and statistical
techniques. And I was trying to find some middle ground where I could inject physical knowledge
into certain structures that could blend well with machine learning techniques. And one thing
led to another, I started getting interested in this area of mathematics called Rimanian geometry
and then topology as a means to express these intuitions and these constraints from physics and
interface them with deep learning or machine learning in before deep learning. So that's the theme of
my work over the past decade, which is try to understand basic phenomena, whether it's, you know,
images or video or human activity. And in recent years, we've also broadened our investigation
beyond computer vision to include things like wearable devices and physiological monitoring where
the phenomena under study is basic human movement and other things. Try to understand it from
first principles and try to express that knowledge in a way that constrains conditions
machine learning. So that's the general intersection of topics I've been looking at.
Okay, and I mentioned in introducing you that one of your appointments is with a school that
has arts in the title. How does that come up in your work and research?
So you're particularly connected to that particular piece of that school.
So that's a whole story by itself. And I can go very organically about how it all began or I can go
in hindsight, this is how it went organically. This is how it began. Our school was founded in 2009
and you know, I graduated from grad school in 2009. But then that was 2009, very similar to 2020,
Wall Street collapsing and you can lose. So I stayed back when I posed or for a couple of years.
And when I went interviewing in 2011, this position opened up in this school under the title
of Assistant Professor in Human Activity Analysis. It was very intriguing. And I had been doing
human activity analysis as far as, you know, understanding a video-based gate analysis.
Okay, so I'm like fitness trackers and quantified self and all that kind of stuff.
Right. So this was a little before all that stuff happened in particular.
And I came in and I visited and there was there was a mind-boggling sense of
interdisciplinary that I saw in the school people in music looking at stuff like that, right?
accelerometers, variables, driving, interactive performance with it. There was a group doing
stroke rehabilitation where you attract human movements through motion capture and
sonify the qualities of your movements. So smoothness or jerkiness would be converted to sound
and you can hear yourself. And that provided additional feedback for you to correct your movements.
Oh wow. It was, yeah, it was a very mind-boggling experience. And even now,
people find it very interviewing when I mentioned these things. So the human activity analysis component
was a way for the school to address, you know, slightly more formal ways to think about human
movement, whether it's sense from a camera, whether it's sense from a variable device, whether
it's motion capture, try to come up with techniques to represent human movement. And then
do machine learning on it or feed into these other applications. And it seemed like I was
like Fritt at the time and I got a job. And I've been here for eight years and it has led me into
very interesting collaborations with, yeah, media artists and health scientists who are interested
in the intersection of computing art and things like health promotion. So that's the other side.
Got it. Got it. You mentioned that one of the big themes of your work is been
integrating physical, physics-based principles and computer vision.
Can you maybe talk a little bit about that in the, you know, broader context of the
computer vision landscape? We've talked about this quite a bit on the podcast and I kind of
described it as a pendulum that's kind of swung from physics-based models to statistical and
kind of is settling somewhere in the middle now. But it sounds like you've been working at this
for a while. I'm curious how, how you think of it? Yes, I mean, you're absolutely right. It's
been a pendulum that keeps swinging and I don't think it settles anywhere. I mean, that's
interesting problem about computer vision. Every time someone thinks it settles, right? Everybody thinks it's
settled now in the soonest chips. So, I mean, yes, it's been going on and off. This idea about,
I mean, I like to think of it as model-based vision versus purely data-driven, you know,
methods of thinking of vision. Yeah. The way the pendulum swings in my opinion is not that
the problems are changing. It's just the language that goes into talking about it and the tools that
go into addressing it keeps shifting, but the problems have remained mostly the same and the
problems are the following in my opinion. So vision is a very unique, you know, some people think
of it as an application of machine learning, which is a reductionistic way to think about it.
Sure, everything is data and everything is fed into a model and outcomes of decision, but vision
and any perceptual, you know, field of inquiry, that can include visions, sound,
haptics, any of these things which have to do with perception, I feel are fundamentally different
than any other application of data analysis. The way we perceive the world is not the way,
let's say, back transactions are processed by a machine learning computer, you know, a machine
learning technique. There is a huge amount of variability is the way I'd call it that exhibits
in the natural world, which is somehow either discarded or properly parsed out by whatever's
happening in our brains and the sources of variability are physics-based to a large extent, you know,
the same picture under a different lighting condition looks different, the same picture under,
you know, a different slightly changed viewpoint looks different. So that looking different part
is what gives rise to statistical variability. And the statistical ways of thinking are, well,
let's just fill up the observation space with more data points and we'll figure out what the
shape of the distribution is from data, which is okay in as intense to infinity, I guess that's fine,
but when data augmentation approaches and domain adaptation and that kind of thing,
yeah, yeah, but under and not tend to infinity, if you only have a few data samples,
you are better off trying to understand how the physics around you affects the observed
imagery. And that's where I think the methods have shifted. So, you know, in the keynote that I have
had CBPR, you know, at the workshop called differential geometry and computer vision, I go through
some of these historical trends. And one of the core themes that brings it all together, the word
that I use is called invariance, which is when you look around and try to classify objects,
we are able to do this in a way that is invariant to a lot of nuisance variables. That is light,
you know, shading viewpoint and also it's of interesting effects that are hard to describe.
When you say invariance, there's two ways to think about it. The physics-based ways to think about
it are, let's say I am looking at this scene, I know everything about this scene, including its
3D geometry, including how the paint reflects off light, including the wavelengths in the incoming
radiation. If I have full knowledge of all of this, then I can re-render a scene, let's say,
I can, just like how it happens in graphics, I can create so many different versions of the same
picture, if I had full knowledge of everything, simply through a forward rendering process and construct
variability. The data driven ways of thinking about it say, if you don't have access to everything
that you need to understand the phenomena, what is the minimal set, what is the minimal piece of
information that is needed to get a job done. That's the dichotomy in the physics-based ways of
thinking and the statistical ways of thinking. When you use this term invariant is the invariant
referring to, say we're talking about a scene with an object in it that might render differently
in different lighting conditions, etc. is the invariant that object that is definitively in the
scene and then we've got all these other effects, or does the invariant refer to something else,
maybe something more in the mathematical from a mathematical perspective.
I mean, the word invariant, of course, will depend upon what the end task is. If it is object
recognition, yes, something intrinsic to the object is the invariant. It is not always as simple
as saying the invariant is the color of the object because that changes. It is often not
same as saying the invariant is the edge map of the object or certain corners of the object
because they go in and out of view. So there's not easy ways of describing what that invariant
actually physically means. So it becomes mathematical at some level. There is no linguistic equivalent
that I can come up with. But if you look at this rendering ways of thinking, if you can render
this object that you're interested to recognize, in all possible wing conditions, all possible
lighting conditions, and you have this huge set of pictures, that huge set of pictures
could be called, you know, the word sometimes that gets used is equivalent class,
or sometimes they call it an orbit. So this object that you're trying to recognize manifests
itself in all these different ways. If you have a handle on that set, you are in good shape.
If you have a different object and you place it in the same scene and you render it in all these
different variations, and you have its own different set, then the invariant that separates these
two is some measure of difference between these two sets of pictures. And sometimes that set of
pictures can have a nice structure which can allow you to compute it in closed form and sometimes not.
So the way we have been trying to express, you know, sometimes delumination is complicated. And
if, in the most general case, we don't know how to describe this full set of pictures,
under some simplifying assumptions, which is rooted in some old work from the 90s,
Bell Humor and Krigman wrote a very famous paper, and I said, what is the set of all faces
under any given illumination condition? And they made some simplifying assumptions of what
of faces, I mean, if I ask you define a face, it's part of how to define a face, right? So how do you
even think? And this is why we've tended towards deep learning and statistical methods over the
past few years because we don't know how to define these things. So exactly. But here is what they
found. There's a, if you define it in some sub-linguistic ways, let's say it's a comics object,
and let's say it's an object which has reflectance defined by some lambershield properties,
then you can actually write down what the set looks like. Now comes deep learning. It says,
I can't define these things, give me data. And the more data you have, the better it is. But
no one knows how much data is enough, right? I mean, the more is better is the answer,
but how much is enough is never known? And we have been positioning ourselves at that intersection,
where we say, look, if I know that I'm looking at faces, I'm going to weaken the structure a little
bit. I'm going to say that, yeah, these objects that we're looking at have some characterization
under these assumptions of simplicity. But then comes deep learning, which allows me to fit
those other degrees, which I'm not able to specify analytically. So we're trying to reduce the
need for larger and larger training sets by restricting the deep net layers somehow that are
motivated by the knowledge of that physics of image formation. Sure, we don't know how much
data we need to get the full specification, but we're saying this will reduce the need for more
and more data. And all things being the same with the same amount of training sets, the same
complexity of the deep architecture, adding these constraints known from the physics of image
formation improves performance. And it also stabilizes performance against degradation of inputs.
You know, typically if you blur a picture, if you surrender a picture in slightly different ways,
performance drops pretty dramatically, we are able to avoid that. It's a middle ground, I'd say.
We are not being super specific about defining objects, nor are we saying more data is good.
We are saying something in the middle, that is, we are trying to come up with some description
of that equivalence class under simplifying assumptions and then let data fill in the rest.
So that's the way we're trying to marry the two things. And is the result
a mathematical analysis in closed form, or is it experimental results on data sets?
I mean, most of the things we do is we end up having constraints which are closed for
mathematical equations. Maybe one layer in the deep net is expected to be orthonormal because
the physics of image formation says that certain variables under certain lighting additions
will have an orthonormal structure. Okay, that's the way we impose the constraint that certain
layers might have an orthonormal constraint put in. But then the network itself has to be learned
end to end with data sets. And the performance has to be validated empirically on data sets.
Okay. One of the interesting things we found is this concept of orthonormality which seems to
have some very special power. What we're finding is whether, you know, think of it. So we played
with this idea in a paper for BMVC last year where we took some classic, you know, disentangling
autoencoder kind of networks. And we had good reason to impose an orthonormality constraint on
the latent blocks of these disentangling autoencoders. By orthonormality, we had to write up a whole,
you know, theory around we expect these factors to represent either movement or lighting conditions
or deformations. And under appropriate relaxation, they all become orthogonal to each other and
they all have this spherical structures. So looking at all of this, it looks like orthonormality
is a trade off, which is coming close to what the physics is telling us to do. And but also being
sensitive to the idea that it has to be implemented easily. We don't want to over complicate things.
And we want our constraints to be differentiable. So it's a design process. So with through in these
orthonormality constraints on disentangling autoencoders and boom, the numbers of disentangling
quality just went up quite significantly. And it's. And so in the case of an autoencoder or in
the layer of a deep network, what does it mean to impose that kind of constraint? Is it, you know,
architectural and does it mean that you're diverging from kind of your CNN, resonant kind of
tried and true architectures or is it, you know, loss function based or something totally different?
How do you impose those constraints? There's a there's two or three ways in which it's happened.
One is we stick with architectures as is don't mess with the architectures, but add-and-loss
functions that works when the constraints are actually expressable as a closed form equation
like spherical losses or, you know, orthonormality. Those can be written on as a closed form equation.
Sometimes the constraints we arrive at do not have an equation, but they have what is called
a manifold structure. And why manifolds arise is very closely related to invariance.
Here is an example, you know, if I say, so the idea of invariance is this, right? I mean,
you have a feature space. Let's say the feature space is something. You have this feature space
in RN and reports specific than something, so it's easier to follow. So let's say it's the, you know,
latent space of AlexNet, okay? Some features come from the latent space of AlexNet,
which is embedded in RN, right? So it's a vector in RN. Yep. And then we come in and we say,
look, I want to impose a slight equivalence here, which is if I rotate my picture,
looks like the features are also changing somehow. I mean, the features are not always
invariant to physical variables like this, right? But if you're able to say that this feature,
this feature, this feature in RN actually represent the same picture, just that they're rotated.
We are trying to basically paste the features and thereby the underlying space into something else
to express that concept of equivalence. And sometimes when that ways of expressing these equivalences
is well defined, what happens is the space gets crumpled. You hope that the neural net learns
to crumple the space all of its own. That is one of the overarching hopes in deep learning
that as you go through the layers of deep learning, the deep learning is learning to squish and crumple
the original feature space into interesting ways to get a job done. But what it's doing is it's not
always getting the job done the right way because you'd never have enough data. But if I explicitly
tell it that here is how rotation affects the features and here is how you paste them together
through whatever mathematics that's needed, then we get some manifold structures. You know,
this crumpling can sometimes be expressed as a manifold. If you want to say in the concept of,
you know, in the paradigm of loss functions, how do you express a manifold as a loss function?
Sometimes you cannot. What you can do instead is, you know, manifolds are basically crumpled spaces
and they have ideas associated with them which are analogous to how we think of maps and,
you know, the earth itself is composed of the earth is a manifold, but then it's also a sphere
approximately. So if you forget the idea that it's a sphere, but if it were a general weirdly shaped
blob, you would represent it by a series of charts and you would explain how the charts connect
and that's the way you specify a manifold through things called charts. And charts are also sometimes,
you know, they have a thing which is similar called tangent spaces. So you sort of flatten the
manifold in local coordinate charts and you can express that tangent space as a vector space.
So once in a while, we have run into these conditions where we have a constraint which was
expressed as a manifold which could not be written down as an equation, but whose tangent space
could be written down. So we were able to enforce conditions of that tangent Z and said,
I want this layer in my deep net to represent coordinates of a manifold on a specific tangent space
and the mapping from that back to the manifold could be written down in closed form. So it depends.
Let me see if I can upload this anywhere close to what you just said. What the way I'm kind of
hearing this is that you've got some problem. Say you've got some object and you apply some simple
transformation to that object, maybe you rotate it. If you've got a deep neural network that is
trying to detect that object, for example, and you've trained it, there may be some feature space
or some representation of that object in the different layers of the neural net. In a oversimplified
world, you'd kind of want there to be a relationship between the rotation of the object itself and
the rotation of the features. Maybe you could apply some simple transformation of the features,
but the world isn't networks aren't that simple. But it turns out there is a relationship
between the features. It's just more like this crumbly manifold thing and you found a way to
express that using the mathematical language of these manifolds that allow you to
detect the actual invariance of the object. That is very correct.
Thank you for giving me those lines.
The only disclaimer is we have been able to do this for a few common sources of physical
variability and that includes things like rotations of objects and deformations of moving parts
in certain cases, lighting conditions, just to be very clear. We haven't been able to do this
across the board for every possible thing. So simple, maybe not three-point studio lighting,
but a simple radio rotation or something like that, but clearly there's lots of things you can
do in the physical world that aren't amenable to that representation.
Absolutely. Yes.
Okay. Okay. Cool. One of the things that comes to mind in thinking about this and in your work,
you fall back on or maybe ground yourself in what you call pragmatic choices of deep architectures,
meaning the popular stuff, the way we're doing things today. I think of Jeff Hinton's
capsule networks is trying to come at some of the same ideas or same problems. Are you familiar
with that work and compare contrast? I mean, we've tracked that body of work also. Again,
he's with all due respect, ACM Turing, I can't do that easily, but it's an over-complication.
I mean, it's ignoring so much. The basic laws of rotations are not that hard if you understand
how to express rotations and we're taking out that invariance is doable without that level of
combination. So I'm correct that you're trying to come at some of the same problems at least.
Right. Okay. In it may be the case that if that enterprise succeeds, if that capsule network
enterprise succeeds, it may be a more general solution to everything, maybe, but if you want to
be a bit specific about understood factors of variation, I feel that's an over-complication.
And there are nicer ways to do that. And I think we're able to do that in a better way.
Yeah. Okay. Yeah. Cool. So you've developed this approach and you mentioned that you've
got some experimental results as well. Can you talk a little bit about how you frame the question
experimentally and what you've seen? Sure. I think the way we frame it is we want to keep
a few things fixed. And the way we keep a few things fixed is we say pick an architecture first
and that can be allocated. We're looking at things like dense net, point net, all those
your architectures which are known to work well for certain databases. Keep the architecture
more or less fixed. Keep the training set more or less fixed. The only thing that varies is,
you know, don't play too much with new fancier data augmentation methods. The only thing we are
doing is adding in constraints, either in some latent variables or we're adding in certain
augmented loss functions. So most of the additional thing that we're doing is a mathematical expression
of some kind. And keeping in, otherwise, it's hard to compare. I mean, if you say, let me train it
for more iterations, but not add a constraint, can you compare it? So keeping mostly the computational
resources fixed. We're asking if this additional mathematical knowledge pushes on the low.
And we've been finding that it does. We have done that for image classification. We've done that for
disentangling networks. We've done that for time series problems recently. And some of our
compelling results are indeed from time series modeling where, you know, we've applied this to
human activity like ignition data sets with either stick figures or wearable devices.
And the kind of factor that we're trying to factor out in human movement is not light and shape
and geometry, but it's time series variability issues, which is, you know, the same action when
performed by the same person, but at a slightly different time will give rise to slightly different
traces because people have intrinsic variability and how they move. And oftentimes that variability
gets expressed through some time warping kinds of relationships. What we've done is express the
time warping property as a constraint, which can be forced by the network to be factored out
in a latent variable if we just throw in that constrictive the loss function. And we've found that
it improves numbers significantly just like that without any additional training, without any
additional data requirements. So the pictures or what I think are the pictures of this if I'm
understanding the problem is along the lines of, you know, start from your seat in the living room,
go to the refrigerator, grab a drink, you know, take off the cover and drop the cover in the trash can,
and you've got this kind of two-dimensional plot of the path that the person might take in doing
all that. And your argument is that the path is an invariant because the task is the same.
It's, you know, do X and Y. And what you're trying to do is identify, well, what is the fundamental
that they said, identifying the path? Is it somehow in a data set with lots of these, you know,
traces or paths, identify which ones correspond to the same actions? It's close. I mean, we haven't
looked at paths in that way, but we've looked at traces of stick figures, you know, so you have
like 50 joints being tracked and you have the full-time series of 50 joints evolving in space
and in three dimensions that comes from motion capture, say. Okay. Yes, the actions not really
unlike what you're seeing, actions in a kitchen, actions in a room, actions in an office, picking
up objects, placing them here and there. And the feature that is invariant, of course, is hard
to linguistically describe, but one of the variables that gives rise to confusion is that
people sometimes take longer to do the same thing. People sometimes are fast in certain phases of
the movement, slow in certain phases of the movement, right? Or there is asymmetry in the body,
you know, the left, the left arm swings more than the right arm. You know, there's all these
interesting sources of variability which are hard to and the only way deep learning will be robust
to that is if you augment it with all these variables, all these sources of variation.
The way we think of it is that the variability here is expressible as a warping of the time
axis, whether it's short versus long or speeding up versus slowing down or if it's one side faster
than the other side or the swings are smaller than the other. It's all a time warp. Sometimes it
can be constant. Sometimes it can be non-constant. So that brings up an interesting question. Do you
assume in your work throughout a single source of invariance or do you also
conceive of multiple sources of invariance? Like, you know, there's a time invariance, but there's
also the left arm swing invariance factor. I mean, that is the, I mean, we are headed in that
direction. I mean, right now our investigations have been affected. That would be the answer.
The goal is to be able to have almost like a linear combination of known invariances that,
you know, you can account for. Right. I mean, at this time, we have been playing it very carefully
that let's take this one source of variable. Let's see if that can be factored out. Let's see if
we can get invaders to that. And we have had success in many different applications.
It sounds like you're further saying, though, that in the case of at least this motion capture
type of a data set that maybe time becomes kind of a meta-invariance that can account for multiple
physical characteristics. Am I hearing that correctly in there? It can. It's hard to write that out
clearly, but it does. Like, for instance, if you had like load bearing, you know, if you were
carrying a heavy bag on your bag, it will have an interesting effect on the time series of your
joins, which is not that easy to explain, but it will sort of stretch out certain phases of a movement
and shrink certain phases of your movement. It does. So, yeah, the stretchings and shrinkings of the
time axis are the key to finding what that invariant is for the lack. Yeah.
And so are there well-established benchmark data sets for these types of tasks? Or are you
rolling your own to explore these methods? No, for motion capture, there are benchmark data sets.
There are, you know, Microsoft has a, it used to have a RGB data set. I mean, the go-by-the-RGBD
activity sort of, you know, keywords. And there's a few out there. There's a few benchmark
data sets out there. NTU has one. MSR is one. And sometimes even, you know, the video data sets
like HMDB have stick figures available through other methods like PostNet, for instance. So, yeah,
there are well-established data sets that we experiment with. And is the task that's posed by
these data sets one of predicting the action that the, it's activity classification and prediction
by and large. Yeah. Okay. Okay. And so what's the kind of state of the art for that kind of
activity detection and how does your method compare to it? So most of the time series in the deep
learning world, most time series things are either a combination of 1D, CNNs or, you know, LSTM models.
So depending upon the data set, the way our process goes is we say, let's find the latest, you know,
benchmarks and we'll improve on those through these mathematical techniques. So, a recent paper
we did in CVPR 2019 used LSTMs as the benchmark data, you know, the technique. And the data sets were
NTU 3D data set and a few others like that motion capture. The tunable parameter in LSTMs is oftentimes
the hidden layers, how many hidden units do you have? And of course, if you scroll through it,
the numbers keep going better and better. The way we've done it is we kept things the same. We say,
let's say 16 hidden units or 32 hidden units. Keep that the same. The only thing will change is add
in this additional module that either disentangles the time or function or adds in as a constraint
and numbers always go out. So in the way we thought about it, if my number, if memory is right,
the NTU RGB data set had like, you know, 80% roughly accuracy with a very fancy LSTM with 200 hidden
units and stuff like that. And we were able to improve it by four five percentage points easy without
any changes to anything, but just this additional constraint added in. So if you find unit more,
sure, there's more things to be squeezed out, but we were able to consistently improve the
performance of LSTM by easy five percentage points and times six eight percentage points with no
change, but a simple constraint on time warping. Yeah. So those are the kinds of results that we've
been finding, which is if you rethink what the constraints should be through understanding the
phenomena first, the payoffs are actually quite significant without any additional requirements on
data or network architecture complexity or training strategies. They can all be very basic.
Mm-hmm. And so now we've talked about a couple of, you know, very different types of problems. One,
kind of a, you know, computer, a very visual type of task in one of this more time series to
apply this to different settings. How much hand crafting needs to go into the loss functions and
the, you know, the different constraints that you're applying to the network? That is where the big
work is. So I think the pendulum is swinging to that level of hand crafting, you know,
moving away from features to architectures and loss functions, right? That's where the pendulum is.
Yep. And the amount of work that goes into hand crafting is a lot of, I would say, studying basically
understanding how these variables actually affect the observed data and try to express it in a way
that is amenable to fusion with the deep net. The beauty is physics is not one way, you know, light
is, there is no single model for expressing how light and surfaces interact. There's layers and
layers and layers to it. Yeah. And you have to know all of that or at least as much as, you know,
as much as you can learn. And then the hand crafting is where in this spectrum of sophistication,
do I stop in a way that I actually have a pragmatic effect on performance without changing anything
else? And that's where a lot of intuition is, you know, you cannot get away from this intuitive
exercise. Despite all the progress of machine learning and deep learning, the networks are arguably
both intuitive and highly unintuitive. I mean, some people have an insight about why a network
works, but presented to someone else, it's mysterious. And the same thing is true of the loss
functions business. Sometimes we can motivate it very easily through simple things like, well,
yeah, cross entropy means where to make sense. Physics is where some of the unintuitive stuff lies.
It's, that's where a lot of design thinking exists and we are doing that. So yes, that's
where much of the work is understanding that when you approach the n plus 1th problem that's
different from the ones that you've looked at previously that you're starting from scratch,
or are there some principles that give you a foothold when trying to apply this method to the
new area? And if so, what are those principles? The principles, I mean, the details, of course,
have to be looked at from scratch, but the principles that we bring to the table are
ideas of geometry and, you know, this idea that look, whatever it is that you're observing,
whatever is the raw space, that is not the space on which you want your analysis to occur. You want
the analysis to occur in a space that is crumpled. And the generalizable knowledge that we bring to
the table is how do we represent these crumpled spaces? And that's the mathematics of humanian
geometry, entropology, group theory. Those are all the new mathematics. It's not new mathematics at
all. It's mathematics of the past two centuries, but in the realm of machine learning, that mathematics
has not made its way in a systematic way. So that's the generalizable knowledge. We bring in group
theory, geometry, differential geometry, topology. That's the way we think about it. But then the
specifics, the problem specifics have to be studied from scratch, but then that knowledge can often
be expressed in the constraints of geometry, entropology, and group theory. And that's where we
specialize. How do we take this domain specific knowledge and look at it through the lens of
groups and invariance? That's a different kind of generalizable knowledge. It's really a way of
thinking about phenomena rather than thinking about data. And going back to your keynote,
are there, do you kind of take a step back and kind of apply this broadly to computer vision,
machine learning? Do you kind of offer any thoughts for where this is all going?
Not. Let's make some up.
So data constraints scenarios, that's where this is all going. Machine learning with unconstrained
amounts of training data is what the last 10 years were about. And we are finding that it's a nice
goal, but there are no guarantees to be ever had, even if you train it forever with as much amount
of data that you've got. If any mission critical deployment requires a guaranteed robustness of
some kind, there is nothing to be given other than, yeah, this is what my numbers are on some data
set. That's all you have. And now if I can just hit pause there, you throughout our conversation,
you've talked about constraints, you've talked about constraints on the network, and
then you've talked about constraints on loss functions, you've talked about constraints on
architectures and not changing architectures. And those have implications on compute constraints.
And you haven't really explicitly talked about constraints on data. How does that fit into
all this other stuff we've talked about? I mean, the way I think about it is if you don't have
access to additional data, you get more bang for your buck by adding these additional
constraints that we were talking about. If you have access to more data and you can collect as much
as you want, you always should. I mean, that's undeniable, but it's becoming more and more clear
that that's not where the future is headed. We are not able to keep training bigger and bigger,
you know, it's an unsustainable path. I mean, there is enough energy going in that direction
anyway, whether or not we like it or I like it, but it's not a sustainable path of progress.
It's smaller and smaller, you know, diminishing returns. I'm with increasing resources.
So that's clear on the margins, but is part of your work trying to get at, you know,
one shot, few shot types of problems or no? We are, I mean, that would be an extreme case.
Yes. I mean, we are thinking more along the lines of if I had to collect more data,
can I first pause before collecting any more data and robustify what I've got with domain
knowledge? That's the way I think about it. One shot and few shot, it's a whole different ball
game. I mean, it's like the wide west of, you know, machine learning and I wouldn't go that far yet,
but will it be applicable? I mean, sure, I don't see why not, but I wouldn't make big claims
of getting one shot performance, but it should definitely help. If not, you know, make it more
amenable to, you know, less training sets. Yeah. Okay. So I interrupted you were talking about
essentially that the data, you know, data collection is always going to be expensive and,
you know, thinking about the problem space, you know, can provide, provide these benefits.
Yeah. Yeah. I mean, unfortunately, human in the loop can't go away. I mean, there is
neural architecture search. Yes. I mean, again, will this succeed? They will succeed at developing
some representations that get a job done. And when you layer in questions of interpretation,
explanation, which everybody's talking about, I have a much simpler take on it, which is,
if you don't have robustness to even simple physical variables, how will you even explain it in
your hand? I mean, if your classification shifts simply because I rotate a picture and you're
asking me to explain it, I think you're asking the wrong question. If you're at least asking me,
can you be first be robust slash invariant to simple things? And then explain it to me,
that's a more well-posed question, but these are premature questions to ask. And some
colleagues of mine have gone so far to say, repeatability, if your machine learning technique is not
repeatable. And by that, things like this, yeah, if I click this picture at a slightly different
time of day, and I think it's really changed, it takes up the time of day, and the decision has
flipped. It's not, the process is not even repeatable. So don't even go to the extent of
explaining a non-repeatable process or trying to interpret a non-repeatable process. Those are all
questions that should come later. So if you think of repeatability, you do an experiment,
you get the same result over and over again. As far as the big things are controlled, machine learning
hasn't yet delivered that even. So we're trying to bring in that level of robustness, I call it
robustness slash invariance. Some people have called it repeatability, simple and repeatability
sounds shinier, and it sounds like the stakes are much higher, but I'm happy to just call it
invariance. Nice, nice. Well, Paven, thanks so much for taking the time to share what you're up to,
and provide us some context for your CVPR keynote. Very cool stuff. Thank you so much Sam. This has
been a pleasure and you've been great. Thank you so much.