Welcome to the Twimal AI Podcast.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
Hey, what is up, good Twimal people?
As many, if not most of us past the 100 day mark of shelter in place, work from home
and other quarantine measures, I want to both extend to you my best wishes for your health
and happiness and also to remind you to not let your guard down.
COVID-19 is serious business and you don't want to get it or give it.
Be sure to wear that mask when you'll be around other people, avoid indoor crowds and
limit your exposure by minimizing the time and maximizing the distance when you're
in contact with others.
Before we jump into today's show from our CVPR series, I'd like to share a few quick details
about the next great event in our continuing live discussion series.
Join us on Wednesday, July 1st for the great machine learning language undubate as we explore
the strengths, weaknesses and approaches of both popular and emerging programming languages
for machine learning.
We'll have great speakers representing Python, R, Swift, Closure, Scala, Julia and more.
The session kicks off at 11 a.m. Pacific time on the first and you won't want to miss
it, so head over to twimalai.com slash languages to get registered.
At this point, I'd like to send a huge thank you to our friends at Qualcomm for their support
of this podcast and their sponsorship of our CVPR series.
Qualcomm AI research is dedicated to advancing AI to make its core capabilities, perception,
reasoning and action ubiquitous across devices.
Their work makes it possible for billions of users around the world to have AI enhanced
experiences on Qualcomm technology's powered devices.
To learn more about Qualcomm and what they're up to on the AI research front, visit twimalai.com
slash Qualcomm.
And now onto the show.
All right, everyone.
I am here with Pavan Taraga.
Pavan is jointly appointed in the schools of electrical engineering and arts media and
engineering at Arizona State University.
Pavan, welcome to the Twimal AI podcast.
Thank you, Sam.
It's a pleasure and an honor to be here.
Thank you.
It's my pleasure to host you here.
I'm looking forward to digging into your paper that will be presented at CVPR, revisiting
invariance with geometry and deep learning.
But before we do that, I'd love for you to share a little bit about your background and
how you came to work in computer vision and ML sounds great.
So my beginnings in this area started as, you know, as a senior in my undergraduate years.
I was looking at problems like face recognition, face tracking from video, trying to do a senior
design project really.
And as I started digging more, this was in the early or, yeah, early 2000s.
And it was a very exciting time to be in the field of computer vision, because the problem
statement in those days would be presented as giving a computer the ability to see and
that felt like, wow, that's a frontier topic, right?
But I said, you know, looks like I'm sufficiently invested in this, looks like it intersects with
things like neuroscience, perception that is interesting mathematics, that is interesting
computing happening, very highly interdisciplinary.
And it felt like there was much work to be done.
So I decided to go to school in 2000, I mean, grad school in 2004 to the University of
Maryland, studying with Professor Ramachalappa, who is a pioneer in this field and very well
known for face recognition techniques and a lot of interesting things in vision at the
time.
And as I started my work in the lab, I brought in from just face recognition to other things
like understanding video, understanding time series, understanding the role of light,
you know, geometry, elimination, reflectance, all these physics based concepts and how
the interface with pattern recognition methods or machine learning methods and as I went deeper
and deeper into it, I felt like there was a big disconnect between the methods of physics
of image formation and the methods that are used in machine learning, where it's just
purely a driven and statistical techniques and I was trying to find some middle ground
where I could inject physical knowledge into certain structures that could blend well
with machine learning techniques and one thing led to another, I started getting interested
in this area of mathematics called a Romanian geometry and then topology as a means to express
these intuitions and these constraints from physics and interface them with machine learning
in before deep learning.
So that's the theme of my work over the past decade, which is try to understand basic phenomena
whether it's, you know, images or video or human activity and in recent years, we've also
brought in our investigation beyond computer vision to include things like wearable devices
and physiological monitoring where the phenomenon under study is basic human movement and other
things, try to understand it from first principles and try to express that knowledge in a way
that constrains conditions machine learning, so that's the general intersection of topics
I've been looking at.
Okay, and I mentioned in introducing you that one of your appointments is with a school
that has arts in the title, are you, you know, how does that come up in your work and
research?
So, particularly, you know, connected to that particular piece of that school.
So that's a whole story by itself and I can go very organically about how it all began
or I can go in hindsight, this is how it went organically, this is how it began, you
know, our school was founded in 2009 and, you know, I graduated from grad school in 2009,
but then that was 2009, very similar to 2020, Wall Street collapsing and getting loose.
So I stayed back when I posed out for a couple years and when I went interviewing in 2011,
this position opened up in this school under the title of Assistant Professor in Human
Activity Analysis, it was very intriguing and I have been doing human activity analysis
as far as, you know, understanding video-based gate analysis.
Okay, so I'm like fitness trackers and quantified self and all that kind of stuff.
Right, so this was a little before all that stuff happened in particular.
And I came in and I visited and there was, there was a mind-boggling sense of interdisciplinary
that I saw in the school people in music looking at stuff like that, right, accelerometers,
variables, driving, interactive performance with it.
There was a group doing a stroke rehabilitation where you attract human movement through
motion capture and sonify the qualities of your movement.
So smoothness or jerkiness would be converted to sound and you can hear yourself and that
provided additional feedback for you to correct your movements.
Oh wow.
It was, yeah, it was a very mind-boggling experience and even now people find it very
interviewing when I mentioned these things.
So the human activity analysis component was a way for the school to address, you know,
slightly more formal ways to think about human movement, whether it's sense from a camera,
whether it's sense from a variable device, whether it's motion capture, try to come up
with techniques to represent human movement and then do machine learning on it or feed
into these other applications.
And it seemed like I was the right fit at the time and I got a job and I've been here
for eight years and it has led me into very interesting collaborations with media artists
and health scientists who are interested in the intersection of computing, art and things
like health promotion.
So that's the other side.
You mentioned that one of the big themes of your work is been integrating physical, physics
space principles and computer vision.
Can you maybe talk a little bit about that in the broader context of the computer vision
landscape?
We've talked about this quite a bit on the podcast and I kind of describe it as a pendulum
that's kind of swung from physics-based models to statistical and kind of is settling
somewhere in the middle now.
But it sounds like you've been working at this for a while, I'm curious how you think
of it.
Yes.
I mean, you're absolutely right.
It's been a pendulum that keeps swinging and I don't think it settles anywhere.
I mean, that's the interesting problem about computer vision.
Every time someone thinks it settles, right?
Everybody thinks it's settled now and then soon it ships.
So I mean, yes, it's been going on and off this idea about, I mean, I'd like to think
of it as model-based vision versus purely data-driven methods of thinking of vision.
The way the pendulum swings in my opinion is not that the problems are changing.
It's just the language that goes into talking about it and the tools that go into addressing
it.
Those keep shifting, but the problems have remained mostly the same and the problems
are the following in my opinion.
So vision is a very unique, some people think of it as an application of machine learning,
which is a reductionistic way to think about it.
Sure, everything is data and everything is fed into a model and outcomes of decision.
But vision and any perceptual field of inquiry, that can include vision, sound, haptics,
any of these things which have to do with perception, I feel are fundamentally different
than any other application of data analysis.
The way we perceive the world is not the way, let's say, back transactions are processed
by a machine learning computer, machine learning technique.
There is a huge amount of variability is the way I'd call it, that exhibits in the
natural world, which is somehow either discarded or properly passed out by whatever is happening
in our brains and the sources of variability are physics based to a large extent.
The same picture under a different lighting condition looks different, the same picture
under a different slightly changed viewpoint looks different.
So that looking different part is what gives rise to statistical variability.
The statistical ways of thinking are, well, let's just fill up the observation space
with more data points and we'll figure out what the shape of the distribution is from
data, which is okay in, as intense to infinity, I guess that's fine, but when data augmentation
approaches and domain adaptation and that kind of thing, yeah, yeah.
But under and not tend to infinity, if you only have a few data samples, you are better
off trying to understand how the physics around you affects the observed imagery.
And that's where I think the methods have shifted.
So in the keynote that I have at CBPR, you know, at the workshop called differential geometry
and computer vision, I go through some of these historical trends.
And one of the core themes that brings it all together, the word that I use is called
invariance, which is when you look around and try to classify objects, we are able to
do this in a way that is invariant to a lot of nuisance variables.
That is light, you know, shading viewpoint and all sorts of interesting effects that are
hard to describe.
When you say invariance, there's two ways to think about it.
The physics-based ways to think about it are, let's say I am looking at this scene, I
know everything about this scene, including its 3D geometry, including how the paint reflects
off light, including the wavelengths in the incoming radiation.
If I have full knowledge of all of this, then I can re-render a scene, let's say.
I can, just like how it happens in graphics, I can create so many different versions of
the same picture.
If I had full knowledge of everything, simply through a forward rendering process and
construct variability, the data-driven ways of thinking about it say if you don't have
access to everything that you need to understand the phenomena, what is the minimal set, what
is the minimal piece of information that is needed to get a job done.
And that's the dichotomy in the physics-based ways of thinking and the statistical ways
of thinking.
So when you use this term, invariant is the invariant referring to, say we're talking
about a scene with an object in it that might render differently in different lighting
conditions, etc.
Is the invariant that object that is definitively in the scene and then we've got all these
other effects, or does the invariant refer to something else, maybe something more on
the mathematical from a mathematical perspective?
I mean, the word invariant, of course, will depend upon what the end task is.
If it is object recognition, yes, something intrinsic to the object is the invariant.
It is not always as simple as saying the invariant is the color of the object because that changes.
It is often not same as saying the invariant is the edge map of the object or certain corners
of the object because they go in and out of view.
So there's not easy ways of describing what that invariant actually physically means.
So it becomes mathematical at some level.
There is no linguistic equivalent that I can come up with.
But if you look at this rendering ways of thinking, if you can render this object that you
are interested to recognize, in all possible wing conditions, all possible lighting conditions,
and you have this huge set of pictures, that huge set of pictures could be called, you
know, the word sometimes that gets used is equivalent class or sometimes they call it an
orbit.
So this object that you're trying to recognize manifests itself in all this different ways.
If you have a handle on that set, you are in good shape.
If you have a different object, and you place it in the same scene, and you render it in
all these different variations, and you have its own different set, then the invariant
that separates these two is some measure of difference between these two sets of pictures.
And sometimes that set of pictures can have a nice structure, which can allow you to
compute it in closed form, and sometimes not.
So the way we have been trying to express, you know, sometimes illumination is complicated.
And if in the most general case, we don't know how to describe this full set of pictures.
And some simplifying assumptions, which is rooted in some old work from the 90s, Bell
Humor and Krigman wrote a very famous paper, and they said, what is the set of all faces
under any given illumination condition?
And they made some simplifying assumptions of what a face is.
I mean, if I ask you define a face, it's probably defined a face, right?
So how do you even think?
And this is why we've tended towards, you know, deep learning and statistic methods over
the past few years, because we don't know how to define these things.
So exactly.
But here is what they found.
They said, if you define it in some sub linguistic ways, let's say it's a convex object, and
let's say it's an object which has reflectance defined by some lambershine properties, then
you can actually write down what the set looks like.
Now comes deep learning.
It says, I can't define these things, give me data.
And the more data you have, the better it is.
But no one knows how much data is enough, right?
I mean, the more is better is the answer, but how much is enough is never known.
And we have been positioning ourselves at that intersection, where we still look.
If I know that I'm looking at faces, I'm going to weaken the structure a little bit.
I'm going to say that, yeah, these objects that we're looking at have some characterization
under these assumptions of simplicity, but then comes deep learning, which allows me
to fit those other degrees, which I'm not able to specify analytically.
So we're trying to reduce the need for larger and larger training sets by restricting the
deep net layer somehow that are motivated by the knowledge of that physics of image
formation.
Sure, we don't know how much data we need to get the full specification, but we're saying
this will reduce the need for more and more data.
And all things being the same with the same amount of training sets, the same complexity
of the deep architecture, adding these constraints known from the physics of image formation
improves performance.
And it also stabilizes performance against degradation of inputs.
You know, typically if you blur a picture, if you surrender a picture in slightly different
ways, performance drops pretty dramatically, we are able to avoid that.
It's a middle ground, I'd say.
We are not being super specific about defining objects, nor are we saying more data is good.
We are saying something in the middle that is we are trying to come up with some description
of that equivalence class under simplifying assumptions and then let data fill in the
rest.
So that's the way we're trying to marry the two things.
And is the result a mathematical analysis in closed form, or is it experimental results
on data sets?
It both.
Okay.
So, I mean, most of the things we do is we end up having constraints, which are closed
for mathematical equations.
Maybe one layer in the deep net is expected to be orthonormal because the physics of image
formation says that certain variables under certain lighting conditions will have an
orthonormal structure.
Okay, that's the way we impose the constraint that certain layers might have an orthonormal
constraint put in.
But then the network itself has to be learned end to end with data sets.
And the performance has to be validated empirically on data sets.
One of the interesting things we found is this concept of orthonormality, which seems
to have some very special power.
What we're finding is whether, you know, think of it.
So we played with this idea in a paper for BMVC last year, where we took some classic,
you know, disentangling autoencoder kind of networks.
And we had good reason to impose an orthonormality constraint on the latent blocks of these disentangling
autoencoders.
Why orthonormality?
We had to write up a whole, you know, theory around we expect these factors to represent
either movement or lighting conditions or deformations and under appropriate relaxations.
They all become orthogonal to each other and they all have this spherical structures.
So looking at all of this, it looks like orthonormality is a trade-off, which is coming close
to what the physics is telling us to do and but also being sensitive to the idea that
it has to be implemented easily.
We don't want to over complicate things and we want our constraints to be differentiable.
So it's a design process.
So we threw in these orthonormality constraints on disentangling autoencoders and boom, the
numbers of disentangling quality just went up quite significantly.
And so in the case of an autoencoder or in the layer of a deep network, what does it
mean to impose that kind of constraint?
Is it architectural and does it mean that you're diverging from kind of your CNN, resonant
kind of tried-and-true architectures or is it loss function based or something totally
different?
How do you impose those constraints?
There's two or three ways in which it's happened.
One is we stick with architectures as is, don't mess with architectures, but add-and-loss
functions.
That works when the constraints are actually expressable as a closed form equation like
spherical losses or, you know, orthonormality, those can be written on as a closed form equation.
Sometimes the constraints we arrive at do not have an equation, but they have what is
called a manifold structure.
And why manifolds arise is very closely related to invariance.
Here is an example, you know, if I say, so the idea of invariance is this, right, I mean
you have a feature space.
Let's say the feature space is something.
You have this feature space in Rn and it's more specific than something, so it's easier
to follow.
So, let's say it's the latent space of AlexNet, okay, some features from the latent
space of AlexNet, which is embedded in Rn, right, so it's a vector in Rn.
And then we come in and we say, look, I want to impose a slight equivalence here, which
is if I rotate my picture, looks like the features are also changing somehow.
I mean, the features are not always invariant to physical variables like this, right?
But if you're able to say that this feature, this feature, this feature in Rn actually
represent the same picture, just that they're rotated.
We are trying to basically paste the features and thereby the underlying space into something
else to express that concept of equivalence.
And sometimes when that ways of expressing these equivalences is well defined, what happens
is the space gets crumpled, you hope that the neural net learns to crumple the space
all of its own.
That is one of the overarching hopes in deep learning that as you go through the layers
of deep learning, the deep learning is learning to squish and crumple the original feature space
into interesting ways to get a job done.
But what it's doing is it's not always getting the job done the right way because you never
have enough data.
But if I explicitly tell it that here is how rotation affects the features.
And here is how you paste them together through whatever mathematics that's needed.
Then we get some manifold structures, you know, this crumpling can sometimes be expressed
as a manifold.
If you want to say in the concept of, you know, in the paradigm of loss functions, how
do you express a manifold as a loss function?
Sometimes you cannot.
What you can do instead is, you know, manifolds are basically crumpled spaces and they have
ideas associated with them, which are analogous to how we think of maps.
And you know, the earth itself is composed of the earth is a manifold, but then it's also
a sphere approximately.
So if you forget the idea that it's a sphere, but if it were a general weirdly shaped blob,
you would represent it by a series of charts and you would explain how the charts connect.
And that's the way you specify a manifold through things called charts.
And charts are also sometimes, you know, they have a thing, which is similar, called tangent
spaces.
So you sort of flatten the manifold in local coordinate charts and you can express that
tangent space as a vector space.
So once in a while, we have run into these conditions where we have a constraint, which was
expressed as a manifold, which could not be written down as an equation, but whose tangent
space could be written down.
So we were able to enforce conditions of that tangency and said, I want this layer in
my deep net to represent coordinates of a manifold on a specific tangent space.
And the mapping from that back to the manifold could be written down in closed form.
So it depends.
Let me see if I can upload this anywhere close to what you just said.
The way I'm kind of hearing this is that you've got some problem, you know, say you've
got some object and you apply some simple transformation to that object, maybe you rotate
it.
If you've got a deep neural network that is trying to detect that object, for example,
you know, and you've trained it, there may be some feature space or some representation
of that object in, you know, the different layers of the neural net in a oversimplified
world.
You'd kind of want there to be, you know, a relationship between the rotation of the
object itself and the rotation of the features, like maybe you could apply some simple transformation
of the features, but the world isn't, you know, networks aren't that simple.
But it turns out there is a relationship between the features.
It's just more like this crumbly manifold thing.
And you found a way to, you know, express that using the mathematical language of these
manifolds that allow you to detect the actual invariance of the object.
That is very correct.
Thank you for giving me those lines.
The only disclaimer is we have been able to do this for a few common sources of physical
variability.
And that includes things like rotations of objects and deformations of moving parts in
certain cases, lighting conditions under, you know, just to be very clear.
We haven't been able to do this across the board for every possible thing.
Right.
So simple, like, you know, maybe not three point studio lighting, but a simple, you know,
radio rotation or something like that.
But, you know, clearly there's lots of things you can do in the physical world that aren't
amenable to that representation.
Absolutely.
Yes.
Okay.
And so one of the things that that comes to mind in thinking about this and in your work,
you kind of fall back on or maybe ground yourself in, you know, what you call pragmatic
choices of deep architectures, meaning kind of the popular stuff, the way we're doing
things today.
I think of like Jeff Hinton's capsule networks is trying to come at some of the same ideas
or same problems, are you familiar with that work and you compare contrast?
I mean, we've tracked that body of work also.
Again, you know, he's with all due respect, ACM Turing about, you know, I can't do that
easily, but it's an over complication.
I mean, it's ignoring, it's ignoring so much, it's ignoring the basic laws of, you know,
rotations are not that hard if you understand how to express rotations and we're taking
out that invariances is doable without that level of combination.
So I'm correct that you're trying to come at some of the same problems at least.
Right.
Okay.
In, it may be the case that if that enterprise succeeds, if that capsule network enterprise
succeeds, it may be a more general solution to everything, maybe, but if you want
to be a bit specific about, you know, understood factors of variation, I feel that's an over complication
and there are nicer ways to do that and I think we're able to do that in a better way.
Yeah.
So you've kind of, you've developed this approach and you mentioned that you've got some experimental
results as well.
Can you talk a little bit about how you frame the question experimentally and what you've
seen?
Sure.
I mean, the way we frame it is we want to keep a few things fixed.
And the way we keep a few things fixed is we say pick an architecture first and that
can be allocated.
It can be, you know, we're looking at things like dense net, point net, all those year
architectures, which are known to work well for certain databases, keep the architecture
more or less fixed, keep the training set more or less fixed.
And the only thing that varies is, you know, don't play too much with new fancier data
augmentation methods.
The only thing we are doing is adding in constraints either in some latent variables or we're adding
in certain augmented loss functions.
So most of the additional thing that we're doing is a mathematical expression of some kind.
And keeping in, otherwise there is, it's hard to compare.
I mean, if you say, let me train it for more iterations, but not add a constraint, can
you compare it?
So keeping mostly the computational resources fixed, we're asking if this additional mathematical
knowledge pushes on the low.
And we've been finding that it does.
We have done that for image classification, we've done that for, you know, disentangling
networks, we've done that for time series problems recently.
And some of our compelling results are indeed from time series modeling, where, you know,
we applied this to human activity like ignition data sets with either stick figures or variable
devices.
And the kind of factor that we are trying to factor out in human movement is not light
and shape and geometry, but it's time series variability issues, which is, you know, the
same action when performed by the same person, but at a slightly different time will give
rise to slightly different traces, because people have intrinsic variability and how
they move.
And oftentimes that variability gets expressed through some time warping kinds of relationships.
What we've done is express the time warping property as a constraint, which can be forced
by the network to be factored out in a latent variable, if we just throw in that constraint
in the loss function.
And we found that it improves numbers significantly, just like that without any additional training,
without any additional, you know, data requirements.
So the pictures, or what I think are the pictures of this, if I'm understanding the problem
is along the lines of, you know, start from your seat in the living room, go to the refrigerator,
grab a drink, you know, take off the cover and drop the cover in the trash can, and you've
got this kind of two dimensional plot of the path that the person might take in doing
all that.
And your argument is that the path is an invariant, because the task is the same.
It's, you know, do X and Y, and what you're trying to do is identify, well, what is the
fundamental?
So you said identifying the path, is it somehow in a data set with lots of these, you
know, traces or paths identify which ones correspond to the same actions or.
It's close, I mean, we haven't looked at paths in that way, but we've looked at traces
of stick figures, you know, so you have like 50 joints being tracked and you have the full
time series of 50 joints evolving in space and in three dimensions that comes from motion
capture say.
Okay.
Yes, there are actions, not really unlike what you're saying, actions in a kitchen, actions
in a room, actions in an office, picking up objects, placing them here and there.
And the feature that is invariant, of course, is hard to linguistically describe, but one
of the variables that gives rise to confusion is that people sometimes take longer to do
the same thing.
People sometimes are fast in certain phases of the movement, slow in certain phases of
the movement.
Right.
Or there is asymmetry in the body, you know, the left, the left arm swings more than the
right arm.
You know, there's all these interesting sources of variability which are hard to and the
only way deep learning will be robust to that is if you augmented with all these variables,
all these sources of variation.
The way we think of it is that the variability here is expressible as a warping of the
time axis, whether it's short versus long or speeding up versus slowing down.
Or if it's one side faster than the other side or the swings are smaller than the other,
it's all a time warp.
Sometimes it can be constant, sometimes it can be non-constant and it can be.
So that brings up an interesting question.
Do you assume in your work throughout a single source of invariance or do you also conceive
of multiple sources of invariance?
Like, you know, there's a time invariance, but there's also the left arm swing invariance
factor.
Yeah.
I mean, that is the, I mean, we are headed in that direction.
I mean, right now our investigations have been-
That would be the answer.
The goal is to be able to have almost like a linear combination of known invariance
is that, you know, you can account for, but-
Right.
I mean, at this time we have been playing it very carefully that let's take this one source
of variable.
Let's see if that can be factored out.
Let's see if we can get invaders to that.
And we have had success in many different applications.
It sounds like you're further saying though that in the case of at least this motion capture
type of a data set that the- that maybe time becomes kind of a meta-invariance that can
account for multiple physical characteristics, am I hearing that correctly in there?
It can.
It's- it's hard to write that out clearly, but it does.
Like for instance, if you had like load bearing, you know, if you were carrying a heavy
bag on your bag, it- it will have an interest
ing effect on the time series of your joins, which is not that easy to explain, but it
will sort of stretch out certain phases of your movement and shrink certain phases of
your movement.
It does.
So, yeah, the stretchings and shrinkings of the time axis are the key to finding what that
invariant is for the lack.
And so are there well established benchmark data sets for these types of tasks?
Are you rolling your own to explore these methods?
You know, for motion capture, there are benchmark data sets.
There are, you know, Microsoft has a- it used to have a RGBD data set.
I mean, they go by the RGBD activity, sort of, you know, keywords.
And there's a few out there.
There's a few benchmark data sets out there.
NTU has one, MSR is one.
And sometimes even, you know, the video data sets like HMDB have stick figures available
through other methods like PostNet, for instance.
So yeah, there are well-established data sets that we experiment with.
And is the task that's posed by these data sets one of predicting the action that the-
Right.
Okay.
It's activity classification prediction by and large, right?
Yeah.
Okay.
And so what's the kind of state of the art for that kind of activity detection and how
does your method compare to it?
So most of the time series in the deep learning world, most time series things are either a combination
of 1D CNNs or, you know, LSTM models.
So depending upon the data set, the way our process goes is we say, let's find the latest,
you know, benchmarks and we'll improve on those through these mathematical techniques.
So a recent paper we did in CVPR 2019 used LSTMs as the benchmark data, you know, the technique.
And the data sets were NTU 3D data set and a few others like that motion capture.
The tunable parameter in LSTMs is oftentimes the hidden layers, how many hidden units do
you have?
And of course, if you scroll through it, the numbers keep going better and better.
The way we've done it is we kept things the same.
We say, let's say it's 16 hidden units or 32 hidden units, keep that the same.
The only thing we'll change is add in this additional module that either disentangles the
time work function or adds in as a constraint and numbers always go out.
So in the way we thought about it, if my number, if my memory is right, the NTU RGB data set
had like, you know, 80% roughly accuracy with a very fancy LSTM with 200 hidden units
and stuff like that.
And we were able to improve it by four or five percentage points easy without any changes
to anything, but just this additional constraint added in.
So if you find you need more, sure, there's more things to be squeezed out, but we were
able to consistently improve the performance of LSTMs by easy five percentage points
and times six, eight percentage points with no change, but a simple constraint on time
warping.
Yeah, so those are the kinds of results we've been finding, which is if you rethink what
the constraints should be through understanding the phenomena first, the payoffs are actually
quite significant without any additional requirements on data or network, architecture,
complexity or training strategies, they can all be very basic.
And so now we've talked about a couple of, you know, very different types of problems
one, kind of a, you know, computer, a very visual type of task in one of this more time
series to apply this to different settings, how much hand crafting needs to go into the
loss functions and the, you know, the different constraints that you're applying to the network.
That is where the big work is.
So I think the pendulum is swinging to that level of hand crafting, you know, moving away
from features to architectures and loss functions, right, that's where the pendulum is.
And the amount of work that goes into hand crafting is a lot of, I would say, studying
basically, understanding how these variables actually affect the observed data and try
to express it in a way that is emanabled to fusion with the deep net.
The beauty is physics is not one way, you know, light is, there is no single model for
expressing how light and surfaces interact, there's layers and layers and layers to it.
And you have to know all of that or at least as much as you know, as much as you can learn.
And then the hand crafting is where in this spectrum of sophistication do I stop in a way
that I actually have a pragmatic effect on performance without changing anything else.
And that's where a lot of intuition is, you know, you cannot get away from this intuitive
exercise.
Despite all the progress of machine learning and deep learning, the networks are arguably
both intuitive and highly unintuitive.
I mean, some people have an insight about why a network works, but present it to someone
else, it's mysterious.
And the same thing is true of the last functions business.
Sometimes we can motivate it very easily through simple things like, well, yeah, cross entropy
means where it makes sense.
Physics is where some of the unintuitive stuff lies.
It's, that's where a lot of design thinking exists and we are doing that.
So yes, that's where much of the work is understanding that when you approach the N plus 1th problem
that's different from the ones that you've looked at previously that you're starting
from scratch, or are there some principles that give you a foothold when trying to apply
this method to the new area?
And if so, what are those principles?
The details, of course, have to be looked at from scratch, but the principles that we've
bring to the table are ideas of geometry and, you know, this idea that look, whatever it
is that you're observing, whatever it is, the raw space, that is not the space on which
you want your analysis to occur.
You want the analysis to occur in a space that is crumpled.
And the generalizable knowledge that we bring to the table is how do we represent these
crumpled spaces?
And that's the mathematics of humanian geometry and topology, group theory.
Those are all the new mathematics.
It's not new mathematics at all.
It's mathematics of the past two centuries, but in the realm of machine learning, that
mathematics has not made its way in a systematic way.
So that's the generalizable knowledge.
We bring in group theory, geometry, differential geometry, topology.
That's the way we think about it.
But then the specifics, the problem specifics have to be studied from scratch, but then
that knowledge can often be expressed in the constraints of geometry, anthropology, and
group theory.
And that's where we specialize.
How do we take this domain specific knowledge and look at it through the lens of groups and
invariance?
And that's a different kind of generalizable knowledge.
It's really a way of thinking about phenomena rather than thinking about data.
Going back to your keynote, you kind of take a step back and apply this broadly to computer
vision, machine learning, and do you kind of offer any thoughts for where this is all
going?
Not.
Let's make some up.
This is all going, pop in.
So data constraints and scenarios, that's where this is all going.
Machine learning with unconstrained amounts of training data is what the last 10 years
were about.
And we're finding that it's a nice goal, but there are no guarantees to be ever had, even
if you train it forever with as much amount of data that you've got.
If any mission critical deployment requires a guaranteed robustness of some kind, there
is nothing to be given other than, yeah, this is what my numbers are on some data set.
That's all you have.
And now, if I can just hit pause there, you throughout our conversation, you've talked
about constraints, you've talked about constraints on the network and you've talked about constraints
on loss functions, you've talked about constraints on, you know, architectures and not changing
architectures.
And, you know, those have implications on compute constraints and that you haven't really
explicitly talked about constraints on data.
How does that fit into all these other stuff we've talked about?
So I mean, the way I think about it is, if you don't have access to additional data,
you get more bang for your buck by adding these additional constraints that we were talking
about.
If you have access to more data and you can collect as much as you want, you always should,
I mean, that's, I didn't know about, but it's becoming more and more clear that that's
not where the future is headed.
We are not able to keep training bigger and bigger, you know, it's an unsustainable path.
I mean, there is enough energy going in that direction anyway, whether or not we like
it or I like it.
But it's not a sustainable path of progress.
It's smaller and smaller, you know, diminishing returns, but I have an increasing resources.
So that's clear on the margins, but is part of your work trying to get at one shot, few
shot types of problems or no?
We are, I mean, that would be an extreme case.
But yes, I mean, we are thinking more along the lines of, if I had to collect more data,
can I first pause before collecting any more data and robustify what I've got with domain
knowledge?
That's the way I think about it.
One shot and few shot, it's a whole different ball game.
I mean, it's like the wide west of, you know, machine learning and I wouldn't go that
far yet.
Will it be applicable? I mean, sure, I don't see why not, but I wouldn't make big claims
of getting one shot performance, but it should definitely help if not, you know, make it
more amenable to, you know, less training sets.
Yeah.
Okay.
So I interrupt that you were talking about essentially that the data collection is always
going to be expensive and, you know, thinking about the problem space can provide, provide
these benefits.
I mean, unfortunately, human in the loop can't go away.
I mean, there is neural architecture search.
Yes, I mean, again, will this succeed?
They will succeed at developing some representations that get a job done.
And when you layer in questions of interpretation, explanation, which everybody is talking about,
I have a much simpler take on it, which is if you don't have robustness to even simple
physical variables, how will you even explain it?
I mean, if your classification shifts simply because I rotate a picture and you're asking
me to explain it, I think you're asking the wrong question.
If you're at least asking me, can you be first be robust slash invariant to simple things
and then explain it to me, that's a more well-posed question, but these are premature questions
to ask.
And some colleagues of mine have gone so far to say repeatability if your machine learning
technique is not repeatable.
And by that, things like this, yeah, if I click this picture at a slightly different time
of day, nothing's really changed except the time of day and the decision has flipped, the
process is not even repeatable.
So don't even go to the extent of explaining a non-repeatable process or trying to interpret
a non-repeatable process.
Those are all questions that should come later.
So if you think of repeatability, you do an experiment, you get the same result over
and over again, as far as the big things are controlled, machine learning hasn't yet
delivered that even.
So we're trying to bring in that level of robustness, I call it robustness slash invariance.
Some people have called it repeatability, simple and repeatability sounds shinier and
it sounds like the stakes are much higher, but I'm happy to just call it invariance.
Well, Paven, thanks so much for taking the time to share what you're up to and provide
us some context for your CVPR keynote, very cool stuff.
Thank you so much Sam, this has been a pleasure and you've been great, thank you so much.
All right, everyone, that's our show for today.
For more information on today's show, visit twomolai.com slash shows.
As always, thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.