Welcome to the Twimal AI Podcast.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
Hey, what is up, good Twimal people?
Before we jump into today's show from our CVPR series, I'd like to share a few quick
details about the next great event in our continuing live discussion series.
Join us on Wednesday, July 1st for the great machine learning language on debate as we
explore the strengths, weaknesses and approaches of both popular and emerging programming languages
for machine learning.
People have great speakers representing Python, R, Swift, Closure, Scala, Julia and more.
The session kicks off at 11 a.m. Pacific time on the first and you won't want to miss
it, so head over to twimalai.com slash languages to get registered.
At this point, I'd like to send a huge thank you to our friends at Qualcomm for their
support of this podcast and their sponsorship of our CVPR series.
Qualcomm AI research is dedicated to advancing AI to make its core capabilities, perception,
reasoning and action ubiquitous across devices.
Their work makes it possible for billions of users around the world to have AI enhanced
experiences on Qualcomm technology's powered devices.
To learn more about Qualcomm and what they're up to on the AI research front, visit twimalai.com
slash Qualcomm.
Now on to the show.
All right, everyone.
I am here with HEMA Lockaraju.
HEMA is an assistant professor at Harvard University with joint appointments in both the
business school and the Department of Computer Science.
HEMA, welcome to the Twimal AI podcast.
Thank you so much, Sam.
I'm super excited to be here.
Same here.
I'm really looking forward to our conversation.
We will start where we typically do on the show and have you share a little bit about
your background and how you came to work in machine learning in particular, your focus
on fair and interpretable ML and the implications and kind of mission critical high stakes domains
like criminal justice, healthcare and public policy.
How did you get started in all this?
So, that's actually an interesting story.
Let me try and kind of summarize it in a hopefully few sentences so that we are not hogging
all the time here.
So yeah, I was actually working in machine learning, right?
So basically I come from India, I moved to the United States for my PhD in 2012.
I have been working in machine learning since I was a student in India.
I was publishing actively in machine learning, but my interest in sort of the applications
of machine learning to some of these domains, like criminal justice or healthcare, that
sort of started or it became a prominent threat in my research when I started my PhD.
And this was, I guess, mostly due to a collaboration now between my advisor and another professor,
and I have a couple of professors and economics who were dealing with behavioral economics,
and they sort of introduced us to all these fascinating problems.
As I was sort of, I think, by then I had already explored machine learning to a reasonable
extent, and I was looking for applications which were more than just like ad recommendations
or, you know, friendship recommendations and so on so that I could keep myself going
in the field and also anchor on to something which is more applied in the sense of, like,
real world settings and so on.
So I guess my PhD was like one of the, you know, main times in my life where I got into
both machine learning as well as its applications to some of these domains which are super fascinating
and the broad field of fairness and interpretability enabled, yeah.
You know, I suspect when we dig into your upcoming, well, actually your recent talk at CVPR
where you were an invited speaker in the fair data efficient and trusted computer vision
workshop, we will learn about a bit of your research, but kind of broadly, how do you frame
out the kinds of questions that you're looking to answer with your work?
All right.
I guess in a broad sense the way I think about my research is it's about enabling machine
learning to help with decision making in high stakes settings, right, and that involves
some sub questions like how can we make sure that machine learning models which are of course
getting more and more complex day by day are, you know, more palatable form to these decision
makers who are not necessarily experts in machine learning.
So how do we sort of explain these models, what are the algorithms that we can use which
can in turn explain these models to people who are not machine learning experts.
So that's of course one of the key questions and also other core question behind interpretable
ML, right, and beyond that when we develop some of these tools which will assist these
decision makers in important decisions, how do we ensure that the tools or the algorithms
that we are developing are by default fair otherwise they can induce their own discriminatory
biases and undesirable biases into the entire real world decision making.
So that's of course another question and more broadly also just trying to develop models
and methods to understand what kinds of biases exist as of now in human decision making
like even if there was no algorithm involved in the picture as well as how to diagnose
biases if someone gives me an algorithm, what is the best way to do that.
So these are roughly the broad questions I think about.
And so your talk is titled Understanding the Limits of Explainability in ML Assisted
Decision Making and there's some interesting tidbits that I'm looking forward to digging
into around like some of the explainability algorithms like Lyme and Shap, but before we
even do that, thinking about the topic of your talk and the workshop makes me think of
a podcast that I did with Cynthia Rudin last year and her perspective seems to come from
a different direction which is we shouldn't even be using black box models for the kinds
of problems that you're studying.
We should be using models that are kind of more fundamentally understandable and in many
conversations I've had in this topic, there's this tension between explainability and
interpretability.
So I'm curious kind of out of the gate, what's your take on all that?
Oh, I think we're already starting with a very interesting and controversial topic.
Yeah, I mean, Cynthia has been a mentor and a collaborator for several years but we somehow
managed to coexist with this dichotomy.
So yeah, I mean, so I agree with this point or rather might take on this would be that
if at all it is possible for you to develop a model that is interpretable by default
and is also accurate and you have the data to build such a model by all means you should
go for it, right?
So because there are no barriers here, but unfortunately the real world is always not
like that.
So in some cases you may not have enough training data for example to build a disease
diagnosis model, right?
So you might be then using another proprietary model that some other company has built and
in that case you would still want to do some diagnostic checks to ensure that the model
is you're doing what it's supposed to do and it's put the way it's making predictions
is reasonable and so on.
So those are the kinds of cases where explaining a given model or a black box model as we are
calling it, you know, is probably the only option, right?
So because you don't have the ability to sort of build such a model because of lack of
data or resources and empty number of other reasons, but you have the capability to buy
or get this model from a third party, but you still want to wet it or understand what's
roughly going on with the tiny bit of data that you have or like just doing some diagnostic
checks with whatever little amount of data that you have which may not be enough to develop
and accurate model, but at the same time might be, you know, decent enough to sort of wet
a given model.
So if that is the context you're dealing with, then essentially explaining or understanding
what the black box might be doing is probably the only option.
So these are of course, like, you know, again, as I mentioned earlier, these are constraints
that arise in the real world and that's what we are sort of thinking about, but yes,
if you have the means to develop an interpretable model from scratch, you have all the data,
you have the necessary means, I think that is definitely and it's also accurate of course.
So that is definitely the way to go, but just that there are many other real world contexts
where that might not be the case which you could actually pursue.
In the scenarios where you can't do something that is more fundamentally transparent, you're
doing something that's a black box and you want to explain it, there are some kind of
known and popular methods for achieving some level of explainability and I mentioned
a couple of those all right, lime and sap, but a part of your presentation references
and previous research that you've done that has shown that, you know, that work can
be vulnerable to attack, you know, with your presentation, what's kind of the broad landscape
that you're looking to carve out and we'll get to the particular areas of lime and
sap when we get to them, but you know, how do you, how do you kind of frame the, you
know, the problem of kind of understanding the limits of the explainability tools?
Yeah, so I think this talk and more broadly my recent research has been kind of exploring
as we are thinking about the limits of explainability and what I mean by that is so far at least
in the past few years, there has been a lot of interest in coming up with new algorithms
which can explain black boxes, right?
So there is like a huge research that has built up I think since 2016, pretty much like
paper on top of papers, every paper comes up with another new method for explaining
a given black box classifier or a prediction model.
So one of the things that as we were seeing more and more work on this topic that, you
know, me and some of my collaborators of this work, we got excited about is how to now
start thinking about what are all the ways in which these explanation techniques can be
gained or potentially even unintentionally misused to sort of generate explanations which
could fool people or mislead and users into trusting something that they should not trust,
right?
So for example, maybe if your explanation, basically if your model, let's say if you have a black
box model which is actually using, you know, lace or gender, some of these sensitive features
which are prohibited to be the key aspects for making, you know, critical decisions like
for example, who gets a bail or who gets a loan and so on.
So if a black box model is using some of these features and if your explanation is somehow
misled to sort of think that that's not the feature that it is using but instead it's
using another correlate, for example, a zip code when making prediction and end user might
look at this explanation and just be misled that, oh, this seems like a model that's not
using grace, it's not rationally biased, it's using other correlates.
So maybe it's fine to deploy it, right?
So an explanation that can be misleading in terms of explaining what the black box is
doing can have serious consequences in the real world as we can just see with this kind
of example, right?
So the line of work that I'm pursuing currently is how to identify some of the issues or
vulnerabilities of existing methods which can potentially lead to these kinds of misleading
explanations and also understanding what is a real world impact if there is a misleading
explanation.
So what would be the consequences of that in real world and for that I'm also doing
a bunch of user studies with students from law schools and healthcare professionals and
so on to see how a misleading explanation can affect their work.
This is pretty much what the talk is all about, yeah.
I've got to imagine that the effects of these misleading explanations vary pretty dramatically
depending on the setting in which they're used.
That is definitely true.
Yeah.
So I think like for example, I think you know since anyways we are discussing this, let
me segue a bit into the second part of this talk which essentially talks about the effects
of these explanations in a particular context and the context we are looking at is let's
say if there is a model that is you know designed to predict who should get a bail, right?
Or at least it's designed to assist a judge in determining who should get a bail, but
in the process the model is also making predictions as to who should get a bail, right?
So before such a model is even deployed in the real world, ideally the judges or the teams
of the people it'll definitely go through a lot of vetting and people would like to look
at what the model is exactly doing before they sort of decide to trust and deploy it in
some sense, right?
So in that context we designed a small experiment with law school students.
Of course, it's all proxy because you know the time from judges and these senior domain
experts is their time is much more valuable and it's not easily available.
So we were trying to sort of mimic that with the law school students here at Harvard
and Yukon.
And basically what we did was we essentially built like a simple, in fact, Cynthia Rudin's
style rule based model which is the actual black box which explicitly has some rules which
are used to determine who gets a bail or not.
And in that we specifically used all these bad features or undesirable features like race
or gender to determine who gets a bail and then we constructed an explanation for this
rule based model which is another set of rules.
And then in that we explicitly avoided the usage of the features race and gender, but
the explanation is free to replace it with its correlates like replace these features
with its correlates.
So race could be substituted by zip code or anything else, but the explanation is just
kind of not allowed to show race or gender explicitly, right, but it's still, it should
still make the same predictions as what would be made by the original black box model that
we constructed.
And there was an actual system that generated these explanations or was this, you know,
did you create these explanations to simulate what a system might do under the set of conditions
that you outlined?
So one of the existing techniques is what we used to generate the explanations for this
black box.
So it's just that we put an additional constraint on that technique that just make sure
that race or gender do not show up in the explanations.
Got it.
Now the experiment was something that revealed very insightful things to us, which is
we showed we basically split people into a couple of groups or we took a bunch of
law school students, we split them into two groups.
For one set of people, we showed the actual model, which has race and gender, and then
we asked them if this is the model or if this is an explanation of a model, which is showing
you that race and gender are being used in making, you know, these predictions of who
should be jail.
Would you trust this model enough to deploy it in your code if you were a judge assuming
you were a judge, right?
And most of the people of course, as I expected, said, no, the model is using race and gender,
I don't want to deploy it anywhere close to me, sorry.
But then when we gave them the explanation, which was tailored to sort of hide or cover
up some of these problematic features and then showed it to the other half of the people.
And we said, this is an explanation generated by state of the art machine learning to explain
a black box using this now do you trust the underlying model enough to deploy it?
And most people said, yeah, sure, because it seems to be doing something which reasonably
matches my intuition of how, you know, we should determine someone should be given a bail
or not.
I don't see you say, which of any prohibited features or problematic features, yeah, sure,
let's go ahead.
So the actual true model less than 10% of the people trusted it and the explanation that
we are generated, which is essentially doing the same thing, but replacing race and gender
with its correlates almost about 80% plus people trusted it.
Oh, so it reminds me a little bit of some experiments that I on a Howard shared with me and her
about her research into just the authority that we tend to confer on computing systems in
her case robots, yeah.
And the examples that she gave were, you know, a robot that is presumably supposed to lead
you out of a fire or a dangerous condition in a building, you will like stand behind
it banging itself against the wall and waiting it for it to, you know, all of a sudden do
the right thing because we just want to believe that these things are, you know, more infallible
than they are.
Right.
Yeah.
No, definitely.
I think this research, I guess, also fits in line with some of that work in the sense
that people are probably already approaching models and model explanations from the perspective
of some prior trust, right?
So they are already willing to sort of trust them, which is why some of these, you know,
issues are like the things that we are seeing are actually being seen.
So, yeah.
And realizing we've kind of jumped ahead to the end of the talk.
But did you further explore around, you know, different ways to present that result that,
you know, helped, you know, besides from, you know, the one example where you kind of
show the race and the other where you hide it and are, are there things that you've played
with like showing the different correlating features or other things that can help the
human understand what's really happening?
Yeah.
So that's actually the ongoing research that we're actually doing, which is what is the best
way in which we can educate people that, hey, the explanation that you saw, it is purely
correlational and it's like when it says that zip code is being used, it could essentially
mean that any zip code or its correlate could be actually used to make predictions, right?
And in fact, one thing is we design like a very short 5 to 10 minute, like a primer or tutorial
just highlighting some of the examples that just because you don't see race, you know,
it could still be present because the correlation between race and zip code is like greater than
0.8 or something, right?
And then designing some examples like these and it's a very short 10 minute tutorial and
using that we can already see some, you know, like mega improvements in terms of how people
already like latched on to some of those ideas and the next time we ask them a similar
question, they are like less likely to make this kind of a mistake.
So we are also just thinking about what training is, might help people in like realizing some
of these things because again, what we are designing or even the way that we are sort
of producing these explanations are intention is that they would be used by someone who is
not an expert in machine learning.
So we should also be prepared to teach them how to think about these explanations and
what they can or they cannot provide in terms of information.
So I guess that's the next step or the next research that we are conducting.
And again, going back to your earlier question, we are also looking at this, of course,
one scenario as we talked about where misleading explanations had this impact.
We are also looking at other scenarios, again, in healthcare and a bit in like the business
domains where we are looking at different kinds of decisions, like some of which are more
high stakes, the others which are a bit more low stakes.
So in those cases, what would be the implications of misleading explanations?
So let's maybe take a few steps back and talk a little bit about the explainability
techniques that you are seeing in use and where you are seeing them in use.
Have you done a survey of the various techniques and how they are being used in practice?
I know you talk specifically about Lyme and Shapp, and I hear those come up probably
more than any others, but I'm wondering if you look broadly at that.
Yeah.
So while it's not an active area of my research, so there are I think some other folks who
are sort of thinking about these things, but in general, you're right that these two
techniques, one of the reasons we also picked those was because they were being very widely
used in practice and industry and in other real world settings, so that was also one reason
to sort of see if there are any vulnerabilities in those first because they're so widely
used.
Beyond that also, there are several techniques which are probably much less popular, but they
try to address some of the issues that are present in the first two techniques, Lyme and
Shapp.
Just to name a few, for example, Maple is another approach that has been proposed which
tries to sort of get rid of some of the, you know, like some sort of an ad hoc perturbations
or like some of the ad hoc pieces within Lyme and sort of make them more systematic.
So that's another approach just to give an example.
And of course, there are like several more which are like, you know, muse and a bunch
of other things, anchors and so on.
So there has been a lot of work just built up on, you know, this entire explaining black
boxes, as I said, like since 2016.
So by now, there are countless approaches, but I think the well-known ones among, the
most well-known among these are Lyme and Shapp.
Now coming to the second part of your question where you're thinking about how are people
using these techniques?
Honestly, the domains that I look at, so we are still kind of trying to make decision
makers like doctors or judges kind of aware of these techniques and how they should even
use them.
So, but that's the domains that, you know, I deal with a lot, but I can easily imagine
that if you're looking at, you know, maybe a startup or a tech company and so on, their
people are like more widely, you know, more well-familiar with these kinds of techniques
and they may already be using, be using some of them in their day-to-day, you know, job,
whether as a developer or an engineer or a scientist, you are trying to understand
what a particular model is doing, maybe to debug the model and so on.
So I can imagine all those kinds of use cases already underway and, you know, where explainability
is becoming a, you know, playing a bigger role in practice in day-to-day applications.
But, yeah, the domains that I deal with, like especially where you are sort of a bit
more detached from, you know, the core machine learning, you're dealing with people who make
different kinds of decisions, they're not tech people, they're not experts, so it is
like these kinds of approaches are sort of like reaching them at this point, barely,
I would say.
In your talk, did you kind of go over how the different techniques work and, you know,
what some of the, you know, weaknesses or blind spots that are inherent to them are and
where they come from?
Yeah, so I think the first part of this talk is mainly about what are the weaknesses
of Lime and Shap and just to kind of think about more broadly, the explanation techniques,
you can roughly characterize them into like two categories.
So one is local explanation methods and the other is global explanation methods.
I guess as the name suggests, local means, you know, you just think of explaining a
complaint behavior only within a particular tiny locality or neighborhood in the data,
right?
So a small piece of the feature space, you are trying to explain what the model is doing
there as best as you can.
So that's the local explanation methods.
And then the global explanation methods is you somehow want to give an in the pick the
entire picture of what the black box model might be doing like the whole big picture,
you know, so that like someone like for example, the use cases of these two could be different
where in the case of global explanation, the idea would be that someone who is deciding
if a model is good enough or whether it should be deployed, like maybe a team of judges.
Or, you know, a stakeholder who has a lot of authority on deciding if some model should
be deployed or not, he or she might use those to wet and decide is this model even reasonable
enough to deploy, right?
So that's where the global explanations come into picture because you are giving like zoomed
out view of what the model's behavior looks like, right?
On the other hand, when you think of local explanations, it could be to just like as a
model is deployed or after a model is deployed, let's say in a hospital to diagnose a disease
or something, for every patient, the model will give you a particular, you know, diagnosis
saying that this is basically what the diagnosis should be, say someone has diabetes or not
for example, right?
So in such cases, you also want to get an explanation for why that prediction is made
the way it is.
So then we focus more on the local or instance level or like singular predictions, whereas
and that's the case where after a model is deployed, a doctor is just double checking
that a single prediction makes sense, right?
So that's the use case and then for the global, it is to decide if a model at a high level
is even good enough to sort of beat it.
And so do the local and global methods share the same weaknesses or issues or are they different?
Yeah.
So in fact, the weaknesses are specific to the exact techniques employed to generate
a global or local explanations, like example, the first part of my talk is broadly focusing
on what is called as perturbation based methods, right?
And I'll get into the details of what I mean by that a bit.
Then there are other methods which focus on, you know, kind of using gradients to sort
of determine what features are being used when making a prediction.
So the attacks, these two classes of techniques have are vulnerable to different kinds of
attacks.
So the same attack would not work both for the perturbation based methods as well as
a gradient based method.
So yeah, the attacks are specific to the exact techniques that these methods are using.
So they're much more finely, fine grained than even just local and global.
Okay.
So in the case of a perturbation type of method, like lime, what does the attack look like?
How are those attacks constructed?
Right.
So let me, I think, start by just giving an intuition about what line does so that it becomes
clear what the attack would look like, right?
So what line does is it is trying to at a very basic or code level, lime is trying to
explain individual predictions of classifier.
So for each prediction, it's trying to give you which features were important and what
was their weightage in making this prediction, right?
So now what lime does is it goes to sort of every data point.
So basically if we want to explain a prediction of a particular data point, lime takes the
data point and then it's sort of perturbs that data point.
And when I say that, think of it as like you add some noise to different features of
this data point, okay?
And then that's what we call as perturbation.
So you just kind of slightly massage the values of these data points, generate another artificial
data point and keep doing this until you have a bunch of data points which were resulted
from perturbing that initial instance or the data point you wanted to explain, right?
So now that we have, let's say we got hundreds such perturbations or massage data points
and then you have this actual data point that you wanted to explain.
Now think of it as you just build a linear regression model on top of this so that that
model is predicting what the black box models predictions are for these hundred data points,
okay?
So it's basically taking a data point, massage it to create some artificial data set around
the data point, now just put a regression model and then it will give you what are the
feature importance weights for each of the features, right?
So that's what lime is doing.
So now why this is called a perturbation based method is in order to even fit a linear
regression model there or any local linear model there, you are generating some perturbations
of this initial data point where you started from, right?
So typically these are the, this is what we call as perturbation based methods, okay?
So now the attack once you sort of know a key intuition becomes very clear and obvious
which is, so what we found as part of like, you know, analyzing what lime is doing and
so on.
In fact, one of the PhD students that works with us found this was the perturbations that
are being generated by lime are actually not the points that are in the data distribution.
So these points look very different than the points that are actually in the data distribution
that we care about, okay?
So these could potentially be even off manifold data points or you know points that are like
very far off because you are just massaging a point and assuming that you'll end up with
a point that is sort of close enough, right?
But that does not always happen.
So given that the perturbations that you are generating using lime are not really the
points belonging to the insample data distributions.
That's a key, you know, point to sort of remember.
Now that has happened or now that we realize that that was the case, what we did was design
a simple attack or like build this kind of a what we call as an adversarial classifier
which does something, you know, very sneaky which is this classifier, it looks at a point
and then it basically decides if the point is in the data sample or if it's a perturbation.
So it kind of makes this prediction as to is this point like generated by perturbation,
is this a synthetic data point or was this point in the data?
Now when a point is in the data, then this classifier says, yeah, let's use race or gender
or any other undesired attribute that you could think of and make a prediction.
But if a point is a synthetic data point, which means it's a perturbation, then look
like you're super fair, like don't touch any bad features, remain like super pristine,
be very careful, like do something very clean and innocuous looking, right?
So when you do that, what happens is and when I give that classifier to line to explain
since line relies so much on perturbations, it thinks, oh, this model is doing fine on
perturbations, I don't see race as, you know, an important feature when it's making predictions
on those, so it'll just assume that the model is not using race as a feature when making
predictions.
Whereas underneath what is happening is this like a wrapper, it's like an adversarial
wrapper, you can think of that.
It's kind of nicely shielding its kind of shady behavior for lack of a better word by
doing all the shady things on in sample data points and then looking very innocent on
any perturbations.
So that is the attack, which is throwing off line and though the model uses race as the
only and main feature in making predictions, because it looks like because it has an innocent
behavior on the, you know, perturbation data points, line is just assuming that it is
using some very innocuous features when making predictions and it can never catch this underlying
racial behavior or that is our behavior which uses race, yeah.
So the setting kind of goes back to your setup at the very beginning of our conversation,
you, you know, maybe you can't use a, you know, a transparent model that you've developed
yourself, so you're getting a model from someone else kind of shelf and the attacker in this
case is whoever's creating the model and the scenario is kind of reminds me of Volkswagen
gaming the EPA when the car is detected that they were, you know, being tested for emissions
test.
Right.
They changed the way that they were, you know, throttled or whatever to make their emissions
fall within spec, but, you know, out on the road, they were, you know, you know, seeding
the levels.
Exactly.
Yeah.
This is I think a very good analogy.
That's pretty much what this adversary who is designing this classifier is also doing.
This off the shelf classifier is also doing.
So the main idea is if people are just using like, for example, lime or shaft to determine,
you know, are there any underlying racial or gender biases in this classifier, then
the adversary can successfully fool them because they're able to fool these explanation
methods.
And were you in this, this work in this presentation, do you propose any protections
for this or are you identifying the attack, the attack vector?
Right.
So that particular piece of work was just identifying the attack because that itself
was, I think, one of the initial works, which even talks about attacks on explanation
methods, but our ongoing work is definitely looking at how to sort of design these explanation
methods, which are robust to those attacks, or which cannot be gained to sort of, you
know, make these kinds of attacks accessible.
So how to think about them?
So that's an ongoing stream of research.
Mm-hmm.
And so it is a method like lime work if your perturbations are only producing or in
the direction of kind of in distribution results, like is that a direction that you're
looking at or?
Right.
Yeah.
So that's one of the directions we are looking at.
But then you can also think of this as there are some two problems, which are like two
sides of a coin, right?
So one is, then you can basically make these perturbations more and more similar to your
data instances, right?
So that will potentially subvert this kind of attack.
So we can make a lime plus plus where your perturbations look more and more similar to
your data instance.
Yeah.
Right.
So that's one thing.
There comes another problem that's a fix for the set attack, right?
But then there comes another problem, which is your explanations will start becoming more
and more data dependent, right?
So because if you have a data set, then the explanation that you build will only hold
for that data set.
So which means if you change the data set or something, then the explanation is no longer
going to hold.
So that's another problem of this because you're making this explanation very tight to the
data.
So now how do we fix that is another problem.
But I think this is again like a bit of a trade off where you can think of this like
a scale where the more you move to one side, you're probably creating some issues on the
other side.
So we are also looking at sort of formalizing those trade-offs and like, you know, saying
that yeah, as you try to achieve more of, you know, perturbations that look more and
more similar to your data, yes, you subvert one attack, but then you're creating explanations
that are only holding for your data.
So is that good or is that bad?
So like what are the trade-offs between these two?
Okay.
In your research, have you identified any other similar types of attacks?
Are there others that have been proposed?
So again, as I said, like this one of the initial ones, I think as a follow-up paper or as
a follow-up work, there is another problem.
Another team in Utah that has recent ICML paper on specific attacks to SHAP.
So that is a follow-up work which again sort of plays on or builds on some of our earlier
work.
But I think so far, there have mostly been attempts at looking at like perturbation-based
methods.
So there is a lot of scope for open work on other kinds of methods including radiant-based
methods and even, you know, global versus local what needs to be attacked and what is
most vulnerable in each of these and so on.
So there's like a whole set of open problems that haven't really been addressed so far.
So yeah.
And are there any interesting connections between the work that you're doing here and the
broader research field of kind of adversarial machine learning attacks?
You know, a lot of this is based on kind of perturbations and noise.
And so there's at least a permanent creature overlap.
Does one have something to offer the other and vice versa?
Yeah.
So yes, a lot.
I mean, I think this work is actually inspired by, you know, some sort of the adversarial
machine learning literature.
So there the focus was more on finding examples or data points which can throw off a classifier,
right?
Whereas here the focus is now let's find something which throws off an explanation method.
So like I guess that way there is like a very clear parallel.
What adversarial machine learning was doing for classifiers and prediction models.
We are trying to do that with explanations.
So I guess that way there is like a pretty tight connection.
And in fact, you know, as I was saying about some ongoing work which tries to address
some of these vulnerabilities like in perturbation methods or otherwise, the way we also try
to fix the vulnerabilities and come up with a new explanation method is also inspired by
how people think of adversarial robust classifiers in the adversarial machine learning literature.
So just like people had this, you know, let's first see what are the vulnerabilities where
things are breaking down in terms of classifiers, then how can we develop a robust classifier.
So the same thing is playing out in parallel in the explainability literature.
So yeah, there is a pretty clear connection.
A lot of that ended up saying, you know, more regularization is there approach.
Is that going to be the answer here too?
That's what I was is equally.
Yeah, but I think so the I guess the there are a couple of things though, right?
So for example, one thing is even beyond regularization, it's also about thinking about like
formulations like maybe minimax, which is, you know, sort of like thinking about the maximum
possible error that you could have on like a variety of distributions that you want your
model to work on or like a variety of datasets you want your explanation to hold on and minimizing
that maximum error.
So I guess those kinds of formulations are also very helpful apart from, you know, regularization
and so on.
So I think those ideas are useful to sort of flow from that community to the explainability
community.
Beyond that, I also am hopeful that there could be other interesting challenges with explainability.
The reason why I say that is because there is as algorithms are being like increasingly
used for various decisions like whether someone gets a loan, right?
Or whether, you know, someone gets a particular treatment or whether they are given a bail
or not.
So there is an increasing sort of like call from both legal scholars and social sciences
scholars to sort of make these machines also provide resources to people.
And when I say that, what do I mean is if I as a bank am using an algorithm and if I
tell someone a loan is denied for you, I also need to tell them what needs to be changed
in their profile so that they can come back and get a loan, right?
So they are making these algorithms more accountable, which means the gaming of these kinds of
methods is going to be like very real.
Like when you think of, you know, classifiers and some adversaries sort of giving you an
adversarial sample or example and so on.
So I guess the danger of that somehow seems a little bit more limited to me than like
when it comes to explainability where people are relying heavily on this and like things
are moving increasingly in the directions that people are looking at these and making
decisions of what models to use, making decisions like whether a prediction is reliable or not.
So as you are hitting more and more of these real world scenarios, I think, well, we also
need to be worried because the risk of these things being manipulated and game is very
real and very high.
But at the same time, I can see lot more real world applications or like usages of these
scenarios probably way more than, you know, someone trying to change pixels and any
image and so on, right?
So that's while that's an interesting concept to think about, you know, to solve a problem
or like from an engineering perspective, technical perspective, here the social implications
are very real.
So I'm hoping that this would also bring with that more interesting technical challenges
as well.
Is there a GAN application here where you've got some model that's trained to try to
fool your, some model that's, you know, you've got kind of these two adversarial models
that are trying to try to pick out, you know, the out of distribution samples or something
like that and, you know, when the one model is trying to cheat the other or anything.
Yeah.
No, I think they're headed there.
I think some of you in our ongoing work is sort of headed there.
Okay.
And I guess the way in which sort of at least like, you know, me and my group or some of
the other researchers are approaching this problem is kind of trying to keep like a real
year to the ground because a case where someone can build a classifier which can do something
messy within sample data points and look very pristine and clean with these perturbations
that the approach relies on is like a very realistic thing and it's not even like a
super sophisticated attack if you think about it, right?
So we are trying to sort of at this point, keep our year to the ground and look at those
most plausible scenarios and how to fix them and then of course, you know, some of these
will automatically happen which are definitely interesting from technical perspective and so
on.
Right.
Well, Hima, thanks so much for sharing a bit about your presentation and your research.
Yeah.
Thank you so much.
This was, yeah, this was amazing.
I had a great time talking to you.
I'm here.
Same here.
Thank you.
All right, everyone, that's our show for today.
For more information on today's show, visit twomolai.com slash shows.
As always, thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.
Bye.