Welcome to the Twimal AI Podcast.
I'm your host, Sam Charrington.
Alright everyone, I am on the line with Deanna, Marcalescu.
Deanna is department chair and professor of electrical and computer engineering at the
University of Texas at Austin.
Deanna, welcome to the Twimal AI Podcast.
Thank you for having me, Sam.
I'm happy to be here.
I am super excited to have you on the show, especially since just before we started recording
you mentioned that you're a long time listener.
And I always love talking to listeners on the show and having the opportunity to host
them on the show.
So thank you for that.
Being a long time listener you know the routine, I'm going to ask you to share a little bit
about your background and how you came to work in machine learning.
Sure.
I'm happy to do so.
Yeah, actually I'd be listening to the podcast for quite some time, especially on my
trips to conferences and more than likely currently we're not traveling that much.
However, we try to do our best to stay up to date by listening to podcasts, especially
in this domain.
My trajectory to working in this field is a little bit less traditional, I come from
the computer hardware systems area.
I've worked for more than 20 years on making computer hardware systems more efficient,
especially more power efficient.
And the way I got to work in machine learning in particular came from the applications side.
So we've used machine learning to make or to perform power management for multicore systems
in the last decade or so.
But more recently in the last three to four years my students and I decided to turn it
around and instead of using machine learning as an application to make computer systems
more efficient, instead we turned our focus to making machine learning models more efficient
such that they run better on existing computer systems or trying to find ways to build computer
systems that are more amenable to running machine learning models and applications.
So that's where the whole idea of the code design of both the machine learning model
and the computer hardware system came into play.
So our first publication in the field was three years ago and ever since we continue
to work in in this field.
Great, great.
And you recently had an opportunity to share some of what you're doing in the field at
the efficient deep learning in computer vision workshop at the recent CVPR conference
where you gave a keynote and working in this field and talking about issues like the
efficiency of machine learning models, often questions about the edge versus cloud come
up.
Did your research focus on one or the other of these settings?
Sure, actually both are really important.
So thinking about where we are now, much of the machine learning applications actually
do run in the cloud.
So for both training, we train them in the cloud, much of the inference also happens in
the cloud if you're trying to run a speech recognition, simple app on your phone or smart
watch, if it's not connected to the network, it's not going to be able to accomplish its
task because everything does happen in the cloud.
On the other hand, our work tries to democratize access to machine learning as an application
such that it's pushing both inference as well as training to edge devices.
So this is where the idea of making machine learning models in particular neural networks
more efficient and more amenable to be run on tiny devices where constraints are really
important.
So yeah, our focus is mostly on edge devices, although looking at the entire continuum
from edge all the way to the cloud is just as important.
So your keynote at the workshop is titled putting the machine back in machine learning,
the case for hardware, ML model co-design.
And it sounds like co-design is a key idea in your research.
What it can know for me is that often we hold either one, the machine or the algorithm
as fixed and try to optimize the other, you know, with the constraint of the thing that
we hold as fixed.
And what I'm guessing here or imagining is that you're treating both of these as things
that we can kind of co-optimize together.
Is that the general idea of your research?
That's correct.
And actually the co-design idea has been used for quite some time in embedded systems.
For a long time, the idea that you want to customize a hardware that runs the embedded
software has been at the forefront for the last 15 to 20 years in the field of embedded
system design.
So it's not a new concept.
What's new is actually putting the focus on the machine in the machine learning domain.
And machine has never left to be honest, the machine learning space, but we're just trying
to put the focus back on the hardware because a lot of the focus that has been happening
recently has been on the performance of machine learning applications, meaning accuracy or
classification error, or things that actually tell us whether it does its job in the proper
way.
Putting things in a historical perspective, machine learning and in particular neural network
research has been going on for quite some time, but it did not get at the level as we see
today without the progress that we've seen in hardware design and everything we've seen
from the single core to multi-core to GPU progress.
So it's important to understand that the reason why machine learning applications have received
so much attention and widespread usage is because of the hardware.
But we're not going to be able to write that wave of dissemination without support from
the hardware.
So our focus is to put the machine specifics and machine hardware metrics into the design
process for neural networks.
And when you do that, you have one half of the problem you mentioned, right?
When you think about code design, you have to add the other half of the problem.
It's not just that the neural network has to be designed with a hardware in mind, but
at the same time, we need to design the hardware with the application in mind in this particular
case machine learning.
So yes, code design is the end goal and we are, we are not quite there yet.
There's quite a few researchers working in this field, but there are a few components
that are needed before we get to true code design.
And one is understanding what are the hardware metrics we need to look at?
How do we expose them to the machine learning design process?
And then how do we design neural network models that take that into account such that they
fit the hardware that we might be able to have or we might be able to design for them?
So it's actually a true cycle, iterative cycle of optimization.
You say that we need to focus on hardware and putting the hardware back into the process.
And maybe I'm asking the same question again, or maybe I'm just going to provide the
answer, but my sense is that, you know, there has been a lot of focus on hardware in
the fields, you know, clearly, you know, different types of accelerators.
What you're saying here is we've focused on hardware for optimizing hardware for a specific
class of problems.
This is going to be an accelerator that works well at, you know, deep neural networks,
as opposed to what I'm seeing in your research is a specific neural network architecture.
We're going to kind of design the hardware for that, kind of design the neural network
to work well with that hardware.
Do all of this at the same time.
And overall, we're going to end up with a system that, you know, performs better than
hopefully the, you know, things that aren't designed, you know, so in such an integrated
manner.
Yes, I mean, that's exactly the point, right?
So any or right, there has been a lot of hardware focus lately.
Maybe it started a little bit, you know, with proxies, right?
They weren't really hard on metrics.
There were maybe flops, flop count, floating point operations.
Maybe it was model size.
Maybe it was some sort of proxy for latency.
What we're trying to do is characterize or provide ways or methodologies to characterize neural
networks from their latency, power, energy perspective on a given hardware.
But at the same time, identify ways to build hardware that minimizes those metrics.
If it makes sense, right?
So the mentioning, you mentioning the talk I gave at the workshop at CVPR.
So one piece that is required to make this code design process possible is the ability
to characterize neural network architectures or perhaps components thereof in terms of
their, the time it takes to process those things, the energy or power it takes and maybe
come up with a joint metric that characterizes their energy efficiency or latency per correct
inference if you want.
In other words, come up with combined metrics that capture both hardware as well as accuracy
in some sense.
So providing that methodology for estimating power, energy and latency for these, it's
actually a piece of software, right, that you write is one of the steps that allows us
to identify the right configuration or architecture for the neural network because you can't optimize
what you cannot model or characterize, right?
And actually, it's easier.
It's actually pretty easy to do that.
We've done this for quite some time in the computer or hardware embedded system domain.
It's much harder to have the same similar kind of model for accuracy.
We can tell how accurate is a neural network until we actually train it.
On the other hand, for a given architecture, we can easily tell what the power or latency
will be for a given hardware platform once you characterize it, right?
So it's a very low-hanging fruit that we should take advantage of.
The idea there is expressed in some research that you've done called neural power.
Is that the one and you're, you know, we've previously talked about, you know, characterizing
neural networks in terms of, you know, things like depth and parameters and layers, and we
talk about hardware in this totally different language, which is flops and power and things
like that.
And you're trying to kind of unify the way that we're able to talk about this.
And you're doing it using a neural network.
Is that right?
Actually, we use machine learning for that.
So we build models for latency and power that we fit using data that we collect from a
lot of synthetically generating neural networks and constructs, right?
Because we look at different types of convolutional layers, fully connected layers, pulling layers,
things that you typically find in neural networks, deep neural networks.
So we try to build a power and a latency model and, of course, also an energy model that
captures all those components.
And then in a composable fashion, you're able to say, once you've done this characterization
and you fit the model once, you can tell just by looking at the configuration of the network,
the latency and to end for an inference will be this much and the power consumption will
be this much.
You don't even have to run it, right?
So you collect the data, you fit the model once, and then you use it over and over again.
And the good thing about this is that you can use it in the optimization process when you
do say architecture search.
Architecture search is very time consuming.
But the fact that you can characterize every single component or block of this architecture
space in a zero cost of one kind of complexity, it's really appealing because it allows you
to put it in this iterative optimization process.
So that's where we took this expertise in characterizing hardware metrics and used it
to identify neural architectures that satisfy hardware constraints.
So this is the second part of the talk that I had that talked about neural architecture
search using a single path approach.
And inside that iterative optimization loop, we did have this kind of latency model.
In that particular case, we were looking at the latency on a very specific hardware platform
Pixel 1.
And so is the idea that if you're applying neural architecture search without the metrics
that you have available via neural power, you would have to run as long an expensive process
and come up with a bunch of candidate models that after the fact you have to see if they
satisfy your hardware constraints, but here you're able to integrate it in and in doing
so it's kind of cut off some dead ends that your search process might need to run through.
Yes, that's right.
So you can prune the search process by removing candidates that do not meet maybe your latency
constraints.
You want to have each inference take less than a few tens of milliseconds, right?
By having this characterization done once and reuse it over and over, you can prune the
search process.
You can also, the way we did it, we actually incorporated in our loss function a term that
captures the cost in terms of latency.
And by doing so, we're able to basically make the neural architecture search process hardware
of aware.
And there are other components to the approach that we've had because it relies on the concept
of a super network that actually shares, it shares its weights across multiple different
types of structures.
But I mean, that's one component, but the reason why it's actually pretty powerful is because
it identifies networks that satisfy these hardware constraints in this case latency while
at the same time doing this in a very efficient fashion.
So like you said, instead of identifying a bunch of candidates that satisfy accuracy,
and then we check does it satisfy latency constraints, we're able to do this through just a single
process.
So it's more efficient.
There's some property of the search space that tells you that if you are looking at
a particular model and it doesn't meet your power constraints, some evolution of that,
not to assume that you're using evolutionary models in here, won't then be better than
the thing that you're looking at, like a convexity property or something like that.
Is that an assumption or is that something that is just kind of demonstrably true about
these search bases for some set of models?
Yeah.
Well, I think it's an excellent question.
We just started to scratch the surface on that our particular approach is a differentiable
search approach, meaning we cast the problem as a differentiable function and then you
just use anything that works on that, like a typically stochastic gradient is and will
make convexity assumptions, although they might not be, they might hold in reality, but
it works pretty well in practice.
And in our case, you're absolutely right, the efficiency of architecture search comes
from two components.
One is the search space.
So what are the components that we actually allow to be the building blocks for our neural
networks?
So that's one.
And the second is how do we do the search and you did allude to say evolutionary algorithms.
There's also reinforcement learning that you can use.
We use a differentiable approach in which all the choices that we make in terms of the
architecture, although they are discrete choices, we perform a transformation that allows
us to do a differentiable search on them.
So apply optimization algorithms that typically are used on those kinds of objective functions.
So the closest or the earliest work that is in the same kind of vein as us is darts,
which does differentiable architecture search for neural networks.
The difference for in our case is the search space.
So the basic components that we consider is broader.
But at the same time, the way we identify the different selections that take us to the
final architecture is done such that we share much of the, for example, for a three by three
five by five seven by seven convolutional kernel, we basically share all the weights.
So the only thing we need to know for a five by five is that we use a three by three plus
the outer layer that takes us to five by five.
So in some sense, it's less for us to identify, you get, it puts more constraints on the
search process, but it's more efficient in the kinds of things that you can't find out.
So, and it is able, so our word that was published last at the ECML PKDD conference last September
in Germany, and we extended it for for a journal paper this year.
It allows us this more efficient search process allowed us to find a more accurate neural
architecture than in the case where you would have more freedom to search.
So I guess it's a fine balance between the exploitation and exploration.
And we were able to find that somehow at the same time satisfying this hardware constraints
in terms of latency.
And interestingly, at the time when we did our comparisons, we were able to be better in
terms of accuracy compared to the manuals.
So to speak designs like mobile net V2, V3 that, I mean, their manual, their zero cost
so to speak, but there was a lot of engineering time, a lot of hours spent by engineers behind
those efforts.
So I don't, I wouldn't want to call them zero time search costs, but, you know, their
manual, single designs, and then, you know, we did even better in terms of the search
cost and accuracy compared to other types of neural architecture approaches.
So because of that, we were able to, because of the efficient search space and the way
we searched, so the two components put together, we were able to push the search time to hours
as opposed to days.
So I think that's where the strength came in only a few epochs.
We were able to find this kind of architecture.
So those are the two strengths are one ability to characterize hardware metrics inside the
optimization process as well as the second component, which is the more efficient search
process overall.
Is the resulting architecture that you are comparing to whatever your baseline is, the
output of the single path network architecture search process, or do you also, you know, apply
other processes to that like quantization or pruning or, you know, compression, other
compression techniques?
Sure.
I mean, single path NASS does just that, the former.
So whatever you said, it identifies the architecture, but of course, on top of that, you can perform
other things like quantization, compression.
There's an interesting question as to whether doing this equationally.
So first, identifying the architecture and then performing compression and or quantization
leads us to a better result rather than doing it together.
I think there's a very interesting, there's some emerging work in that space.
We're also looking at ways to identify how quantization or precision might play a role
in this architecture search process.
But to answer your question, you can do this.
So once you identify a neural architecture, you can apply quantization.
You can apply model compression or pruning, right?
Those are techniques that exist, you know, going back to the presentation I had at the
CFPR workshop, we did present some of the ideas that we had in that space, especially
as they relate to quantization as well as to pruning, channel pruning.
And so in the quantization space, the idea, I mean, there's been quite a bit of work, you
know, ranging from binarized neural networks all the way to using limited precision, fixed
point, limiting the number of bits for representation.
Our idea was actually pretty simple, so that we published first on this in 2017 and then
ever since we refined that further, we wanted to limit the number of bits representing
weights to a fixed number.
And it turned out that in practice, using just one or two bits is sufficient to get the
best in terms of efficiency, but still not miss much in terms of accuracy.
So the idea is that for each weight, we identify the, say, the combination of two powers of
two that, when stochastically rounded, give you the best accuracy.
So we have a few examples in the original paper where we show how using stochastic rounding
actually on average will give you, you know, in theory, will give you the same accuracy
as the original, unquantized neural network.
So we call this light an N, so light weight neural networks.
And light an NK uses K bits to represent the weights.
We still maintain the activations in the original precision.
And it turns out that you can get to up to two orders of magnitude, reduction in the
either power, memory, storage, and still maintain the original accuracy.
So this is pretty powerful.
This was for Cypher 10 data set and then we extended it for ImageNet.
Of course, the downside for using a quantized model is that to actually get these benefits
you will need to build an accelerator that relies on replacing every multiply, accumulate,
or MAC operation with these logic operators, operators that just do shifts and adds, right?
And GPUs are not readily doing that.
You could program CPUs to do that, but might take some effort.
So I think the, what is out there right now is that if you're going to use this type of
quantization, you will need to build a specialized piece of hardware to do it.
So there will be true accelerators, but I think the results are pretty encouraging for
us to continue to do so because it does achieve quite a bit of energy and hardware efficiency
in general for not much of a loss in accuracy.
From the other perspective, you could also do pruning, right?
So you could consider how you want to prune the network.
You don't want to lose much in the accuracy, but you want to simplify the model even further.
So our work in that space, and actually that work was just published in the conference
in CVPR as an oral presentation.
The idea is, so the name we used is ledger.
Basically is using a layer-based global ranking to identify where do we want to do pruning?
So we do pruning based on importance.
So we don't want to prune uniformly across the board.
We want to prune only where accuracy is not going to suffer the most.
And by doing so, you're able to achieve additional efficiency on the model site.
And of course, that translates into hardware efficiency as well.
So was the name of that paper ledger and intentional head fake to get people excited about
some Bitcoin quantization approach?
Hopefully.
I think we need to ask my student why he chose that.
I like the name.
Going back to NeuroPower and this model for the metrics.
You touched on the data source, but can you elaborate on that a little bit?
Did you run a bunch of simulations?
Did you pull power data off of actual hardware running some suite of models?
That sounds very expensive and hard.
How did you collect data to fit a model?
Yeah.
So that's an excellent question.
We actually did a lot of profiling.
So we started with one GPU platform and that we added more GPU platforms.
And like I said, we as machine learning to build the power and latency models.
So we needed a lot of data to train those models.
So we relied on profiling on several GPU platforms.
We profiled power.
We profile latency.
We profiled also memory usage, although we did not use it explicitly, except for a component
in one of our models.
And also at the same time, we had to profile a lot of these synthetic neural networks that
exhibited different types of combinations of convolutional and fully connected and pulling
layers.
So we took a lot of effort.
That's true.
The idea though is if you are using any of those platforms, you can use data that we
collected.
But of course, if you want to use your own platform, you can use our methodology.
So our code is available.
You can use your own platform, perform the same type of profiling and then fit your own
power and if latency model.
So it's a methodology that allows us and others allows everyone to apply on different types
of platforms.
But it is data intensive.
As you collect the data, though, it's just a one time kind of thing.
Great.
And you did that for, is it a handful of GPU architectures or, I guess, how specific
is a particular model that you develop to a hardware platform?
Is it kind of the architecture family or is it a specific model or generation of a platform?
How what is it generalized as the hardware evolves?
Right.
I think that's an excellent question.
So a methodology is as good as its potential use, right?
So and I always get this question.
So okay, neural power is good, but if I can't use it for my own platform, if I can't
generalize to other types of computer hardware platforms that don't even exist, how is this
going to be used or how is it going to be usable?
And the answer is, I think this is where the co-design comes into the picture, right?
So we've done, we've built this methodology on an existing platform.
However, if you are in the business of building specialized computer hardware for machine
learning applications, you have an idea, you have a blank canvas that you can start
from, maybe not as blank, maybe you start from some components that you want to use.
So the idea is that you can decide how you put together this architecture.
And there are a lot of interesting ways to characterize a platform in terms of latency
and power before it's even built, right?
This is what we've done for many years before, I mean, we haven't started, you know, we
don't build computer systems by building one and then measuring power in latency.
We know what those numbers will be at design time, right?
So the same approach can be used in this case.
I really think computer hardware designers, as well as machine learning model developers
have to work together because that's where the strength comes from and that's where the
generalizability comes from, you're going to be able to get the expertise from both
and come up with ways to do the actual true co-design.
So it's a hard problem because the search space will be, you know, the cross product of
the two, but we've done a lot of progress on the computer hardware side, right?
So a lot of them, especially on the edge device embedded systems, this is automated quite
a bit.
So we can use all the expertise that exists there and then incorporate some of those things
in the machine learning design process and the co-design as well.
So when you combine all these things, neuropath, single path, architecture search, the light
neural networks, can you talk a little bit about the results you've seen, you know,
what were the baselines, what did you, were you able to demonstrate, et cetera?
Right.
So in terms of, I mean, our models once built the power and latency models once built,
they are just zero cost or constant cost, you know, you just plug in the parameters where
the architecture configuration and you get the numbers, right?
So that's, you know, you do maybe a lot of work in the beginning, but then it, it amortizes
across multiple uses.
The neural architecture search approach basically reduced the search time by three orders of
money to them more.
So we took it from days all the way to ours.
And there are many reasons why that was possible.
One was the way the search space was defined.
The second was how we did the search and of course the fact that we shared these structures,
parameters across different configurations helped quite a bit as well.
So three orders of magnitude in the search, meaning training time.
And then in the inference efficiency, if you look at the impact of quantization or pruning,
you can get maybe two orders of magnitude efficiency, especially from quantization.
So that's quite significant.
We're actually looking now at custom hardware that, you know, post synthesis, post layout,
how much of that will translate into the actual hardware.
There's still going to be at least 40 to 50% savings that still translates because the
tourism I need to that I mentioned looks only at the computation.
There's also quite a bit in terms of storage that we need to capture.
So I think there's quite a lot of good news.
So overall, on the training search side, several orders of magnitude on the inference side,
a lot of efficiency from quantization.
On the training search side, do you look at like ablations, you mentioned several different
characteristics or several different properties that go into producing your, you know, several
order of magnitude, advantages and in train time.
Is that all or nothing?
Is there something magical about this combination?
Or, you know, have you looked at the individual tricks that you've tried to apply and, you
know, there's an individual, one of those gets you 80% of the way there.
How did the different techniques come together?
Right.
So I actually think it's the combination thereof because there are other differentiable
neural architecture search approaches like Dart's inspired.
Once you do that explicit representation, unless you do this super network kind of approach,
you're not going to get the savings.
But at the same time, the ability to consider this specific building blocks allowed us to
perform this comparison with mobile net V2 and V3, right?
So I guess you could design your search space differently to make other types of comparisons.
The results might be different.
But I think the fact that we limit the search space and we also share these parameters across
configurations made it for the fast search time.
And so what is ahead in this general line of research for you and your research group?
Yes.
So we are actually, we have not completed the co-design dream yet, right?
So because we do have the power, latency characterization, we have the, you know, neural network search.
We put in the hardware metrics, but do we have a push button solution that we say, okay,
my task is this robotic vision application or this ARVR application, and these are my constraints
in hardware.
And these are my specifications for accuracy for the machine learning model.
Just build for me something that does that.
We did not get there yet.
What I think is needed right now is to actually, even your hardware constraints are relatively
coarse, right, the power latency, things like that on a typical, an actual chip CPU, for
example, you can get tons of metrics and capabilities from the chip itself about, you know, that
may impact the way your search operates.
That's absolutely right.
And, you know, everything we've done looks at one machine learning model running on this
piece of hardware, and that's never the case.
There are many more things, even more machine learning tasks running.
What maybe one does, speech recognition, one does image recognition, one does object detection.
Maybe there's some sort of multimodal fusion that happens.
That's a huge space that we're looking at, right?
So, I think the, I guess the goal would be to, the ability to say, okay, these are, this
is what I would like to run, and it's not just one machine learning model.
Maybe it's multiple ones.
Maybe it's multiple modalities.
Maybe it's different tasks, maybe it's the same task with different inputs.
How do I run this most efficiently for this particular application?
And by application, I mean something that is not a platform is, like I said, it could
be robotic or an AR, VR application.
So you have the ability to define or design what the platform will be, or will look like.
So Truco design will happen when we're able to close the loop, right?
So we're able to say, okay, this is an initial version of the hardware I think might work.
Based on this, I think your network or networks should look like this.
However, when I do it again, it looks like the hardware needs to be tweaked.
So it's going to be an iterative continuous process until you get to the right configuration.
The question then stands, well, I'm going to build this.
But what if I want to run an additional task on this piece of hardware?
Will I be able to do so?
So one is the ability to reach this code design.
But the second one is programmability and flexibility.
And that's where, you know, there's a balance that you need to, I mean, do you want your
system to be able to run these new applications, or maybe it's the same task, but the data
set is different, right?
You need to retrain it.
Does that affect the way your hardware looks like?
So I think these are all interesting questions that we're still looking at.
And it sounds like this vein of work is primarily operating under kind of traditional
GPU-like assumptions, and there are all manner of other proposed directions that one might
go with hardware, you know, from kind of graph-native implementations and other things.
Do you think these ideas apply similarly to some of those other types of constructs?
Yes.
I think that's a nice one question.
I think we're pretty much, I mean, if you look at the classic machine learning research
papers, they do run on typical GPU platforms, right?
This is where much of the training happens.
This is where inference, I mean, maybe inference can be done on, or they provide results on
other types of platforms.
But I really think, so one is, okay, what are the other options for us to go to in terms
of the hardware that we're looking at?
So that's where accelerators come into the picture.
And there's quite a bit of work on that end.
On the other hand, what is beyond neural networks?
I mean, neural networks, I think, are, I mean, it's just deep learning has become, I don't
know that it's because it's on more understandable, I don't think it's that.
I think it's because it offers quite a rich field of questions that are still unanswered.
But there's quite a bit of other types of machine learning models or modalities that
we have to look at, right?
Is there any computational impact?
Of course there is on those other ones.
Is there a role that hardware, computer hardware designers or developers should play in
that space?
Of course they do.
But I think right now, much of the, if you look at 90% of the work, I think it's just
deep learning, especially vision and, you know, deep neural networks, neural architectures,
research, things that are really well-defined and quite a bit of work happens there.
I believe there's still quite a bit of unsolved and interesting questions that have yet to
be answered in other types of machine learning that perhaps have not received that much attention
because they're not as amenable to be run on GPUs, right?
Maybe this is why, I mean, there's a chicken and egg.
Those made deep learning, you know, on the visible end of our attention, but all the others
are probably not receiving the attention because they don't really run well on GPUs which
all of us have access to.
So I think we can elevate those kinds of machine learning applications by looking at ways
to make them more efficient and increase the size and their applicability and dissemination.
So I think there's quite a bit of impetus in this field.
It's really hard to say, I'm not going to look in the crystal ball and say, okay, in ten
years, everything on the DNN or deep learning side will be solved and then we're going to
look at, I don't know, probabilistic graphical models or something.
I don't know what that might be.
I was going to ask, right?
Yes.
Right.
Well, my students asked me all the time, should I still work in this because I don't
know.
When I graduate, we'll also be able to find a job.
Definitely.
I mean, this is definitely going to be a hot space for high tech.
Though I think this conversation is standing out as one of a couple in the past, a couple
of weeks where there was this undercurrent or suggestion of us being a peak deep learning
which has not really been much of a thing in my conversations.
It's a little bit, you know, that's a lot to extrapolate off of two comments.
Sure.
But interesting that you're saying that and so probabilistic graphical models is one
of the things that you think about as a, if not a contender, a co-existing thing, are
there others that come to mind as, you know, you're worth?
I mean, yeah, well, closer to neural networks, I mean, you have RNNs that can benefit from
much of the things that we've talked about.
But I think makes DNNs and actually RNNs as well or anything that has a deep learning
component in it like, you know, when you look at deep reinforcement learning, it does rely
on using or encoded the state action using deep neural networks.
So I think the appeal of that is that it's a very well structured way to look at a problem,
right?
Because you understand or we think we understand where the components are, we don't
really understand how they work.
But we understand what the components do.
So I think it's, people are still going to stain that space quite a bit.
What I think needs to happen for others, and I just mentioned probabilistic graphical models
because it's really different, right?
It's not as structured.
And you know, when people think of AI, there's many other things that, you know, are not
quantizable as how many MAC operations can you do in parallel or efficiently, right?
So there's more on the decision making side.
And that's what makes it a true AI, right?
So I think the gap between where we are now and where we could be is quite, quite wide.
I think to get to see more interesting things happen in other types of machine learning applications
is a need for those things to happen more efficiently.
And maybe that need is not there yet because we can still perform those tasks using
existing approaches.
Another way to see an impetus in that space would be to have hardware that supports it.
But maybe not because of them, because of some other type of application that is really
requiring that.
So I think machine learning was the lucky winner of the GPU revolution.
GPUs were built in mind with, you know, parallelism.
And we switched from the single core to multi-core, but then multi-core were not enough and
then GPU came into the picture.
So can we envision a trajectory like this for other machine learning applications absolutely?
I just don't know.
I mean, there's many other things that people are looking at from the hardware side.
I know there's quite a bit of interest in removing the memory wall bottleneck, which has
been there for quite a bit of time.
But to be able to do that, to do processing in memory, or to do other kinds of advances
in that field, you need help from the technology.
So I think maybe the progress in that space might be slowed down because we don't really
have a replacement for our current technology, although it's still working quite fine so
far.
So talking about exponential trends, I mean, Moore's law was supposed to double performance,
you name it, transistor density, pick your favorite every couple of years or every year
and a half.
And it stopped, but it doesn't mean we stopped in making things more, you know, better and
better and more efficient.
So there's always something that we can do, and I'm really hopeful that's going to be
the case in machine learning as well.
Awesome.
Well, Deanna, thanks so much for taking the time to chat with us.
It's great to learn a bit about what you're up to.
Thank you.
Thank you for having me.
All right, everyone, that's our show for today.
For more information on today's show, visit twomolai.com slash shows.
As always, thanks so much for listening and catch you next time.