Welcome to the Twimal AI Podcast.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
All right, everyone. I am pleased to be here with Eric Topol. Eric is Professor of Molecular
Medicine at Scripps Research, as well as the Director and Founder of the Scripps Research
Translational Institute. Eric, welcome to the Twimal AI Podcast.
Thanks very much, Sam. Great to be with you.
I am really excited to have you on the show. I've been a fan of your Twitter feed for
quite some time. You have been one of the resources that I've tended to turn to to try to understand
the COVID-19 and coronavirus situation as it's been evolving. So thank you very much for
that. I'm really looking forward to digging into talking about your perspective on that.
But before we do, I'd love to have you share a little bit about your background. You're
trained as a cardiologist if I'm correct. I imagine that a lot of cardiologists have their
time well full studying the heart, but you've managed to really dig into the role that technology
plays in medicine and in particular, artificial intelligence. How did that all come about?
Well, it's interesting how I got into this, Sam. Back in college, I was in genetics. The
major, and I always loved that area, but I drifted to cardiology, got into the interventional
that is putting its stems and balloons, arteries, and whatnot. But I mostly got back to the
genetics in the mid-90s to try to understand why people had heart attacks or heart disease.
And then, when I got to San Diego in 2006, I started up this new institute. I realized genetics
wasn't going to do enough. We needed sensors and other layers of data to understand each
person. And that led to the total kind of digital medicine, the interest. And then became pretty
natural that if you have a genome and you have continuous sensor data, you need some advanced
analytics to really understand what's going on. So that's kind of the progression how it
all came to pass. That is understanding each person who is unique in every layer of biology,
physiology, their environment, and anatomy. So this is kind of the story how it's unfolded.
Great. So in terms of COVID-19 and coronavirus, at least as far as the work from home and
quarantines and all that goes, many of us are recently passing a hundred days in for
folks that have been studying it closely. We're quite a bit beyond that in terms of it's
having been on the scene. Maybe we can start by having you share a little bit of your
take on kind of where we are with our understanding of the disease and how that's evolved over
the past few months. It's been amazing really how six months time we've learned quite a bit
and still every day we learn more. So at first it was built as a respiratory virus. And then
we learned that because it goes after the ACE2 receptor, it actually goes to many different
organs, especially the heart, kidneys, and to some extent, pancreatic and brain liver. So it turned
out that what was just a lung disease became complete body potential for this virus to have
its impact. And so the other thing that kind of been shocking is the spectrum here that you can
have people 30% or more who experience no symptoms whatsoever. And then you have 1% or less
that it can be fatal. So it's quite a spectrum. And then you know people who are this without
symptom group up to a half may even have internal damage or hurt that they don't even know about.
So for example with lung CT scan in four different series we've seen this evidence of lung effects
that they had no idea they had symptoms. So this is a really challenging virus. No wonder we
have a global pandemic because it is unique. It's a stealth spread but it can be fatal. And the
other thing I think that's becoming more evidence than the recent weeks is the cornicity issue.
A lot of people don't get fully recovered can linger for a long time. That may be part of the
immunologic reaction why people feel really washed out and you still have problems with breathing
and other issues. And so we're just starting to learn about that and not of course discouraging too.
Early on as the disease emerged and the scientific community and in particular the data science
and machine learning community heard about this. You know lots of folks wanted to jump in and
help understand this and people really struggle to make sense of data. I think my sense is that
we're still struggling. There are still lots of different representations, lots of challenges
with getting clean data but I'm curious your take on how data has impacted our understanding
of the disease in particular and what we've learned in the past six months.
Well we have learned in the United States does them have very good arms around their data
and that's been a more challenging. So most countries where there's a national data
dashboard we have nothing. The CDC basically didn't show up and there is this bootstrapping
COVID-19 tracking project that was developed by the Atlantic and volunteers and that's actually
collecting the data going to 56 different websites every day to try to call the number of people
who are tested at the results and whatever they can get which is limited. So we don't know at any
given moment how many people are in the ICU, how many ICU beds are available in hospitals and
you know the demographics and so many things. We just have a sense that the people were affected,
infected, have shifted to a younger group since the reopening started to begin but we're in a
country that's leading the epicenter of this pandemic and it just shows you how we don't have
the data, the input. You've got some real powerful output. Are you finding that are there any
particular analyses that you've seen emerged that you're finding particularly helpful in understanding
the epidemic? Well one of the most impressive things is that during this surge that started
you know in mid-June in the US where we have this extraordinary steep slope of new cases. Now you know
well 40,000 and even today during testimony Tony Fauci mentioned it could get up to 100,000
but today we keep seeing a reduction in the death rate which is an incredible divergence
that's poorly understood. That could just represent a significant lag. It also could represent
that younger people are affected and they're now showing up in hospitals more and they may take
time to see that or for that to reverberate in their own communities but because of not having
data we're more hampered. We're compromised and understanding having an absolute analysis of
at a macro level that's quite important. Yeah. You've also been involved in some of the efforts
around contact tracing and wearables and other technological interventions to you know both
understand and treat maybe you can give us a lay of the land of you know what's what's happening
there. Starting with contact tracing and some of the the applications and implications.
Yeah so it's interesting contact tracing is being used now in many countries but it hasn't
been validated and so it requires a large portion of the people in that country or place to use it
but also because it can generate false positives it could create lots of issues on privacy and
confusion and so it's alluring from a clever technical standpoint of using smartphone
chirps to help alert people and try to prevent spread and as you well know we don't have enough
human contact tracing people so it could be a booster but it remained
unvalidated and has privacy concerns. Well we've been working with this digital surveillance
music smartwatches or fitness wristband and we have almost 40,000 people now in the US where we're
getting their continuous heart rate physical activity and they have it on during sleep we have
that both metrics and we already are seeing signals that we may be able to pick up
the cluster of people so we have all 50 states covered and as we get more and more people in
in hundreds of thousands and not millions we hopefully can stay ahead of the pandemic because
you hear task task tests but you can't test 330 million people no less once one off but on
our frequent basis so the digital continuous with recurrent neural network analytics to understand
where and when there may be a burden cluster and then do guided testing and conflict tracing
and isolation that we think could turn out to be a way to start to get some control of
an unambated unbridled or increasing cases which is accompanied now by increase in hospitalizations
in the state where this has been chiefly occurring. So this system that you're working on it's
not about contact tracing but about identifying the disease and individuals preemptively based
on different signals you're able to pick up from the smartwatches and fitness meters.
Right we have done that work with flu a flu like I almost published in
earlier this year that we could pick up flu throughout five states exclusively well better than
other CDC methods of today earlier and as accurate. So the hope is that we can use that but there
are other alternatives for there's some akinza smart thermometer that's out there in more
than a million Americans that take their temperature each day at least one and that's been helpful
to localize the tensile cluster there's also you know things like the URA rain which has got
lots of metrics that it captures through the rain chips inside the interlining so
orthogonal data from many sources could be helpful but the reason why we picked the smartwatches
we had published data and because a hundred million people in the US already have a fitness
band or a smartwatch so it's passive and we could get a large number quickly and of course
they relies on AI analytics to help localize where there is a potential issue it's not good at
individual level it's really only useful to look at a special temporal geographic type
caution okay when you say it's not good at an at an individual level meaning are you trying to
identify the individuals that may have the disease based on the the data that you're collecting
and what way if if you are doing that and what ways that not useful for the individuals it just
not accurate enough to a signal for that individual to go do take action yeah exactly so let's
say Sam you had an increased rest in heart rate which is the chief metric and it went out from
your normal just from 60 to 70 okay and your step decrease and your sleep increase those would
all be the three parameters that might forget you had 2019 but on an individual singlet on it
we you know you could have many others but if I found out that all your neighbors all your
networks were showing similar signs I'd say that's a signal so it's just not sharp enough I'd
add a one to you choosing you got a pretty coarse metrics to to look at for an individual
exactly or some of the are there you know technologies out there and some of these smartwatches
that you know can give you more granularity in terms of you know temperature I you know what would
you what would you wish you had access to to make it more useful for an individual well if we got
both body temperature accurately and oximetry the oxygen saturation of the body which now
the smartwatches have or are can activity we we could probably start getting more granular and
and get signals that would be useful potentially at an individual level but a lot of people never
have fever at least half or not more and oximetry the oxygen saturation you know that's not
going to drop down until the disease or the infection is further along but what's interesting
you bring up here is that because the asymptomatic carrier rate is high 30% or we think that
third people will have defines will have the higher heart rate because we know some of them have internal
hits or by ordinance at least the lungs so we think we'll be able to pick those up and that's
going to be important because otherwise these people would never know that they had an infection
yeah they were I think that the stats early on we're saying that or the stories early on we're
talking about folks we're losing I forget the specific percentage of lung capacity long term
even post disease and I think I always took that to be you know those folks that were you know
seriously affected and ended up on respiratory you know ventilators and the like
is what you're saying that you know even the asymptomatic folks will have that kind of
long-term effect do we know kind of the magnitude of potential long-term effects or the range of
long-term effects for the you know this huge population of asymptomatic folks yeah we don't know
unfortunately because we only had those four series they did the CAT scans of the lungs they
didn't repeat any CAT scans we do know that their lung abnormalities were similar to those who had
symptoms and we don't even have enough follow-up on the people with symptoms to know how soon
that that resolved most likely it resolves in most people but there may be some group we don't
know how frequent where it becomes an enduring issue and there isn't complete resolution and that
may be partly mediated by the immune response that it just is not either sufficient or hyperactive
you know there's many different kind of responses here it's the way people handle this virus is
so heterogeneous yeah yeah in your book you talk quite a bit about deep phenotyping kind of this
really deep understanding of the individual on you know lots of different levels
you know how far have we gone with kind of trying to you know correlate some of that phenotyping data
to information about COVID to understand you know what might make someone the asymptomatic
having asymptomatic response versus what makes someone likely to you know have a more serious
response yeah that's a great question because is it just viral load or does some of that come from
the phenotype of the individual yeah it does come from the phenotype as well there's been now
several genomic studies getting back to my grounding when I the air add particularly
like to work in but there's been the so-called genome-wide association studies where you don't
consume anything you just let the genome talk and there's been two of those and they both
found that the blood type ABL blood type that the A type is got some intrigues risk perhaps 20 or
30 percent whereas all blood type has protective effects and there's also a locust on chromosome 3
which is many different immune receptor genes that lights up it's even that's even more prominent
so there are some genomic aspects of each of that that modulate our response there's immune
aspects that are tied to that but also in addition to that that are starting to show up we have
seen like for example there's a very rare syndrome in kids like Kawasaki's disease that is a tie to
the at least some of the kids have an immune system abnormality because 70 some of
some of these people of the kids that get this are actually very healthy they never had any preexisting
condition but there's something the glitch in their immune response whereas a hyper immune response
that a couple of weeks after an infection leads to their rare condition of multi-system and
inflammatory syndrome so-called MIS-C and this is a significant can be fatal in two to four
percent of children even though it's very rare so there's a continuum here and it is not just the
virus not just the setting but also the host the the individual you think about kind of where we've
come over the past six months and the the role that artificial intelligence could play
you know what are some of the things that you know you'd love to see or you know will expect
to see or think that um you know are missing in the way we've applied AI to to this particular
situation well we touched on one which is better detection before an outbreak really gets legs
and now I think we will be able to get to that it's already getting to be the case in Germany
and in China we're behind my we're behind everything here but hopefully we'll get there
another important application Sam is can people who are presenting to an emergency room
or telemedicine at their sick and then confirmed that they have an infection and should we
admit them to the hospital or let them stay home and I think we're going to see algorithms that
will help guide that because we want to keep people out of the hospital so they can stay in the
convenience their home with their family loved ones and also the expense of the hospital and hospitals
in some areas are already maximizing capacity so I think AI is going to help that we've got to get
validated algorithms to prove it yeah uh the other area that I think that's got lots of potential
is to support clinicians so that for example right now um there's some difficult choices like
should you use a blood pen should you put a patient on a ventilator and if we can get all the data
of not the individual but also as new data comes in from literature all a process we can help
clinicians to make better decisions more accurate interpretations of the overwhelming data that
they're doing. One of the conversations in the book that I thought was most interesting was
and when you started to you were kind of bringing in this concept of system one and system two
thinking and how you were just talking about you know what happens when a patient presents in a
hospital uh how a lot of the success of medicine if you can put it like that is based on kind of
system one immediate responses and how a lot of medical training is honing that you know system one
response uh and you know there's a clear parallel between that system one thinking and uh what
machine learning is currently good at what deep learning is currently good at Andrew Wang says
you know machine learning is best for anything that a computer can do or that a human can do and
less than a second kind of these snap uh judgment and responses um yeah I was wondering if you
can elaborate a little bit on um you know this whole idea of system one and system two and the
interplay with AI yeah I know it's really important and fundamental actually I hear because
doctors make a lot of mistakes by reflexive thinking instead of reflective system two thing
uh Danny Connerman kind of nailed it in terms of that our brain makes reflex
judgments and decisions and in medicine that may not be good for person health
in fact it leads to a lot of diagnostic inaccuracy whereas if we had the machine support
then it would be more time to switch in to reflective system two thinking and get more
accurate so you have both a combined effect of the machine processing data for that person
but also the gift of time to think which is not enough of in medicine today that's the ultimate
gift that AI can bring to medicine is the gift of time. There was some data points that you presented
that's if I interpreted them correctly seem to be suggesting that when doctors actually do think
they're uh the accuracy of their diagnoses decreases that seem to suggest that you know that when
they you know hone their kind of reflexive you know thinking and kind of make these immediate
judgments that they they tended to make better diagnoses am I interpreting that you know those
data points correctly and and how does you know how do we kind of integrate that with you know
giving doctors more time to to think about um you know what they're seeing. Well I think that's
a little off Sam I think that what the data showed for example if as a doctor I keep if I think
of the diagnosis in the first five minutes in working with a patient I think of it on a list
then the accuracy is pretty good but if it doesn't come to mind the accuracy dropped off from
you know whatever 90 plus percent to 20 some percent and so the point thing is humans are biased
and so are of course all conditions of caring for patients and we have 180 different types of
bias yep and so that bias it's in the way of that reflexive thinking and so when you have support from
validated algorithms that can you know handle this data and you can provide that oversight for
example in that example that example I just gave you might not have included in your mental
list the diagnosis the patient actually had is you just didn't come to mind but you got prompted
because the algorithm suggested that there's a probability of whatever 20 x percent
this dialogue should be considered and then now you're thinking about that it never was in your
mind so that's uh I think availability bias and I think that's this one example of many whereby
you seem support and a human oversight is the best combination. You're thinking about medicine
you know more broadly you know where what are you excited about seeing in terms of AI since you've
you know started researching this and wrote the book. Well there's kind of a short term and a
longer term expectation short term the accuracy of image interpretation should go way up I mean
it really has all the potential and we'll see it not just in radiology dermatology pathology all
aspects of medicine cardiology and what's interesting is that the mode for the randomized trials
have been a gastroenterology to pick up pilots randomized throughout six of them and ophthalmology
is leading the charge in terms of every potential serious eye condition to be better diagnosed with
support through deep neural networks so that's the short term and I'll add in that short term
getting rid of keyboard in the doctor's office then it depends on that is using the voice and
synthetic notes instead of having to lose that intimate eye contact it's vital for the human
connection and that's a segue to the longer term which is restoring the medical
intimate relationship with trust the human connection between patients and their doctors and
nurses and that's where I think we have this unparalleled opportunity if we work on it and the
premise there is that you know by you know shifting from a keyboard oriented interaction to
voice the doctor can be more present with the patient and establish that trust or do you see a
more direct role for AI in that establishing that trust relationship well you certainly brought
up one key way which is the ability to actually talk to patients be with them have a presence
but we also review the fact that it's impossible for any person now any doctor or nurse clinician
to review all that data and you know use instead of that time where it would detract from the patient
interaction that would be processed and crystallized for that condition but the other part that we
haven't brought up really is the patient economy so most of the common diagnoses like a skin
rash or a lesion an ear infection in the child a urinary tract infection heart rhythm
abnormalities both on and on AI tool will give patient a doctorless diagnostic capability they've
never had before we've already started seeing that so we can shift the interaction between
doctors and patients the more important matters like the treatment for that condition that
was diagnosed by them or things that are of important nature like a new diagnosis of cancer
neurodegenerative disease or heart disease something like that so the whole idea is that we can
use this foundation of analytic to restore the immunity in those machines keep getting smarter
hopefully humans can get more human. We first started seeing a lot of the successes around
machine assisted or machine identification of things in medical imagery a lot of the media
and conversations were around AI replacing radiologists and the like I think in I hope and you
know the community of this podcast where beyond that but do you feel like as a broader community
you know we're beyond that are we still you know struggling with this kind of either or
relationship between physicians and AI and technology in general really great question
the problem is that we're still in the mindset like when Gary Pesborough played big blue
and chess and we're still there almost all the papers that come out comparing the algorithmic
versus the doctor rather than the deep neural network data versus the combination of that and
stuff so whether it's radiologic images or pathology specimens or whatever it is God Sam we don't
we're not in the mode generally there's been a few papers that looked at that but most of them are
painting machines versus man which is the wrong that's not wait it's going to go all night
in the future so we're still stuck in that mode of the classic I guess competition and it's
silly eventually we'll get beyond that but though there's very limited studies that have really
looked at the way it stimulates how medicine will ultimately be practiced when we're at full
machine support yeah there was one that comes to mind out of one of the medical centers in Boston
I believe they were looking at breast cancer imagery and this was you know three four years ago
I was one of the first ones that looked at doctor versus you know algorithm versus doctor plus
algorithm and it was you know their result was clear that the doctor you know and the algorithm
performed much better than either alone has you've said that you know there haven't been enough
studies there but has that have we seen any replication of that across different you know
types of images and diseases yes the problem is most of the studies that have been done now hundreds
of them are retrospective okay so what they're doing they're just going back and they have pristine
data set and then they're testing their and validating their algorithm and saying well look this
works as well or better often claiming superior performance the only way to really do it right
as you're getting to which is showing that the combination is better than machine long or the
doctoral is a prospective study and there are some of those perhaps you know more than 10 now
approaching 20 but those are much fewer and far between that they're just we need more of those
just like we need more randomized trials and it's all the way is it just a matter of time or is it
uh the cost and you know complexity or other factors associated with these prospective studies
well the convenience is that there's these large annotated data set what it's shifted for AIDS
or cardiograms or mammograms as you mentioned and they and skin regions they just get used
over and over again whereas to do it right you've got to have developed your own new large
annotated data sets and that is what the challenge is that you as you touch on its expense it takes time
it has been done uh but you know I think we need more of that uh that'll help with you
mm-hmm are there any particular studies that you are currently tracking that you know seem you
know interesting and promising well we're just about to start one where we think it's exciting
about diabetes okay believe it or not if you're a diabetic now the only algorithm you have to
support you is your glucose is going up or down if you have a glucose sensor which is pretty
incredible it's 2020 I think and that's the best we can do right so we're working on a multi-dimensional
prospective study and a thousand people with type 2 diabetes with a glucose sensor taking pictures
of everything they eat and drink getting their gut microbiome their genome their physical activity
their sleep their stress you know everything you can think of and developing an algorithm to help
them manage based on their data their glucose regulation and we know that certain foods have a
completely disparate response and on an individual basis so we hope that we can do is provide each
person in the future as this ideally is validated and expanded much better than your glucose is
going up or down yeah I mean it's just it's just incredible and that's just kind of where the field
is right now we're we're at a primitive state where we have so much vast potential in front of us
yeah you your example kind of points out this idea of personalized medicine that has been I
think that probably grew out of the the work in genomics 10 20 years ago and I'm curious your
assessment of how close we've gotten to that or you know where we've we've had success with that
it certainly doesn't seem from my perspective as a layperson and a consumer of medicine that
when I'm going to the doctor my experience is particularly personalized based on you know genome
and and all these things in spite of the fact that a lot of the things that we said we would need
in order to get there the the cost and time of doing a whole sequence on an individual you know
we've achieved a lot of those milestones you know what you what and where are we and what's
lacking yeah well it's funny you mentioned that because last Friday during 26 with the 20th
anniversary of the human the genome sequence graph you know the White House the whole fanfare
and those 20 years has been remarkable progress but not in the things that you're getting at which
is rare doesn't is unknown to these is in cancer that is the sequence helping to guide therapies
many patients in people in women who are pregnant to help guide whether they made the harboring
serious chromosomal abnormalities in the fetus without having to go through amniocentesis
there's been select major transformative progress but it hasn't been made and as you said the
sequence can be done for thousand dollars which is still expensive but compared to a lot of other
tests we do in medicine like cat scans in MRI it's not that crazy but it isn't accepted by the
medical community yet there's still lots of resistance and unfortunately that is holding us back
and also we don't interpret the genome adequately because we need hundreds of millions if not
billions to be able to get the most extract the most information from a genome for that person
so we're still on that kind of early stage we're only limited health systems have started to
implement it like geising or in Pennsylvania but most places are not using dynamics on a
wide scale basis yet they're holding back part of it's been the cost and the reimbursement
of lack of education of clinicians and a bunch of other factors but eventually I think we'll get
there but I have to agree with you that a 20 years post genome sequence in some respects it's
been disappointing when you say millions or billions you know we'll need millions or billions
what are you referring to samples or something else yes if we had millions of people
sent to people sequence and then with their phenotype that would follow because your phenotype
today may change you may have a heart attack or you may have a new diagnosis of whatever
so if we want to have all that data things like your response to medication and all sorts of things
if we had a common data set with that large number of genome with the accompanying
technical information then it becomes more valuable then it gets to mind a dream state or fantasy
thing of the planetary health system where you have a digital twin infrastructure so let's say you
got sick Sam and I can take your data put it into the resource find it six twin of your that
match on every possible way which way and nearest neighbor analysis and then I get
saying hmm this is your best treatment is your best outcomes or I can say here's how we prevent
the condition but we are a long ways from that we can't even get the resource really built
uh no less all the countries to work together to develop this planetary learning health system
but theoretically possible and we are seeing it starting in areas in specific areas like cancer
hopefully we'll see it much more in general in the future yeah that brings some on you know as
did our conversation about contact tracing earlier on you know issues around privacy and others
that you need to be accounted for in you know realizing visions like like yours anything interesting
happening in that space yeah it's funny you have to love that too um kypholini and I
published a paper on this nature biotent it takes the planet and basically we wouldn't
believe in and talk about this this planetary health system or this you know massive information
ignored without iterating AI so the data never left the place and basically you know the algorithm
can't do the data to preserve the privacy and security and homomorphic encryption so the new tools
are now available that weren't necessarily refined to more recently that are going to help
achieve this ideal of privacy protecting privacy uh and uh having the data in such a state that
the chances of having like we have today uh breaches and hacks and all sorts of
of course nature of uh important precious data that we can avoid that so that's the whole that
will employ these new methods that are actually pretty exciting because without them these idea
would be ill-conceived great great all right thanks so much for taking the time to chat with us
and share a bit about your perspective on uh the field and the pandemic any parting thoughts
or words for our audience no i really enjoyed the conversations and we've had so many great
questions and hopefully that listeners will get some ideas about where the field can go
because it really is exciting uh and it could be the most important impact on medicine going
forward the likes of which we've not ever seen before it may not be seen for generations
today absolutely thank you thank you all right everyone that's our show for today for more
information on today's show visit twomolai.com slash shows as always thanks so much for listening
and catch you next time