All right, everyone. I am here with Constantine Rush. Constantine is a PhD student at ETH Zurich.
Constantine, welcome to the podcast. Thanks for having me here, Sam.
Hey, I'm really looking forward to digging into our conversation, which will focus on a couple of
your recent papers, both of them focused on RNNs. But before we jump into that, I'd love to have
you take a few minutes and kind of share your background. How did you get started working in
machine learning? Yes, absolutely. So actually, my background is mathematics. So I did my
bachelor's in pure mathematics in Germany at the University of Bonn, which is a kind of nice place
for mathematics in Germany. Then I did applied mathematics for my masters in the UK.
And now I'm at ETH. I'm actually affiliated with the mathematics department here.
And I'm doing my PhD in applied mathematics. And I'm focusing mostly on machine learning,
of course. And also not only on classical machine learning, but also on machine learning for
scientific computing, you know, to solve physical systems and so on. And yeah, so how did I get
interested in machine learning? I think actually two years ago, I didn't even really know what
machine learning was. So I really was interested, you know, in this classical applied mathematics,
like doing numerics, solving partial differential equation, equations,
domestic differential equations, and so on. And I even worked for almost three years for the
German aerospace center. And there I focused basically as a student researcher, and there I basically
focused on this classical scientific computing problems, you know, as I said, solving PDE,
and so on, and geometric problems. And then during my time in the UK, when I did my masters in
applied mathematics, I did basically two really nice courses. The first one was about dynamical
systems, so nonlinear dynamics and chaos. And the second one was computational cognitive neuroscience,
which was super awesome. And there was actually some kind of connection because in this computational
cognitive neuroscience course, we took a look at, you know, mathematical models from neurobiology.
So for instance, at the Fitsunagumo model, maybe you heard of it, probably your audience had.
So it's basically the mathematical model of the firing of the action potential of a single
biological neuron. And you know, you can describe it more or less as a so-called relaxation oscillator,
and you can do all this kind of mathematical theory around that. And it was just super interesting.
And so far, it had nothing to do with classical machine learning, you know, like classifying
endless digits and so on. But then I started a project and I was searching for some literature
about this connection between neurobiology and dynamical systems. And then I found a lot of
very recent papers about dynamical systems theory in actual classical machine learning,
meaning, for instance, using dynamical systems to construct architectures, deep learning architectures,
RNNs or feed forward neural networks and so on. And I was directly hooked and I really liked
these papers. And then yeah, I just started to read more, read more. I had my own ideas. I tried a
bit and here. So that's basically my background. Awesome. Awesome. We should maybe kind of establish
the definitions. When you say dynamical systems, what exactly does that entail?
Yeah. So it's basically systems, which are time dependent. So basically you have two kind of
systems, a continuous time systems and discrete time systems. And mostly in physics and biology,
we use continuous time systems where you know, your time parameter is actually an element of some
interval 0 to capital T, for instance. And you look at so-called ordinary differential equations
or systems of ordinary differential equations. And I think they're quite famous. I mean,
they're also used already directly machine learning like this neural ODE stuff and so on.
And then there's discrete time dynamical systems where your time is this is more like an
iterator. It's not continuous anymore. And so you don't have an ordinary differential equation
anymore, but you just have some recurrent update of your so-called hidden state. So of the one
you're propagating forward and time basically. Cool. So you took these classes when you were
working on your masters in the UK and your current work is focused on the same field. Did you
come to the PhD with these ideas, with ideas for applying dynamical systems and oscillators to
RNNs or is that something that you developed more recently? No, actually I already had this
kind of ideas before I came to ETH. But I started more or less, I had to pause them for a bit
because I came here and I first focused on some more mathematics based papers and problems. So we
did some sampling related kind of problems which are only applied in scientific computing and not
in classical machine learning. But it was all the time curious and I tried so many things in my
free time on the weekend and I had really good results. And so I talked to my supervisor,
C.D. Mischra, and we decided to go a bit deeper and really try to figure out what is the reason
for these good results and what is it modeling at all and so on. Great. So let's start talking
about the motivation for the paper. What's the broad problem that you are trying to solve here?
Okay, here. So the motivation was that for recurrent neural networks, so all we do is we
suggest a new RNN architecture, recurrent neural network architecture, and the big problem for
recurrent models RNNs is that it's quite hard to learn very long time dependencies and that means
okay, for RNNs, if you apply them to data, it's always sequential data. So there's some kind
of sequential internal dependencies in your underlying data. And for instance, if you have
internal dependencies for long range, so for instance at the beginning of your sequence,
you have important information which is needed at the very end in order to classify the sequence
for instance correctly, that we would call a long time dependency. And now it also depends on how
long this dependency is of course, right? So RNNs are typically very, very good for sequence length
of 100, 200. If you go to a thousand, it's already super hard and not mentioning doing 10,000
or whatever. And the problem behind that is basically the way you train your recurrent neural
network. So what you do is you use backpropagation through time where you basically unfold your RNN
in time. And while you backpropagate the errors back in time more or less. And if you would write
down the full gradient you're interested in computing, then you would see that there is one term,
which is basically just the influence of a hidden state from a previous time, let's say at time k,
on some hidden state at a later time, let's say a hidden state n. And so it's basically partial
derivative of your hidden state with respect to this hidden state of the previous time. And now if
you look at this term and you basically apply the chain will all over again, you will have a long
product. And this product has basically n minus k plus one factors in it. And so if you imagine
if on average these these factors are a bit less than one, let's say they're 0.9, then it's
basically just 0.9 to the power of n minus k plus one. And if n minus k is very long, very big,
then you just go to 0 exponentially fast or you go to infinity if it's a bit bigger than one
on average, right? If it's like one dot one on average, then you explode. And so this is called
the Wenishing and exploding gradient problem because exactly of that. And it may sound, well,
okay, then just stabilize this gradient in some way. But it's actually not that easy. So of course,
if for instance, if you consider your recurrent model as just the identity, right, then your
gradient will just be the identity matrix. Great. Now we're super stable, right? But we learn
nothing basically. And so that's the point. So basically it's twofolded. On the one hand side,
you want to have gradient stability. So the gradient doesn't blow up or Wenishing. But at the same
time, you also want to be expressive that you can learn actual interesting data, which the identity
map won't be helpful for, right? So we have some success with tech architectures like LSTM's
and GRUs and addressing this. Absolutely. Absolutely. So LSTMs, what they do, they use some kind of
gating mechanism. And if you carefully write down the gradient there, you will see that you
actually have a chance to mitigate the Wenishing gradient problem. However, the exploding
gradient will might still happen. So the gradient can still explode for LSTMs and for GRUs.
And there's a lot of papers where they have used LSTMs for long-range long-term dependencies.
And they kind of start to fail at a few hundred like 1,000. So if the sequence has like a length
of 1,000, it's kind of tricky for the LSTM to learn that. But LSTMs are super expressive,
so that I can say already from my experience. And I think that's one of the reasons why LSTMs
are still the most used are in an architecture. Maybe, I don't know, maybe the most used architecture
at all, I don't know. They are quite popular. Absolutely. And so, so you've got this, this exploding
vanishing gradient problem with long-term sequences. You know, there are things like LSTMs,
but they're not perfect. And so your approach is inspired in some ways by the year, you know,
what you learned about the neurons and the oscillators and the neurons. Tell us, you know,
how it connects to what you observe there. Yeah, absolutely. So our approach was really
inspired by neurobiology. As I said before, if you take a look at the dynamical systems,
which model this kind of firing of the action potential, you have this kind of oscillatory
behavior, right? It's actually a relaxation oscillator where you basically accumulate your
stimulus. And then if you surpass a certain threshold, you just fire and then you relax.
And so you have this periodically, this oscillatory behavior more or less. And you see also this kind
of oscillatory behavior. If you, for instance, consider full parts of the brain, for instance,
the hippocampus, they're people call it, I mean, I'm not a neurobiologist, I can just tell you
what I read. And they call it also hippocampus oscillations. And you can, they're actually very
beautiful papers where they measure these kind of oscillations in vivo and in vitro. And yeah,
that was basically the motivation. So something which makes kind of sense in neurobiology,
but we don't try to exactly mimic this kind of behavior, right? So that's just the abstract
essence. And now we just forget about all this complicated underlying biological behavior.
And we just take the message, okay, using oscillators might be a good idea.
Yeah. Yeah. And that's what we did. And I think if you think about oscillators, I mean,
this kind of harmonic oscillators where you have some linear combination of sine and cosine
as a solution, it's super stable, right? If your amplitude of the oscillations doesn't blow up
or vanish, it's it's perfectly stable. And also, I mean, if you take the gradient, you again
have some kind of, if you take the credit of sine, you have cosine and vice versa, right?
And so even the gradient is very nice behaved or you would expect that it's very nice behaved.
And coming from this neurobiological background, we were also kind of hoping that, you know,
it's the kind of expressive because if that's something you can find more or less in nature
and in neurobiology, then why not try it, right? And so we came up with this coupled oscillatory
RNN architecture, which is basically a system of ordinary of second order ordinary differential
equations. So second order ODE's modeling these kind of coupled oscillators, where we also have
two to additional controlling terms in there. So as I said before, if your amplitude goes to infinity
or goes to zero, then we basically got nothing, right? So we have to make sure that they are also
kind of nice behaved. And we can do that actually by adding some some controlling terms in there,
controlling the damping. So that means like over time, how much do you, do you damp your oscillations?
And and a controlling parameter for the frequency of the system. And yeah, in the end, it's it's
really just just a damped controlled and coupled oscillator. And we discretize that with a so-called
implicit explicit discretization scheme and IMAX scheme, just to make sure because we are not
working with the continuous formulation of the system, but with the discrete time formulation of
the system. And to make sure that we have all these structure preserving behavior in our discrete
time system now, we use some kind of well-behaved numerical discretization scheme for ODE's,
which is just this IMAX scheme. And then we come up with this discretized ODE, which we interpret
as an RNN. And yeah. When you describe the oscillators as coupled, what exactly does that mean?
Okay. Where are they coupled? Yeah. So the system has many dimensions, right? So basically,
each dimension corresponds to one neuron in the recurrent titan state of the RNN. And so typically,
for for normal problems, you use like 128 dimensions or 256 dimensions, which would mean you have in
your, we are only talking for one layer RNNs right now, right? And so you typically have 128 hidden
neurons or 256 hidden neurons. And coupled means that the information from one dimension can go
also in the other dimension. So that means basically the hidden weight matrix we have is not
sparse or has any any weird structure. It's it's it's a simple dance matrix visit.
And you say you you have this system of of coupled oscillators. You write those as ODE's. And then you
express those as an RNN. How does that last stage work? Is that a kind of straightforward
expression of the ODE as RNN or is there, you know, are there work or tricks that you need to do to
to be able to do that? Yeah, that's actually a really good question. So no, it's it's not
so at least to me, it was not directly totally clear how to interpret that as an RNN. And there are
different choices actually to do because for instance, you have something like a time step for
your discretization scheme, right, some some kind of DT, which is just a small, small parameter.
And the question is how to treat this parameter, for instance, is it a hyperparameter of your
RNN architecture? Do you want to train it? You if you want to train it, you have to constrain it in
some way because it shouldn't be too big and it shouldn't be negative because you don't have negative
time, right? You want to be have something bigger than zero, but you also don't want to be too big.
So there are actually many, many questions. And well, we went for the easiest first answer,
I guess, we just treat them as a hyperparameter. And also our two controlling parameters I just
mentioned are two hyperparameters. So in the end, we have an RNN with three hyperparameters,
which you do not really need. So you can actually treat them as trainable parameters too,
but you have to constrain them in certain ranges. As I said before, for instance, by using
sigmodel activation function, or really you, because also this controlling parameters should be
just non-negative or positive. Let's say they should be positive.
So you have your system expresses an RNN and then what next? It sounds like maybe the next step
was doing some benchmarking against existing approaches for RNNs.
Yeah, not directly though. So first, all I said so far was some kind of intuition that it might
be stable. Also, the credience might be well-behaved, but the key feature of our, or the key goal of
our paper is actually to show, to mathematically prove now that this gradient is actually stable.
So we have two to main propositions. You can also call them theorems if you want to,
which we actually fully prove. And the first one is basically showing that the gradient can't
explode, giving some assumptions. And now many people, I guess in the audience, will be like,
okay, assumptions. Now it's not going to be met. And you know, everything was garbage. But in this
case, we can actually check these assumptions that they are very mild. So we actually, we check
them for each experiment we did. And they were always satisfied during the whole training procedure.
So it's nothing crazy. It just means that your weights of your RNN are not too big. I mean,
in the end, if they go to infinity, then what's the point of using this RNN? So that's a reasonable
assumption. And with this assumption, we can actually show that the gradient is bounded from above.
That's the first theorem. And the second theorem was maybe a bit harder even to show.
It's some kind of asymptotic expansion of this gradient, which shows that we have some
terms, some sort of asymptotic expansion means that we have some expansion in some orders.
And we choose, in this case, to use the time step dt, which is quite small. And we had some
expansion of orders in this small time step dt. And we can see that the leading order of this
expansion is of order, I think time step to the power of three over two, something like this.
And this is actually independent of your sequence length. So it doesn't matter anymore if you have
a sequence of length 10 or of length 10,000. This leading order term will always be there and
will always be of the same order. So that means that the wenshin gradient problem is actually
mitigated and for all sequence lengths, basically. And so to recap that part,
essentially, because you've got this specific form of RNN based on the coupled oscillators,
you're then able to produce some closed form bounds on the, is it the convergence of the gradient?
And that requires some assumptions that you make. And these are assumptions, they're not constraints,
they're just assumptions. And by observation, you've not seen them being violated in kind of normal
use of the RNN. Exactly. Yeah, absolutely. Yeah. And maybe one more point because it was actually
quite interesting. So these two propositions, we proved in the full discrete case. So for the real
RNN, because if you go discrete, some wild things can happen. So it's always a bit tougher to prove
the discrete tastes and not only the continuous case. And so that's actually the case of the RNN.
And interestingly, we also did the continuous case. And for that, we only can
bound the gradient from above. So we can mitigate the exploding gradient problem. But because we
had this expansion in this time step, right? And in the continuous case, you go with your time step
to zero, because you want to be continuous in some way. We don't have this kind of feature anymore.
So that's really the mitigation of the Wenzhen gradient problem is really a feature of the
discretization and not of the oscillatory dynamics anymore, which I thought was quite interesting.
And so I'm so very curious how this, what kind of result you saw and how it compares from a
performance perspective? Yeah, that's yeah, that's even more interesting. That's true.
Because if you have a good theory, okay, that's nice, but it also should work in real life, right?
We have things like LSTMs that we know how to use and they work pretty well.
And so the question is, we've got, like you said, you've got theories on the bounds of the gradients here,
but is it useful? Yeah, absolutely. So we applied it to many long-term dependency benchmarks.
So the typical benchmarks, for instance, the first one, which I really liked was, and it's already
quite old, so it's the adding problem. And it was first proposed in the original LSTM paper, actually,
and it's just a synthetic sequential, no, it's actually regression. And the idea here is that you
have sequences of arbitrary length, and they're two-dimensional, and the first dimension are just
uniform random numbers. And the second dimension are all zeros, except for two positions,
they're set to one, and these positions are chosen randomly, also uniform randomly,
and they are chosen in both half of the sequence. And now the goal of the RNN,
especially to the output should be the two random uniform numbers of the first dimensions
at the position indicated by the ones in the second dimension. And so it's just adding them
together. So they call it adding, and the nice part here is that we can, you know, use sequence
length of 100, we can use 1,000, and we can make it harder, harder, harder. And actually, we tried
until a sequence length of 5,000. I think, actually, I've not seen that before in another paper,
so normally what you do is you try 50, 100, 200, 500, something like this. Some people go up to 1,000,
and you can see that, for instance, LSTMs, they already fail at 500, 750, so they are not
able to converge anymore, so they can't effectively learn this kind of problem. And for corn,
we actually had that, even in the case for 5,000, you get more or less direct convergence,
which is really nice, yeah. Yeah, I really like it. Any interesting observations in terms of
computational complexity with this approach? Yes. Yeah, so efficiency, yeah, the question is
in this task, actually, how long do you try, so how long do you let the RNN model learn, right?
So if I'm saying LSTM fails for 500, it doesn't mean if you do maybe a million iterations,
learning steps, it might converge, who knows, right? And the interesting part really was here
that you need maybe, I don't know, in terms of hundreds, we needed maybe 10 of them, and we tried
LSTMs at least for 600 hundreds, so for 60,000 learning steps, and it did not converge at all,
and also the other important architectures, like this exponential RNN, which is basically some
kind of unitary RNN, which comes from the idea that you want to constrain your hidden to hidden
structure, and all these kind of famous architectures, they did not work so well, especially in the
very, very long case, so that was actually quite nice. But of course, it's just a synthetic
test, right? It's just a synthetic benchmark, so maybe no one cares about this in the end,
so you have to try more real world data, of course, and maybe a second one, which was quite interesting,
was something like, and that's not a long-term dependency task anymore, because what I said
at the very first beginning, that okay, you want to have credit instability, you want to learn
long-term dependencies, but you also want to be expressive, right? You want to learn complicated
problems, and so we tried this task from, it's basically human action recognition, it's
basically on a smartphone with the sensors measured six different activities, like standing up,
walking, running, something like this, and the idea is that you have some time series measured
from your sensors over time on your Samsung S3, I guess, was it? And so in the end, you want to
classify, based on these action, action time series, what the people have done, and even there,
we got extremely good results. I mean, it's not a huge benchmark, so it's hard to say it was
outperforming everything, what is out there, but it was at least outperforming everything we were
aware of, so all the papers that have done that, we were outperforming them, which was quite nice.
Awesome, awesome. You're working on a follow-on paper to the corn paper. Can you tell us a little
bit about that one? Yeah, so the follow-up is called Unicorn, but with a double N in the end,
so it's really like a neural network, and it stands for undamped independent controlled
oscillatory RNNs. It was kind of chosen, such that we have this kind of nice Unicorn name,
you know, but that's, so the idea here is that instead of using coupled oscillators,
we first uncoupled them. And so basically, if you have heard of this independent RNN,
where they instead having a hidden to hidden weight matrix, which is just the full,
hidden dimensions, time-hidden dimensions, dense matrix, you just have a vector,
and you just multiply it. So then you don't have any interconnection between the different
neurons anymore, between the different hidden neurons, or in terms of dynamical systems,
you don't have any interconnections between the different dimensions. So in the end,
what you do is you just solve for each dimension, you solve an independent system, you don't even
have to do it on the same computer. So that was one of the points, so you can solve one dimension
on this computer and another dimension on the next computer. And because of this kind of
independency, and we are undamped, so we don't have some damping term in there anymore,
we can show that this system is actually a Hamiltonian system. And if you discretize these
kind of systems with some symplectic integrators from Hamiltonian mechanics, also people in
molecular simulations are very interested in that because they model basically everything
with Hamiltonian systems. And so the numerics to use here is so-called symplectic integrators,
and you can show that you more or less end up if you integrate them with the discrete time
Hamiltonian, which is quite close to your actually continuous time Hamiltonian. And the nice feature
of Hamiltonian systems is that they are invertible in time. And that means now that, for instance,
if you train it with backpropagation through time, as I said, right at first you propagate
forward in time your input, and then you have at the end some output, and then for backpropagating,
you propagate this error back in time. And for that, you have to store each hidden state at every
time. And so you can backpropagate, but in this case, because it's invertible in time, you can
just store the last hidden state, and reconstruct these hidden states based on the last hidden state,
because it's perfectly invertible in time. And so you know, you kind of have the same memory
efficiency, like in neural ODEs, with the nice feature that you don't have to go continuous,
because for standard neural ODEs, it's only true if you're going with your time step to zero,
which can be very expensive. And I mean, on a digital computer, you can't go basically to zero,
but you always have some rounding errors and so on. And here we don't have any problem anymore.
We can even use the time step of 0.1, and it's still perfectly invertible. And so yeah,
it scales just perfectly. It's very memory efficient. And on top, because we have this kind of
independencies, as I said before, we don't have to train it on the same computer. And that makes a
lot of sense if you use it on GPUs directly, where you basically have an independent thread,
or you don't even need a thread, so it can be even threads of different blocks, which cannot
communicate with each other. And you can just train each independent dimension on an independent
thread, and just in the end, add everything together. And this is extremely fast. So
I actually did an experiment, and we have some some really efficient code on GitHub already.
You can check it out if you're interested in it. It's directly implemented in CUDA. So it's,
of course, it's using PyTorch, but it's some CUDA extension, where we really do this kind of
independent threading. And maybe it's interesting to hear, but on my local GPU, I had a speed up of
one epoch on sequential amnesty took me like half a day on the GPU using PyTorch for a
three layer unicorn, for instance. And with this CUDA extension, by really using this kind of
independency, I got speed up from half a day to half a minute. And so how is the
expressivity of the RNN impacted by the independence? Yeah, good question. We did some benchmarks,
so one of them, the problem for for expressivity is that you know, for credit and stability,
you can formulate it mathematically. You can say, okay, it should be in this in this range,
and it shouldn't blow up or go to zero. You can write it down. There's no problem with that,
but for expressivity, you know, what's the mathematical formulation of expressivity? So I don't
know any, I think what's maybe the closest to it is some kind of universality, right? If you can
prove universality, that's at least something you would need. It's absolutely not sufficient,
but it's at least necessary. So if you can show some kind of universality, that's that's nice.
But besides this, I'm not aware of any expressivity mathematical results. And so what you do is you
classify it more or less by empirical data. So you use some some benchmark, which people think
requires high expressivity. And if it performs well on that, you say, okay, it has high
expressivity. At least that was my impression. I'm, you know, happy to learn, maybe I was wrong,
and there's a nice mathematical formula for that, but I can't come up with one and I'm not aware
of any. And so we tried it on one benchmark, which is called IMDB, which is basically just
classifying its sentiment analysis. So you classify movie reviews from this IMDB database,
exactly. And that can be long, and that can also have long-term dependencies, right? I mean,
the front of the reviews would be, I don't know, some kind of irony thing. You know, I really love
this film. And then in the end, or this movie and in the end, you say, I love it because it sucks.
So you have some kind of long-term dependencies, but you also have high expressivity because
you do natural language processing. I mean, they're way better benchmarks for that, I guess, but it's
at least a start. And on that, we got quite good results. So it outperformed corn actually,
but we have to say we are using two layers for that. And for corn, we're only using one layer.
So it could also be a layer thing. But for this independent unicorn, you can't use one layer,
because then you really have no interdependencies. And you also struggle a lot. So this interdependencies,
you still have them, but they come from the input to hidden matrix. And so you basically
delay them by one layer. Do you know more or less what I mean? So you need at least two layers to
have some kind of interdependencies between the hidden neurons. Okay, awesome. Where do you see this
research going next? Yeah, so my personal big goal is to, you know, so far what we did was we have
some kind of great instability, which is great. We can learn long-term dependencies, but there's
a reason why people use LSTMs all the time, because they are just so expressive. And for instance,
if you if you try something like this PTB pantry bank language modeling task, where for instance,
you have some some Wall Street articles, I guess. And the the chart level would be that you read
in the sequence of the words of the characters. And you want to predict the next character,
basically, in the sequence. I mean, as humans, we are quite good in that, I guess. I mean, if I would
say to see the and then would say, okay, next comes an S to see this, for instance. So for us,
it's it's quite quite easy to do maybe, but for RNNs, it's quite hard, especially if they're not
expressive. And if you're honest and you try, you know, all these more or less famous long-term
dependency RNNs, they are not performing very well. So if you if you take a look at the metric they use,
then it's all the time way worse than LSTMs. So X, RNNs are worse, our corners worse or
unique corners worse. All these kind of nice nice RNNs, they suffer from limited expressivity. I
just want to be so honest, right? So I'm not saying that corn is like the best thing out there.
It's a silver bullet, use it all the time. No, there's a real use case for this. This is long-term
dependencies, but if you do like high crazy expressivity tasks where you don't require long-term
dependencies, then don't use it basically. And so the idea is that LSTMs are very strong in that,
but they suffer from not being very good at learning long-term dependencies to have something,
you know, which kind of bridges these two things, which kind of connects these two things. So
something which has good can learn long-term dependencies very efficiently, but at the same time
has high expressivity. And actually we are working on something like this. We are working with
the group in Berkeley right now, and maybe in a few months, you know, we will publish. Yeah,
yeah, then there will be some good news. I'm really motivated. I'm really thrilled about this
project. It's working really good. And yeah, that would be my ultimate goal in this kind of RNN
community. Oh, that's great. That's great. Well, Constantine, thanks so much for taking the time to
share a bit about what you're working on. Yeah, no worries. It was a pleasure being here. My pleasure.
Thank you. Bye-bye.