Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimmel Talk, the podcast where I interview
interesting people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
This is the third and final show in our series of podcasts from the recent Wrangle Conference.
As you might know, a few weeks ago I was in San Francisco for Wrangle, which is a great
little conference brought to you by our friends over at Cloud Era.
This is the second time I've attended a Wrangle, and each year it brings an interesting and
diverse community of data scientists to an intimate and informal setting for great talks
on real data science issues and projects, not to mention cowboy hats and barbecue.
If you haven't yet caught the first two episodes in our Wrangle series, Twimmel Talk No. 39
with Drew Conway and Twimmel Talk No. 40 with Sheriff Rao, you'll want to be sure to check
those out.
They're both great interviews and the intro to the first show in the series includes
important announcements about the series as well as our latest ticket giveaway, our online
research paper discussion group, and my email newsletter.
To show you're listening to now features my interview with Aaron Schelman. Aaron is a
statistician and data science manager with Zymergen, a company using robots and machine
learning to engineer better microbes.
If you're wondering what exactly that means and involves, I was too, and we talk about
it in the interview.
Our conversation focuses on Zymergen's use of a patchy airflow, an open source data management
platform originating at Airbnb.
Aaron and her team uses airflow to create reliable, repeatable data pipelines for their machine
learning applications, and we explore all that in the interview.
A quick note before we dive in, as is the case with my other field recordings, there's
a bit of unavoidable background noise in this interview, sorry about that.
And now on to the show.
Now we start by having you tell us a little bit about your background.
Sure.
So my background sort of at the intersection of computer science, statistics, and biology.
So I went to graduate school at the University of Michigan.
I did my masters in biostatistics, and then my PhD in bioinformatics.
So always kind of working at the intersection of data and biology, and when I graduated
sort of maybe counterintuitively, I came out to the West Coast, I live in Seattle, and
I worked at Nordstrom in Nordstrom technology.
Interesting.
Yeah.
And I was on a really cool team called the Data Lab there and built product recommendations
for Nordstrom.com.
Okay.
And then did a stint at AWS, and now I'm at Symargin.
Nice.
And what specifically do you do at Symargin?
Yeah.
So I was initially, I was the first data scientist at the company, and I was a data scientist
there for the better part of nearly two years, and then recently I've transitioned into
managing the data science group there.
And we're now eight people including myself, so a lot of growth since I started.
Okay.
So yeah.
So a friend of mine and a former, a previous podcast guest, Josh Blum, has said that the worst
job in the world is to be a company's first data scientist.
Do you agree with me?
That is a, there's a lot of truth to that.
It really depends, yeah, it depends on what you like.
So what I like about, so actually maybe surprisingly all of the jobs that I've had, I've been
the first onto that team, and that wasn't really on purpose, but what I like about it is
that you really have the ability to kind of structure what the goals and what the mission
is, who you hire and how you build out that team.
And I really enjoy that part of the job, sort of the higher level, maybe not so data-centric
parts of the job.
Okay.
And you definitely have that kind of stuff more available to you when you're the only
person on the team.
It hasn't been like building out a team from having that experience as being the very
first.
Does it change your perspective on team composition and how you build it out?
Yeah, it definitely changes your perspective because when you're the only person you're
quite resource-constrained, and so the hiring matters in some sense more than when you
have quite a bit more staff because every, you know, you double to two people that's
still quite, not very many people, and so it's really important that you get somebody
who has skills that complement your own or somebody who can teach you a lot of things
that you don't know to make everybody more productive.
So it's definitely a different experience than being in a big group with lots of people,
but I actually, I think I like it more.
I prefer it.
Okay.
Awesome.
Now, Zymergen, I'm betting is a company that not a lot of people in our audience know
about what does the company do?
Yeah.
We're a little bit different than, you know, the Airbnb's and the Facebook's and all
of those type of those companies, though we use a lot of Airbnb's technology, so kind
of like Airbnb for microbes, not really.
But yeah, so at Zymergen, what we're doing is we partner with companies who use industrial
fermentation to make materials and molecules, and so what we do is we operate, we optimize
strains, microbial strains, to be more efficient or more effective at producing molecules
of interest to our customers through fermentation.
So often these are companies who are already using fermentation at scale to produce molecules.
So it turns out-
I'm thinking beer.
Yeah, exactly.
Is it beer?
Yeah.
Another use case is zero.
So, you know, we, the common application, right, of fermentation is to make alcohols,
alcoholic beverages, but it turns out that you can use that process to create lots of
different types of molecules, and you can use that to make molecules that can be precursors
for pretty complicated materials as well, and so that's what we do.
We kind of do the same process, but we're making all kinds of different types of molecules
for different applications.
What are some examples of those applications?
So examples of applications in general, not specific to Zymergen, are, well, for example,
insulin is sort of a classical example of using fermentation in health sciences to produce
insulin.
So that was a huge revolution in terms of being able to create it because it was a very
expensive and kind of grew some way that we used to do it in the past, which is largely
through extracting it from pigs, which is not pretty.
Obviously, if you feel it's a lot better if you can, you know, use microbes and do it in
giant fermenters, and you can produce a lot more at lower costs, so it's kind of the
same thing, yeah.
And so is it a direct byproduct of fermentation, or is it, is there a byproduct that's used
in its creation?
Yeah, it kind of depends on the microbe and the molecule that you're producing, but
often what we're doing is sort of augmenting or kind of ramping up normal metabolic processes
in the cell, so these microbes will ingest, you know, sugars, metabolize things like that
to create these molecules, sort of as sometimes their waste products, it really depends, and
they excrete those into the surrounding fluid inside the tank, and then we harvest that
or we extract that.
Oh, wow.
Yeah, to get those molecules.
Wow.
So what was your talk about?
Yeah, so I was talking about some of the sort of the challenges that we face.
So I was talking a little bit about our mission, actually, of the Data Science Teams mission,
and our goal is to use our testing platform.
So the way that we do what we do as I imagine stepping back for a second is that we rely
on robotic automation, sort of combined with machine learning to build this test platform
that allows us to simultaneously measure the performance of lots of different strains
in parallel.
Okay.
And we use our goal on the Data Science team is to use all of that data that we're generating
through this high throughput screening process, use all of that to then make machine learning
models or make predictive models to help us make better decisions about the experiments,
the strains that we design in the first place.
So basically to help the scientists design better strains so that we don't have to spend
as much time experimenting if we could get to the solution or get to the answer faster,
that's really our goal.
That's an ambitious goal, it's not easy to do, and so part of what I was talking about
was sort of the things that make it hard to accomplish that.
So what are sort of the practical data issues that we encounter and how we're solving those
so that we get really clean in analysis ready or modeling ready data for those complicated
models.
Okay.
And so what are some specific examples of the data sources and data types that feed your
models?
Yeah, so by and large, a lot of the data that we're consuming is really kind of measurements
that represent concentrations.
So we've got these microbes, they're metabolizing things and they're excreting these compounds
or these molecules into the solution around them and then we measure the concentration
of that so that we can tell whether the microbe has improved over its predecessor and then
move that into make a decision based on that essentially.
And so for the most part, the data that we're working with is some measurement, is some
measure of concentration.
Got it.
And what's the scale that this is happening at?
Like is this concentrations in vats of things or like microarrays or somewhere in between?
Yeah, that's a really great question.
So it's kind of all of those things.
So what we do practically in our testing platform is we kind of do it more, not quite as dense
as a microarray, but typically it's something like 96-well plates.
So we have these kind of plates that have 96-wells, each of those wells contains fluid, contains
the microbe and sort of the experimental input.
And that's the level that initially when we're doing our initial screens that we're experimenting
at.
Once a strain, for example, demonstrates improvement compared to its predecessor, it'll go into
another round of that testing, we basically want to validate or replicate that performance
again.
Once it's done that, we actually validate those strains in fermenters.
And so it's kind of a challenge to, you know, the size of a fermentation tank is much
larger than that of a tiny well on a plate.
And so we always want to validate those strains before we deliver them to a customer, for
example, to make sure that the performance and the plate actually represents the performance
that we expect in the fermentation tanks.
And so we do both at Xymrgin, and then we also like to partner with people and run them
at scale in their tanks, too, when possible.
Okay.
Interesting.
And so you started your talk, talking a little bit about kind of the context and your
mission, and then what?
Oh, and then, yeah, and so I was talking a little about some of the challenges we face
with our data, some kind of practical challenges, and how we're using Airflow to build a pipeline
that addresses some of those challenges.
Okay.
What's Airflow?
So Airflow is, it's a Apache incubating project.
It's a Python module, basically, that allows you to construct data processing workflows,
and you're basically constructed DAG of that workflow, and allows you to do things like
scheduling, monitor the progress of those jobs, and even a little bit of reporting.
Yeah.
So it basically helps us orchestrate all of our sort of complicated ETL steps.
Okay.
Where are you eating the data from?
Where does it tend to live?
Yeah, so, and mostly, so we have what's called a limbs, it's sort of a biology, that's
right.
Okay.
I've never met anyone who was, like, not a biologist who knew what that was.
Yes, that's exactly what it is.
So we have a, we have a limbs, and we have a corresponding front end that the scientists
can upload and sort of download data from, and then that gets persisted to a sort of a single
source of truth, like a data warehouse, and that's, for the most part, with the data scientists
access the data from.
From a data warehouse?
Okay.
So you use Airflow, how long have you been using that?
We've been using it, I guess, almost about a year.
Okay.
And that's, you mentioned earlier, you use AirBnB stuff.
Airflow is an AirBnB product?
Yeah, it was a project.
Yeah, exactly, it was an AirBnB product that I think they opened source, and then it was
picked up by Apache, and now it's kind of an incubating project, which, yeah.
And how does it compare to, I'm trying to remember the name of the product that complements,
like Google Cloud, has their data flow, and there's an open source, it's also Apache,
it's not.
It's like oozee or, yeah, no.
It's comparable to that.
It's comparable to oozee?
Yeah.
Okay.
And it's agnostic to sort of, I think oozee is sort of a part of the Hadoop ecosystem.
Airflow is not.
So it's pretty generic in that sense, so you can really use it, it's pretty powerful
in that sense.
So it doesn't have any opinions, really, about the platform when where your data come
from.
Okay.
And so what are the implications on the way you kind of craft and deploy the analytics that
sit on top of the underlying, you know, the data, kind of the data engineering pieces?
Like does airflow, does the weight, any of the semantics of airflow have direct impact
on the way you view the analytics, or is it, you know, kind of separate concerns?
I don't know.
I think maybe they're largely separate concerns, although I guess one of some one of the sort
of use cases that I described was, you know, we do a lot of experimentation as I'm
origin, lots of different types of experiments.
And our scientists use lots of different types of tools to work with data.
And the result of that is sometimes the data doesn't make it into our limbs, so it doesn't
make it into the warehouse.
And one way that we've addressed that is that airflow has all these nice sort of hooks
or operators into third party things like Dropbox.
And so one thing that we've had success with is to be able to work with the scientists
and get them to make some standards around where they put their data in Dropbox, and then
we make really lightweight ingestion pipelines to grab that data and ingest it into our limbs
for them.
And then we're using also a NARB&B product called SuperSet, which is sort of a dashboarding
tool.
So we've now hooked that up so that we can ingest data from Dropbox, and then we can
produce dashboards for the scientists to actually consume their own data that way.
And that's been kind of a success story, making really lightweight stuff, doesn't take
very long to make it all, and can surface the results right there pretty quickly.
Okay.
And so what were some of the insights that you were sharing about using airflow?
Yeah, so I was sharing, I was kind of stepping through a couple of use cases that we, well,
I was describing some of the our limitate or the challenges that we face with our data.
And then sort of the challenges we had when we were working on our own sort of homegrown
ETL solution or platform, and why we eventually sort of abandoned that and adopted airflow.
And so I imagine that a lot of people start there.
Yeah.
Like what are some of those challenges?
So one of the, I think more difficult challenges was that, I mentioned that largely the,
a lot of the data that we're working with is concentrations of things, so we're measuring
how much of something there is in a certain volume of solution.
It turns out measuring concentration of something is not that straightforward, so there are
a lot of different ways that you can measure the concentration of a solution, of something
in a solution.
And depending on the group and whether, like who they're working with and sort of the
way that they choose to measure that, that has implications for the data that we can
expect.
But we need to basically process everything the same way, regardless of the sort of the
format or the type of experiment that they used.
And so that was challenging to kind of articulate ourselves, there's just a lot of overhead
and there's sort of a lot of logic that we would have to encode to do that.
Another challenge was describing this sort of complex dependencies in between our processing
steps.
So, you know, I need this to happen and then that's going to kick off another job that
does this and that's going to kick off something else, but orchestrating sort of that communication
and writing all the logic to, for what do I do if the first thing fails or what if I,
what do I do if the second thing fails and doing all of that ourselves is challenging.
And we have all the, we have data coming in at different velocities and that's also hard
to orchestrate.
So some of our products, they start processing data as soon as a scientist uploads data
into the limbs or into the warehouse.
Others can be scheduled and so it runs nightly or weekly and, or doing all that orchestration
ourselves was, was very challenging.
And, and so I imagine the upside is that airflow kind of handles, handles all of this for you.
It, you know, does the impedance matching from, you know, the different, different velocities
of information coming in and things like that.
Yeah.
So, airflow does a lot of things for us in terms of sort of handling different data inputs
and being sort of agnostic to that.
It's been huge for us for that.
So, we've basically in our processing steps, we have created sort of a generic interface.
So we have sort of three big processing nodes that need to happen.
And they all have very generic interfaces.
So they don't know anything about the data that they're going to receive.
And then basically we, we contextualize it at the time that we've received data.
And so, and that, that has made it very flexible and modular for us so that we can, you know,
a new experimental platform comes online.
It will be very easy for us to apply the same, well, I wouldn't say very easy.
It will be much easier for us to apply the same set of processing steps with a new data
set just because we've, we've gone through the effort of making the interface generic.
So that, and that was something that's harder to do.
Yeah.
Sorry.
Are these three, you said nodes?
Are the three nodes, are they, is this an artifact of kind of the way you would ideal
or design your own processes or is this something that's kind of imposed on you by the way air
flow does things?
Oh, no.
It's, it's more just like sort of the flow of the pipeline, the processing pipeline.
And it, which so happens to have three steps.
Yeah.
So like the, the initial step, one of the, one of the things that we see, you know, I
mentioned, I think that we use, part of the reason we're able to do what we do is that
we rely heavily on robotic automation to do a lot of the heavy lifting in the lab, but
robots fail sometimes or weird things happen in the lab, you know, it's a, it's, the experimentation
is, is challenging.
And so the result of that is we'll see sort of extreme values or like outlying values
that, you know, typically indicate a process failure.
And so that first step is really just an outlier detection step.
So let's, let's identify those process failures and filter those out of any downstream processes.
The second step of that pipeline is something called normalization.
And that's really meant to address sort of another challenge that we face, which are batch
effects, which is a very common phenomenon and high throughput screening environment.
So, you know, you've got a bunch of, you've got a chip with a lot of samples or a lot
of, you know, probes or on it.
And you're asking a lot of questions in a very tight space.
And so these types of environments tend to have strong temporal effects.
So even if you imagine you do the exact same experiment this week and next week, they
might look like they're coming from different distributions.
And that doesn't actually reflect meaningful biological variability.
It's actually just kind of a reflection of the process or of the temperature in the room
at the time.
So yeah, the person who ran it or all these other things that we don't actually care
about.
They're kind of nuisance things.
Right.
And so the second step of that processing pipeline is normalizing the data to try to
eliminate those process, process-related biases.
Okay.
And then sort of the third step and sort of the third challenge that we face with our
data is we have a motto at Zymrogen that is any micro, any molecule.
And what that means is that we, we've built a testing platform that is agnostic to
our customers, microbe, and to the molecule that they're making.
We think that we have a process that will allow us to optimize those strains regardless
of the actual application.
That's amazing from a sort of a business strategy point of view because we can work in lots
of different industries.
We can work with lots of different bugs and make lots of different types of molecules.
But it can be challenging from a data perspective because it can result in a proliferation
of solutions.
So we don't always have agreement on what the right way or whether something that constitutes
an improvement for one group might not be considered an improvement in another group.
And from a modeler's perspective, it's not always clear what the result of the experiment
it is to us as consumers of that test data in a way.
And so one way that we're addressing that is this sort of third piece of that processing
pipeline where we actually do the matching up of the candidate strain with its reference
strain, and we do that testing, and we, like statistical hypothesis testing, and we write
that result so that regardless, sort of independent of the decisions that our scientists make,
we have some indication of what we think happened in the experiment in a sort of a consistent
view of what improvement looks like for our models.
Interesting is it from a modeling and statistical perspective, is it challenging to imagine
it to be challenging to kind of normalize results from comparing one molecule to another
or one biological process to another?
Is that challenging?
So in general, we're not doing that, so we don't share data at all between sort of projects
or...
I guess what I understood you to say that, you know, you've built this general platform for
testing the results of these molecule production, microptomolecule production processes,
and then as a way to make sure that you understand their efficacy, you know, you're kind of
taking that analysis all the way to, you know, what would tell me, what is that end result
that you're driving for?
Yeah, so that note or that last step in the pipeline is often called hit detection in
sort of the biology, the high throughput screening literature, and that's really just
the process of identifying in your screen, which of those candidates that you were exploring
seem to have the characteristics that you're looking for.
And so it's sort of a, it's not as, because it's a screening scenario where our statistical
criteria isn't quite as high as it would be if you were doing a single test, like I
want to know, you know, we're screening, and so actually we care more about keeping false
negatives low than we do about having high false positive rate and you know, retesting
something that actually wasn't a very good strength.
We would rather waste some resources testing something that wasn't good than lose the
opportunity to test again something that actually was good.
Meaning you're screening for possibilities, and the more possibilities you have, the
more opportunity you have to find the thing that actually works.
Yeah, exactly, yeah, yeah, yeah, so it's kind of a different, like way of thinking about
it then, you know, often like in an A, B test, for example, you want to know the right
answer.
Right, right.
Okay, got it.
And so you talked about the challenges that led to deploying airflow.
What about the challenges of deploying airflow and kind of building out this system?
Did you encounter anything in particular there?
Yeah, so, you know, it's sort of probably challenges that are typical of adopting anything
that's kind of an early project.
Right.
One of our bigger challenges was really just finding non-trivial examples of how it's
used in production.
So what I think was some of, at least I experienced this, I feel like this was sort of the general
experience of everybody on the team is that, you know, there's a certain way you're supposed
to write these DAGs or these workflows in airflow every time I would write when I felt
like it was the wrong way.
So I would either try to, it felt like I was putting too little processing sort of in one
node and kind of making too many nodes or it felt like I had one big node that did everything.
And so it was really hard to like get a sense for what the right way to construct, what
unit of work was appropriate and was sort of intended by the design of airflow.
That was challenging, took some getting used to it.
The team is using it a lot now, so I feel like we've got that a pretty good handle on
that now.
That was certainly challenging, sort of getting familiar with it and finding good examples
of non-trivial examples of its use, which I don't know.
It's interesting, it's something that comes up a lot in my conversations with folks in
different domains.
You know, both in take as an example, architecting neural nets or this, there's the documentation
and there's the research and the literature, so much of adopting these new technologies,
like tribal knowledge or black art, or it just practice that, you know, you often don't
find good sources for how to do that stuff.
Yeah, and that makes it, I don't know, that's kind of a friction on adopting this stuff.
Like you want to see some success stories of somebody having used it so that you can
be sure that before abandoning, like our home grown ETL system, we want to be reasonably
sure that the thing that we move to works isn't going to be suffer from the same problems.
And of course, at the understanding that it is a new project and that there will be
sort of foibles as a result of that.
But in general, we want to make sure it solves the bulk of the problems that we have with
our own solution.
And that can be hard to demonstrate sometimes.
But in our case, it worked out Airflow is a really powerful tool for our group.
Has that changed at all since you started to use it, are you seeing more of these examples
or more, you know, better documentation of these more subtle, either use case examples
like you described, or kind of some of these more subtle design philosophies and decisions?
Yeah, I mean, even today, like I was the speaker right before me to talk a lot about Airflow
and then right after me, it was a panel where they talked a bit about Airflow.
So it seems like it is now becoming quite a popular tool and being used pretty pervasively.
So I expect that we'll see more and more, more and more of these kind of stories of how
it's being used in production.
And it's a very flexible tool and it has a lot of functionality.
And so we're using it in ways that we didn't actually expect initially.
And so I'm excited to see how other people are using it.
I'm sure there are a lot of really creative things that are being developed on it.
Nice.
And for the, or is it intended, do you think that the main consumer of the tool is a data
science team, as opposed to a data engineering team or some other variation on the term?
Yeah, I think that's a good question.
I'm not totally sure what the intentions were, but it's definitely a tool that's very
powerful for data scientists in terms of just like the way that we think and being able
to construct workflows that way, it just feels very natural.
I guess it's even a hard question to answer because data science and data scientist means
so many different things.
This actually came up in my last interview as well.
We talked about how this has evolved since five years ago when everything was considered
data science, or data science was considered needing to know all of the different bits
and pieces of moving the data around and doing the analytics and getting it to production.
When I hear you describe the tool, I think plumbing, I think kind of no-level stuff.
And that was really the source of the question, like, is it is, do you think that that is typical
for data science to kind of dive into that level, or is our data scientist typically
that's supported by other groups that are kind of putting the plumbing in place?
Yeah, so for us, the way that we ended up kind of productionizing our airflow environment
was with the collaboration with data engineering.
We have, our group is pretty engineering-heavy anyway, all the data scientists are fairly
do a lot of engineering.
And so of course we had help from actual data engineers, and then members of the team
who have that skill set as well, are responsible for sort of doing all the configuration and
the start-up scripts for people.
Because our group is pretty mixed in terms of the background and interests and the skills.
And so that's been great, like, they spent a lot of time really developing structure
around how to get it set up, and so that all of the data scientists, when they come
online, can easily set it up and then start doing what they already know how to do,
which is construct the workflows and Python.
So it's kind of two levels.
I think we did probably need help from data engineers to actually get it up and get it
running consistently, and sort of in a production level of an environment.
But then once it's there, it's actually, I think, a very simple tool for the average
data scientist to quickly start making processing workflows.
And part of that is that it has a really cool out-of-the-box UI, so you can write your
workflow in Python, and then you can go to the UI, you can run it there, you can view
all kinds of metrics about the pipeline, there's even stuff about sort of which tasks in
that pipeline are sort of the bottlenecks, and what are the performance metrics of each
of the individual tasks.
So it allows you to kind of see, get visibility into those workflows that, in the past, I
haven't had actually really anywhere, so it's great for that.
Interesting.
Is that user experience, is it kind of analogous to a notebook, or is it more like a job processing
type of tool?
No, it's more like a bonafide application.
So it's got sort of a table of all of the jobs that are around, and you can kind of change
the scheduling right there in the UI, turn them on and off, and then tab over to metrics
and all kinds of other things.
You can view the logs from there, so if something failed, obviously you can log into the machine
and view the logs there, or you can just use the UI and view the logs directly, see what
happened with your job, you'll get a bunch of rich diagnostics about which part of the
workflow failed, and all kinds of stuff right there in the UI.
So it's actually, it's a pretty developed tool.
Oh wow.
It's really helpful.
Oh, very nice.
Very nice.
Anything else you'd like to share with the audience, or leave with the audience?
I guess just check it out, it's been a really great tool for us, so the reason that we
invested in it really is to support our work in predictive strain design, that is sort
of our mission is to use machine learning so that we can construct better strains and help
our scientists get to the solution faster.
And airflow has been incredible in helping us solidify that processing pipeline to support
that work.
It's a clean analysis ready or modeling ready data that's consumable directly from this
pipeline, and a lot of it, a lot of the headache of what's sort of traditionally, or maybe
not associated with being a data scientist, but with data scientists know it's actually
about, can be sort of addressed with airflow, or at least can be ameliorated some so that
it's not, so that 90% of your time isn't actually spent cleaning data and munging it and moving
it around.
We can do, it's very flexible, can do all kinds of different types of tasks, and that's
been really helpful for getting, sort of, trying to eliminate sort of the boring stuff so
that we can do the cool stuff.
Awesome, awesome.
If I can draw you back in, that was kind of a great summary, but we haven't really
talked a lot about the specific models that you use, like we've talked about this tool
that helps you get the data to the models.
Yeah.
A bit about the types of models that you're building, the modeling techniques you're
using, things like that.
Yeah, I can't talk a ton about them, but the conceptually what we're doing is we're
taking information about what we know the scientists are engineering into the strains,
so the type of change that they're making, where it is, so what gene is it that's being
perturbed, or being engineered, and we're basically making models to predict combinations
of those changes, so the typical microbe has something between three and 5,000 genes in
it, and so if we were to perturb each of those individually and then start perturbing
each pairwise combination, that's an infinite, combinatorical space to explore, and so what
we're trying to do instead is take all of the information about the things that we know
we've already done, and then make predictions about how we think those are going to perform
when they're combined.
So a little bit of evolutionary genetic algorithm types of things, or...
A lot of things, actually, so we have a lot of different types of models and some work
in better context than others, so we have models that kind of address different things.
Some work better when you have a bunch more information, so after a project is fairly
mature, and we have a whole lot of test data that we can use to train on, our models are
different than when we're at the cold start problem, where really all we know, maybe
is the metabolic structure of the microbe, we haven't started doing anything yet, so
how do we guide the experimentation in that case when we don't know at all about really
where to start, and so those suite of models are a little bit different and they rely
more on structural information about metabolism than experimental information, which can
happen later, after we've collected a bunch of information from experiments.
Okay, all right, very cool, very cool.
Thank you so much, everyone, for taking the time to jump on the podcast with me.
Yeah, thanks so much for having me.
There's a lot of fun, thank you.
Yeah.
All right, everyone, that's our show for today.
Thanks so much for listening and for your continued support of this podcast.
For the notes for this episode, or for any feedback or questions, please leave a comment
on the show notes page at twimmaleye.com slash talk slash 41.
Thanks again to Cloud Era, our sponsor for the Rangle Conference series of podcasts.
To learn more about Cloud Era and the company's data science workbench products, visit them
at cloudera.com and be sure to tweet at them using at cloud era to thank them for their
support of this podcast.
If you're interested in joining the twimmale online meetup, we'll discuss research papers
like Apple's recent paper on generative adversarial networks.
You can register for that at twimmaleye.com slash meetup.
And don't forget to sign up for the newsletter at twimmaleye.com slash newsletter.
Thanks again for listening and catch you next time.