All right, everyone. I am here with Tim Rockteschel. Tim is a research scientist at Facebook AI
research and associate professor in the Department of Computer Science at University College London.
Tim, welcome to the Twomol AI podcast. Thanks so much for having me. It's great to be.
I am really looking forward to digging into our conversation. We'll be talking about one of my
favorite topics, which is reinforcement learning. But before we do, I would love to have you share a
little bit about your background and how you came to work in the field. Sure. Yeah, so I started a
PhD actually in natural language processing at University College London in 2013. I got interested
in generally knowledge representations and knowledge graphs and how we can reason, you know,
about knowledge and for new facts from these knowledge graphs. I also did some work on
textual entailment and other NLP problems. But I got more and more excited about reinforcement
learning. I felt in NLP, lots of the data sets back then, they were static and it was mostly,
you know, chasing scores on leaderboards. And I was very intrigued, I guess, by work that came
out of, you know, top AI labs like DeepMind and OpenAI at the time. So I, you know, went over to
Oxford to the postdoc with a human white son's reinforcement learning group there. And then after
the postdoc, I joined UCL as a lecturer back then and also Facebook research in London.
Awesome. Awesome. And when you think about your kind of research,
agenda at the university and the work that you focus on at Facebook, how do you characterize it?
What are the bounds of your interests? So the thing that we care most about at this point are
being able to train agents that can somewhat generalize to novel situations. So we strongly
believe that over the last decade, quite a bit of the research in the field has unfortunately
focused on very limited environments. So, you know, games like Atari Games come to mind. This
has been obviously really fantastic for advancing the field, but it can only go so far in that,
you know, Atari Games are deterministic. There's only so much kind of novel situations that you
encounter in these kind of games. And we are really far away from being able to apply these
reinforcement learning techniques to lots of the real world problems that we would care about.
So really, my work focuses on how we can move closer towards these kind of real world problems.
How can we drop some of these kind of simplified assumptions that are baked into some of the,
you know, environment simulators that we've been used for driving reinforcement learning research?
And from there, basically, it's a slippery slope into procedally generated games and, you know,
training agents that are intrinsically motivated and curious, even training agents that can design
their own kind of problems in these simulated worlds to then hopefully get agents that can generalize
better to new tasks and new situations. And when you talk about kind of these constrained
environments versus unconstrained environments is a unconstrained environment, something like,
you know, what we might be familiar with with OpenAI Jim or Mojoku or something like that,
where you have these figures or humanoids or do you think about that differently?
So it's a bit different. So OpenAI Jim is a really fantastic interface that allowed us researchers
right to basically speak the same language in terms of how to interact with environments.
But it's really just an interface, right? And then there are lots of different
and actual environments that connect to that interface. For example, Atari games are, you know,
connected to this OpenAI Jim interface. So if you, as a researcher, want to create a model
on new, you know, our agent that should, you know, do something sensible in these environments,
you can just follow that interface and other researchers kind of can, you know, write other models,
and they're all kind of compatible in terms of interacting with that environment. Same goes with Mojoku.
So the problem with things like Mojoku or, you know, other environments that we've been using for
a long time is that they are somewhat limited, right? Each of these environments make or have
baked in certain simplifying assumptions that unfortunately mean that when, you know, cohort
of researchers over a long time, the research on it eventually they find ways to basically
exploit these simplifying assumptions. Now, I'm not saying that, you know, we can directly jump
into completely unconstrained environments. The only such environment that comes to my mind is
the real world, right? We would have to, that would be make a jump towards training, you know,
real robots in the real world. And that's for many reasons, I think, very challenging, right? It's
it's slow because you can't, you know, speed up time. You have all kinds of engineering
challenges with robots falling apart and whatnot. So I'm saying we still find to use
simulated environments that are somewhat constrained, but we need to be very explicit about the
simplifying assumptions that are built into these environments. And we need to gradually remove
them to be able to then develop methods that are somewhat of a general nature so that we have the
hope at some point to learn something generally about training agents that can do things for real world
tasks. We've talked a lot about in the context of, for example, computer vision, how
deep learning models are so good at picking up patterns. They, you know, will pick up a pattern
that is correlated with the result that you want, the label that you want, but not really the
one that you want them to pick up. An example that comes to mind from a recent conversation was
the, you know, a pen mark that happened to be used on a radiology image to, you know,
that's correlated with whether there's cancer in the actual specimen. You said something that
kind of suggested that, you know, in the RL setting, the models will, you know, pick up on these kind
of tangential constraints of the environment and that impacts the way that they, the way that
they're trained, et cetera, is that is the, you know, there's similar effects in that way or
it's actually worse. It's, you know, that problem we also have, right? So the moment you use deep
function approximators like deep neural networks that get any input as data, they might, as you
said, they might just latch on to certain spurious correlations in the data. That is true for
natural language processing, computer vision. It's also true for reinforcement learning environments,
right? If you happen to have, for example, a certain, you know, visually rich reinforcement
environment where the agent is supposed to do a certain task, maybe there's a certain queue
in the training episodes that allows the agent to, you know, do well there, but then once you
change something slightly, you change the background, you change some of the textures in that,
in that environment, the agent will most likely break down and not do anything sensible. So that's,
that's, that problem is there too. What I'm talking about is I think of somewhat a worse problem
in that and we as researchers, right? We oftentimes design in RL, we design our own kind of
environments to do the research, right? We create, you know, our own kind of games or we use
games like the Atari games. And that works for some time, but if you are then not careful,
right? You as a researcher over years and years as a, as a research cohort, right? You start to
actually exploit that simulator. You say, okay, now we have an agent that can, you know,
solve some of the hardest exploration problems in Atari, but then really what does that tell us
for the real world? Right? What does it tell us for real world problems when let's say all your
agent is doing is kind of memorizing over time, what are the right steps to do? If you change
anything in that game, you know, this agent would be screwed, right? So how do you, how do you learn
something general about AI agents that you want to deploy at some point to solve, you know, actual
real world problems? That's the, that's the challenge. Got it. So going back to the comparison with
computer versions, kind of the overfitting on image net problem. Yep. Yeah, exactly. And so how do
you propose to address this problem? What are, what are some of the things that you've done in this
area? So, I mean, to be honest, I think one can step back a bit and say, actually, there were
multiple researchers that recognized that problem some, some time ago. So a few years ago, people
started to use what's called procedurally generated environments for training and testing our
agents. And what that means is that you actually have a generative process that given the start of
an episode can generate a new, all your world basically, right? A whole new kind of problem,
right? A new maze or a new new game with new dynamics. Or yeah, if you think about, for example,
Minecraft, right, really a new kind of landscape where whatever you, I mean, whatever you learned
before in terms of the topology of the world, you find yourself in, it's going to be different now,
right? Certain things stay the same. The environment and dynamics stay the same, right? So the way
how certain items work and what certain, you know, enemies do to you, right? That stays the same,
but at least in terms of the, the kind of visual inputs and the topology of the map, right? Things
change dramatically. And there were multiple researchers who've been taking that approach, right?
Starting to create procedurally generated environments to test the generalization capabilities of
our agents. Some prominent examples are actually indeed Minecraft. So that has been used for
reinforcement learning research, although it's a somewhat a slow simulator. There was the obstacle
tower challenge where you have a basically 3D jump and run problem environment. Again,
wherever you episode, the blocks that you have to jump over and doors and keys that you have to,
you know, interact with the position of these change. So that was quite exciting. And then
more recently, opening, I released this project and benchmark. So these are 16 games that look
a bit like Atari games, but that are actually procedurally generated. That means in every
episode, for example, again, the mace structure changes or the textures even off the game assets
change. So your agents really have to systematically generalize with respect to certain factors of
variation. And, and that is interesting, right? Because now we are talking about a regime that's
closer to actually what people do in computer vision and natural language processing where they
have a training set. And then I have a held out test set and they actually test for generalization,
right? They can see how much actually overfitting is happening. So now we can do that. And yeah,
that's what what other people did in the space back then. And we looked at that and honestly,
we were really, you know, really excited about this. It's to me, research is really not a zero
sum game. It's great to see what other people are doing. But one of the gaps that we identified
back then, and as is roughly two, three years ago, is that these environments, these procedurally
generated environments, they're either quite rich, like Minecraft, right? They're where there's
really lots of things to do, lots of, you know, entities to interact with. But they're really slow
to simulate. So that's not great news for like contemporary reinforcement learning approaches. So
you can't really do like good research with it unless you have really tremendous computational
resources, and even then it's it's problematic. Or these are procedurally generated environments,
but they're actually relatively limited in terms of the richness, right? In terms of interacting
with different entities and agents having to acquire certain skills, they actually more like,
okay, I have to move around, maybe get a key open the door, but then that's mostly it. Whereas
what we would want, ideally, is something that is really rich and complex, but at the same time,
very fast to simulate, so that we can still make progress with like, currency of the art
reinforcement learning methods. So that's the kind of gap that we identified two, three years ago,
and then basically that lead led to looking into a very interesting class of games,
called Rooklikes. So these are dungeon crawl games, and they have a very long tradition.
So Rook, I think itself was implemented in the in the early eighties, and then there's
another much richer game called NetHack, which we then settled on in terms of turning it into
reinforcement learning environment. NetHack is I think was developed in 1987. It's played
entirely in the terminal. So every thing that you observe is actually ASCII characters in a terminal,
and that makes it really, really fast to simulate, but it's extremely rich and complex at the same time,
as well. It has hundreds of items, hundreds of monsters that all behave differently, so you have to
learn over time how to avoid them or fight them. It's, as I mentioned, procedurally generated,
so every time you played, it's different. The moment you die, the game is over, you have to start
from the very beginning of the game, and again, it's procedurally generated, so you can't really
memorize anything about certain landmarks or positions in the previous game. It's very long
as well. It takes an average player, something like 50,000 steps to complete the game. It's very
different to some of the grand challenges that have been used in the past for AI. If you think
about StarCraft 2, for example, that game takes something like 15 minutes, and depending on how many
actions you allow the agent to do per second, it means something like 2,000 steps for an episode,
whereas here we're talking about, as I mentioned, 50,000. NETAC is open source, so then we decided to
say, look, we're going to turn it into an RL benchmark, and we're going to see how, well,
vanilla, deep brain, phospholining approaches do. That's what we did.
What does completing the game mean for NETAC? Is it kind of finding your way through a world?
In overcoming the various challenges that you mentioned, fighting with monsters, and finding
treasures, and that kind of thing? Yeah, so it's fantasy dungeon crawl game, so basically,
you get thrown into a dungeon with rooms and corridors connecting these rooms. You have to
explore in there because the environment itself is partial observable. You only see kind of what's
in the current room. The moment you go out, there can be things happening in there that you don't
see. That itself is challenging for RL already. It's stochastic, so in the moment you attack a monster,
there's a die roll in the back, like in dungeons and dragons, right? And your outcomes of the
actions are uncertain. That's, again, a really major challenge for, like, a current state of the art
or other approaches. But yeah, yeah, as a player, you would basically try to fight your way down.
There's their cases down. You get to the next level, next level. They're over 50
procedurally generated levels that become more and more difficult. At the bottom of that dungeon,
that is, without hopefully spoiling too many people, is an amulet that you need to retrieve,
and then you need to make your entire way up again. And then there's five more really challenging
elemental planes. And then at the end of it, you need to offer the amulet to a in-game deity,
and then you ascend to demigothood on your one-game. It's extremely challenging. Was it a game
that you played before you started doing the research in this area? I did, yeah. So I did play
a much simpler kind of clone of it that you can play easily on the smartphone, which is called
Pixel Dungeon, which I enjoyed a lot. But then it was at a time, actually, when I was commuting
between Oxford and London, so that's kind of a two-hour commute door-to-door where you take a train,
and on that train, at least in evenings after a full day of work, yeah, I did then start to play
Nethack. Specifically, when we started to get serious about this project, it took me two years
to win in this game for the first time. So it is really, really challenging, but also very funny.
Nice, nice. When you talk about it being procedurally generated, how many parameters
are, you know, do you have a control over when you're generating a game? Is it, you know,
you give it a seed and that kind of creates everything? Or do you have more fine-grained control over,
you know, number of levels or difficulty or other things?
So, yeah, basically, if you just take Nethack as it is, you define a seed and then the dungeon
is created, it's very subtle, actually. It's very tricky, in the sense that actually there's a
random number generated in the background, obviously, that is only advanced when you do an action that
would lead to a stochastic outcome. So depending on the kind of, even if you set the same seed
in the beginning, depending on the kind of interactions you have on the first level,
the moment you go down to the next level and depending on how far that random number generator
has been already advanced, the next level is going to look differently. So one thing you
alter, even by fixing the seed, you won't get the entire dungeon the same way, just get the first
level the same way. And that is been true for like contents in kind of containers like, you know,
boxes. So it's, it's a bit like basically at disk qualifies many of the, you know, approaches that
have been proposed that would, you know, make use of the fact that the simulator is deterministic,
even if we try to make an hacked deterministic, it's a bit challenging.
And so in publishing the, the, the environment and the challenge to you, have you also attempted
to solve it? And what have you learned? What do you run into when you set RL agents loose in this
kind of environment? When we released the, the network learning environment last year and presented
it at NURBS, we have in that paper results of a distributed deep reinforcement learning approach,
a pretty much kind of vanilla model. And we originally thought that this won't work at all,
basically. It's way too hard, even for such a kind of state of the art approach to learn any
meaningful behavior. We were actually surprised that our agents do learn some sensible behavior.
I mean, they're not really getting very far in that game. They're not anywhere close to winning that
game, but they learn like certain things like, you know, exploring the dungeons, even looking for
secret doors, which can be quite tricky, kicking in locked doors, which I found a very interesting
behavior because it's a pretty difficult thing to explore. Like when you're actually kicking and
you're kicking against walls, you take damage and you might die. So it's interesting to see that
over time, if you give it enough kind of interactions with the environment, it learns actually
these kind of basic behaviors and skills. It learns to go deeper and deeper into the dungeon.
It learns to avoid certain very powerful monsters. It learns to eat, which is very important in
the game to actually not starve to death. But, you know, they get to like, you know, average dungeon
level five or six, some lucky agents get to dungeon level 10 or 15, even. We saw that too, but
that's all like very basic, basic behavior. It's not on the level of like a human when they start
learning to play Natagon, they've never played it before. If they play for a week and they get to
the same kind of level of skills, I think they're quite good. But then, you know, afterwards humans
just are much, much better at kind of nailing this over time. And is there a score associated with
the game or what is the like the fundamental driving signal that you're giving your agents to give
it success, some kind of success notion? Yeah, that's a fantastic question. There is an in-game score.
That score captures things like, you know, how deep did you go down in the dungeon? How many
monsters did you kill? And it's a really terrible metric to try to optimize for in terms of actually
winning the game. But that's basically what we did, right? We started simple and say, okay,
let's use any kind of metric that we can think of. We tried the score and what happens is basically
what you expect. Like, if you get reward for going down a dungeon level and killing stuff,
you get an agent that just, you know, goes completely berserk, tries to kill everything in their
path, more or less, and just tries to run down the dungeon level as quickly as possible without
caring about actually, you know, finding items, equipping them in order to get stronger the long run.
So it's a very tricky challenge, right? How do we, what's even the right reward function?
So that we can guide an agent towards winning the game. And to be very honest, I think humans
don't care about score when they learn to play this game. They don't even care about winning
because it takes them hundreds or maybe even thousands of games before they win for the first time.
For humans, something different happens, right? They get just excited about exploring
and they are intrinsically motivated to learn about how this game works and what kind of
funny things you can do with it, isn't it? So that's an interesting, interesting angle to it.
We have to, I guess, you know, find ways to intrinsically motivate these kind of agents to explore.
Yeah, and so that that sounds a lot like curiosity and leads to ideas about kind of the
explore exploit knob. Is that something that, you know, what do you see when you kind of play
with a knob like that with an agent in this environment? Yeah, so we, we provided another
baseline in that, in that Europe's paper, which is indeed, like, such an intrinsic reward mechanism.
It's called random network distillation. It's a very robust method. And it does give you small gains
and significant, but small gains. I think we have to, more long term, I think we have to think
about more fundamentally different ways of encouraging agents to explore things that are not
directly based, for example, on counting. That really doesn't work here, right? Because every game
looks different, so you can't really count the observations because most of them you only see once.
You could try to come up with intrinsic motivations derived from how much you can predict the future,
but even that is really difficult in a stochastic environment that's
procedally generated where you go around a corner and you can't really know what's going to
be around the corner or in the next angel level because it hasn't been generated yet.
I think ultimately where we had to get to, and now this is, I kind of, I guess, full circle to
what I've been doing my PhD on, like, a few years ago, is actually encouraging agents to
expand their knowledge about the environment dynamics. You as a human, you basically become
a scientist within this environment. You want to understand, okay, if I take this potion and put
it together with that potion, what happens, right? Or if I'm, if I'm, you know, if I find this
wand of digging, can I, you know, maybe dig downwards and fall just through the dungeon levels and
things like that, like getting almost like a causal understanding of what's going on in this
environment. So ideally, I think we at some point have agents that just reward themselves by
discovering something new about the environment dynamics, not so much about actually what happens
in a specific episode. And going back to what you worked on in your PhD is the implication that
you think that some kind of knowledge graph is the way you might represent what the agent is learning.
Yeah, I think, I mean, we're not, like, working on that explicitly right now, but one of the things
that are, I think, exciting is the environment itself is symbolic. So you don't actually observe
the pixel, you don't have observed pixels. I mean, you can do that, but you don't have to,
right? You can actually just take the characters that are on the screen, the ASCII characters,
and try to represent each symbol, right, using a vector. And then you could, you could basically
build relatively structured models, neuro symbolic models for that. We haven't done that, but
but that is an option. Another thing that's interesting about that direction is the fact that there's
also what's called the Nehag Wiki. This is a basically 3000 document domain-specific Wikipedia
for the game of Nehag, where humans over decades have been basically collecting all kinds of advice.
And it's very interesting because it's not like a step-by-step walkthrough that you would normally
see in some of the kind of video games that people play, right? It's not like a step-by-step that
tells you, okay, here you have to go left, here you have to collect that item to then be able to do
this or that. It can't be, right? Because the game is presumably generated, it can only be very
high-level strategic advice. So how to utilize that for kind of, you know, imbuing agents with a
lot of prior knowledge in terms of how to explore, or what to do in certain situations, I think,
is a very interesting direction. Partly also because that Nehag Wiki itself has lots of structure,
so lots of, you know, names and entities that are linked to each other that you could use in some
way. And have there been attempts to do that? Not that I know of. So we have this approach that we
really like sharing these kind of environments and the baselines and our research publicly and openly,
so we've open sourced on of that people are invited to compete on that environment. We've even
for this year, organized a Nehag Challenge where we got sponsorship from Facebook, I research in
and deep mind as well, where we invited both deep reinforcement researches as well as actually
bot makers. So people try to hand craft solutions for this environment. And we really want to see
what people come up with. Obviously, we have our own kind of research directions as well, but
often we use Nehag more for kind of inspiring, you know, problems that we want to work on rather
than trying to say, okay, we're going to do anything we can do just to beat that game, right? We're
going to use, you know, hundreds or hundreds of thousands of GPUs to just like try to work for
our way. We really see it as a generator for kind of problems that are interesting for reinforcement
research. And we started this conversation talking about trying to provide an alternative platform
for our research that was less compute intensive than some of the previous things, but it sounds
like it still can be computationally intense to, you know, set an agent up it to navigate this
environment. Can you characterize the, you know, is it, you know, hundreds or thousands of GPUs
required or GPU hours or like what's typically required to train an agent for this environment?
Yeah. So the environment itself is not the bottleneck. So we can, if you have an extremely
fast model, you could run this environment for tens of thousands of steps per second with a
relatively basic, the deep neural network agent, we get to something like 14,000 steps a second
with the monster we released for nerves. We now have versions of that that run roughly 20,000
steps a second, 30,000 steps a second. So basically it means with a relatively basic,
you know, deep RL agent, you can train in this environment for something like one to three
billion steps a day. That's a lot of interactions. That's basically more interactions than humans
had with this game, human kind had with this game per day almost. So the environment is really not
the bottleneck, but once you start creating, you know, bigger and bigger, you know, deep learning
models, then at some point those become basically the bottleneck. So you basically, you then just have
to live with the fact that your model itself might require let's say a GPUs, right? And then if you
want to, if you want to do a hyper parameter sweep or you have multiple, you know, ablations that
you want to run, then you find yourself, well, n times that, right? But for researcher, I mean,
you can, I think you can do really exciting research with that environment with just one GPU. That
was the plan from the, from the get go. You mentioned that the goal of the project isn't so much
for your team to solve it, but to inspire other research directions or advances. What are some
examples of those? So, well, one example, we already mentioned right that this is, you know,
how do we imbue agents with intrinsic motivation to learn to explore and such an environment in a
somewhat open-ended way, right? I mean, there's so many things to explore. There's so many,
as I mentioned, hundreds of items and entities to learn to attack with. Another direction is
learning from demonstrations. So humans have been playing this game for a long time for like three
decades. And as of, I think two decades ago, they're kind of online web pages where you can play
the game by SSHing into a server, and you can actually record your game because it's so incredibly
hard to play that game. Basically, people were interested in getting proof that they actually
won this game with fair means, right? So, that's part of, of that story. And actually means there are
five million online recorded games that everyone can have access to. They're hosted on Art.org.
And an open question is, how can we learn from these kind of human demonstrations? It's very
tricky because these human demonstrations don't record the actions. So usually in learning from
demonstrations, we see the states and actions, and then we can do things like behavioral cloning.
So directly trying to, you know, just mimic basically human policies using supervised learning
techniques. Here, you can't do that because you only see the observations, not the actions,
but that's again very interesting, right? It kind of exemplifies a real world problem,
namely, you observing a third person doing something. And we humans, we can still kind of infer
from that how we should maybe act, right? With FOA agents that can be relatively tricky. So that's
another direction. Yet another direction is how can we potentially try to step back out of a
specific episode and put the agent into a situation where it can experiment with the environment,
right? Where I give it, you know, think of like something like a holodeck where no, the agent can
experiment. We, you know, can put certain objects or certain things into that kind of contained,
you know, simple space. But the agent over time learns to pose itself more and more challenging
situations. And then ultimately might be able to transfer its knowledge about the environment
dynamics over to the full game, the actual task, curriculum learning type of direction.
Yeah, exactly. And so NetHack, this project ultimately led to another project called MiniHack.
What's that about? Yeah. So MiniHack is going into the direction that I just mentioned.
The problem with NetHack is you can basically put out a really challenging environment and people
can start to experiment with it. But the problem becomes that in research, what we often like to do
is what we like to actually have a specific research question that we want to tackle, which might
isolate a specific problem of an RL agent, right? In NetHack, you have multiple problems all
appearing at the same time. I've been touched upon them quite a bit already. What if you now say,
okay, really, I want to, well, I want to do research on this, but I want to start simple, right?
I want to have maybe only kind of a few things like I don't want to have even monsters, I don't
want to have any items. I just want to navigate me as a example, right? Yeah.
And so that's a common, common, I guess, pattern in AI research. We start really simple,
get to a proof of concept result, then we start to crank up complexity, right? So how do we smoothly
move on this kind of spectrum of NetHack super complex and difficult or like, let's say,
really simple kind of grid world where we have full control over what's going on, right?
And that led to MiniHack. MiniHack is basically leveraging NetHack to create a sandbox in which
you can very easily create problems of varying difficulty by tapping into the richness
of NetHack. The way this works is that NetHack itself has so-called description files.
So to procedurally generate the game, there are basically, there's a specific language that people
can use to, you know, create, you know, random rooms and random corridors connecting these rooms.
They can even, with certain probabilities, specify that certain items or monsters appear somewhere,
they can sample even, you know, entities from a distribution of monsters or our items.
They can even draw in ASCII like a level. You can actually sit down and basically type a maze,
and then you can kind of compile it into NetHack and you get an actual kind of maze to traverse.
So this kind of domain-specific language is what enabled MiniHack. So it's basically a way
to create, um, create lots and lots of interesting wheat fostering environments that are more
contained, but also very easy to extend using that domain-specific language. It's a whole environment
zoo basically. So when I asked earlier, how many degrees of freedom do you have when you're
spawning one of these procedurally generated environments? In NetHack, you have your seed,
but here you basically have an unlimited number of possibilities for creating the environments.
Can you talk a little bit about, you know, maybe stepping back more broadly, the,
you know, we talked about curriculum learning earlier. You know, the suggestion with NetHack is,
you know, maybe you want to train agents to, I guess similar to curriculum learning to focus
on particular areas and maybe see if those skills generalize other ways. What's the, you know,
kind of current state or thinking or frontier of curriculum learning and transfer learning
in the realm of RL? I guess we have, I mean, there's some work that we are focusing on,
but I think more generally, I guess there's just a question around even what kind of
generalization we want to see, right? Do we assume we have, you know, a fixed number of tasks
and we have to, you know, we can sample problems for each of these tasks and we learn over time
basically to identify when we are on an episode which kind of tasks we're in and then do well.
The same agent, you know, do we, is the goal for the same agent to play breakout in
Montezuma's revenge in NetHack? You know, the tasks we're talking about, for example.
Yeah, that could be, that could be the task, right? You might have all the over 50 games in
in Atari and you might say clearly there's something to be transferred from learning how to play
one game over to learning to play a different game and maybe you want to figure out in which kind
of order you should be presenting these kind of games to a learning agent. But yeah, I think, I mean,
this, this, it's really tricky, right? Like how do we, how do we test for the kind of generalization
that we want to test? What are the kind of assumptions that we bake into the kind of curriculum
method that we that we're developing? In our case, we started off with the assumption that there's
actually a seat that generates the same kind of world every time we, you know, use that seat.
I already mentioned in NetHack itself, that's already not possible, but in somewhat more simplified
environments, for example, open-eye proxjans, benchmark with these 16 different proceed-generated
games. For each of these games, you can specify a seat and then you're going to have the same kind of,
let's say, maze or the same kind of, you know, jump and run kind of level. And what we then were
interested in is can we learn? Because if you sample from these seats, right? You will sometimes
get really easy levels, things where, you know, the agent has to just step left and has already
won, right? We'll finish the level. And then there are really, really challenging levels that you
could, you know, happen to sample. And then there's everything in between, right? So the normal
approach in our L is to just uniformly sample from these kind of levels, right? Or you could also
call them tasks, actually, it doesn't really matter at this point. So that's the normal approach.
What we were interested in is can we learn how to, how to sample these kind of levels in the way
that we start with the easier ones so that the agent can start to learn certain skills and then
gradually move over to more and more challenging levels. And this is, this is interesting because
you basically always want to be at the frontier of what the agent can currently do, right? You don't
want to present levels that are too easy and not levels that are too hard. You always want to be
somewhere where the agent doesn't really show whether it's going to do well or not. And we actually
exploit exactly that property. So in many current early agents, we are using what's called a value
function to stabilize training. So basically, the agent at every step tries to predict how well it's
going to do in the remainder of the episode and actually turns out we can use that value function
to estimate a value error. So basically, that's a discrepancy between what the agent thought,
how well it's going to do and then how well it actually did. And now if you think about it, right?
That for kind of setups, there's you think you're doing really poorly and you'll do really
poorly. So that's not interesting because you basically just realize you're in a really tough
situation. You think you're going to do really well and you're actually doing really well. Again,
that's not very interesting because that's way too easily. But the other two are interesting. So
you think you're going to do really well and you did really poorly or you think you're going to do
really poorly and you actually did really well. So these are the kind of levels or configurations
that help you if you were to replay the level in the future again and try to learn from it,
that actually helps you to actually learn something. And this is this approach is called
practice. Every play we it has level in the name, but actually it's more general in that any kind
of environment where you have a configuration that you can reset to, you can apply that approach.
So if you think about, for example, a robot simulator where you have certain blocks that need
to be stacked and they blocks are arranged in front of the robot, right? That kind of arrangement
is a configuration you could specify that by a seed and you could apply that approach.
It's analogous to an active learning kind of scenario where you're trying to provide some signal
into the training process for where you have the opportunity to gain most new information.
Yeah, exactly. Okay. And going further now, this is a paper that we just got accepted at NUREPS,
we can actually turn that into a approach for what's called uncivilized environment design.
So an uncivilized environment design, you basically separate your agent into kind of two agents,
one that's the student that learns basically to do an episode and the basically agent you
at the end of the day care about because that's the agent you're going to use to then test whether
it's any good. And another agent, a teacher agent, and that teacher agent is basically trying to
generate problems. It's generating actual, you know, levels or environments. And it turns out,
if you actually not really treat that as an agent, but you just randomly sample from your
procedurally generated kind of environment design space, you just randomly sample seats.
And you rank them or you basically filter them by the learning potential for the current
student's policy, then over time, the levels that you keep, the levels that you actually use for
training student, they will gradually become more difficult and more difficult and more difficult.
And basically through that kind of complexity increase, you see very interesting problems,
you know, emerging through that process, as well as you see a student that's actually very strong
at at the end of the day, generalizing to held out handcrafted problems. So what we call it,
we call that usually zero shot generalization. So taking taking that agent into a complete new
situation, see how it does. And can you or how can you predict the learning potential for a given seed
before the agent has attempted the seed? We talked about it previously. It was the difference
between their results. They're expected outcome and their actual outcome. Yeah. So you can't.
So you have to play at once. And then when you've done it once, you basically have a score for
that kind of level in terms of the learning potential for presenting it again in the future.
And you keep that in the buffer now. Basically, at every time step, the student agent,
and either sample, it's basically completely new level, right, from just your seed, or samples,
one of the levels from the buffer and uses that to train. Okay. And then
ultimately, you're trying to drive with this adversarial approach by greater training
efficiency and converging on successful agents more quickly. Yeah. And what kind of results have
you seen in applying the technique? So the, the things that we did was we started again,
very simple, right? I mean, again, I mentioned this comes back from our focus. You can say,
here's a super complex environment. And here are like more kind of toyish grid worlds.
We started with the grid worlds and we trained agents to basically generate
mazes and then student ages to navigate these mazes. That itself is not a super interesting problem
because you could just code up a symbolic agent that is really good at traversing mazes.
But it presents an interesting challenge for reinforcement learning because you only get
the what when you finish the maze, right? And depending on how big your maze becomes,
this is very, very tricky. And so now we have this kind of process, you know, that's generating,
the teacher generating or crew rating. Basically, that's how we call it crew rating levels for
student to learn. And then you actually see over time, the kind of levels that are kept to train
the student agent, they become quite complex. They have quite interesting structure that resembles
to some extent actual mazes. So now the student learns in that and then we take it out of that kind
of space and actually presented with handcrafted quite tricky mazes and we see how well the student
doesn't these. And actually, we do see quite quite strong zero shot generalization to these kind
of held out problems. So just to be very clear, this is really kind of out of domain generalization
in that these kind of handcrafted levels were not within the distribution of the levels that
you would normally see during training, right? So that's that's a kind of interesting bit. And then
we thought, okay, if that works for mazes, maybe we can also do this in a continuous control
environment. So we actually moved over to to the car racing and we let the teacher to basically
over time generate formula one tracks. I mean, non actual formula one tracks, but basically
racetracks. And we have this student kind of trying to get through this as quickly as possible.
And then we again have held out handcrafted racetracks, namely actual formula one tracks
and see how well the student can generalize to these kind of unseen tracks. So in both cases,
we see a strong generalization performance. Got it, got it. And when you say the the handcrafted
maps are out of distribution, how far out of distribution or are they out of distribution in any
particular ways? Are they more complex? Are they do they have different features?
Oh, yeah. So they have more blocks. They have more structure in the kind of, you know, levels you
get by just randomly sampling basically blocks on a on a on a map, right? You you're not necessarily
getting a lot of really complicated structure. But we have like mazes where you have a labyrinth
for example, or you have mazes where you have lots of different kind of corridors and you have to
basically check each of them and you have to backtrack what you have to memorize where you already
been. And and these were the kind of held out mazes. I don't have a quantification of how much
out of distribution they are, but basically on you look at the paper and you you eyeball basically
up here are the randomly generated ones. Here the handcrafted ones should see a very notable
difference. Got it, got it. And then what's next? What what what research directions? You know,
we've talked about several potential directions. What are you most excited about in terms of building
on this foundation? So one of the things I'm very excited about is this this space of unsupervised
environment design. I think we as a field only started to scratch the service of that. And then
you know, ideal world in the next kind of few years we have, I think, very interesting AI
systems that really can create very complex rich, you know, interesting, you know, whole worlds,
right? I mean, not just like 2D mazes, but you know, imagine kind of, you know, 3D Minecraft
environments, right? And we had then have also students student agents that learn to do very
interesting complex stuff in these environments. I think that would be something that would be very
exciting, but I think it requires a lot of additional work in that you need to basically,
I think, overtime compound complexity, right? If you were to design a level for me, I don't think
you would just randomly or like just with one kind of stroke sketch one, right? You would actually
start somewhere and then develop it slowly over time. You would test it out, right? See what
actually a student now does in the level. And then depending on whether it does really well or
poorly, you would start to, I guess, refine it a bit. So I think there's lots of stuff to be
to be done in that space. And there's some, one of the things I'm very excited about.
The other thing I'm excited about is I guess more ways to intrinsically motivate agents as we
discussed earlier, right? How do we make sure agents just get excited about expanding and knowledge
about certain dynamics in the environment? Really some kind of open-ended process that just
allows the agent to explore all kinds of things in the environment, becoming basically a scientist
within such a simulated environment. That's something that's also very exciting to me.
And then I think also just looking more for applications in other domains and environments.
I think one of the things that we really want to, I guess, be able to do is develop
methods that are of somewhat general nature, right? That's where we care about, can we start in
a grid world with discrete actions, but does it also work in a continuous control environment,
right? So this is, I think, very, very important. Likewise, I think it's very important for us as a
field to be very explicit about the kind of simplifying assumptions that are baked into some of the
environments that we use for research. And I think mapping that out in a bit more structured way
would be very useful as well. Awesome. Also, sorry, just on the environmental line aspect, I mean,
we talked about how it's useful to train like student agents that then generalize.
I think that's also something interesting, maybe going forward, where we also make sure that these
kind of levels might be interesting to a human, right? I'm not really sure how do we quantify that,
but that could be a nice side effect, right? How do we create more and more engaging content
for human players in some of these kind of environments? Right. Right. Awesome. Awesome.
Well, Tim, thanks so much for joining us and sharing a bit about what you're working on.
Yeah, thanks so much. I really was really excited in the discussion. Thanks. Thank you.