All right, everyone. I am here with Edward Wrath. Edward is a Chief Scientist at Boos
Alan Hamilton. Edward, welcome to the Twimal AI podcast. Thank you so much for having me.
Really excited to be here. Looking forward to jumping into our conversation. You lead a
machine learning research group at BAH. What is a machine learning research group at BAH? Focus on.
Yeah, so it's a little different for us compared to many other organizations that have research
teams because we are consulting firms. So our business model is basically based on renting out
people's brains. And you have some hard problem you want to solve. So we need to have smart people
who can work on these hard problems. So we sort of view research both as a way to sort of let
people know like, hey, we actually work on some really cool things that require this level of
difficulty and thought and challenge. But also as a way to train staff like one of the things that
we've been doing a lot of work around is adversarial machine learning where there's you have your
model that you've developed and you put blood sweat and tears into it and it's your baby and
you want it to work well and go into production. And there may be some nefarious actor out there
who wants to subvert your model. So like a lot of my work is in malware analysis, malware detection
where the malware author like actively wants to subvert the model. They don't want to be detected
as malware. They want to be able to run uninhibited. So if there is someone who's going to try and
sort of mess with your model and try to make it produce errors, how do you prevent that or how do
you even accurately quantify what's happening. And there's no course that you can sign up for yet
on adversarial machine learning and school that's not part of anyone's curriculum yet. So if we want
people of that skill set, we sort of have to grow them organically and research is one of the ways
to do that and to blow people up of these really deep technical skills that we need but are not
sort of off the shelf yet. Yeah, yeah. I'm glad you brought up adversarial ML because I know
that's an area of personal interest for you and that's one of the things that I wanted to dig
into with you as a way to get that conversation going. It's actually been quite a while since I've
had someone on the show focused on this intersection of AI and cyber security which has continued
to be of interest particularly as we see more and more activity let's say in the cyber security
realm. Can you give us an overview or what's your kind of temperature read your take on the space
and where it is and how it's evolved over the past couple of years. Yeah, I mean it's interesting,
it's if you go back to like the first like applications of machine learning for malware detection
goes back to like 1985 people have been looking at this intersection for a long time and in many
ways it's still nascent despite having been a problem and been something that like people were
really looking at for a long time in part because it's so different from normal data like okay
convolutional neural networks and deep learning have come in and eat and everyone's a lunch at
image classification at natural language processing a signal analysis all these different problems
but all these problems have some underlying similarity of like things near each other are
related to each other the words that I'm saying right now like they have meaning based on their
order and the things that I say tomorrow really have no relationship to what I'm saying today.
There's this correlation in time pixels in an image if you look at this sort of pixel on my shirt
and it's blue you look at the pixels around it they're probably going to be a very similar shade of
blue there's this spatial correlation that's true for signals as well malware that does exist
but it's so much more complex than that you've got this sort of arbitrary system designed by humans
that is like instruction code and assembly and how that gets converted into like literal zeros and
ones and how the compiler is optimizing the layout of the code and which functions get put together
and not and inlining and just a huge amount of complexity that is very different from what people
are working on it's a very different scale a single executable like if you go download a new browser
that's like 30 megabytes would be a really small browser download but if you look at that as one
data point that's a massive data point like that's huge like most people like data point you're
working on is maybe like a kilobyte at like the most we're talking about 30 plus megabytes is
like pretty like normal thing to occur anything if you're looking at your you've got some data set
of software programs and you've trained malware detector on software programs your browser would
be like a feature a 30 megabyte feature that you're trying to do inference or classification
against is that what you're that what you're about that it's like a variable size feature and like
maybe there's an image and maybe there's multiple images embedded inside of it maybe there's a
word doc embedded inside of it there's like every other file format could be embedded inside of this
one file format and it's describing like code this like thing that could do anything of arbitrary
complexity like that's what turning completeness is and we have proofs on like how you can't know
what any arbitrary code is going to do about running it well you don't want to run it because it
might be malware so there's there's just sort of this huge explosion of complexity as you dig into
all these details and machine learning in the broader communal sense has not really
developed the tools to deal with data that's so weird and so different in all these unique ways
so there's a lot of just sort of unsolved machine learning problems at this intersection
and that also creates lots of avenues for attack at this intersection because the malware author
they don't need to abide by their rules that's part of the whole point is they're trying to break
the rules if there's a spec that says oh you don't set this flag and executable because it will
behave poorly well if that helps the malware author they're going to do it they don't care
yeah so it's it's it's a very rich and interesting area I think from both like a machine learning
math side of like how do we get the math to work with these new kinds of complexities these new kinds
of relationships but also just from like the low level really technical side of like I could use
some undocumented instruction to try and make my malware work that like oh yeah this only runs
on new CPUs that have this undocumented instruction because it causes some weird side effects
wow and like I've seen things on like research that gets done on a like specter-based malware
where like the malware only works in the like prefetching of the CPU trying to prefetch code and
data so that if you run it on like the wrong type of CPU or like in a virtualized environment it
won't prefetch the same way malware won't run so you sort of hide what's actually happening and
if you just look at the code the code doesn't make it obvious what's going on because the malicious
intent is hidden to the prefetching logic so just a huge richness of complexity that that makes
it interesting and fun and malware is you know just one element or part of this broader kind of
cyber security patchwork or you know set of problems problem domain is it representative do you
think of the other aspects in that other aspects of cyber security kind of suffer from the same
kinds of problems or are they all kind of unique in their own ways I'm definitely I'm a machine
learning man first and learned about cyber as like an application area or malware specifically
so I don't want to speak too authoritatively but I think a lot of these have their own sort of
unique snowflake problems especially around data collection and building a data set that is
again sort of like unique to this problem space in general where if you want to get your data labeled
it's really easy to go like for images like you can a toddler can label images literally like
you could you could set up that app and they put it on the iPad and they would do it for hours
no special training required to be like this is a cat this is a dog like okay here's this
this arbitrary executable tell me if it's malicious or not or like what kind of malware family it's
from that's a huge amount of work or like if here's some keycap data here's some network traffic
data like is anything weird going on on this network I would just stare at you I don't know maybe
what do you what do you think the answer is like it's it's very technically deep and complex
and each each avenue sort of has its own unique problems
one of the ways that you've taken on this malware problem is a recent paper focus on
adversarial transfer attacks can you talk a little bit about that paper and the problem that
it's seeking to address yeah so this was a paper's adversarial transfer attacks with unknown
data and class overlap that a couple of people on our team have worked on Luke Richards was the
lead author on it some great work we also had one of our collaborators from Nvidia and UMBC this
paper we were really looking at a core adversarial machine learning problem which is
been motivated by a lot of work recently but you have some model that you want to defend
and we'll call you the victim because someone's going to try and attack you and so there's some
adversary that wants to attack the victim model and they know that the models there or they know
you're going to do it but they don't have access to the model specifically so quote unquote black
box attack black box it is black box and it's a specific type of black box attack that we
sort of generally call transfer learning because what the adversary does is they build their own
model that sort of does the same task and they attack their own model and the assumption is well
I built a good model you're doing the same thing these attacks should probably work on your model
and the research that's been done to date sort of says yeah that does work
and we were thinking about this and thinking about it from like okay if we were doing this in
really real life does this match reality and maybe maybe sometimes but oftentimes not because
what a lot of this work has done has sort of said I know you're working on this problem I know
you have a model to detect malware because you're the government and malware is coming at you or
you're a large bank or everyone has malware detectors you're supposed to that's part of the game
or you can you can imagine sort of like many different tasks you would expect like the
government should be doing this like that would make sense and if you're an adversary you just
want to like mess with people you're a bad actor and so you build your own model but you're not
probably going to have the exact same data that the victim does and you might not know like you're
know you know you you can guess what they're going to do but you don't know exactly how they've
set it up like there could be reasonable design choices on like well what are my classes exactly
and where is that line so if you're in that situation where you don't have access to their model
you're probably not going to have a perfect match for their data or how they've designed the
class structure and it sounds like a lot of the prior work assumed that the adversary was
operating from the same playbook so to speak it was using the same data and or the same classes
the exact same data and the exact same data and exact same classes guy which is like unrealistically
optimistic which like if you can defend against like an omnipotent adversary good for you
congrats but I want to know what's going to happen in real life so that's for the motivation
and I'm not claiming ours is perfect to real life but I think it's closer so we started building
some tests to sort of vary like from zero percent overlap in the data to like a hundred percent
and how much how much is that data overlap really a factor in the transfer success rate
and also overlapping the number of classes that are in common so you have like all the exact same
classes as each other to you have like two classes in common so like a very small attack
attack surface there we spoke a little earlier about the difficulty of kind of defining the data
in this space as a feature an executable or is it something else in this particular case in
the example that you used in this paper what was a piece of data feature and what did the labels
look like and this we were focusing just on the the adversarial machine learning part so we picked
easy data that everyone has access to so we just did image data like CIFAR 10 CIFAR 100
mini image net and the the classes were the normal classes like cat dog car truck
okay deer and frog I think are also classes in there
I mean we're just focusing on the the adversarial part for for this one all the complexity of
malware just like that's too much extra complexity right now right you're you're you're basically
trying you're hey let's step back take a simple model and just test this fundamental assumption
about transferability different data and classes yeah something that I often
probably probably one of the best skills that I try to like pass on to like employees and students
is like okay like you have this complex goal just figure out some way to cut this down into
different chunks because you can't eat the whole sandwich it's too big forget about an elephant
you can't even eat the sandwich it's too big you got to cut something off so we cut off this part
so we're using just image data's convolutional neural networks that everyone sort of like feels
comfortable with you're going to understand what the results mean and when we set this up
we we saw that both less class overlap and less data overlap both would hurt the attackers
success rate which makes sense but we also saw some odd behaviors that it wasn't sort of as
consistent as you would expect it wasn't sort of like the smooth degradation down like it would
get worse and it would like start to get better again but randomly and as we start like some kind
of generalization property kicking into effect or something that's that's part of what I think
it is because what really became very interesting is from just one of the base results of that
behavior we think a lot of it is like it once you sort of reach a minimum sort of threshold of
like lack of similarity there's a lot more randomness that comes into play that the model just
is not trained to like expect in any possible way and now it's making errors maybe not because
the adversary did such a good job crafting the example but the data is just so different from
what the model itself understands because the amount of overlap has decreased so much and
the the the really sort of scary part is when it comes to like okay you want to defend your model
what defenses work currently the the overall best defense is adversarial training
it's been the best defense basically since it was introduced in like 2017-2018 and it's pretty
simple strategy of like okay you have your model you train it and now as you're training attack
your own model then feed the attacked inputs back into the training and just sort of be doing that
continuously so you're constantly training the model to be better at correctly classifying attacked
data points and our result showed if you do this in this more realistic scenario adversarial training
actually weakens the defender wait what yeah the attack success rate increased on models that
had been adversarially trained I think what's happening there what we what we sort of believe is
going on is when you're doing adversarial training you're in a way overfitting to a very specific
adversary an adversary that has the exact same classes and data you do but when the adversary
has different classes their attacks are going to naturally go in different directions that your
model has just never optimized for because it sort of started from an initial condition and it
got better that it's sort of just converging on whatever initial path worked best and so it's
sort of overlearned to the sort of unrealistic scenario and these new attacks are tightly coupled
like the the data is the same because it's it's baked into the process of creating the model
exactly and so the attacks seem to transfer more successfully if the victim has done adversarial
training in this sort of imperfect knowledge scenario which if you're actually trying to build a
robust model for real life production like that's actually a huge concern now because you say okay
I'm going to keep my model private I'm going to try and sort of mitigate as much information that
the adversary could acquire by sort of keeping this close hold and you want to do all the best things
okay I'm going to do adversarial training like oh actually if you believe that's the correct
threat model you might not want to do that it might actually make you more susceptible
rather than less interesting can we maybe take a second to kind of punch into the degree to which
adversarial training and a lot of these you know techniques around adversarial ML generally
the way the degree to which those are you know practical concerns and implemented by people
that are building actual models versus academic thought exercises that people really aren't
thinking about when they're putting models in a production at this point but what's your read
on that from where you sit I think on average it's more academic for most real most most real world
like usage of it is more academic like people don't necessarily a reason to really believe
they're under attack so a lot of people motivate this with like self-driving cars that
someone's going to trick the self-driving car into plowing through a stop sign
which like I don't want that to be a thing that can happen to my future self-driving car
match true I'm sure maybe some horrible person out there like tries to screw of them but like in
general it's not like a very well-motivated threat like who's going around just trying to
destroy every self-driving car it's like it's important I think it's more important in like
the academic sense of like trying to figure out how to make models robust to just like errors
in general then it is there's an actual adversary trying to trick you and a lot of times a lot of
the research that gets done becomes sort of somewhat cartoonish and like the amount of information
that they give the adversary makes it like why would they do it this way if they were that
powerful like I remember seeing some work on like all adversarial attacks on medical imaging
and they'll they'll adjust the medical image and the to make the AI models would give you
their long prescriptions and the wrong drugs and the wrong medication to like hurt your health
and if they have like that much control to like you get all this data and like access model
it just flip a bit in the database like it seems I'm like if they're that powerful there's
so much easier things they could have done right so sort of the goal of like how we came up with
this work to begin with was like well in a realistic scenario what's it actually going to look like
and for malware it is a really like true true to life realistic problem that people do deal with
like day-to-day which is part of why I like doing work in this space is it's it's not academic
it is like this is really happening meaning not the the broad existence of motivated adversaries
but the specific application of adversarial attacks to in kind of the malware world
I mean a malware you know there are existing malware detectors that are based on machine learning
models and there are people out there that are trying to deploy adversarial attacks against those
models and there are people in that world that are building adversarial robustness into those
models like that's all real and extent today yeah that that that is all real to varying degrees
today it's more complex in the malware space because an adversarial attack in the malware space
can happen earlier in the process so because again like these they're so executables are so complex
you can sort of mess with the executable itself to maybe screw up the way that the antivirus
process is the features to begin with so you can change like the whole floor out from under the
the model that you're trying to fool uh and meaning like like obfuscation of the the malware code
within the broader executable or something different that that's one of many many possible ways so
you could uh there's a thing called packing which is like let me put my executable inside of
another executable so you're sort of you have to figure out how to peel this onion to figure out
what's going on underneath or like a dynamic analysis which is when you do try to run the malware
or to get features a lot of malware will just like initial like step of the malware is just like
wait 24 hours because you're probably not going to run this dynamic analysis for 24 hours you're
going to run it for like three minutes tops so they're just going to try and like outweigh you
and so like you might have features that like oh does it call this api does it call the crypto
functions that's that might be a good sign of ransomware does it call the file delete functions like
okay that's a really good sign of ransomware it has both of those oh they just wait until the clock
runs out then you never see the features to begin with um so there's more complex and interesting
ways that the malware adversary can sort of mess with the model uh and uh I I can go on like lots
of fun tangents on my favorite one that I've seen which is not I've never seen it actually used
by malware but it's more it's just fun that like this is possible uh there is this project that
people released called the mob fiscator uh fiscator mob like MOV until you've instructed yeah because
it's an instruction for people who are to wear it's like this is the assembly code that moves
data from one location in memory to another location in memory okay and so you might say like
please move like please move this memory from like please move this data from like memory into this
register because I'm going to do some work on it or from register like back to disk to save it or
whatever uh this one instruction has so many side effects that is actually turn turn complete
so you can compile any program into one that contains only the move instruction
ostensibly it looks like this program only moves data and never actually does anything with it
mm-hmm but it has so many weird side effects that you can actually and it works you can recompile
any program to contain only one single instruction wow because the program itself is just
putting bits into memory locations and executing them yep right and there's there's
enough special like side effect cases on there's one instruction that that's the only instruction
you technically need to be able to do anything on an x86 computer wow you see weird stuff like this
with malware so often it's just like yeah at anything you can think of like I'm sure there's some
way someone could get around this and then it becomes a numbers game I'm like how many more
machines am I protecting how many more cases am I covering and am I sort of making any new like
gaping holes that I need to address because you're not going to get it all um but you got to
that doesn't mean you sit around and go like well I can't solve it perfectly so I might as well
not do it no you build the best solution you can you sort of get it out there you try and fix
what you can and see how do they adapt what what happens next and sort of this continual back and
forth of you taking a step in the adversary taking a step so malware you know is a place where
these kinds of things are happening today and we kind of got to that from talking about the
adversarial or adversarial training adversarial robustness kind of incorporating into
training and that having an adverse effect on robustness um is there a solution to that
working on it I'm not out of a job yet though thank you
it's it's sort of a double edge sword if we can I mean if like the the gut reaction of everyone is
like these adversarial attacks are definitely a bad thing we don't want them to exist we've got to
get rid of them uh which yes it is definitely a bad thing uh but it's in the context of how things
are being used if someone's using a machine learning model in a bad way then being able to subvert
that model now actually becomes a defense a good thing so if someone is using the machine learning
model to sort of like create like a surveillance like state or something uh like okay that we're
not comfortable with that we don't like that um there's actually there was a recent paper I had
this idea years ago but didn't do it um I get no credit for just having a nice idea but uh this
is a really interesting paper that got published uh or put online at least on uh using like adversarial
attacks to figure out how to put on makeup in such a way that you look normal but the machine learning
model will just be like yeah there's no one there so sort of giving you a way to sort of get some
of your privacy back you don't want to be tracked or looked at so these are things that um they're
complex from many perspectives they're not just from a technical perspective but from like an
ethics perspective I'm like what is and is not an okay use of machine learning
how do we want to deploy these things these are the things that we often have to work about and
think about and be conscious of uh but it also does mean that adversarial attacks and defenses
are like whichever way it goes we we ultimately can or cannot defend against these attacks
also means we ultimately can or cannot subvert people using machine learning for
or inappropriate unethical use cases uh yeah so that's something that I uh think about a lot
the main idea is that hey we don't uh you know the research that's happening here isn't really
considering our real world scenario your paper considered a real world scenario and you found that
um in general the less overlap um the more difficult an attack is but in a kind of weird way where
a weird non-linear way and in addition we could from from the attackers perspective we could
restore some more predictable behavior to the attacker uh so if we sort of simulated uh
attacking a model with unknown classes or if sort of imperfect classes by sort of like
randomly masking them out and we generate the attacks so we're like each time we attack it we're
going to randomly pretend some of these classes don't exist and don't count um so maybe you're trying
to uh maybe the model's first gut instinct is to convert the uh model from predicting truck
to car you say well we've masked out car that's not an option so you're not getting credit for that
you have to do something else uh if we do that we restore a lot of behavior that makes more sense
so it it sort of removes the variance of uh class overlap from the attacker's accessory uh so
rewind this for me this is when you're training your target model you are doing what
so when we're when we're generating the attacks uh generating the attacks okay
okay to sort of transfer to the victim uh so the adversary has their own what we call a surrogate
model they built their own model that they think hopefully matches what you've done
and they're basically going to perturb their own surrogate model in order to simulate that
they don't know exactly what you're doing and that uh the attacker pays a penalty in terms of
attack success rate in order to do that but what they gain is sort of certainty about their
attacks success rate if that makes sense so in the normal situation uh maybe the average
success rate of their attack would have been 40% but they're not sure that it's actually 40%
they're well maybe it's between like 15 and 60 and I can't really tell what exactly it is
but then if you do this modified attack they're pretty sure that it's somewhere between like 30
and 35 so it's lower but they they actually know what they're going to get so kind of greater bias
less variance yeah exactly and on the the adversarial training um the adversarial robustness
training um are you or are you aware of folks that are like how would you go about trying to
um like reformulate that problem in light of kind of the real world thing like you know I'm thinking
of hey is there an analogy to dropout that's like class dropout where you kind of forget about
classes in the adversarial loop and like does that help like are folks working on that specific
problem we're not not the class dropout thing that the broader problem we actually tried the
class dropout thing and unfortunately did you we tried that one I didn't work we were very sad about
that but uh no I I don't know what the answer is yet uh something that I want to look at and
part of the problem with these experiments where they were hugely expensive to run because
instead of sort of attacking one model for one data set we have to attack like 50 models
for one data set because we have to vary the class overlap and the data overlap every single time
and then we want to run it multiple times for each combination because
you can pick different classes each time that might bias the results so it turns into this
computational explosion of model training and attacking so something that we want I want to look at
but I think we might need to figure out something more intelligent first is these approaches that
try to sort of build provably robust models from the onset where you can sort of think of it like
your model makes a prediction and it's sort of making a prediction about like a single data point
like one point comes in and you get one answer and what they try to do is they try to build models
this is one approach anyway there's multiple but they try to basically classify instead of one
data point like a region so you sort of have like the data point is the center and there's like a
sphere around it and you're saying everything in this sphere gets the same answer and if you can
do that then you've sort of you're provably robust to attacking that data point for a certain sized
radius and then as you train you try to sort of increase the size of that sphere that you can do so
that spheres start out sort of infinitely small well you just the data point and you try and push
them wider and wider as you go and that means you're becoming more robust theoretically that would
work better but I'm not sure in theory there's no difference between theory and practice but in practice
there is it sounds like that has strong implications on the the type of model you're using like
you know maybe even as far as not a neural network model or can you incorporate that kind of
technique into a neural network formulation you you can for a neural network it's it's really
expensive so it's sort of like if I wanted to do that for these experiments I'm going to increase
the compute time by like at least another factor of 10 or it took us like four or five months to run
all these experiments I was like all right 40 50 months okay maybe I think in terms of
real world like when you're really thinking through do I need to be concerned about an adversarial
attack am I an entity that is likely to be attacked if I'm a government if I'm a bank if I'm a
large enough corporation then yeah you you are likely to be targeted and attacked then okay what
what are the models that I train that are sort of the most likely to be attacked or that people
are going to try and subvert so like if you're a credit card company like you have fraud detection
models yeah that people are trying to subvert all the time so okay I have this model like I have
these models that I have then identify these are the models at risk and now let's really think
through like the specifics of the threat model for this particular thing not this sort of academic
abstract I can apply this to any problem kind of thing but what do we know about the domain
that we can use to build a robust model for this specific problem that's what I've had the most
success doing anyway that's the way that I generally try to help like our clients approach these
kind of problems is to really focus in on that scope and narrow down like where do we actually
need to do this let's not panic and think that everything's under attack all the time because
that's not realistic and you're going to give yourself a heart attack and we've done that we've
done some of that for malware for specific kinds of malware models and we've done some of that
for a computer vision before and gotten a lot of success much more quickly with that approach
and as you say like part of that can be like well maybe you shouldn't use a neural network maybe
you should be using a linear model and sort of carefully crafting your your features to make a
linear model work well or maybe a shallow decision tree or a random forest or something would be
better because you can sort of understand to what degree can this really be attacked and what's
that envelope and and design around it so like part of how we did that for some of our malware work
was if we if we go back to like the example of dynamic analysis where if you're actually going to
see the thing run let's just assume it's not perfect I don't claim perfection
but if you say okay I'm actually going to see the thing run I'm going to see it
delete the freed in the files encrypt them write them out delete the original files
I know this is malware and for it to be ransomware it has to like actually have those steps
if you build a model that can only sort of normal models look for things that both indicate like one
or the other so I look for things that tell me it's ransomware I look for things that tell me it's
not ransomware that's a design flaw in this scenario I shouldn't be looking for things that tell me
it's not ransomware because if it does those sort of finite things that qualify it's ransomware
and what malware will do is what what they can do is just insert lots of random other benign
activity like oh look at all these benign things I do that way that outweighs all these malicious
things I did and a normal machine learning model go yeah that's right you did do more benign
things than malicious things you are benign that doesn't make sense at all if you do anything
malicious it's malicious and by default everything is benign it's benign until you do something bad
so we can incorporate that into the model that there are no features that contribute to a score of benign
that that's just sort of the default and then you have to do enough sort of malicious indicators
for the model to change its decision to be like no no no you're actually malicious you don't get
to run anymore and is the the implication then that the models that tend to be used in the space are
kind of very heavily hierarchical or ensemble or something like that where you're
identifying you've got modules that are identifying specific features or characteristics and then
kind of bubbling that up like Microsoft has published some of their like strategy for how they
handle Windows Defender and trying to protect computers and they they've published they have
this whole hierarchical strategy of like okay here's the super fast model and sort of
they can handle a lot of things and for the things that can't like bumping that up a stage
to something more complex it's going to do something more sophisticated and I forget how many
stages it had in it but like the end stage was sort of like okay we're actually going to like run
this and like a dynamic environment in the cloud to try and figure out what this is doing
so you yeah people definitely do that of this sort of building this hierarchy of
speed and complexity trade-offs because you can't afford to run everything through dynamic
analysis all the time like that would just be running all computers but again like there's
not a lot of computers be running all the programs that we want to run to make sure the computers
can run them it doesn't make sense right right right yeah when you were talking about dynamic
analysis I imagined it to be uh well maybe not dynamic I imagined it to be like this design time
tool like hey we collect all these samples of things in the wild and like we run them through this
dynamic analysis thing and like maybe we're creating labels or something but it sounds like
from this Microsoft example it's like no you try to run this app and it says hey hold on I'm
going to you know put this in the malware detector in the cloud and I'll be back to you shortly
yep I remember one of my colleagues who's uh he's a malware analyst uh a lot of experience
you're telling me about how like for the for the analysts who are just doing their job like as part
of a manual process to figure out what things are they would have a big sort of a virtual machine
cluster to run things and try and observe them and see what they're doing and uh sometimes there
there is malware that has what's called a VM escape where there's a bug in the VM and it is
possible for the the code to recognize it's being run inside a virtual machine and leave the
virtual machine and infects the host that it's on and occasionally that would happen and they
would just be like all right burn everything down like yeah this is you're complex now just
light everything on fire we build again from scratch this is the only way to make sure it's clean
right right uh that that might be a slightly hyperbolic description but it's the
the complexity is just so great it's never ending yeah awesome awesome um
what what kind of future directions you know as if we haven't already talked about enough of them
are you excited about in this video uh I'm excited about uh graph neural networks
they've been getting more traction the past two years uh that I think is good uh some of it's
been a little contentious on like relating to a theme of uh reproducibility that's also been
picking up on like okay graph neural networks were very nascent a few years ago and then there was
sort of like a small like kickoff of people iterating and publishing oh here's my new fancy this
and then a lot of people were saying like oh actually all this is wrong and really you just
didn't tune things correctly but so there there's still a lot of sort of working things out there
I think uh and are because like the complexity of dealing with graphs like it's now much more arbitrary
connectivity and how much this depends on the specific kinds of graphs you were looking
what looking at versus someone else's graphs uh but I think a graph structure really is going to be
the most at least from like a machine learning modeling perspective the most ideal way to model
a lot of malware you can sort of create this graph of like which code parts connect to which other
code parts you can have features on the nodes of the graph but also features on the edges of the
graph so you can also have uh if there's a chunk of the executable that you couldn't disassemble you
couldn't figure out what's there you could still have that as part of the model with some features
sort of indicating that like this is connected here somehow but we're not sure what's actually
happening at the node um like bailed to parse correctly uh so I think that's something that
is probably the right direction to be headed in but is not yet fast enough and scalable enough
for the malware sort of use case where like our data points are like the size of other people's
datasets um like I wanted one of the datasets that uh I work with regularly the largest file in
the dataset has like 200 megabytes which is like all as if our 100 is 200 megabytes like literally
there's one data point is the size of this dataset everyone's using uh it's interesting that you
provided that context about graph uh graphical models graph uh neural nets has applied to this
space I'm pretty sure one of my first interviews around cyber was on graph stuff and I did not
realize that there was a bit of a graph neural networks and security winter that happened
I'm not sure it's so much as a winter is uh the the graph neural networks for malware just like
hasn't germinated yet in the first place okay so the graph neural networks in the machine
or in the machine learning land people have done graph based things for malware a lot before but
just like normal graphs not neural network based uh got it uh so I I can see like the room for
rules to collide but they haven't collided yet got it very cool very cool well Edward it was
wonderful chatting and learning a bit about what you're up to in this space thanks so much for
joining us yeah thank you again for having me it was a really fun conversation and I really enjoyed