All right, everyone. Welcome to another episode of the Twimmel AI podcast. I'm your host, Sam
Charrington. And today I'm joined by Erwin Bello. Erwin was formerly a research scientist at
Google Brain and is now on the founding team at a stealth AI startup. Before we get into today's
conversation, please be sure to take a moment to head over to Apple Podcasts or your listening
platform of choice. And if you enjoy the show, please leave us a five star rating and review.
Erwin, welcome to the show. Thank you. Thanks for having me. I'm looking forward to our conversation.
We're going to be digging into your research on sparse expert models as well as some of the
trends you're following in large language models. But before we do that, I'd love to have you
share a little bit about your background and how you came to work in machine learning.
Yes, so I have a background in applied math and stats. I studied both in France. Then came to
Stanford as a great student, mostly statistics and computer science. And during that time,
studying, you know, I slowly got into AI and mostly deep learning, starting with computer vision,
also doing some natural language processing. And I thought that that line of focus was really
interesting. And so after graduating, I went to Google Brain to keep working on deep learning.
I spent, you know, roughly five years there, mostly doing deep learning research,
some product stuff as well, worked on a bunch of, you know, on a wide range of projects,
like starting with a combinatorial optimization and ranking, also worked on some auto-ML,
where you use machine learning to learn machine learning itself. And most recently, I worked on
computer vision and also large scale models with a focus on this new exciting class of architectures
called sparse expert models. Nice. That is a great segue. Why don't we jump into that topic?
I guess we should start at the top. What is a sparse expert model?
Yeah, so perhaps the easiest way to define them is by contrast to regular dance models.
So regular dance models apply the same parameters to all inputs. And by contrast,
sparse expert networks dynamically select which parameters to use for each input.
So that means that part of your neural networks, like parts of your neural network are activated
on a pair example basis. You know, in practice, if you have a batch of examples,
all of the networks, parts will be activated, but for a single example,
that single example is only going to see part of the network parameters. And so this allows
to increase model capacity in the sense that you're working with much more parameters
without increasing computation of flops. Because each input and in that context input can refer
to either sentence or a token. Each input only interacts with the same number of parameters and
therefore has the same amount of computation applied to it.
And the case that you're looking at here with these sparse expert models, are you specifically
targeting extreme levels of sparsity in the data? Or, no, okay, no. So usually other examples of
sparsity can refer to the datasets. For example, you know, in reinforcement learning,
people will talk about sparse rewards. Sparse expert models like the sparsity is in the model.
And the reason the way you can, the reason why it's called spars is because they're equivalent to
having very large dense models where parts of the model weights are zeroed out. And so if you look
at your metrics multiplies, at your matrices in your model, having a set of experts is the same
as having a very large matrices with a lot of zeros. And so this kind of sparse.
Sorry, experts in this case refers to dynamically swapping out parameters based on an error.
In this case, like it's sort of an independently learned neural network that has unique weights.
And so typically you'll have a bunch of them, like let's say you're working with a hundred experts.
And an input comes in. You have a router network that decides where to send that output, that input,
you know, you might send it to only one expert or three experts. You reach two experts.
You know, so the experts take the input, computing output, and then at the end of your layer,
the expert outputs get sort of average with expert probabilities as well.
On top of that, when you train these architectures, you have a low-spanning
thing objective to make sure that all the experts are, you know, used roughly uniformly because
you don't want to be in a situation where, you know, a lot of your experts are
unused during training because that's bad for utilization. But yeah, at the very high level,
this is equivalent to having a very large dense matrix with a lot of zeros.
Is having some large number of independently trained experts, I guess the way I originally heard
you describe this or what I thought I heard was not necessarily these independently trained experts
or networks, but swapping out parameters at a particular layer of a single network based on
the input. Are those kind of functionally equivalent? Yeah, that's correct, yeah.
Yeah. So, you know, typically you'd have a dense layer, you have an input,
it's multiply in the, you know, in the easiest case, it's multiply by matrix and that matrix has weights
and it corresponds to a single expert, right? In the case of mixture of experts, now you have
a lot of experts, you know, it can go up to hundreds, even more. And you selects, each input is
routed with a network that is also trained. Yeah, everything is trained, you know, jointly, but, you know,
that router sends an input to an expert and that expert does the computation. And the other experts
do not get to see that input, so that's why it's pass. Yeah, this allows, you know, the networks to
like vastly expand the number of parameters because instead of having, you know, one expert in the
dense of, in the case of a dense network, now you have, let's say, a hundred. And so these
these layers have, you know, a hundred times more parameters. These parameters are not sort of
functionally equivalent to dense parameters because they're sparse and so it's not the same as
just, you know, a hundred X in your model size, but it does bring a lot of benefits at pre-training
and now it's when we're tuning on the stream applications as well. And are each of the experts
also typically deep networks, or did they tend to be shallower networks then?
Okay, so it's usually, you know, usually your entire deep neural net is pretty deep, so let's say, you know, 50 layers. But each
expert layer is usually, you know, a two layer neural net actually. Okay, you know, you can do it one or two
like we do two because, you know, paper, it's tied to our choice of activation functions, but those
are pretty shallow. And we find that this is kind of the best, this gives the best results. Another
thing we found in that paper is that you don't want to use expert layers everywhere because that
leads to a bad sort of quality to latency tradeoff. So, you know, the name of the game in a lot of
these researchers to get the most performance at a given, you know, training cost or in
French budget, right? And so, when you do sort of, when you optimize your architecture, what you do
is like you're trying to get like, no, good accuracy, but maintaining the network speed. And so, for
that we find that, you know, having expert layers, every four blocks of layers is a good, is a good
choice. And that's what we went with in that paper. Okay. Can you talk a little bit about the
kind of the scalability of the method? How well does it scale? And what did you have to do to get
it to scale? So, just zooming out a little bit. With mixture of expert models, now you have
two dimensions that are different. So, you have the number of formulas versus the flops or the
amount of computation. Usually, they're the same. For dense models, they're the same because more
primers means more computations as well. With expert models, if you scale the number of experts,
you're not scaling the number of computation that is applied, for example. And so, this adds
like an additional dimension that, you know, makes the problem a little bit more difficult to study.
But so, yeah, actually, scaling mixture of expert models was kind of an solved problem
that motivated our research on the subject. And so, one thing that people noticed was that
they were able to scale the number of experts, to the number of primers. But when they were
scaling the flops, or like just the amount of computation applied throughout the model,
training these models would usually lead to instabilities. So, until recently, these models were
quite unreliable at scale, at computation scale, flops scale. And so, you know, one contribution of
our recent work with my co-workers at Google Brain was to figure out how do we make this large scale
mixture of experts train stably, right? So, you know, we did a large scale study of
quality versus stability trade-offs. One thing we found is that usually the techniques to improve
stability, health accuracy or performance quite a bit. And so, that's, you know, that's not super
satisfying. We ended up sort of repurposing an auxiliary loss called the Z loss. So, that loss
is usually applied to the final sort of layer logits. Now, we applied it in the router of the
experts. So, again, the router is the small neural network that takes inputs and decides where to
which experts to send them. And so, one thing we found was that when we apply an auxiliary loss
on the router to sort of make the probably distribution over which experts to send each input,
we make that distribution more, you know, more smooth. We found that this helped a lot with
stability. So, that's one of the contribution of the paper. Another, you know,
a line of work was that you want to design these models and scale them while taking
your hardware into considerations. So, that process of routing inputs to experts, you know,
requires your accelerators to communicate between them. So, you know, let's say in our case,
we were working with TPUs. And so, you know, one simple way to see it is like, let's say, you know,
you have one expert per TPU, right? So, depending on where you want to send an input,
you're going to have to send that token to a different TPU. And so, there are communication costs
associated with that process. And so, that's kind of, yeah, a requirement to think ahead and think
about, you know, the trade-off of communication versus computation to set some of the model dimensions
optimally. And so, that's one thing we explored a bit that we explained in the paper.
And did you set those dimensions empirically or did you develop some formulation for
how you might optimize that? A little bit of both. I would say, it's mostly empirical, but
you know, in what direction to go usually. So, the process is usually, you know, you'll train
a network and you'll both look at its, you know, its loss or accuracy. And at the same time,
you'll profile the network. And so, you'll see, okay, how that much time is spent on, you know,
communication in that layer, that much time is spent on computation in that layer. And as you're
run more and more experiments, you start getting a sort of a mental model for how to, you know,
improve performance or improve latency without holding the other. So, that was kind of an iterative
process mostly. Going back to your previous point about the introduction of ZLOS,
you know, was it clear in the process of designing the architecture that, you know,
that was what you needed to do? Or how did you get to, oh, ZLOS is going to fix this.
Well, you know, the credit goes to one of my collaborators, Sparratt, who figured out, but,
no, so, you know, we started by exploring sort of all the classic techniques to, to improve
stability. You know, usually it's like you inject some noise so that if the model goes
unstable, it's used to walking with noise. And so, maybe it can recover from that instability.
Another technique is that you clip activations so that the model does an output, you know,
activations that are out of its usual range. But these techniques, you know, we found that they
held model quality a lot. So, that's not satisfying. I think we thought about the ZLOS in the context of
around of errors and numerical precision. So, you know, one direction that a lot of recent
large tail modeling work is exploring is to reduce, like, you know, to use lower precision
format, format, exactly quantization. Because this enables more efficient communication
cost between processes, between processors and our memories, also faster computation,
and, you know, just also less memory requirement for storing distances and activations.
The issue with lower precision formats or quantization is that it comes at the expense of larger
round of errors, right, because depending on which precision format you have, you know, sort of a minimum
distance between two consecutive floating points. And so, yeah, if you use lower precision,
it's faster, but larger round of errors. And in certain cases, this round of errors can lead to
instability that you can't recover from. This is when, you know, the training loss
all of a sudden explodes, and you don't recover from from that point in the weight space once
you fridge that. And so, what the ZLOS does is that, so it's a little penalty that you add on top
of the logits of the router to encourage these logits to be small in value. And because they're
smaller, they're more accurately modeled in floating point format. And so, what we found is that,
so first of all, whenever you use logits, you want to use sort of a FP32 format,
like kind of a high precision format, because these logits are like exponentiated. And so,
if there's a small round of error in the logits, there's going to be a much larger round of error
in the exponentiated logit, which are the probabilities. But we found that, so, you know,
that's a trick that, you know, a lot of people know, and most of these architectures are using,
it's like, you use float 16 everywhere, or B float 16 everywhere. But in your softmax functions,
or when you have a logit, you use, you cast your inputs to float 32. But that wasn't enough
for the router. And so, the idea was like, yeah, let's, you know, let's have this additional loss
to make sure that these logits are even smaller, so that they can be more accurately modeled.
To be clear, were you also using quantization in your process, or was it more
quantization in general introduces noise, and z-loss is used to fight, you know,
quantization noise may be at a work with our noise. Our architectures, you know, we use B float 16.
She's a precision format with 16 bits, which is slightly different from, well, actually quite
different from FB 16. But, you know, B float 16 is supported on TPUs, and it has sort of a larger
range of numbers it can, it can represent, but at the cost of also larger round of errors compared
to FB 16. And so, you know, we already knew of this trick of always using, you know, full
precision or FB 32, when you're used, when you're in logits or before applying softmax or
exponential, exponential, exponential. So, we already kind of did that by default. You know,
we're not the ones that figured out that trick out. I think we explained it pretty well. We,
know, we go in depth in that paper, you know, trying to solve as a guide for people who want to
design large scale models and sparse models in general. But we didn't invent that. What we
figured out though was that this wasn't enough in the router. So, remember that the router,
you know, decides which, where to, which experts to send each tokens to. In practice, you know,
the router outputs are probably distribution over all of the experts. So, you know, this is
implemented by a softmax, right? Like, you take, you have a scalar for, you know, or like a
log probability for where to send the expert, your input token, and then you take a softmax of that.
And so, we thought, you know, if FB 32 is not enough, what can we do? Right? Like,
one thing you can do is to push these logits to be smarter, so that run of errors, how to even less.
What did you find experimentally overall with the method? What, what, what data sets did you
benchmark it on and what kind of results did you see? Yes. So, we pre-trained on, mostly on C4,
like CommonCrawl, you know, which is a few hundred billions or even more depending on how you filter
tokens. But so, one of the issues that we also solved in that paper was that people were having
sort of uncertain quality when fine-tuning this mix of expert models. So, usually the way you
get set up the art and this NLP task is by pre-training large language models for quite some time,
like, you know, hundreds of billions of tokens, and then fine-tuning on the task of interest.
And so, sparse models were showing a lot of promise in the pre-training phase where you
you would see, you know, speed ups around 4 to 7x, you know, so that would mean, like, you know,
instead of training a dense model for like 10 days, I can get the same results with a sparse
model for two days, trained for two days, but only at pre-training. When you would move to that second
phase of fine-tuning, yeah, like the sort of improvement of the sparse model over the dense model
would kind of like vanish, you know, and this was, you know, that was kind of a big issue, right?
So, there were two big issues. Meaning, pre-training took just as long as with a dense model or
pre-training took way longer and undid all the gains on, I'm sorry, fine-tuning.
So fine-tuning undid all the gains. Okay. Usually fine-tuning is faster because the datasets are
faster, so you were less about sort of the duration of fine-tuning, but fine-tuning undid all the gains.
Okay, so that was the second issue we addressed in that work, the first one being that
these models didn't scale reliably because of instability. And so, you know, we
we run a lot of experiments on fine-tuning and we identified a rather counter-intuitive
property, which is that the way you fine-tune sparse models is quite different than the way you
want to fine-tune dense models. And so, if you just take the same hyper-primers that you usually
take for dense models, those hyper-primers are pretty bad for sparse models and actually
using them for fine-tuning will undo all the gains that you had from pre-chain.
And so, we had to, you know, we come up with sort of hyper-primer recommendations
in the paper. Usually, you want to increase the noise at a high level, you want to increase the
noise when fine-tuning sparse expert models. We believe that this is because sparse models are
more of a prone to other feeling, right? With sparse models, you have a much larger
modeling capacity because you have way more parameters. And so, there's a risk of other
feeling on these, you know, smaller fine-tuning datasets. Another thing that, you know, is a
potential hypothesis, you know, there's no way to, no one has really verified that yet, but,
you know, I think that's kind of an ectotic evidence from a couple of papers that this is the case,
is that there is, there is a range of parameters versus computation that is optimal for sparse
models and you don't want to deviate too much from that range. So, you know, as I said earlier,
now, the amount of compute and the number of parameters are not necessarily related
anymore because when you increase the number of experts, you increase parameters, but you don't
increase computation. You know, and a bunch of papers have tried to, you know, yeah, let's use
a thousand experts, you know. And so, you have a Nance model, like a sparse model with
trillion of parameters, but relatively much fewer computations. And so, I think there's some
evidence that this is a bad scenario and that you want to keep in the more, you don't want to stay
in the more reasonable ratio of parameters versus compute. And yet, there's this like, you know,
maybe somewhat instantiated theory that parameters correspond to knowledge and computation correspond
to, corresponds to intelligence, you know, for whatever nibblest definitions of knowledge and
intelligence, you want to work with. But I think this kind of makes sense, right? It's like more
parameters, like parameters can encode knowledge and computation referred to, yeah, how much
computation, how much can you sort of modify an input. So, that kind of makes sense to me. And
this is also what's supported by some of these experimental results. What
tasks did you, were all of the tasks that you were looking at in the paper NLP tasks? Yes.
And is the method applicable to other types of tasks? Yeah, it's actually been applied
to vision kind of concurrently. Like the first user of mixed-up export models was for NLP,
but yeah, it's been done in vision since. So, this is really like a modeling or like a new class
of architectures. You can apply to different modalities, different tasks. I think, you know,
maybe NLP and maybe textual domains, I think intuitively, might make more sense. Because
tokens are kind of sparse, you know, in the NLP. Whereas vision, I feel like, is a bit more
continuous. And do you see these types of models as being something that, you know, it's a tool
on the shelf or in the tool bag and under a certain set of conditions, you know, it might be the
tool that you reach for, or do you see it as more of a, you know, a step in evolution. And this
is what we're going to be doing as a standard approach at some point in time.
So, I think our paper tries to take it from, you know, the format to the letter.
Okay. So, this is definitely, you know, like an additional tool, not two chefs in the
deep learning toolbox per se. But the results are comparing enough that this is something you
seriously want to consider. Again, as I said, there are quite some technical details in
getting them to work reliably. Also, especially making them fast on your hardware and software
stack. So, you know, as I explained before, like depending on some of the, you know, under communication
costs on your hardware, you might want to set this mixture of experts differently.
Then there's also a question at inference, which is that, you know, if you do inference for a
single sort of input, it's very inefficient because you have all these other experts that aren't
used at the same time. And so, I would mostly use them for, like, batch inference when you know
that all of the experts are going to be used. That's one. Another thing that makes inference a little
bit more complicated is that, you know, with a dense model, if you have a very small batch size,
you know, it can fit on few accelerators. But now, sparse models may have much more, you know,
way more parameters. And so, you need a large number of GPUs or TPUs also at inference.
So, and again, that may only be worth it if you know, if you have high throughput, like a lot of
queries per second, and you can batch things together. But I would say there's definitely something
to consider seriously. It just takes a little bit more technical expertise. And, you know,
there are also a lot of other things that I think are very exciting in the space at the moment
that people should also consider. That kind of complimentary, you know, like, mix of experts,
I really see as like this new class of architectures that I really think, I think, you know,
I think in 10 years it's going to be like, what are people who are really applying, like,
all the same parameters to all inputs, like that's kind of insane, right?
Well, I wanted to go down on the idea of new class of architectures. One question that was
emerging for me is, in some ways, it sounds like a technique. And in other ways, it sounds like
an architecture, meaning, you know, there's part of me that wants to, hey, can we just take,
you know, off the shelf burt or something and apply mixture of experts at individual layers?
You know, verse, but you've also articulated that there are, you know, that there are constraints
around the number of consecutive layers that you'd want to have, for example,
to suggest that, you know, it's not ever going to be a plug-and-play kind of thing. Can you talk
a little bit about that? I think it's kind of this, you know, if you think about belt and GPT,
you know, these architectures have also been optimized, right? Like, the way that the model
dimensions are set, or like, the normalization, the activation functions, like, people have
optimized these over the years. And the fact that we recommend, you know, hey, maybe apply
the sparse layer every four layers, that's just an optimization that we figured out and that people
can apply directly, or like some of our recommendations on how to set up some of the export-related
dimensions based on the hardware. There's also something that we figured out that people can
apply directly. I would say it's harder to, you know, understand and to work with then
dance models, but, you know, for some of these large-scale runs that, you know, are costing
in the millions of dollars, this is something that, you know, it's worth figuring out.
Yeah, and maybe another way to ask my question is, you know, if you, if, you know, knowing what you know
and having this tool available, you wanted to create a kind of, you know, best-in-class,
large-scale language model, would you, like, start with, you know, a bird or a GPT or something,
and try to apply mixture of experts to it, or would you start with, you know, what you know
about mixture of experts, and try to build off of that to get to a language model. Does that
question make sense? Yeah, I see what you mean. I would start with, you know, the easiest,
which is, you know, selling from GPT or about, then, like, creating, like, I think we really wrote
this paper as a sort of a design guide for using mixture of experts. Got it. So it's not, you know,
fundamental, new, it's not, I'm not trying to, it's both disparage it. And new architectures.
That's the technique of having mixture of experts, right? Like, now you have, you have these
two dimensions that you can scale independently and so on. And Sparsity in general is kind of a,
I was going to say it's a mindset, but, you know, it's a, it's a general technique, right? But if you're just,
a practitioner, or you want to use them in, like, you don't care too much about figuring things out,
then I recommend using sort of the architectures that people have figured out. Right, right.
And what I'm here is not fundamentally incompatible with existing things. You just have to,
you know, be careful in how you apply it and follow along with some of the learnings that,
you know, this paper articulates and what will surely come after. Yeah, exactly. So the same way,
I guess, yeah, you know, the same way we have different architectures, like CNNs, you know,
transformers, like births, GPT, others, you can specify all of those architectures, right?
In that paper, we walk with, uh, in color of the color transformers models. And so our recommendations
are kind of general, but also mostly applied to in color of the color models. But if you were to,
you know, specify a, a, a, you'd have to do something slightly different, you know, and so it's kind
of like a new, it's like a new class in the same way that, like, it opens a new dimension for scaling
these models. You can take any architecture and make it spouse on that spouse, basically.
Awesome. Awesome. We had a couple of other things that we wanted to talk about and, you know,
maybe one we can jump into is, you know, and it follows a little bit from talking about language
models, but you are, you've got some research interests in kind of retrieval problems and alignment
problems in that space. Let's talk a little bit about what you've seen on the retrieval side.
Tell us about the problem and why it interests you. Yeah, so, you know, one thing I said when we're
talking about spouse models is that one of the benefits of increasing the number of parameters
that has two impacts, two factors, right? Like, first, you have additional compute at training
and inference time. And so the model is smaller in a way, but you also have increased
memorization of the training data. You know, again, there's a story that more parameters
corresponds to more knowledge. And so rather than simply scaling the model size, one alternative
is to equip models with ability to directly access a large database when performing predictions.
And so this is also like what a recent line of fork is exploring, just like retrieval from
large databases as a complementary to simply scaling language models. And so there are a few
sort of like different directions. The first one is retrieving from the training data set.
There's this recent paper called Retro, like retrieval enhanced transformer from friends at DeepMind,
where they augment the training set with, you know, each chunk of the training set
with its key nearest neighbors from the training database. And so during training and also at
inference, the model has access to these neighbor chunks and can utilize them when making predictions.
And so what they find is that, you know, you can match the performance of much larger
language models with much smaller language models. So I think in their papers, they say, you know,
we have like comparable results as GP3 with a model that's 25 times smaller. And so, you know,
of course, you know, this retrieval process, you know, adds some latency and some, you know,
some complexity, but, you know, this kind of like scaling gains, like 25x, also very exciting.
That's, yeah, something else to explore besides just scaling or like sparsity.
And I think that's very interesting. There's one thing even more recent that
consists in like retrieving from the web, right? So, you know, when you retrieve from a fixed
training database, you're not going to be up to date with the world's latest knowledge and
events, right? There's this aspect of generalization that scaling doesn't help with,
it's like temporal generalization. Like if your model was trained in 2019, it's not going to know
about 2021. You know, you could argue that like a good enough model can predict the future,
but I don't think we're there yet. So, so what people have have proposed is to, you know,
continuously update the database with the latest state of the world and the latest knowledge,
but that's basically the internet, right? So, what you can do is like outsource
documentary retrieval to the web by using, you know, like a search engine, like Microsoft being
or Google search. And yeah, learn, have your language model learn to interact with the web
to retrieve documents that help for predictions. So, there's this recent paper from a
player that I really like called WebGPT that does just that where, you know, they have humans navigate
the web to answer questions. So, they collect demonstrations from how humans use the web,
and then they train a language model to replicate that. And so, similarly, they show that like a
much smaller model can match performance of much larger models and that this retrieval process helps
into factual accuracy, truthfulness, coherence, and so on. And so, I think that's also very promising.
Are these these ideas in the case of the the data set or the web? Are we primarily using retrieval
to augment generation? Or one way to use retrieval is to to augment generation, right? You
reach out to some data set, you get some chunk of text and that gives you a little bit more richness
to manipulate when you're trying to spit something out. Another way is to think about the
data set as as you described earlier, kind of a pure knowledge store that you're kind of,
I think it was like operating on when you're trying to make an inference decision. How do you
do you see aspects of both of those? And how do you think about retrieval?
How do you distinguish also maybe the distinction between both aspects is like how clean the database is?
Is that correct? I think what I'm trying to get at is when the how and when the data is being
used and you know, maybe pulling it back to this analogy, you know, how kind of pure the databases
to what degree is the data is the database really knowledge as opposed to augmenting expressiveness
later? It's mostly the the later like. Okay. In this in this in this recent walks, you know,
the retrieval knowledge base is just your training data set or whatever the web gives you, you know,
and so this is going to be very noisy. This isn't like, you know, sort of entity, entity knowledge
bases where you have, you know, like person, date of birth, like country, right? This is just like,
you find a nearest, you find the top K nearest neighbors in all of your training
corpora and you use that to have additional context when making predictions. And that's kind
of enough to get really good results. You know, it could be that you get better results with sort
of a more created database retrieve from, but I think that, you know, your efforts are and budget
are this better spent somewhere else. We also mentioned alignment and those problems. Can you share
a bit about what you're seeing there? Yeah. So, you know, dislodged language models are kind of
becoming the the Swiss army knife of of an LP. They have fairly amazing like transfer learning
capabilities in the future or zero-shot setup event. So, you train on a lot of text mostly coming
from the internet and then at inference, the model is doing pretty good at like random tasks
that weren't really part of the training set. But there's one sort of issue here is that the
pre-training objective that we use to train these language models is basically predict the next
token, right, from a web page in the internet. You know, that's where most of the data comes from.
And so, that objective is quite different from the objective, you know, follow the user's
instructions, you know, and preferably in a helpful and safe manner. And so, as a result,
like large language models, you know, in spite of all the impressive results that have led to
are not that good at following people's instructions, right? There's like a misalignment between
how you train them and how we intend to use them. And so, there's been efforts towards sort of aligning
these models with human intent by fine tuning them on data we care about. So, they're kind of like
two lines of work in the direction. The first one is called instruction tuning, where during fine
tuning, you're going to augment each task with a verbal description of the task itself, right? So,
you should fine tune on, you know, translation data. You're going to be like,
translate from, you know, English to French, then you're going to have your English sentence
in the target is going to be the French sentence. And by having enough of these tasks that are
described verbally, the hope is that at inference, the model can generalize across new tasks that are
unseen during fine tuning. So, using that example of translating again, maybe at inference,
I could be like head translate from legalese to regular or simple English. And because the model
kind of knows what it's supposed to do when translating, now it just has to sort of, you know,
understand, okay, what is legalese and what is regular simple English to perform that new unseen
task. And so, you know, there's a similar story here that you get equivalent performance
as much larger models. I think this paper called T0 reports, you know, 16, like similar
performance with a model that are 16 times smaller. The second line of work in the direction is
more direct alignment, where, you know, it's mostly driven by open AI and public. What they did is
that they basically gave access to these models. They gave access to these models to people that,
you know, just try to use them. And they generate like the collect actual data of how users want to
use these models. Yeah, basically, it's kind of like assistant-assistant like data, right? Like
help me plan a wedding or like help me write a marketing campaign for Red Bull or whatsoever.
And so, they use this approach called reinforcement learning from human preferences,
which is a two-step process. So the first step is to collect comparison data based on human
preferences. And so, for example, you can output, you know, let's say, so human inputs,
some prompt to a model and the model will propose two-candy data outputs. Then the model
selects which one it prefers, right? Sorry, the human selects which one it prefers. And so,
that process creates a data set of comparison data, right? Like given to, given an input and two
candidate outputs, this is the one that is preferred by humans. So what you can do is train a model
on that data. And this is called a reward model, because you're going to use that model as
to provide reward to sort of, you know, like a reinforcement learning algorithm. And so,
the second step of that process is to train your language model with a policy-gradient method,
with the reward model providing these rewards. And by sort of going through that process iteratively,
you get very close to the outputs matching what the humans would have preferred. And this is kind
of like aligning models with human intention. There's a similar story here that like, you know,
actually the results in these walks are pretty impressive, like yet. Rather than having GP3,
you can have a model that's 100 times smaller. And by, you know, aligning it with human intentions
with this two-step process of like collecting comparison data and using it to train your language
model with reinforcement learning. You get better or like preferred outputs to a model that 100
times larger. So I think something that I'm kind of really looking forward to is when people are
going to combine all these recent advancements, figure out, you know, which dimensions to scale,
like, yeah, I think once you do a mixture of experts, like alignments, retrieval, you know,
you spend a lot of money and you use to scale everything, figure out how to do it the proper way.
Yeah. No, I think we're looking at something that's going to be fairly amazing. So pretty exciting
about that. Yeah, I mean, that's kind of the name of the game. We've got point optimizations,
heading in different directions. And we just need to figure out how to combine the model to
create some more general version of intelligence. Yeah, exactly. That kind of research is pretty
costly, though, because it's very hard to extrapolate performance, you know, at small scale.
Actually, one thing that I saw, again and again, when I was at Google, it's like, you know,
you see a paper that that proposes a new idea or like a new architecture, you know, like Google,
let me try it. And then you trade it like Google scale, which is usually, you know,
in order of magnitude larger than academic scale, right? Yeah. And you find that like,
you know, improvements completely vanish. And so it's that a is that a reproducibility problem
or is that a fundamentally the method just didn't scale the mental issue? Yeah. But I think
that's really like sort of a, there's something deeper behind that fact is that,
yeah, it's very hard to extrapolate techniques. Also, people, I think this kind of stuff would be
seen if people were, you know, designing, scaling laws in a very rigorous way. But, you know,
that takes a lot of time. And usually people just say like, hey, you know, the baseline is this,
I did that and I get a better number, but we have no idea what happens when you scale.
I also think, you know, like this whole like scaling direction has made
rigorous baselines much harder, having rigorous baselines much harder because, you know,
these models are pretty costly both in time and of course financially. And so each data point
that you consider for your ablation study, you know, my cost you weeks are hundreds to millions of
dollars. And so, you know, research has kind of evolved from like this very, at least in that
field, right, like from very rigorous settings to let's just try to, you know, figure out
among a lot of noise, what works best. I mean, I'd say, you know, even there was already a lack of
rigorous baselines even in overfield, so that just doesn't help. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah, I mean, that brings into, brings into light or the conversation, a lot of issues that we've
been talking about in the field, the lack of rigor overfitting on, you know, a few data sets,
you know, all these I think are accentuated by the scale that you're trying to operate at.
Yeah. I wrote a paper about this last year, actually, like that show that in computer vision,
a lot of the improvements that, you know, research that posted about came from training tricks,
as opposed to the so-claim architectural improvements, that you could still get very competitive
results by simply scaling resnets, which are, you know, like six years old or seven years old,
that you didn't need like all these like fancy new stuff. It was just like, yeah, tech,
the architecture that you know walks, figure out how to scale it properly and training properly,
and usually you're going to be very close to state of DL, you know, trying all these architectural tricks,
like, doesn't matter, basically. And I think that's something that people have come towards, like,
now there's much less architectural research, you know, people use transformers most of the time.
You know, there's this mixture of experts thing, which is kind of like, which I think is a big
enough change that like, it's a real change. It's not like, you know, hey, use a depot ice convolution
here instead of a convolution there. But yeah, I think, you know, with that scale, with the
scaling direction, like, we're kind of moving away from the academic research setup, right? That's
like a widening gap between what can be done in academia and industry. And only a few organizations
have the technical expertise or the financial leeway to support this kind of work. Then I'll see
that gap closing anytime soon. Yeah, I mean, I don't doubt if you like, you know, open efforts,
like the third AI and big science. Stanford is also starting a, yeah, exactly. Stanford is also
starting a group. So, you know, I think some people are rallying and, you know, realizing, hey,
we can't just let big companies have access to those. But there are a little bit behind,
and like, yeah, there's dark kind of questions about, you know, how long you can sustain that kind
of research and this kind of costs. Yeah, awesome. Well, Erwan, thanks so much for taking the time
to chat for those who are still with us. This interview has been a long time in the works.
And Erwan's continued it to advance his research. And I'm super glad we're able to finally get
together. And I really enjoyed the conversation. Thank you for having me. Awesome. Thank you.