All right, everyone. Welcome to another episode of the Twemal AI podcast. I am, of course,
your host, Sam Charrington. And today I'm joined by Adrian Gaden, head of machine learning
research at TRI, the Toyota Research Institute. Before we get going, be sure to take a moment
to hit that subscribe button wherever you're listening to today's show. Adrian, welcome
back to the podcast. We last spoke in May of 2019, believe it or not. And we had a great
conversation. I encourage everyone listening now to check back to episode 269 where we discussed
advancing autonomous vehicle development using distributed deep learning, a lot of what
you were doing around MLOPS and kind of productionalizing these large scale models. It was a great
conversation, and I'm super excited to have you back on the show. Sam, it's really my pleasure,
and it's been too long, so I'm really glad we get to chat. We're going to spend some time talking
about among other things, data-centric AI and some of the things you're doing from a synthetic
data perspective. But to get us started, why don't you introduce yourself, reintroduce yourself
to our audience, and we can spend a bit of time talking about what's new since May 2019 for you.
Yeah, okay, sounds good. Thanks, Sam. Yes, so hey everyone. My name is Adrian Guedon, but you can say
it in the American way, Adrian Guedon. So I'm French, obviously, but I've been living in the Bay
area for five years now. I've been working in computer vision and machine learning for almost
14 years. Ten years in industry and five years at TRI as leading the machine learning research
team there. One of the things that characterized my research is a lot about going beyond supervised
learning. I have labeled data myself back in the day, a few people that know the Pascal VOC
challenge, which kind of predated image nets. We're going to Oxford, a famous visual geometry group,
and clicking on pixels, and then my hate for labeling started around that time, and so that guided
a lot of my research, because I think clicking on pixels is not the way to AI. And so treating
machine learning as a problem of really finding ways that machines can learn in a more
efficient way without supervision. And so I did a lot of research on using synthetic data. I'm
sure we're going to get to talk about today, but also self-supervised learning. Probably one of
the things that we've been most well known for, especially in the autonomous driving space,
is we've been doing a lot of self-supervised learning and monocular depth estimation,
which has been actually deployed in production and is used in various applications, not just
autonomy, but something that is near and dear to my heart, which is saving lives. As you know,
there's 1.3 million fatalities on the road every year. And so that's something that keeps me up
and motivated to work on this very important problem, in addition to deep learning and everything
being super, super cool. So yeah, so basically that's who I am as a scientist and as a person,
I love climbing my family and stuff like that. And with COVID, I got to spend a lot of time with
my daughter and actually learn some things about how humans learn, which we're sure we could get
to talk about that too. So yeah, happy to be here. Awesome, awesome. Let's maybe talk a little bit
about your focus as a researcher at TRI and some of the main things that you think about. Yeah, for
sure. So as I mentioned, going beyond supervised learning has been a big area of research for us,
and it's always been a very interesting challenging position to work as a researcher in industry,
because you have to focus on science, this big breakthroughs, have an impact and
but at the same time, it needs to be useful. So we call this, you know, the pastor Quadrant,
you know, it's like you have the curiosity-driven research, you have the problem solving kind of
research, and then you have where we are at TRI, which is really nice, which is where use inspired.
So we're not necessarily solving the problem that's right now for the next six months,
but we're listening to all the people that have all these problems and all these products that
they contribute to. And then we're trying to extrapolate a little bit beyond, in say like three
years or something like that, to say, what is actually the problem that if we hit it at the base,
if we work on the foundations, it's going to have a massive impact. You know, like you're talking
about platforms regularly and things like that. It's a bit the same thing, but except with
infrastructure, which, you know, was a topic of our podcast, and we talked about the platform
of tooling and infrastructure to enable people to do machine learning. Now it's a bit more of
the scientific foundations, the scientific platform. The ideas that are, again, going to be largely
beneficial to, you know, for robotics applications. One of the big things we want to do is we want to
make useful machines that amplify people, whether they be cars, whether they be robots, or whether
they be just programs, you know, and virtualize. Although a lot of the research we do is about
physical sensory motor machines. And that's something that is really exciting. I was writing in our
car recently, you know, and we have robots in the office that move stuff around. And there's no
avoiding gravity and reality and all the kind of problems. You know, your robot breaks or your
car does something bad. It's something real, you know, it's not something you can avoid. So all
these concepts of, you know, AI ethics, et cetera, they're rounding. Yeah, exactly grounding and
embodiment. It's not about a game, you know, nothing leaves the Natari for us. Everything is real
world. Everything is high stakes and safety critical. And we take things very seriously because
they obviously matter, because they are made of matter. So that's what we do. And so the research-wise
scale is kind of important, but we have a kind of a nuanced notion of scale. And maybe you can
talk about the data-centric AI there and our positioning there, which is a bit contrarian, I would say.
So we can talk about that a bit more tomorrow. Yeah, let's just jump right into that.
So I think, you know, in talking to folks about data-centric AI, my first few conversations I've
been asking folks to kind of define it. And I think everybody has similar definitions, mostly
around, you know, to be frank, kind of the way Andrew has framed it, Andrew.
Yeah. And, you know, when we spoke, as you alluded to, you of course, I think frame it in a similar
way, but you also have some kind of contrarian viewpoints around it. Let's kind of start there.
What's a contrarian viewpoint that you have around data-centric AI?
Yes. So as a French and a scientist, I love contrarian viewpoints. So let me start with an opening
counterintuitive hook, which is, I believe that in measuring, we had tremendous progress.
And that's why there's so much excitement and really excited about it. And I believe now we know
how machines learn, but we don't know how to teach them. And so I think that's what's kind of
a bit contrarian and kind of interesting. So let me explain a little bit. I think I have a contrarian
take that we don't actually know how machines learn. I will let you continue.
You're even more contrarian than me. You're a honorary French member now.
So what I mean by we know what machines learn is that the genius out of the bottle,
deep learning works so well. In 2012, I had done my PhD in video analysis and using very hard
core math, kernel methods and everything like that. And it had to become vex. It had to have
statistical learning guarantees. And then Kuzewski arrived and then the whole world turned upside
down and we entered the age of empiricism of things that we have good principles or hints
intuitions for why things work. And we managed to make things work even when we don't fully understand
or explain. But it does work and the evidence and empirical evidence is undeniable. And the benefits
we received in industry from it, right? Computer vision went from a very interesting
problem because it doesn't work to a very interesting problem because it works really well. And how
we go beyond and again, beyond and again, beyond. We know how machines learn. I agree it's kind of
a fairly bold statement, but there's very few people in machine learning right now that are
questioning fundamentally SGD and back propagation and deep learning. Again, because the evidence
is kind of overwhelming. So you want to make something work, you will use a overparatized model
that you will learn on as much data as you can get with, you know, stochastic gradient descent,
back propagation, all the tricks of the trade and this huge cookbook that we developed through
empiricism, right? Through a lot of experimental evidence that we collected over the year that is
open because it's open source that is reproducible. Many people, many different people from many
different areas have been building on top of that. So that's what I mean by we know how machines
learn. Maybe not the best way they can learn that for sure, but a way to make them learn we know.
But in the framework of data centric AI, what I mean by we don't know how to teach them is that
building data sets and efficiently building data sets and efficiently teaching machines is not
at all what everybody is doing right now. Everybody is just following a simple recipe, which is
under the name of the scaling hypothesis, which is bigger is better, right? And we know, I think
some people know at least that bigger is not always better. And there's obviously a trade-off,
a fundamental trade-off. I mean, it's a physical fundamental trade-off between scale and efficiency.
And so a question is really like how do we find this trade-off? So there is the scaling loss,
which are very interesting, right? It's very hard to estimate, you know, there's some kind of
the dpt scaling law versus the tinchila scaling law and did with people tune the hyper parameters
in the right way. No stuff we learn in a PhD, which is like make sure your experiments are clean,
you study all the extra parameters. But we have limited computation again. So there's a trade-off
between scale and efficiency. So you can't try all the combinatorial explosion, I have hyper parameters.
And then in the end you make assumptions and then you have different scaling laws that says,
oh, models are much more important. Increase your model size much more for a fixed data set.
Versus maybe data size and model size is equally important with all this foundation model research
that's going on. But when it takes tens of millions of dollars to do an experiment or train a model,
you have to work off of first principles. And I think this is one other thing that characterizes
our research is something that I like to call kind of like principle-centric AI versus it's a
bit of a different way than the data-centric AI. Because my definition of data-centric AI is a bit
more like focusing on increasing the data, which is, you know, I think what we've seen is not
necessarily the best principle. Yeah, I don't want to spend too much time getting contrarian
with your point. I don't know that data-centric AI necessarily implies increasing. I think a lot of
times the idea is spending more time and investing more effort with your data and often the implication
is that you're curating. You're making your increasing quality, you're reducing the size of the
data set as opposed to increasing it. Like fundamentally, I think the contrast is, hey,
traditional academic, you know, and Kaggle Machine Learning is like, hey, we want to solve this
problem, get more data, label it, and throw it at the model, and, you know, stochastic grade
into sense going to figure it out for us. And data-centric AI is kind of saying, well, yeah, maybe
spend more time on the data, and that could involve changing the way you label. It could involve
examples that are bad for your model. It could involve using machine learning to, you know,
decrease the size of your data set. You know, I think that there's, I think I'm intrigued by
principle-centric AI. Like I like, there's something compelling that the way we approach AI should
be based on principles, and one of those principles is actually data-centric. I'm like, we should be
thinking about our data. And so I'd love to hear you elaborate a little bit more about some of the
other principles that drive the way you think about this. Perfect. Okay, that's great. I mean,
you know really what you're talking about because we're getting to the subtle points. I love it.
So, okay, let me give you a little bit of, you know, a good story has some characters. So,
let me introduce some characters. So, what is not, like, I think, principles are, and it's
not the best way. So, there's a couple of different people in the field right now. There's
what I call the supervisors, okay? Okay. Big tech, you know, people that label a lot, you know,
like more data, more labels and etc. Which, honestly, is most of the really big successes, right,
in deep learning. So, let's call them the supervisors. Okay. So, they label as much as possible.
Again, my idea for that is that I've been labeling things, I've, and in the open world,
I think it's an endless pursuit, you know, you're going to label forever. And we want machines to
work for us, not us to work for machines. So, I don't think the supervisors are necessarily,
it's what it got us where we are now, but it's not what's going to get us to the next level.
So, I'm not one of the supervisors. Then you have another area, which actually is kind of
important for us in driving, which is called another type of characters, which are the Geofensers,
right? And you know, probably two of them, very well-known, you know, Waymo Cruz and like companies
that are doing amazing work in, you know, Robotaxi, right? So, that's what's they called, like,
a Geofence. I don't know if you've probably heard of this before, but it's basically your
designating an area and some conditions where your machine learning model, in this case, a robot,
right? It's going to design to operate. And you know how it's going to operate. And you have a safety
case around it. And so, in safety critical conditions, you build a fence and you describe inside
this fence, inside this playpen, my robot is safe, you know? So, it's like, what I do with my
daughter when I put her in a playpen, you know, it's a Geofence, it's safe, she can be autonomous
there. And so, again, I think the Geofensers, they're autonomous in the playpen. And it's great,
and the whole thing is making the world your playpen, but I think it's also a bit of a challenge
because you're trying to turn an open world into a closed world. So, it has a lot of challenges.
So, I'm also not a Geofenser because I want to work on autonomy. I want something that scales
that learns autonomously, that adapts, and that can be deployed in the world, right? Not just in
the playpen. So, you have the supervisors, you have the Geofensers, and you have the ones that are
pretty cool. I call them magicians, but you got to spell the AGI, an uppercase in magicians,
and AGI, itchians, right? And so, the magicians are obviously the people that believe in AGI,
and that believe that all roads lead to AGI. So, this is the open AIs, the deep minds, and a lot of
other folks. And especially now with foundation models, people get really excited about that,
because of the power of language, right? As an API for almost everything. And so, the magicians,
they believe in the scaling hypothesis. So, you're right that the story has multiple different
characters that have different interpretations of data-centric AI, et cetera. The magicians,
they really believe that scale is the way to go. And if I train on all of the internet,
I'm going to have AGI. And if I train a big enough model on a big enough data set,
and I have some safeguards in place, right? So, I'm not saying that people just do this
recklessly, because people now are more wise, then I'm going to get to AGI. I'm also not an AGI
person. I like autonomy more than intelligence, because I want robots to be useful. I don't want
to sleep robots to be smart. I believe that to be useful, they need to be smart. But I don't want
them to be smart for the sake of being smart. I want them to be useful, right? And to be useful,
they have to be autonomous. If I have to click on every pixel for every frame of a robot, for
all my life, for it to be able to help me with my chores at home, that's not very helpful.
I think that the principle-centric AI that we're thinking about is more inspired by a fourth
character, which is my daughter, Cassie. And there was something weird that happened during the
pandemic I can talk about, which is I taught my daughter seven years old now how to bike.
And I tried for a year before, and I tried it with reinforcement learning, basically,
which is basically put her on the bike, try it, and I catch you. I catch you when you're about
to do something, so that way she doesn't pay too bad of a negative reward. But encourage her when
she does well and all these kinds of things. Add some safety guardrails with the little training
wheels, etc. And I tried for one year to basically brute force the problem with reinforcement learning.
And as we know, reinforcement learning is not really good at simple efficiency, so at learning
efficiently. So after one year, not so much progress. And then I had a discussion with our CEO,
Gil Pratt, the famous roboticist, etc. And he said, oh, check out this method, which is a method
called pedal magic. You can find it online. And I'm not going to tell you details and stuff like
this. We could talk about it if you want. But basically, it had some principles about how you learn
how to bike some mechanical principles that actually relate to how Cheetahs take turns and use
their tails. It's a bit kind of a bit wacky mechanically speaking, but it has some principles
that are physically motivated, physically grounded. And it has an exercise that it derived from
these principles, which is basically just a mini environment and a mini training set. And I run
my few training samples with my daughter, five minutes in this small environment. And then
10 minutes later, she was biking. And I was like, wow, after spending a year trying so much,
like giving her so much data, so much guidance, so much supervision, I tried the supervisor's trick,
I tried the geofancer's trick, I tried the magician's trick, I tried everything. And then
something completely different that was not data centric AI, because I didn't give her examples
that related directly to the task of biking. It was not model centric AI, because I didn't change
the hardware, like you assume bike, same daughter, same dad, it was everything the same. And so
something happened that she learned really, really quickly. And two years later, after thinking
about it, basically the whole pandemic, and like, what happened? How do I make machine learning
as good as this, as fast at learning and as robust at lit, because she learned on the parking lot,
and then we've been biking everywhere. So she's been generalizing out of the main and all these
kind of things that we hope machine learning eventually gets to. And so this idea of principle
centric learning principle centric AI is kind of what emerged from there. And kind of explained
also some of the stuff, you know, some of the research we've done has worked spectacularly well,
like the same stuff, the self-supervised stuff. And eventually, you know, like, I mean, we made
60 papers, but half of those papers ended up in production, useful in production. And you're
wondering, why are the other ones used in production? What happened with these particular papers that
actually made the difference in our robust real world? And so you're trying to backward explain,
and I found some traces of the principles and how we use those principles to either design the
data sets or design the learning objective, and that enabled like really robust learning,
which includes in particular one thing, which is simple efficiency. I think like, like, you know,
finding the right way to use compute and minimize compute, but at the same time,
use enough compute to actually learn. So I'm not a, you know, an AI extremist, you know,
neither maximalist nor a minimalist, you know, it's not about the biggest data set, but it's also
not about, you know, short and sweet. There's a good trade-off between scale and efficiency and
with disgust. And I believe that principles is the way to find this trade-off.
That's such a great story. Is principle-centric AI the fourth character?
Exactly. Is that what you call it or is there another name for that fourth character?
Principle-centric AI is how I think about the research and what we're doing. If you want the name
on the characters, I would call us the educators, you know? It's like what we said is that we want
to find ways to teach machines, right? We know the mechanism by which, you know, we design
architectures, we learn with SGD, backprop, etc. But what we don't know is how to make a course.
It's interesting that you say educator and course because the thing that popped up for me was
an element of pre-training, yeah, as well as an element of curriculum learning.
Exactly. Yeah, yeah. And you know, these words, you know, they're used in teaching in schools,
you know, I started to teach at Stanford computer vision and I hadn't taught a course in a long time
and I co-teached this with Juan Carlos Nebles who's also a well-known computer vision guy in
Faye Faze Lab. And so we worked a lot on the course. He has a lot of experience and so I kind of
learned, relearned how to teach a course from him and we taught hundreds students and I taught
geometry, computer vision with geometry, which is also a lot of the things we had success in our
research for driving and robotics, which is self-supervised learning using geometric principles. And I
found that all these parallels between my daughter, between teaching at Stanford, and between
our research papers, and as kind of like was really kind of, wow, it kind of opened the new world
for me of like, oh, how do we be the educators that use principle-centric AI to efficiently
teach machines? This is super interesting. So when I think about these different characters,
the supervisors think implicitly that the path to AGI, let's say that that's the goal for
generalize. The path to AGI is through human labor. The geofensors think that the path to AGI
or whatever the goal is is constraints. Yeah, maybe Amari can drop it in my dock and I'll
remember the name of the episode, but I had a really interesting conversation or a couple recently
about the role that constraints play in ML. The magicians think that it's some nebulous notion
of scale, which is basically or another alternatively or complementarily self-supervision, maybe.
I think self-supervision can see one way to unlock scale. It's because you remove the bottleneck
to be able to train that scale. But it's really scale. It kind of emerges magically from all the
data that you're feeding it. That's what people get. I'm amazed by Dali. I'm amazed by GPD3
who isn't when you see the inferences. But that's the thing is that what I realize is why are we
amazed? We are amazed because we don't know how it emerged from the data. And if you like listen
to Ilya and all the smart people, that's the same. They're like it's working because we're feeding
it more data and also because I mean there's a lot of secrets also in feeding the data. So I'm not
saying like magicians magic doesn't exist. It's like people have these tricks, right? And so there's
a lot of tricks to make it work. But so the magicians is really about how to unlock the powers of
scale. That's what they're really really good at. I think that's where it's going. But I don't think
that's the that's the panacea. That's the end game either. I guess the question that I'm trying to
get to is like what is that kind of fundamental one word tool or currency of the educator? Like what
is it that they have you know perfected that is going to be that path? It's principles. It's
principles. And so basically okay there's two types of principles. Let's like answer your question
you said like be more precise about the principles. So there's two types of principles. There is
the principles you teach. And there's the principles you learn, right? So the principles you teach
are things you principles, right? So some people call this inductive biases or inductive priors
or you name it, right? But it's basically things you you know is true about the world. You know
Newton existed, F equals M A existed. Maybe we don't have to reinvent it. Maybe we can use that
prior knowledge, right? I think as some of the things that I've listened to and during talk about
in data centric AI is a lot on that also on like how do we use expert knowledge? But in a data-driven
way, right? So it's not like they're going back to expert systems, right? It's about like how do I
if I know some principles and it can be ethical principles, it can be legal principles if you have
compliance because you know there's the AI act and all these regulations that are coming in AI
and including in you know robotic space. And so if you have some principles that you want your
system to adhere to, right? Being compliance with or common sense, you know like when we talk about
embodiment and grounding, you know, that's what we mean. So how do we inject those principles into
data-driven learning processes? And then there's the principle we learn from the data. So that's where
we train on the data set and it's not just we're building autonomous prediction machines, right?
That are just there to automate the prediction at scale, basically because that's what machine
learning does, right? But maybe what we want to extract is not a bazillion number of predictions,
but we want to extract, we want to learn something from what the machine learned itself. And so there's
all this cool area of machine learning about machine learning for sciences, et cetera, you know, where
people are discovering new physical laws maybe or finding out understanding a bit better human
behavior because if you want to assist and amplify humans, it's not about automation, right?
Autonomous prediction machines are there to replace, but if you want to amplify, you got to understand.
And so this is the principles that you want to understand from data. So it's a two-way street
in a sense. And I can give you some examples of our research where actually this already is
happened, right? This is not just principle-centric AI, it's not just a cool expression, you know,
it's actually just a way that I use to kind of define a little bit our successes and what we're
actually building at TRI. Yeah, I do want to transition to that because I think while this
philosophical conversation is really interesting, I do want to kind of make it a bit more concrete
and talk about some of the things you're doing around self-supervised and synthetic. Before I do
that episode that I was thinking about was my conversation with David Ha, the benefit of bottlenecks
and evolving AI that was really almost entirely focused on this idea of constraints, not in a
geofencing sense, but in more broadly in AI in another context. So your research, where do you
want to start there, self-supervised? Yeah, self-supervised I think is great. So I think one of the things
that we know about the world really well, and especially what I'm teaching at Stanford,
is geometry, right? When we see the world, when we perceive the world, we have a lot of really good
equations. You know, actually some of the things dates back like 3,000 years, you know, back to,
you know, Chinese philosopher, I think Mudzi, people knowing about, you know, the pinnacle camera model
and all these kind of things. So there's a lot of knowledge we have about how the world works in
terms of let's say just physics of light, right? And so when you want to do computer vision,
how do you leverage that prior knowledge? And historically, it's been in the way of we hand
design algorithms, right? We write algorithms that solve the problem based only on our prior knowledge.
Now with machine learning, we want to be data driven. And so we've kind of like thrown the baby
with the bathwater and say, well, it's all in the data. And so one of the thing again, as I said,
we are always kind of in the moderate route, which is, of course, data is powerful, but of course,
prior knowledge is powerful too. So we want to combine both. So self-supervised learning is
actually a really good revolution that I'm really excited about because and that we've been doing
a lot of papers over the year. I think they're probably like 15, 20 papers at CPR, etc. I think we're
presenting four papers at Ikra in a couple of weeks and four papers at CPR and on related topics.
And so self-supervised learning is the way where we use these constraints or these knowledge is
prior knowledge about the world, let's say like, you know, the reproduction equations if you're
using the panel camera model, and we use that to as a learning objective. So in self-supervised
learning, you're not solving directly what you want, which is dog versus cat or, you know,
detecting a pedestrian or things like that. But what instead you're doing is you're providing a
pre-training objective. And so there's two big areas. One that I was mentioning now is geometry,
where actually it turns out we can solve the task, which for instance, it's a lot about predicting
depth how far objects are because we want to avoid collision with them or we want to grasp them
if it's a robot hand and things like that. So predicting the depth of a scene turns out you can do
that without ever having any supervision. And so this is self-supervised learning for monodef and
something that we have open source code. You can go to GitHub, you know, a TRI page, a repo called
Pactnet SFM, which has 1,000 GitHub stars. And so it's very popular. People use it for all kinds
of crazy things because you can train it only from video. So you can just feed it raw videos and
what it will learn. It will learn to output point clouds or death maps from there. And the way it's
trained is just by using reconstruction, but not just a black box reconstruction of critical
pixels. And I'll tell you if they look like the pixels you should predict. Instead, it's
predict me death map. And then if you're right, if your network weights are correct, and your death
map will be correct. And then knowing the equations of geometry, we can recreate a past frame
from the current frame by warping geometrically using an equation. And then if the warping
is correct, the pixels align. And if it's not correct, the pixels don't align. The colors are not
the same. And you're wrong, not because geometry is wrong, not because 3,000 years of history,
human history in science is wrong. But because your neural net weights are wrong. And then you can
do back propagation as you do. So this is going back to what I said earlier. We know how machines
learn. We don't know how to teach them. In this instance, we know how to teach them geometry. We
teach them by reconstruction using geometry as an equation in the middle to get the prediction.
And then we learn using SGD back prop and the way we do it. So we have a bunch of papers. We started
from stereo setup with two cameras, to just a singular camera, to now all the crazy sensor
suites. And actually, we can even, you know, because we've worked on the hardest problem first,
which is monocular camera, the reason we've done that is because the common denominator behind
almost any platform. You have it, you know, I have it in my phone. I actually have more than one
camera. Everybody has cameras. Cameras are everywhere. But if you solve the problem
well enough for a single camera to predict step, then you can use it to predict that for multiple
cameras for cameras that are stereo or not stereo for a LiDAR for any kind of sensor suites.
And that's what we've been doing. It's a very pragmatic approach. It's not to replace everything
with a single camera. Some applications might work with a single camera. Some definitely won't.
But it's to be solving the common denominator. Again, this idea of a platform that foundations
and building on top of it, right? So self-supervised learning using geometric principles to teach
geometry to deep nets is a big thing we've been doing. And I mentioned the second way that you can do
self-supervised learning, just for pre-training, it's contrastive learning. If probably, you know,
heard about this, had podcasts over this, it's very, very popular. One of the very cool things we've
done in collaboration with a really, really good machine learning professor at Stanford is called
Teng Yuma. We've had a couple of papers at Nurebs. We had iClear spotlights and a bunch of
papers with them on trying to make sense of self-supervised learning, especially contrastive learning.
Why does it work? Because there's all these bells and whistles and these tricks and these
cookbooks. And going back to the philosophical discussion about empiricism, you know, we've
built a lot of things that work. And obviously work, we show that it works, but we don't really
understand why. And so understanding why is really important because you have to convince people
that are not necessarily ML believers, crazy, woohoo, you know, let's use machine learning just because
it's cool, but actually people that need to invest real money and take real risks and, you know,
and putting, you know, say, if you want to save lives, you need to make sure that you have a
really good justification that your system will do so. And so understanding things a bit more
and the theory and garnering the principles out of the data driven is really important.
And one of the things that I'll highlight there briefly is one of the principles we found
from self-supervised learning, which is just learn, you know, contrastive learning. So you do
data augmentations because you know that if you change the color of things, it shouldn't change
your predictions. So you have all these kind of data augmentations that represent properties
like principles of invariance and equivalence that you know hold true. And you want your system to
just adhere to those constraints again, like in this idea of constraints you were talking about.
So you train by just saying when you're out of the constraints, when you're out,
when you're not grounded anymore, when you're making a very weird mistake, right?
But you're not telling it what's the solution, you're just telling stop making weird mistakes.
And if you see enough data, it will stop making weird mistakes and what's going to happen is
going to have something that's this pretty good initialization for it made, you know,
a few shot transfer and like small data kind of cases, maybe something that, you know,
in data centric AI, you get your experts to label just the right amount, but if you have good
pre-training, you don't need more than that. Necessary but sufficient. So what we found is why
does self-surprise learning and particularly contrastive learning works so well? And and
particular, a benefit that we found was very surprising is that it's robust because you would
think if you're in the supervisors mindset that's okay, Adrian is saying supervisors is bad,
but it's just a matter of cost. If you can pay the cost, you know, if you're return on investments,
justifies labeling forever, just label forever and it's the best thing to do, right?
Wrong. Because actually we know that if you just collect the, you know, data has bias,
natural data has biases, right? And if you just label more and label more and label more,
you're going to increase, you're going to create distortions, you're going to have human biases
injected in the labels, mistakes or, you know, you're going to label more the mode and all these kind
of things that yields issues. Yeah, particularly in your case in AV where you're collecting a lot of
data of the usual thing happening. The problem is all about the corner cases that don't happen
very frequently. Ding ding exactly right. Yep, absolutely. And so, and so self-surprise learning,
what we found surprisingly is more robust to the imbalance. So if you, if you collect data at
scale, it's very imbalance. You have this long tail of edge cases and rare conditions, rare
events, as you mentioned. And, and some of them are noise, but some of them are really bad. Like,
you really want to make sure they're very important for you to, to, to know and, and learn. And so,
but you can't tell from just the data itself, it's just rare events, right? And so what we found is
that self-supervised pre-training is actually better than training with labels because it's more robust
to the, to the long tail to the imbalance. And we were like, okay, cool. Another empirical fact
that self-supervised learning is a good idea, but why? And in this paper that we actually just
present that I clear as a spotlight, we found the explanation and the principle for why. And it's
a bit counterintuitive. So what we thought was that when you do self-supervised learning,
you learn more from the tail. You learn richer features, better features from the tail.
Because the label is not leading you astray. Take an example of driving, you drive mostly straight,
and then you have all this kind of weird maneuvers, evasions, etc. And so when you drive straight,
and you say, drive straight, drive straight, that's your label, basically, you're just, the model
might just collapse on the mode, right? And might just say, all right, just drive straight all the time,
that's enough to minimize my loss. The rest is just weird. There's no pattern, right? And so,
and so if you just do supervised learning, this is what would happen. But if you do self-supervised
learning, our assumption was it generalizes better, it's more robust because it's going to learn more,
it's going to have to try to explain or reduce the loss on the rare things too. And so it's going
to learn better features from the tail. But what we found out is that it's not true. It actually
learns better, more diverse, and more generalizable features from the mode. And let me give you an
example for, and so we have like very cool semi-synthetic experiments in the paper, a bit hard to
explain, but you can look at it. So where we basically just probe this and verify this, both with
theoretical explanation and with like controlled experiments to show that our principle,
our explanation is correct, not just that the performance is good, but that's also we know why.
But let me give you an example. If you want to do that, is the specific case you're referring to
self-supervised by you've got some geometric relationship and you're projecting through that,
or is it the data augmentation contrastive learning case? It's the contrastive case. So for this
particular paper, we found that it's the contrastive case. Because for the first, the other case,
we know the principle because we teach by principle, right? The contrastive one is more the other
way around. I mean, there's this principle of invariance, but we wanted to know why does it work
and get the principle out from the model after training and why it works, right? And so this
principle is it learns better features from the mode, because like the example is, if you learn to
drive straight, right, all the time, you say drive straight, you're basically ignoring things that
happen behind you. So I don't know if you've, when I came here, you know, in Europe, we used to
with J-walk, you know, it's like we cross the street whenever, you know, again, maybe the French,
maybe that's just me, you know, we cross the street from New York, we also J-walk.
There you go. But you typically don't J-walk right in front of a car, right? You typically wait
for the car to go and then you just cross, right? So the J-walkers are always behind the driver.
So when you're learning to drive, you're basically can safely ignore the pedestrian and the
back, it's not gonna affect your policy. So if you're very focused in the supervisor's way or
the geofancer's way, you're just saying, all right, just focus in front of you and just what
matters is avoid collision in front of you. But in a self-supervised way, you will say, oh,
something weird happened behind you. And I don't care about you learning the policy. I care about
you satisfying the contrastive learning objective. So you have to understand the world. You have
to explain what happened behind you. You have to verify your invariance and equivalence properties
also on what happened behind you if it's if it's part of your of your input signal, right? And so
then you will see basically J-walkers and you will have to learn features about these J-walkers
even though they don't relate to directly optimizing your angle, which is in this case would be
drive straight. And so now linking back to my daughter, Cassie, I tried to teach her biking by
teaching her to bike. But when I teach her taught her the principles about biking, right, about how
not to fall, basically, then she learned how to bike because she had internalized the principles.
And it's basically the same thing here is that it internalized the principle of you have to
explain what's happening around you because you might you never know someday that J-walkers that
you've seen behind you, they might actually cross in front of you and you need to be able to
represent them because if you don't represent them, if it's are not there in your feature representation,
you're going to you're not going to be able to react to them. And so that's what we found. This
counterintuous principle, which is it generalized better, self-supervised, contrastive learning,
generalized better, not because it captured better features from the tail, from the rare events,
but because it captured more diverse features from the mode. Because all kinds of things happen
around you all the time. And in the mode, you have equal diversity because you're still
experiencing the same crazy world is just that the long tail of actions, right, does not correspond
to the long tail of events of things that happen in the world. Did you find a way to control for
this idea that the reason why you had increased robustness isn't necessarily that the model was
you know, learning about the things in a raviou mirror, but rather just that you gave it multiple
things to do. And so in this, you know, based on kind of what we've learned about multitask,
like just having the model, doing multiple things independent of what those things are,
it creates some robustness. Yeah, I think I encourage people to have a look at the paper because
there's a very cool visual experiment to that validates. So there's some theory, right? And uh,
and I mean, of course with assumptions that not necessarily reflect all the practical applications
and successes as usual, but under some consideration, some constraints might offer this,
we know why and we can prove it. And then we have some visual experiments where we show that
basically what you do is you have an image where you have the left side that has the category
that you that corresponds to the label. And then the right side that has a confounder or even
just a black, you know, like a black image. And so then what you do is you train on that. So you
basically introduce the confounder and at a test time, you remove that confounder or you swap it.
And then what you want to see is you want to see, well, at training time, the supervised way,
it will have just focused on the half part of the image that corresponds to the labels because the
rest is noise. But the self-supervised part, it trained on both sides and it learned features from
both sides. And then when you apply it on the test time where you said, oh, now I changed the
environment and the relevant part is not on the left. It's on the right now. Then the self-supervised
feature says, no problem. It's still things I know how to represent. Whereas the supervised part is
now very causally confused, right? And causal confusion is just one example of like,
how spurious correlations affect very negatively supervised learning and the supervisor's way.
And that's why it's the same thing as the supervisors and the geofensors. You're just running after
a fact that the world, there's only one thing that's constant in the world is change.
Which is why you just label forever and then you're growing your operational domain and the
world changes and most likely your system has to change also. So this is why the self-supervised
learning is all about learning from diverse data in a diverse way. This is the whole, the
quality and diversity of data in the data centric realm, which is still a bit more art than
science. And that's where our research is. It's like, like you said, data centric is not
necessarily just about scale. It's about focusing on the data and being better about using the data,
designing data sets and etc. But as you know, it's still very much more an art than a science and
we're trying to make it more into a science by using principles. In the paper that you were describing
was did synthetic, was there a synthetic data component to that or is that separate research?
The synthetic data, it's a different set of research where the idea is there are certain sets of
principles. We don't exactly know how to, you know, include them in the machine learning pipeline,
right? Whether the data augmentation that I mentioned, like contrastive learning or whether
the self-supervised objective that I was mentioning. And the big one is that relates to grounding
and embodiment is physics, right? So we don't know how to have f equals m a into a deep net, right?
We don't know how to, like, how do you make the connections? Which way do you, like,
we don't know how to do that. But we know it's true. We know gravity and we want grounding
into these systems. And that's the whole embodied AI area. And so, but what we know how to do
is we know how to program it into simulators. And simulators are basically a huge opportunity
for data set generators, something what we call programmable data. You write a program and this
program generates you data sets. And these data sets are actually generated according to
principles because they're actually generated according to a program that is written by humans
that represents our prior knowledge. Again, f equals m a and all these kind of things.
So a lot of the things we've been doing, which originally came out of necessity because
sometimes you don't have the data, like for accidents or for things that are, you know,
like things you want to react to and you want to anticipate. But collecting that data would be
unethical or it's too rare or it's impossible. But yet, you want your system to be able to
handle those cases. So synthetic data is a great, great way to do that because you can program
those principles into the data set generator. And then you have basically built problem sets.
You've built a curriculum. You've built a set of exercises, right, for your machine learning
model to digest and internalize the principles in its own way, in its weights. So you program in human
language or human code, f equals m a, generate a lot of images and videos that then you feed
through the usual machinery. Again, we know how machines learn, SDD, backprop, etc. But this time,
we know how to teach. We teach through a simulator that is a data set generator, essentially.
Yeah. And a lot of ways this, there's kind of a unifying idea between that and the use of geometry
that we're referencing before. It's, you know, we've got some set of knowledge or heuristics about
the way the real world works. And we use that to generate data and then use SDD and the techniques
that we've proven out. It's kind of interesting kind of reflecting on the evolution of the industry.
And I've talked about this ad nauseam, folks who've listened to the show for a while, probably
no one I'm going to say. But like, you know, we started out, you referenced your early work
in computer vision. We had all of these, you know, ground up rules and, and, you know, equations
that, you know, we built everything around and it wasn't statistical at all. We kind of swung
the other end of the pendulum and everything we wanted to be statistical and, you know, throughout
the rules, we get enough data and the system will, you know, learn the rules on its own. And,
you know, in practice, you know, it doesn't really make sense to thought all the rules. And so
you've had, I think, you know, some attempts at like, how do we fuse a real world-based model
with a statistical model. But I think what, what, what in, in this conversation, both in terms of
the use of geometry as well as the use of synthetic data, it's another approach, which is, well,
let's just use the rules to create data or labels and then use the statistical approaches.
Exactly. Yeah, I couldn't have put it that way. I mean, it's basically, we're in the age of
reason now, you know, it's like there's always the pendulum swings one way or the other, you know,
we know everything, we can program everything, logic, etc. Which, by the way, was doomed to fail,
we knew it from theory, from Kurt Goddell, right? But then, then there is the other swing of
the pendulum, like you said, it's like throw it all away, it's all in the data. And honestly,
the reason is also because it's easy. It's, I mean, I mean, it's hard to make large-scale systems
work, but conceptually, it's just scale things up, right? And now we're in this realm where
how do we get the best of both worlds? Because nothing is all good or all bad, right? It's always
these gray areas. And so finding the best of both worlds, as you said, which is how do we use our
knowledge, how do we use the data-driven approach, and how do we combine them together? And what I was
trying to explain is that there is the, using the rules to generate the data, as you said,
using the rules to generate the supervision. And of course, there's all this prior knowledge that
goes into the model architecture, although now we're kind of realizing that the model architecture,
we have powerful, generic model architectures. So I believe that the data centric and the self-supervision
side, I think those are, those are really where I'm excited the most about and most of our researches.
Awesome, awesome. Well, we've been digging deeper and deeper, and I feel like we're still at a
fairly high level, and there's so much more I'd love to talk through exactly how you're doing
synthetic data and just go into a lot more detail. We don't have time for that this time,
but maybe we'll be able to get you to Twilmokon, which would be in the fall, to share a lot more detail.
But until then, or we need to speak more frequently than every three years. But all that, not with
standing, it's been a pleasure having you on the show, Adrian and great chatting and learning
about what you've been up to. Likewise, and yeah, it was very high level, but we have, I think,
like 20 papers this year, and they're all on my website and etc. So people dig in, feel free to ping us,
come to ICRA, come CPR, conferences are a thing again, looking forward to Twilmokon and chatting
with people live. And yeah, looking forward to talking again, hopefully not in three years.
Yeah, awesome. Thank you, Adrian. Thank you, Tom.