All right, everyone. Welcome to another episode of the Swimwell AI podcast. I am your host,
Sam Sherrington, and today I'm joined by Johan Braemer. Johan is a research scientist at Qualcomm AI
research in Amsterdam. Before we get going, be sure to take a moment to hit that subscribe button
wherever you're listening to today's show. Johan, welcome to the podcast.
Hi, Sam. Thanks a lot for having me. Super excited to have you. We're going to be talking about one of
the papers that you presented at NURPS on causal representations, as well as some of the things
that your colleagues presented at the conference. But before we do that, I'd love to have you share
a little bit about your background and how you came to work in machine learning. I grew up as a
particle physicist. So I was trying to figure out the best way that we can measure the properties
of all these elementary particles around us, like the Higgs boson, from all the data collected
the large header and collider. Now, that's an inherently statistical problem, right? You need tools
from statistics and from machine learning to solve this problem with all the high-dimensional data
and the many pyramids you're trying to measure. During that time, I figured out that I actually
enjoy working with the methods with the statistics and the machine learning much more than talking
about the theoretical questions I set out to solve in the first place. So from there, it was a
slippery slope. I started working on statistics for particle physics. I then did some machine learning
for the sciences, and suddenly I found myself an Amsterdam working on machine learning problems
that have nothing to do with particle physics with some great colleagues. And initially, or immediately
into communications types of problems and the kind of things that you work on at Qualcomm, or
did you start in another area? So in my first year at Qualcomm, I worked on a video compression
with neural networks. I think my colleague, Alke Viggas, from the team was recently on your
podcast and explained all that much better than I would do justice now. But there was a nice
introduction to Qualcomm and all the research that we're doing there. But then one year in,
we started a new team on causality. Now relative to some of the other folks that I've talked to
on the Qualcomm AI research team, causal work is much less applied than video compression,
for example. Yeah, totally true. I think Qualcomm has kind of this full spectrum of research that
ranges from pretty applied, like model efficiency, neural network quantization, video compression,
these kind of things, to pretty fundamentally like a geometrically learning, a covariance, and now
also causality. But they're all united by this idea of making AI more efficient in some way.
And I think for causality, the idea is that causality may be a framework that helps us solve some
problems that are currently pretty much unsolvable with the standard paradigms in machine. But it may
take some years to get there. And what are some of those types of problems that you think causality
can help us solve in in ways that will be much more efficient? Yeah, so machine learning systems
right now are great, like just by scaling up the datasets and scaling up the models we can solve
many problems much better than we thought we could. I mean, look at ChatGPT. But there's still
some things that are really hard for these problems. And one case is kind of the brittleness under
changes. If you train a model in one type of conditions and then deploy it under different
type of conditions, then often the performance goes down quite a bit. Like the machine learning
systems have a hard time with seem to real with any kind of changing conditions. Now causality
on a very high level is a framework about reasoning about actions, about reasoning about changes,
about robustness under changes. So on an intuitive level, I think it makes a lot of sense that
this can help us address these these open problems. However, I should say that it's not totally
clear concretely how this will work, right? This is an open research field. Causing machine learning
has really just started gaining momentum a few years ago. So let's see where this takes us.
Yeah, before we dive into the paper about your research, Qualcomm, is it entirely focused on
causality or are you covering several areas as well? It's about causality and interactive learning.
So it kind of focuses on a lot of topics that bother on reinforcement learning. We have some
projects on imitation learning. Maybe we'll get into that a little bit later. We have some projects
on unsupervised reinforcement learning. What can you learn in a setting where you have an
interactive environment, but no reward function, and no expert demonstrations, and then there's
kind of the more classical causality. Awesome. And so this particular paper that we wanted to spend
some time talking about is called weekly supervised causal representation learning. unpack that
title a little bit and the goals you have for the paper. Yes, excellent. Let me start a little bit
from the end of it, right? So the paper title ends with representation learning. And one of the
two goals of this paper is to learn meaningful representations of data. What do I mean with that?
If you have data presented to you in some kind of low level format, think the pixels of an image
or maybe of a video feed or anything that we can record with sensors 3D, we want to train
into a network to take that as an input and output a much smaller number of high level variables
that capture the meaningful aspects of a system similar to how humans reason about system.
When I show an image, you're not thinking, oh, these are some really nice collection of pixels
here, right? You think this image shows, for instance, a car on a road in front of a traffic light.
And the relevant variables are probably something like the position of the car, maybe the speed of the
car, and then the state of the traffic light, whether it's red or green. So this is a much smaller
number of meaningful variables and we want to train a new network to put this out. So that's the
representation learning part. Now going one word more to the beginning, there's a causal in there.
The second goal in our work is that we also want to learn a causal model between these high level
variables. And its causal model is about the interactions between concepts. So again, in this
example of a car before a traffic light, as humans, it's very intuitive to us that we think that
the traffic light state, whether it's green or red, influences causes the behavior of the driver,
whether they accelerate the car or break the car. So there's a causal effect from the traffic
light state to the velocity of the car, but not the other way around. And this is important
because it allows us to reason about what if questions. As a human, it's very easy for us to say,
if the traffic light would turn to red, the car would break. If the car would break, it wouldn't
necessarily make the traffic light go red. Now, machine learning systems, at least the majority of
them, do not really reason about this kind of cause and effect relations. Most machine learning
systems are stuck at the level of describing correlation patterns. So for instance, looking at a
data set that shows you images of cars on traffic lights, machine learning systems could figure out
that green lights are correlated with fast velocities and red lights are correlated with braking cars.
But this doesn't allow the machine learning system to answer a question, what happens if the car
breaks? Does the traffic light then suddenly change? So this is really a new kind of capability that
doesn't exist in most kind of machine learning systems. Now, there's the weekly supervised part in
the title. In this paper, what we do is we learn a neural network that that learns that
represents data from pixel level into this kind of low number of meaningful high level variables
and also learns the causal relations between them. But we do this without explicit labels in the
training data. So there's no label that tells us in this image, the velocity of the car is 30 kilometers
per hour, that's 20 miles per hour, or what have you, anything like that. So we just train this from
example on the pixel level. But it's impossible to do this fully unsupervised. There are some papers
that prove that this problem is really underspecified if you have just IID data just images.
And the way that we solve this is by by breaking the ID assumption, we consider non-ID data,
so kind of data with some structure in it. And concretely, we consider the case where we observe
the system kind of pairs of before and after images. So we take a picture of the street,
then something changes in the scene, like some effect is applied to it. For instance,
you switch the traffic light state from red to green and let all the causative effects of that
play out, and then you take another picture of the scene. And we just need this kind of before and
the after image, but no further labels, no information on what happened before and after. If we have
this kind of paired data, then we can show that this is enough to really learn the true causal
variables in the scene and the true causal effects, the true causal graph, all the mechanisms that
come on the scene. Now, I'd love to maybe start talking about how far along you are and how far
the method that you've identified can take us and ask that in the context of this one diagram
that you have at the very beginning of the paper that kind of articulates what you're hoping to do.
It's a picture of some standing dominoes that you're before picture and then you have
some dominoes tipped over and presumably there's an intervention between the two, someone
tipped a domino. And you know, the grand idea is that you, with enough of these domino pictures,
you can start to learn that if you've got some kind of domino tipping intervention,
what the outcome will be after you've applied that intervention.
Yeah, that's exactly right. And yeah, we're not at the point where I can, you know,
giving your trained model, take a picture of some dominoes and apply this intervention somehow
or say that, okay, give me the picture after the dominoes have fallen and get that resulting
picture, correct? That's unfortunately correct. Yes, I think we make a pretty strong claim.
In this paper, right, we have this really strong claim that we can identify the causal structure
and the right variables and everything correctly. But to get such a strong result, we also need
strong assumptions. And the strongest assumption is I think there's this kind of data regime that we
need this data in this before and after pairing. And we also need to assume that nothing else
changes between the before and the after image, just like one thing is intervened upon one action
happens. But we also need to make a couple of more technical assumptions. And unfortunately,
many real world examples violates some of these technical assumptions that we need for our theory,
at least. So in particular, in this domino case, if you have two domino pieces, if you push over one,
it would knock over the second one. If you push over the second, it could knock over the first
one. So they're kind of the graph here in some sense is cyclic, right? Like each domino,
like they affect each other pairwise. And this is something that standard causal frameworks
can't really deal with so easily because we always assume that the graph of causal interactions
needs to be a cyclic. Something can be the cause of something else, but that can't also be the
effect of that variable. There's no back and forth relation in classical causal models. Now,
there's some ways to resolve that. But in this work, we just assume that the causal structure is
indeed a cyclic. So there's a clear causal ordering of mechanisms. The traffic light causes the
velocity, but the velocity doesn't cause the traffic light, just one of these two things is possible.
And so this is one setting that that that domino example violates. But I think it's really good
to look at these cases that we can't do with yet because ultimately what we want to do is we want
to solve real world problems. So we really need to kind of look at what what our theory can't
describe yet and push there. And I think the way forward maybe to give up a little bit on the
theoretical rigor to maybe not aim for theorems and proofs, but aim for just algorithms that empirically
work ultimately. But in this current paper, we are kind of at the closer to the fundamental side
of things. We have some theory. I think we understood some things better, but we don't have this.
One size fits all algorithm that you can deploy to real world examples. And certainly not we haven't
solved autonomous driving yet. Yeah, for sure, for sure. But what you've done is you've demonstrated
that it is possible to identify these causal variables from, for example, from just pixels,
which is pretty impressive in and of itself. Does the paper just demonstrate that it is possible
or does the paper demonstrate how to derive the causal variables themselves?
It does both. So I think a large fraction of the contribution of this paper is the theory. So
that it's basically mostly one theorem and the proof that it accompanies it. But we also have a
practical implementation. And essentially it consists of a variational autoencoder. So there's
an encoder that takes as input pixels and it outputs some latent variables. And these latent
variables are the causal variables of the system. And then there's a decoder that knapset back to the
pixel space. And what's new about this kind of variation autoencoder is that we describe some causal
structure in the latent space. So the latent variables are not just described by some, you know,
IID Gaussian prior, like most fear is to it. But we have a prior that really incorporates
the causal structure, the graph between the variables, this graph is learned during training.
And also the exact mechanism, how each variable affects each other very well.
And yeah, this kind of VAE, we trained this on these paired data sets before and after
the intervention images. And then we show in a series of experiments with some, we start with
some very similar toy data sets as we worked towards a simple image data sets that this works in
practice. Is it interesting or kind of obvious and not interesting that the parallels between
the video compression stuff that we talked about before that might use an encoder decoder type
of architecture and that you're able to do the same thing here. You're kind of compressing
the dynamics of the system happening before and after the pixel space into some kind of reduced
dimensionality, you know, causally semantic space. Yeah, that's a good point. It definitely has
some parallels like the overall architecture is very similar. But I think there's one important
difference and that is that the kind of goal that we are trying to achieve, right? And compression
is really about this aspect of compression, but then kind of how we use these different bits,
how we use the representation of the latent space, doesn't really matter like the model can do
whatever at once. And if you visualize the latent representation that compression autoencoder
learns, you'll see that it's really not interpreted by humans. Like varying one latent variable
leads to some very weird outputs in image space. And contrast, our model doesn't really care so
much about the bit rate used in the end. I mean, it does play a role in the loss function a little
bit, but it's not really the goal. The goal is really that the variables in the end have some
meaning. The latent variables are exactly the true latent variables up to some permutations
and rescalings. There's definitely some kind of machine learning knowledge that we gained
on this compression work that we could use in the causality work, but I think the interpretation
of the results is very different. Can you maybe talk a little bit broadly about
the, you mentioned that there's kind of this one theorem that's at the heart of the paper. Can
you talk a little bit more detail about that theorem? Yeah, I'm happy to. So this basically says,
if you have two models, and with model, I now mean kind of a causal model between some variables,
and then a map that takes these causal variables and maps them to some data space, so think pixels.
So we call this a latent causal model. Now, what the theorem says, if you have two latent causal
models, such that both of these latent causal models give rise to the same kind of data set,
if you look at them. So if you kind of look at what kind of images you would get from the first
latent causal model and what kind of images before and after images you'd get from the second causal
model, they are the same. There's the same distribution. Then the two latent causal models are the
same in the sense that they have the same latent variables, they have the same causal structure
up to some equivalence class. This equivalence class basically tells you that for instance,
we can't resolve permutations. If one model has variable one and two, and then the second model
has variable two and one in the opposite order, then there's just something we can't further resolve
because we never get labels. But up to this kind of small, and one might say irrelevant effects,
those two models need to be the same. Now, why does this theorem matter? Because if you think of one
of these two models as the generative process, the ground truth process, the generated observed data
in some setting, maybe it's like the physical laws of the universe or it's like the rules of
the traffic scene or maybe there's some human psychology and there would have some ground truth
process that generates a data set. And the second model is some neural implementation of
the latent causal model. So we use a VAE, we use neural permutations of the causal structure,
and we train it to maximize our training objective. And then another some additional assumption
that we have a good optimizer that we have enough data and so on, like the usual machine learning
assumptions, then our theorem implies that in the end our learned model will recover the ground
truth causal variables and the ground truth causal structure. Of course, the hidden assumption
here is that indeed nature operates as such a causal model. And as we've already discussed
with this domino example, there's sometimes some subtleties where our assumptions are not satisfied.
And what are the mechanisms that you use to prove this theorem?
Oh, that's a fun question and I like to talk more about this, but maybe I try to keep this
kind of short. My two collaborators, my two main collaborators on this paper, Pim de Han and
Takako and are both believers and practitioners of a field of mathematics called category theory.
This is like the most abstract of mathematics. I really try to find like the most general structures
that exist and try to unify many different fields of mathematics. We are not really using
category theory, but we're using one tool, one particular graphical language developed in
category theory, called string diagrams. And we use string diagrams to kind of represent
different probabilistic equations, kind of relations between different probabilistic distributions
graphically. And then you can use some nice manipulations on these and then use that to prove
the theorem. I have to say, when I started out of this project, I was a bit skeptical about this
and I like to make fun of my colleagues. And category theory in general? No, I think category
theory is beautiful, but I was skeptical that it would give us practical advantages for this
concrete project. But then it did simplify the proof here quite a bit. And I say by colleagues
really showed me the way a little bit there. That's awesome. Did that just happen to be the
approach that worked or was the project conceived with that as part of the approach that you
would, was the project conceived as, you know, with that solution in mind? No, I would say we started
out just from the actual kind of question. Can we, can we identify, cause a variables, can we
identify, cause a structure just from pixelabid data? And then our first version of the proof
looked much longer and much less elegant and did not involve any fancy diagrams, but then that
evolved over time into something prettier. So it was more of a later stage of the project.
Okay, okay. And you're careful to distinguish the causal variables and the causal structure
or the causal relationships. Can you kind of more carefully distinguish the two and really talk
about the relationships and how, how causal relationships are expressed? Oh, yeah, that's
a great question. So in causality, one of the really important things is that we really don't
just reason about variables, but reason about variables and the mechanisms that generate them.
And what I mean with that is that the causal model, or there's different frameworks, but the one
that's most widely used these days, describes the relation between variables is kind of factorized
into a number of, if you want cause and effect relations, each of them takes the form of some,
some, some mechanism. So in the, the root example that we had, one mechanism could, for instance,
be how the, the traffic light is programmed, right? It probably has some frequency, how often it's
green, how often it's red, how the changes, that's, that's one mechanism. And then a separate
mechanism is how the car behavior adapts to, to the traffic light and maybe also the other things
it sees on the road. So that kind of determines the car velocity as a function of all the other
inputs, in particular, as the function of the traffic lights date. This is something that depends
now on, on the particular driver. And what's kind of cool about this is that these mechanisms
are independent in the sense that if you think about a different version of the scene, let's say we
move to a different city, then maybe the, the traffic light frequency is totally different. So you
can kind of change this one mechanism, but the way that humans react to traffic light will stay
the same, right? That's kind of universal. So we only have to swap one mechanism when we change
the scenery, why can keep, why we can keep the other one. This as fast mechanism shift hypothesis
at its call sometimes is the essential reason why people believe that causality can help us with
things like domain shift. Because we can think that if everything is composed of mechanisms,
it's quite likely that when you change conditions, if you go from seem to real or from one country
to another one, just a few of these mechanisms change, while other things are more universal,
like the laws of physics are the same everywhere. Some human behaviors are the same everywhere.
Yeah, but other things change, like go to the UK and suddenly you have to drive on the left side
of the road. Now going back to the exchange we had about the parallel between compression and
what you're doing here, identifying causal representations. You mentioned that in the case of
compression, the goal is to find kind of the minimalist representation of this function, if you will.
In this case, you're trying to identify a representation that is true to the causal nature that
you're trying to model. I don't know if it's related to the, I guess intuitively, it strikes me
that the causal representation would also be minimal. In the case of the traffic scenario we're
talking about, really, the only things that matter are the traffic light and the cars and everything
else is noise that might be captured by some other model, but the fundamental things that are
causing the system to behave the way it's behaving are the traffic light and the car behavior.
If you can model those and just those as a set of causal relationships, that would seem like it
should be minimal. Where does that break down? Yeah, that's a really interesting point. I am actually
not sure if anyone has tried exactly this, but it's true that most people find it likely that
the causal description of the system has the most or relatively simple components as opposed to
a non-causal description of the system which could have very complicated probability distributions.
So, yeah, that's a great question. It is true that in some sense causal mechanisms are generally
assumed to be simple, especially for humans. We assume that if we factor a probability
distribution along the causal mechanisms, so if we describe everything with a kind of
causal mechanisms, it's a much simpler thing than if we parameterize it in some other way.
Now, I think where this breaks down is that ultimately what's simple to humans and what's
simple to machine learning algorithms, at least right now, isn't quite the same yet. So,
the way that machine learning capacity works translates into different notions of simplicity
for a totally neural prior and then a neural decoder, then notions of simplicity for kind of,
when humans read an expression, what do they think of the complexity of something?
But I do think it's very interesting to explore this further and think more about things like
the minimal description length principle and how that could be applied maybe to compression.
Maybe indeed there is a deeper relation how we can use some of these ideas of simplicity that
pop up both in causality and in compression. There was some prior work that attempted to do
something similar, identify causal representations, but found that it was not possible.
Is that the case? That's exactly right. There's a very well done paper by Francesco Locatello.
I think it won a best paper award at ICML, I want to say 2020. They basically show that if you just
have IID data, if you just have individual images, but kind of just one image from each scene,
that then you can't even identify the variables, even if you assume that the causal relations are
in some sense trivial and that kind of implies that for more complicated causes structures you can
also not do it. So, the way that we get around this is by introducing this non-IID setting,
where we have these pairs of observations. And actually for full fairness here, I would point out
that this is not a totally novel idea. There was another paper by Francesco Locatello
at ICML 2021, I think, where they already think about this weekly supervised setting in observing
a system before and after something has changed. But they focus on the trivial case where
trivial sounds are negative. What I mean is the case where all the causal variables are
independent. So, there's no causal relations between anything. You just have statistically
independent latent variables and they shall show that those can be identified. What we do in our
papers, we extend that to the setting where there's actually non-trivial causal structure
and that we can even then learn the variables and even more that we can also identify the causal
structure. Is there an experimental component to your paper at all? So, in the sense, yes,
that we evaluate our via algorithm on synthetic data. We start with some simple toy data sets and
then we scale up to image data sets. But also these data sets are not real photos of some real
scenes or anything like that. We start with a standard benchmark for causal representation
learning, the causal 3D-ident data set or a variation of that was introduced in a paper by
Julius van Kugelgen and others. And then we introduce our own data set. We call the causal
circuit because we weren't quite satisfied with the available benchmarks. And in this causal
circuit data set, you see a robotic finger operating a bunch of buttons that are connected to lights
in a way. And we show that in this data set, you can correctly identify kind of which pixels
map to the buttons and to the robotic finger and how everything is related. I guess the
salient point in this data set is that the robot, when the robot interacts with a button and it
turns on that light, that doesn't impact any of the other lights, for example. Is that true?
Yeah, kind of. So we actually, just for fun, we added a little causal relation there that like if
you press one of the lights, it turns on one of the other ones as well. But in principle, you could
also have the kind of independent thing. But I think one very obvious thing is like the robot
which is also in the scene that causes the lights, right? It's not the other way around. You could
in principle also think there's some kind of magnet on the table, if whenever one light activates
that magnet pulls the robot, I'm closer to it. Just from looking at individual pictures, there's
no way of telling these two apart. But the, yeah, with these kind of paired data,
this data setting that we introduced and we show that we can actually resolve this and we can
learn that the robot causes the lights to go on another way around. I think there's a really
interesting paper and I'm personally interested in following along with kind of how that work evolves
and how far we can push this idea of just pulling causal representation from images and
you know, woodling down the set of constraints that need to be applied to the model that you create
from them. But I also wanted to talk to you about some of the papers that your colleagues presented
at NURBS and there were several. A couple of those were on combinatorial optimization broadly.
Can you talk a little bit about those? Yeah, I'm happy to. So my colleagues wrote two papers on
combinatorial optimization that we accepted at NURBS, one that was written by Mukul Gagrani and
Karado Rhinona and some others on neural topological ordering for computation graphs. And a second
that was on a batch-based optimization over permutations led by Chang-Yung-Oh,
Cuba students who student at the University of Amsterdam in a Qualcomm sponsored lab there.
What both of these papers have in common is that they are about the problem of finding some
optimal ordering of some objects under constraints. So where this shows up, for instance,
is in computation graphs when you have some, for instance, neural network that has a number of
operations that need to be performed and you want to execute them on your hardware in the right order,
where right order means you want to be as fast as possible, you want to use as little memory as
possible, but you also have to satisfy some precedence constraints that you don't execute an
operation while all the inputs aren't available yet. And this is a hard problem because the number
of operations can be large and the number of possible orders of operations grows very quickly
with the number of operations. In this neural topological ordering paper, my colleagues develop a new
attention-based graph neural network with a suitable message passing algorithm to solve this problem.
It's called a topoformer. I think what's really key about this idea is that this graph-based
transformer combines both the local topology of the computation graphs, so kind of for each
operation you have the information kind of what are the preceding operations that you require and
for which other operations is the output required, but also in the computation you're readily available,
you have readily available global information about the structure of the graph. So each node can
kind of talk to each part of the graph at the same time in this message passing algorithm.
Now there was a bit technical, but the bottom line is that this works really well. If you just
compare to similarly fast algorithms, this is really state of the art, both on synthetic graphs
and on a few real-world examples. And I think it's still competitive with algorithms that are some
orders of magnitude slower than this method. In this context, when you compare synthetic graphs
versus real-world, elaborate on that, real-world problems will be kind of represented as a graph,
the graph itself isn't real-world necessarily. That's a good point, but what I mean with
the real-world problem here is more something like you have some neural network that somebody
really trains, so usually people use some kind of standard neural networks. And then if you look
at the structure of the neural network, you can extract the computation graph from that. So
the graph is as much real-world as the neural network is. It's not that you can see it on the
street, of course, but there's kind of some consensus in the field of what these networks look like.
So this is a problem that appears for real-world compilers when these networks are executed.
While synthetic graphs is really you want to generate a graph with, you say, I don't know,
I want 10,000 nodes and I want like each edge to exist with the probability of 0.1 and I want
the graph to be a cyclic and those are kind of the constraints you put in. And then you just
put on your random number generator. So typically these have a little bit less structure than
real-world graphs. Got it. You're not generating synthetic
programs and extracting the graphs from those programs or models or something like that.
How about the other paper? The other paper, batch-based optimization on
permutations using acquisition weighted kernels is essentially on the same problem. So
it's still about finding the right order for a number of objects. But now they consider the case
where computing performance for each order, so the cost function or whatever you want to call it,
is really expensive. I see you can only run it a few times. So this setting you have to be smart
about how you perform your training, which different configuration, which permutations you query.
And Bayesian optimization is one framework that allows you to do this in a principled way. So you
kind of at each step you try to find that permutation that allows you to gain the most information
on the optimal configuration. Without getting into too many details here, I think my colleagues
here introduced the first batch-based optimization method for optimizing over permutations.
This batch means that you can kind of evaluate the number of configurations in parallel,
which is really practical if you, for instance, have multiple devices, multiple GPUs during training.
And again, like this other paper, I think what really stands out is after developing the algorithm
that this is just state-of-the-art, it beats existing methods on standard benchmarks.
As we mentioned earlier, a number of your colleagues work on
a core variant deep learning, and a couple of the papers at this year's NURBS were on that topic.
Can you talk a little bit about those?
Yeah, we have two papers on a key variant deep learning at NURBS. The first is led by Gabriela
Chesa, and three of the four authors on that paper were actually previously on your podcast.
I believe there was Arash, Taco, and Max were all colleagues, or in Max's case, former colleague
of mine, and who you talked at some point. Anyway, this paper is about a cryo-electron microscopy.
Have you heard about that?
No, tell me more about that.
Yes, it's a really cool and pretty new imaging method for structural biology,
and it has really revolutionized this field a little bit, and I think it also has one
Nobel Prize in 2017. So the idea is, you're biologist, you have some molecules, say a protein
or something, and you want to reconstruct the 3D structure of that.
Now that's hard to do because molecules are kind of small. So what you can do is take a bunch
of these molecules, solve them in some solution, freeze the solution in a very thin layer,
and then bombard it with electrons, and image kind of the size of this. This gives you a bunch
of really noisy two-dimensional images. Now the task is, of course, you have kind of have to combine
these noisy two-dimensional images into the 3D structure of the molecule that you started with,
and that's really difficult, one, because of the noise, and two, because you don't know the
orientation of the molecules, right? They are frozen in some liquid, but you have no idea which
way around. So you need to infer the pose for each of these molecules first.
And this is the problem that my colleagues tackle here. They develop a new algorithm
for inferring the pose of three-dimensional molecules from these trial EM images,
and they tackle this using some strategy from group theory. I think it's called a group synchronization
framework. It's quite technical, but the bottom line here is that they incorporate the structures,
the geometric symmetries of the problem, into the algorithm as much as possible, and then they,
those are smart people, they figure out that you can infer the 3D poses of these molecules
from these 2D images a little bit better than before. This is the starting point to then plug
the residing post-estimates into some 3D reconstruction algorithm and then get better
reconstructions of these molecules. Maybe on a slightly higher level, I think this is another
example for how when you take into account the geometric structure of your problem, the symmetries
of a problem can really make your machine learning algorithms or classical algorithms more efficient.
And that's a lot of what the group focusing on the aquarium and stuff focuses on those symmetries
applied in all different places. Yeah, that's right, and maybe that's a good transition to this
other paper by Arash Bberodi, also a Gabriele and others called a PEC Bayesian generalization bound
for aquarium networks. Now here, they really study how much you can win when you include
in corporate aquarium variants or kind of the geometric structure into the architectural
choices in NREL network. And they do this using a framework called PEC Bayes, so the idea is
basically that you can develop a theoretical upper bound on how much your loss can become worse
when you go from training data to test data. And what they do is that they show that this bound
on the loss, so this kind of generalization error becomes better, the more symmetry constraints
you incorporate in the architecture of your neural network. So in some sense, they theoretically show
that aquarium neural networks generalize better than non-aquivariant neural networks.
What I really like about this paper is that the result of this this theoretical bound also depends
a little bit on the architectural choices you're making your neural network, so you can use this
to provide some guidance for the design of aquivariant neural networks.
How are the architectural choices parameterized?
So I think this is all about what kind of representations of your group you use in the hidden
layers of your neural network. So representations of a group are kind of a classification of
the different ways that groups can manifest themselves on mathematical objects
in particular on vector spaces. So if you have some latent variables, some hidden variables
in a neural network, you can think about them, for instance, as vectors or as tensors or higher
order objects, and they all transform differently under group transformations. Now, that was
quite dense sentence I just said, but basically if you think about, for instance, translation
symmetries, you kind of the idea that if you shift the input a little bit, the output should also
shift a little bit in some way. Then one representation of this is kind of just shifting in the same
way, the standard representation. Another representation is kind of the trivial representation,
where you just stay constant, no matter what happens. This is exactly invariant. So if the input
shifts your hidden layer or your output would kind of stay at the same point. And then there is
higher order representations where when you shift something, the hidden variables or the outputs,
we have in a more complicated way, but still in a way that reflects the symmetry structure of your
problem. And what my colleagues find here is that these representations are that you choose for
for the design of your network are related to the bound on the generalization error. So they give
you some guidance on how you can build a query networks in a way that have as small as possible
bound on the generalization error. The question again. There was a paper on quantization as well.
Yes. Our last paper at NURBs called FP8 quantization, the power of the exponent. This was led by
my colleagues Andrei Kusmin and Mart van Bealen. And I think one of the authors' time has also been
on your podcast before is indeed about a neural network quantization. As you know, a neural
quantization is maybe the most efficient way of making neural networks more efficient. And with
that, I mean, run faster, useless memory, useless power are these things. That's quite important
when you run to run things on device. And that's something that Qualcomm cares a great deal about.
But it's also maybe just important from a sustainability perspective.
Now, one problem with quantization is that many different formats for the representation of
weights and activations have been proposed. So there are integer representations and there are
floating point representations, for instance. And for floating point representations, there's also
many different ways you could construct the representation. What my colleagues do in this paper
is that they compare 8-bit representations in theory and practice. In particular, they compare 8-bit
integer representations and 8-bit floating point representations. And they train neural networks
both in a quantization-aware way, so they kind of take into account how your quantitative
already doing training. And for post-training quantization, where you run the quantization as an
afterburner after your neural network has converged. The result of this paper is a very clear
it depends. So if you have, if you want to use post-training quantization, and especially if you have
large neural networks, let's say large transformer, then a floating point quantization can be
beneficial. But they also find that if you use quantization-aware training, so if you already
include the knowledge that you're going to quantize your neural networks during training,
then the difference becomes much smaller. And another point they make is that the performance
of floating point quantization really depends on the hyper parameter structures. And this is
much more sensitive to the choice of hypermills than int8 quantization. Finally, I think it's important
to say that if the performance of the things is kind of equal, integer quantization has the
advantage that the hardware that is compatible with running that is often much more energy efficient.
So all of the things being equal, I think the go-to recommendation is maybe still int8 quantization here.
Awesome, awesome. How about we quickly run through workshops and demos? Were there any of those as
well this year? Yeah, I'm happy to talk about those as well. We had a couple of workshop papers.
I'm a little bit biased here, but I'd like to cherry-pick just one of them because I was involved
with it personally. And this is a paper called Deconfirmed Immutation Learning, led by my colleague
Risto for Oreo, and presented at the deep reinforcement learning workshop. Now, you know
imitation learning is about the problem of training a policy to not just maximize the reward
function, but imitate behaviors in some offline data set, generate by some experts, right?
And this is advantageous because it doesn't require you to come up with a reward function,
but also it can be beneficial for safety, for instance, in autonomous driving.
And where does the confounding problem that's apparent in the title come in?
Yeah, yeah, exactly. We're getting to that. The confounding problem appears when the expert
and the imitator don't see exactly the same data. Let's say the expert has access to more data
in his inputs than the imitator. Maybe let me give you a silly example for this. So,
let's say we are trying to solve autonomous driving and we are doing this through imitation
learning where the data set is generated by some human drivers. It's a reasonable setting,
but these human drivers generally will have lots of additional information that then later the
autonomous agent will not have. For instance, imagine a human driver listens to the weather
forecast on the morning of generating the training data. And maybe on the weather forecast,
they hear that the road conditions are going to be icy. And then even if you don't see anything
on the road, I bet that their driving will be a little bit slow and a little bit more careful.
A little more cautious. Yeah. Exactly. And that's a problem because then later the agent in the data
set observed multiple examples where the inputs look the same or the behavior of the agent is different.
So what are they going to choose? Are they going to drive slowly? Are they going to drive fast?
They have no way of inferring this. So they must make some random guess here. And then it gets
worse because once you make an initial guess, later the agent can use its own past behavior
as evidence for what the correct behavior is. This is something known as causal delusions and was
pointed out in a series of papers by Pedro Ortega who used to be at DeepMind. So if you just train
an imitation learning agent with a standard algorithm and it kind of decides to go fast initially
and then a few time steps later, it can kind of look back and see, okay, I used to drive fast
and in all the training examples where early on the driver drives fast, he continues to drive fast.
So then this is kind of evidence for continuing with a high speed. Of course, that's not
ideal if the road is potentially icy. So this is a slightly exaggerated example. Of course,
autonomous vehicles right now do not really have exactly this problem, but maybe you get the idea.
And what we do with this paper and what particular is to us in this paper is study this problem
theoretically and characterize the different conditions under which we can solve it in imitation learning.
And mostly limited kind of simple toy scenarios, but we also develop an algorithm that we can run
on reinforcement learning or imitation learning settings and we demonstrate it on a few
continuous control problems. Interesting. How toy? So for instance, we have one environment,
it's one of these standard open eye gym environments where you have like a robotic arm with a few
degrees of freedom and it can strike a ball. And there are some parameters that the agent doesn't know
like the weight of the ball or how much it slows down later kind of the friction.
And the expert knows these things. You can imagine that the expert maybe picked up the ball and
placed it on the table before they hit it to play some mini golf or whatever you want to call it.
So this is something if you just do it once, there's just, if you just train it on imitation learning
and out there in your test environment, you have no way of knowing how hard to hit the ball.
But we learn a policy that kind of does it twice and based on kind of observing how the
ball behaves the first time, then then figures out the value of the friction and the mass in these
things and corrects the behavior for that in the next time. So it's still pretty toy, but I think it's
at least not a kind of tabular data set anymore, but it's slowly moving towards bigger problems.
Awesome. How about demos? Yeah, it was a great fun. It was the first time for me to be at the
Qualcomm booth at least physically. And a lot of people came by and looked at the four demos
that we had there. I talk to you about what exactly they were in a second, but I think what they all
have in common is kind of maybe Qualcomm AI research core competency, which is really
making AI ubiquitous in the sense that we want to run machine learning systems on any kind of
device. So we don't just run our systems on GPUs or even bigger systems, but we had two phones
there. We had one tablet there and we had one AR goggle there and we were running our AI systems on
all of these devices and of course all of these included Qualcomm ships inside. Now more
concretely, we had one demo on super resolution. And here the main novelty was that we quantized
the super resolution network to in four to four bit integers, which is quite a bit small and
quite a bit more efficient than what has been done before at least in terms of real world demos.
We have another demo on conditional compute for video understanding on device. So here the idea
is that we want to solve an action recognition problem. So you see some video data and you want to
recognize what is being done in that video. And most methods do this by kind of parsing the full
video all frames and then classifying the action. But my colleagues developed this method called
frame exit. I think it was presented in CVPR last year that it basically just looks at a few frames
and then the size of it is seen enough and can make the decision already. And once it is seen enough
it kind of stops the computation. It doesn't require processing of all frames and thus makes
a still very efficient decision but exactly with much less computation time also running on
device yet. And we had one demo on multi-model future learning on teach your AI. So we had a
cute simulated robot doc on a tablet and you try to teach gestures that we are performing
to this dog. So you talk to the dog and at the same time you perform some gesture to tell the
dog I don't know something with your hands and and it would kind of after seeing it on your
few times it would kind of learn what these gestures meant by matching what you said and what
what kind of past as audio input with with the video feed. Also running on device.
And then finally we had a demo on a 3D reconstruction on AR goggles. This is about the problem
of depth estimation in AR. So when you have your AR goggles on to do anything with your environment
you really need to kind of reconstruct the 3D scene around here right you need to know how far
away are these pixels that the cameras recording from you. And in particular you want to be able to
do this with very strict hardware constraints. Ideally even just from a single camera feed.
So here my colleagues developed a monocular depth estimation network trained with
a self-supervised learning and then quantized that and ran it on device in a different way.
The processor and the AR goggles roughly equivalent to something that might be in a mobile phone.
I think it's a little bit more restricted. I'm not an expert on this but I believe that this
thing was a Qual Snapdragon 888 chip in there and I think these are less powerful than the
you know the Snapdragon 8 Gen 2 that we just announced that was running in our one of our phone
demos. Okay. Awesome. So I would like to add one thing to this and I think what's really
unites these four demos and what what makes them work in addition to kind of these these ideas
on the method sides is this philosophy of full stack optimization. So at Qualcomm and I research
we do everything from developing the architectures thinking about the training algorithm
to quantizing the neural network. We use this AMAT AI model efficiency toolkit that's
open source and then finally also running it on our chips actually that you can hold in your hand
at the demo booth. I think that's quite neat. It's awesome and I'll link to an interview that I
did with one of your colleagues Morale on that full stack philosophy as well as some of the other
interviews that you've mentioned as well. With all that said it sounds like quite a successful
nerves for you and your colleagues so congratulations. I'd love to have you maybe close us up by
talking a little bit about kind of where your research goes in the in the future and kind of what
you're most excited about across the various things that we've talked about. Yeah thanks for
the question. So this causal representation learning paper that we talked about at length
earlier is really one example of how action and perception should inform each other. In the
sense that in this paper we show that if we can observe the effect of actions it gives us a
principled way of learning perception learning representations. But I think this this relation
between action and perception goes goes further than the justice one direction and in the future
my colleagues and I would really like to continue working on this and maybe also going in the
other direction. Can we learn principled ways of of learning to act learning policies in an
interactive environment based on ideas about causality based on ideas about structure of a system
based on maybe ideas of how representations should behave under actions and that's one direction
I'm very excited about. More broadly we talked about this already before but I really think we
should try to move away from identifiability theorems and more towards thinking about downstream
applications. But I you know what I've had really beautiful in machine learning is the following
like sometimes you have this hammer based research where you have some elegant idea and some
beautiful theory and then you just try to make this theory somehow work in some way and sometimes
you have this nail based research where you have a really well problem you really want to solve it
and the working is the only way that matters and often it ends up being more of an engineering
effort than then really kind of beautiful. But every now and then these two things come together
and you can really kind of hit a hammer with an air you can really use something elegant
from the theory side to solve a really well problem and that's that's where the beauty is
that's that's where machine learning is really fun. Awesome. Awesome. Well Johan thanks so much for
taking the time to walk us through your paper and some of your colleagues work at NURPS.
Yeah thanks a lot thanks for having me this was fun.