All right, everyone. Welcome to another episode of the Twilmo AI podcast. I am your host Sam
Charrington. And today I'm joined by Tony Jabara. Tony is a vice president of engineering
and head of machine learning at Spotify. Before we get going, be sure to take a moment
to hit that subscribe button wherever you're listening to today's show. Hopefully Spotify.
Tony, this conversation is a long time in the works. We're super excited to have you
welcome to the podcast. Thank you, Sam. Great to be with you and with all the folks joining
us here today. Very excited. I'm super excited. I mentioned to Tony before we got started
recording that I've got this memory of I think 2017 or something like that at the rework
deep learning conference in San Francisco. I think it's the hiate that's up on the hill
just by Chinatown. And I think you did a presentation while you were in Netflix about maybe machine
learning for for breakfast or something. And I kind of harangued you. You were on your
way to a meeting out of the hotel and been trying to get a conversation going for a while.
So super excited to finally connect. Yeah. Yeah. Great. We're doing it finally. You know,
thanks for for keeping up and you know, hopefully there's more folks in the audience today
than in 2017 as your podcast seems to be taking off. So that's great. Yeah. Absolutely.
Absolutely. Absolutely. There's no better time than the present. This episode is going to be
part of our NURP series and you participated in a couple of workshops and NURPs mostly
around the topic of reinforcement learning. And that'll be one of the main things we focus
on in our conversation. But before we dig into RL in particular and or at least the the
workshop participation in NURPs in particular, I'd love to have you share a little bit about
your background and how you came to the field of machine learning. Sure. So I was, you
know, excited by what computers could do a long time ago before machine learning really
was a thing. I was looking at computer vision, looking at a bunch of computer science in
general and saying how do we automate what people seem to be doing so well and how do they
recognize faces and images. And you can write a bunch of rules, thinking here's how I would
do it as a person and those were quite brittle. And so, you know, when I first started
in the 90s, it was write rules for things to make computers intelligent. And then that
didn't really seem to scale. It turns out it's much better to show the data and have an
algorithm that learns all by itself what to do from examples of real data, real examples
of intelligent behavior. And so that was, I think, how I really started and I was an academic
because there wasn't much going on in industry in the 90s in the early 2000s. But then of
course, industries where a lot of the big machine learning is happening these days. And
so I went to Netflix and then at Spotify now where machine learning really is driving
a lot of our advances and as a huge part of our business and our personalization offer.
Maybe talk a little bit about your role as head of ML at Spotify. What are some of the
aspects of machine learning that kind of fall under your purview there?
So I'm focused on how machine learning can help across all Spotify. But also in particular,
I lead the teams that build a homepage, the search engine, the programming platform, the
user evaluation and understanding models, the content understanding from music understanding
to talk understanding. And as well, some of the technologies that help us with playlists.
And then I also advise all the business units about how they can incorporate best practices
of machine learning. So our ads business unit, our let's say messaging and user membership
growth business units. All of them really have to work with the same machine learning
infrastructure and best practices. And so I'm also tapped into those conversations, but
you should that we're pushing for the right investments for the long term across all
aspects of Spotify's business.
Any thoughts on how the company's use of ML has evolved since you joined?
Yeah, so ML has been an important tool in our tool chest, but now we're increasingly
relying on it as we have it making so many more decisions more often in every part of
our personalization and our, let's see, connections between the user base and the content.
And what we've seen is huge scale growth of both sides. So we've not only added music
to our catalog, but we've also started looking at talk and audio books and podcasts and live
and video as well. And our user base is grown across countries and cohorts and different
plans. And so the complexity on the, on the people that want to listen and the creators
and the content that should be listened to, that's growing on both sides. And so machine
learning's actually increasingly important to figuring out what is the right valuable connections
to make between the listeners and, and the artist's creators and content. And so that's
been growing at a great clip. The other really interesting thing is Spotify kind of started
off as a curation engine. You would come to Spotify and organize your own playlist and
curate what you thought would be great audio experience. But over the years, we've evolved
from a curation first experience to a recommendation and machine learning experience. So we're still
having people curate their playlists and build them and share them with friends and, and
in the world. But we're also creating playlists for you automatically, creating a homepage
for you that's tailored to what you would be interested in driving discovery, promotions
and search that are tailored for you. And so we're moving very much from a curation
first product to a recommendation first product. And then even beyond that, a recommendation
first product that also explains to you why you should care about this recommendation.
So giving meaning to the recommendation is another aspect, understanding why this makes
sense and how to explain to you and convince you to give it a try. So that's that's been
the journey. So more and more machine learning throughout every stage of that journey.
Can you talk a little bit about the kind of the business value that those recommendations
provide for Spotify? I'm thinking back to a paper from Netflix actually may have been
while you were there. I forget the names of the authors, but one was the head of product
and there was this note in the paper that even back, you know, whatever that was 2015-16,
they attributed a billion dollars of value to the recommendation systems that were built
at Netflix. Can you talk about the, you know, how you, how the business thinks about the
value of these kinds of recommendations? And I'll maybe contextualize this a little bit
with my personal experience as a Spotify user. I'm not, you know, I'm not a big music person
necessarily. I've got some things that I listen to and, you know, that I like and I've
got enlist in Spotify. And I usually just go and, you know, play one of those and or play
one of, you know, the same couple of playlists. Like, I don't necessarily, I'm not your best
consumer of recommendations necessarily. And so I'm wondering kind of how broadly how
they play out across the business. Sure. So we've been investing in a series of AB tested
wins. Each, each test improves retention, reduces churn, increases engagement. And we
can take all those tests or layered on more and more machine learning and say, well, what's
the some value of all of those? The problem is that's happening while users are coming
through the platform and being acquired even not just retained but acquired by machine
learning. And it turns out if you go and survey people, users and, you know, premium subscribers,
which is the majority of how we generate our revenue. And you ask them what drives you
to Spotify? What makes you sign up for Spotify versus consume and find your music elsewhere
or through some other channel or medium? 81% say it's because of the personalization.
And that's really heavily driven by machine learning. So you can think of it as the majority
of users are coming to Spotify's thing at Spotify because of the personalization. And
of course, the content is crucial. You can't personalize when you don't have content.
There's nothing to personalize. But the bigger the content catalog becomes, the more
of the personalization matters. So we're now at, you know, over 100 million tracks, over
100 million podcast episodes. We've added hundreds of thousands of books and we keep going.
And so that means personalization constantly gets more and more important. And the machine
learning algorithm is to find the right thing for you, especially when for you means one
out of half a billion people almost. That value becomes much bigger as the user population
grows as the content catalog grows. And as we improve and roll out more intelligent algorithms
with better wins that are av tested.
I guess that brings us to your presentation at the offline RL workshop, which talks about
some of the ways that you apply offline RL for personalization. But before we jump into
that, talk broadly about the techniques you use. Are you kind of mostly using RL for personalization
or is that one of many tools that you use depending on the specific scenario?
I'd say it's one of many tools. So we leverage a lot of machine learning tools. Think of the
machine learning treasure chest as having, you know, many, many buckets. RL is one of those
buckets. You've got deep learning in another bucket. You've got causal techniques, it
causes inference in another one, probabilistic models. For one of the things we've realized
is we kind of iterated our way and realized that we need more and more RL. And that's
because we started doing heavily, let's say multi-arm bandits at the beginning where you
basically do things like try things out, do a little exploration and then start taking
action that seemed to get good responses from the user. And we did that in all sorts of
places in our systems from our, you know, surfaces like our homepage, to our banners and
our promotions. We use these techniques from baby RL, which is multi-arm bandits. This
is like if you have a forgetful RL agent that doesn't know what state it's in, then basically
it's a bandit. But that's maybe chapter one of the RL textbook. There's many more sophistications
after what you start to say. Well, there's a state, you know, people change as they consume
and discover and help new habits. And so you can't just think of it as a, you know,
multi-arm bandit in the casino, which kind of doesn't really remember what happened before.
You have to really understand users are impacted by your recommendations or what they consume,
that changes who they are. And then they come back the next day and maybe the decision
then is actually a little bit different. So then you understand that you're really not transacting
in the moment only with the user. You're building a journey that's going to last many months
with them, especially if you're a subscription service like we are. Users are with us for
many months, many years. We're now thinking of our business more about building a journey
rather than getting you to just click on something with a bandit and building a journey is
much more of an RL style problem. If you look at what you're actually trying to do with
RL, you're trying to play games and get to the end of a maze and so on or get a robot
to do some useful tasks. Well, it turns out RL is also about getting a user to go on a
journey and discover new things and enrich the way they use Spotify and their day-to-day
life. And one of the themes that occurs in your presentation in the workshop is this
idea of kind of transitioning from a single-step reward to optimizing over the lifetime value
of a subscriber. Can you talk a little bit more about that and the complexities that it
presents for you? Yeah, absolutely. So we started by just optimizing
for the next click. And if you looked at our old-style homepage, old-style search pages,
old-style playlists, it really was about just getting that next consumption, that next
track, that next play session, which is really kind of click through a maximization. You
want to get a good click to the rate. Which makes sense if you're serving ads, but I guess
it's better than the customer closing the app. You're right. So you don't want to completely
give up on instantaneous rewards. You need to do something when the customer opens the
app. However, you can't just always think about what's the easy thing that gets the immediate
click. Because for us, especially, the easiest thing to recommend is just listen to what
you listen to yesterday. Here's the exact same playlist. Here's the exact same tracks.
We know it's not going to be a trust buster. It worked yesterday, so it's not a pretty
good click through rate. The problem is if you keep doing that over and over again, and
you don't worry about the user tomorrow and six months from now and how happy are they
this Spotify? You realize you quickly wear out this user because you haven't layered the
familiar recommendations with discoveries and long-term growth. So you got to go for a
short-term instantaneous reward, but also set up for long-term success. So the user keeps
coming back and in the way is enriched and feels more long-term fulfillment at Spotify.
Because they're building new discoveries of content, new habits, maybe now they're
listening to a weekly podcast on Mondays that is a new habit for them. It's not just listening
to dance music on Saturday, which might be why you started your subscription with Spotify
to begin with, but we want to add new habits. Monday afternoon, listen to this podcast,
maybe Thursday evening's meditation podcast on Sundays, maybe an audio book. So those
habits really keep you coming back for the long term, and maybe they have lower clicks
at a rate immediately, but once you do click, you keep coming back afterwards. So we've unlocked
not just the next reward, but the sum of cumulative rewards into the future, which is what really
RL is all about. Yeah, you've got this interesting kind of pictorial illustration of this where
you talk about machine learning, kind of moving you in circles around your current state versus
RL, which does a better job of getting you to that higher value state.
Yeah, so I like that picture because it really captures what we actually did see in our data,
where users would just go around in these circles of, you know, they play yesterday's thing,
and then they play their typical kind of routine stuff, and they just circle around through
their five, six frequent playlists. And you know, that's great, but if that's what you're doing
eventually, you're going to get worn out by that, and you're not really, you know, getting
more value out of Spotify, you kind of stuck in that rabbit hole going on the circles. And that's
happening a lot with a lot of, let's say, recommendation engines. So how do you make you deliberately
break out of that rabbit hole and go to a higher, you know, altitude location where you are
expecting many more future rewards? Because you're now open to content categories, you didn't think
existed before, you, you know, you've discovered jazz, and now you're going to open up that new source
of reward, which is amazing jazz discoveries for many, many months to come. So that's how we think
of altitude. You're at a higher point where, you know, much more about the audio landscape,
and you can consume for the future much more easily. I'm not sure I thought of myself as stuck as
a Spotify user before this conversation, but now I'm going to be super self conscious about it,
and if not the recommendation systems changing my behavior, maybe this conversation.
We'll take it. We'll take anyway we can. When you start thinking about, you know, this broad
or longer term journey with the user and trying to make decisions around that, do you run into
challenges with attribution? Yeah, absolutely. Attribution is a big problem because it's very easy
to attribute an instantaneous reward to an action because the reward shows up, you know, a few
hundred milliseconds later. You presented the thing I clicked. Exactly. So then it's pretty clear
that, you know, our recommendation that got a click, you know, a hundred milliseconds later was a
good one or a bad one. But when we're talking about, you know, the user retaining longer and
building habits, it's harder to say it was one specific action, which triggered this thing that
may actually have needed several nudges, we call them. You know, I nudged you to try out a podcast
once. It got it into your mind. You thought about it, but you never actually followed through.
And then some other time, you typed a search query that was related to that podcast and they
showed up again. And so it takes a few steps before we actually get the user to build a new habit.
And then you have to reinforce that habit by showing it in shortcuts at the top of the page. And so
that's kind of a long term outcome. And it's harder to say, here's the thing that actually
created the reward. It's several things in sequence. And it's pretty easy to lose the attribution
when it's several sequences of actions that led to the reward. And the reward is delayed. So
causality and attribution become much trickier. What are some of the ways that you apply causality
or causal modeling in trying to model attribution? Well, I mean, we do track lots of
actions. So we have the ability to stitch together an entire, let's say, set of actions that
led to an actual stream. So we have linkages through our data sets, which lets us follow the user
throughout the app and the sequence of actions that led to the final stream and not just think it
was the last last page that triggered it, but maybe you searched and went to an artist page,
then came back and then searched for something else, came to a different artist page and then finally
pushed click and play. We connect those little steps along the way. So we have little trajectories.
And those trajectories get stitched into longer trajectories. So we've built trajectories
for all the users, the history of what they've done and what they've consumed. And that trajectory
data is actually a rich data set that's perfect for things like offline RL because we see
not just action reward, action reward, we actually see the whole trajectory of state action reward
triplets in a time series. And then we can say, all right, this time series clearly is leading
to great outcomes and long-term rewards and consistent rewards. This other time series doesn't
lead to, you know, a bigger sum of cumulative rewards. So we actually are now working with sequence
data and are able to do things with our offline sequence data before going into an AB test.
And we also are building simulators, which is another way to capture this kind of long-term
attribution problem. We simulate how our homepage will look and how users will respond to it.
We simulate playlists and how the users will skip and play them. And so simulation is another
key technology. And both of those were topics of the workshops. So how do you work with offline
sequence data, which we have, and we've logged across our user base. And how do you work with
simulation, which we've built for our homepage, at least, and our playlists? Let's jump into the
offline data. How do you do that? So for every user, we don't just keep track of, let's say,
the last session. We actually look at the series of actions they've taken, the recommendations
we've made, the rewards they've generated for us. And so we actually have time series data.
And that's been valuable. We also use this to build lifetime value models. So we look at users
on the service for many months and say, okay, who is retaining after X many months and who isn't?
And those models look at the history of consumption and also some sequential aspects of
consumption and engagement with our app. And that sequence that is used to make a prediction,
saying, how much longer is this user going to stay? How long will they survive on Spotify, for instance?
And those are things we were able to build also because we have long-term historical data
on retention and what led to retention. So we look at sequences of actions. We look at
long-term consumption histories and how they've led to retention and survival. And then of course,
we build the simulators. But one of the things we've converged on is, in a way, lifetime value models
have been around for a long time. They're used in kind of subscription services. We've realized
lifetime value models are really just the reward function in RL because it's the sum of cumulative
rewards with a discount. And that's literally what a lifetime value is in businesses, in subscriptions.
The link goes a little different, but they actually turn out to be the same thing on
an equation line at least. Yeah. How does that translate to implementation land? Is there
are you building some model that at the end of the month, if the users are still around,
there's a 995 reward or whatever that is. Now it is. Yeah. So one aspect is we literally say
each month when you subscribe, that's a big reward for us because you say, hey Spotify,
you did a good job last month. I'm going to keep betting on you. Here's my 995 or 10 bucks.
And so what we're trying to capture is, you know, we've got 10 bucks for this user,
but how many more months are they going to keep giving us that 10 bucks? And if I can change that,
make it go from 15 more months of 10 bucks to 17 more bucks, then I'm really happy. That might
not show up for a while, right? That user is going to be around. We're not going to know it until
15 months go by and oh, wow, they stayed a little longer. But what we're trying to do is calculate
the sum of those monthly rewards. And we actually do it over a rising of 60 months. So we look at
over the next five years, you know, what's the probability each month that you're going to stick
around? And we sum up all those probabilities multiplied by, you know, the dollar value of that
month. And it's, you know, roughly 10 bucks for subscribers a month. But for free users,
it's coming from their ads and their ad load. And actually, it's a little more complicated. So it's
summing all their future months and with various degrees of ad load as the dollars. And we also
applied discount factor because a dollar today is worth more than a dollar tomorrow, let's say. And
that's exactly what a, you know, the RL textbook problem is it's the maximize a sum of discounted
cumulative rewards. And it turns out LTV is exactly the sum of discounted cumulative dollar rewards.
Is that in a lot of areas in machine learning applied to kind of business types of problems,
you've got to create these proxy metrics because it's, you know, either your actual metric is,
you know, too opaque or too difficult to, you know, turn into a metric suitable for a machine
learning model. Is this an instance where you're able to more closely map the business metrics to
machine learning than in other examples in your experience? Or is it just different?
It is a good proxy metric, as you say, because at the end, yes, a business wants to optimize.
So it's still a proxy metric is kind of the first thing you're saying here. It's not a holy
grill of like we've, you know, fully captured the business need in this computational model here.
Yeah, it's not the perfect metric. It doesn't capture every aspect of the business. There's all
sorts of other costs and revenue and, you know, it's not, we're not trying to put the CFO
at its entire organization into one ML model, but it is a very good proxy, let's say, because
it really is capturing, you know, especially for a business like ours where we have subscribers
and actually multiple plans and free and, you know, churns and premium. We're trying to capture all
of that with a model that really summarizes, let's say, a good portion of the revenue and the margins
for the business, but not all of it. It's not a simulation of the entire business, but it's actually
the best we have considering, you know, it's a very complex business at the end.
So we capture, I would say, a good chunk of the business complexity with this proxy, but it's not,
it's not as good as the actual real data that's showing up every day when we actually see the real
dollars and the real payouts to the artists and to the creators and so on. So it's, there's still
some proxy there. It's not perfect. A big portion of your talk is kind of reviewing some of your
teams, papers over the past year. So the first one you talked about is LTV and survival models,
and I think that's what we just kind of talked about this idea that LTV is really the sum of
the probabilities of, or this weighted sum of, here it's expected gross profit, but I think you map
that to the survival model and the probabilities there. What's the right way to say that?
Yeah, so it's basically the sum of survival probabilities scaled by the profit for each month,
and then you also do it at discount factor because, you know, there's a, you know, the capital
has a time discounts. Yeah. So you could think of it as net, net present value, lifetime value,
or you can literally think of it in the RL normaclature as the value function, V of S, where S is
the state. So if the user is in this state, what's the value? And it's basically the sum of expected
rewards. If you play well from the starting state, according to, you know, a good policy. So
it depends on the policy, of course. So if you continue to act, as we've acted, this user in this
state will generate the following future rewards. And that's, and we've been modeling that with these,
we call them beta geometric survival models, because you don't want to just use geometric,
geometric is kind of the, you know, users don't really flip a coin each month and say I'm going to
stay or not, they actually have these more complicated probabilities that actually depend on
something more than just a single coin. And so we look at everything we know about the user,
and we actually describe their survival through basically two numbers that are computed from
everything we know about them. And those describe the shape of their future survival. And that's,
that's been something we've published in a paper in 2021. And then we recently, in this past summer,
published a version which extends beyond survival to multi-state. So it turns out, you know,
users aren't in just one of two states that's modified. They're not just either subscribed,
they're not subscribed. They actually can have many states. They could be
subscribed. They could be in a free state. They could be in a family plan. They can be in a duo
plan. They can be churned out. They can be churned out, but still registered. We still have
information. They still have emails. And we can still, you know, potentially resume their
account where they left off. And then there's users who just have never even interacted with
Spotify whatsoever and have yet to enter any information into our, you know, into our logins,
let's say. And so, and then furthermore, you can slice those states into more granular states of,
is this user in this country or that one? And we can keep going. But then we've extended the
survival modeling to multi-state survival. And then that starts to look like multi-state reinforcement
learning. And also, a lot of the lessons learned from survival map to this kind of multi-state world.
So, you know, LTV was really about a binary survive dot survive. We've extended to multi-state.
And it actually now looks much more like a nicer connection with RL because RL almost from day one
was multi-state to begin with. It never was just a binary state. And that paper you get into talking about
talking about categorical distributions and Dirichlet distributions. What's the, where did those
come into play? So, just like, you know, in, so if you're going to stay subscribed and not
stay subscribed, we said it's kind of like a user flipping a coin. Each month, the user's flipping
a coin and if it lands on heads, they turn off, if it lands on tails, they stick around for another
month. That model is not perfect because it turns out users aren't just flipping a coin each month.
They're, think of it as they're drawing a coin from a coin factory and flipping that coin each
month. And so, that's how you think about it. And that's the coin factory is called a beta
distribution. And then the coin flip itself is like a Bernoulli event. And it's a coin factory
their next state. And the flip is whether they go there or not. So, what we're doing for each
user is trying to predict what kind of coin factory are you writing as a user. And each month,
you grab a random coin from that coin factory, you flip it and that decides what you do.
And so, that was the analogy. And it turns out that fits the data way better. If each user is
described as having their own coin factory, and that fits the data way better than saying each
user has a secret coin that they flip. So, it's analogous to the beta survival model where you had
these two parameters that you're trying to figure out for each user. Now, you're trying to figure
out a coin factory number of parameters. How many parameters characterize a factory?
So, the beta is the coin factory. And then the Dirschley is the dice factory. And so,
okay. And so, when you have multiple states, you don't just flip a coin, you roll the dice.
And so, I'm a state 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, or 6. And it turns out users don't transition
by rolling at, you know, the dice. What they also seem to be doing is they have their own dice factory.
They grab a dice from it every day. The dice are slightly loaded differently, and then they roll
the dice. And that actually fits the data better. So, it turns out, you know, human beings are not
a single dice or a single die. They're not a single coin. They're acting more like a factory
of these things. And there's a distribution of dice or a distribution of coins. And that captures
the dynamics of multi-state transition better than what we saw with just the simple models,
like the Markov models and so on, that, you know, are single dice and single coin models.
And now that's what we're using in our systems. Got it. Got it.
And so, the next paper you talked about is the RL and temporally consistent survival.
So, this sounds like an extension of the idea to temporal consistency. What were the
challenges that you were looking at there? So, this was kind of like the last, you know,
put the bow around the connection between LTV and RL. And so, this was published
last week at NURRIPS. And what we said was, these survival models are great. They look like RL
kind of as well. But there's one aspect of RL, which is missing, which is when you estimate
a survival model, let's estimate my survival model for today. Tomorrow, you're also going to
look at my data and estimate my survival model. Those two survival models should be consistent.
You shouldn't estimate complete different survival from one day to the next. And yes,
maybe they can start to change a little bit because today, maybe I discovered one more great
podcast, the Tumel podcast with Sam. And so, maybe now I want to survive much better.
But there should be some consistency in time. And if you enforce that consistency,
you actually get a much better estimator for these survival models that works better than just
fitting them to the data with maximum likelihood, which has been how we did this before.
Or Bayesian kind of marginal likelihood. So, if you enforce temporal consistency,
everything also seems to work better. And that was an aha moment. And that led to, again,
a performance improvement in our models. So, you add temporal consistency to survival models.
And you go from point flips and dice rolls to factories of coins and factories of dice.
Both of those two ideas really seem to improve how well these models fit our real human data.
And that's those are the lessons learned. And it turns out, those bring survival modeling
very close to RL. And we feel like now, you know, there's almost a kind of a one-to-one
the source between the two communities where you can say, okay, I've got this concept of temporal
consistency. Oh, that's related to, you know, how RL enforces Markovian dynamics and Bell
many equations and temporal difference learning. So, there's kind of a nice the source between
these two technologies that have existed in very different communities, kind of all mapping to one
one real big framework that's consistent. That strikes me a lot of evolution of the around
the sophistication of the way you're applying RL to your problem over the course of just a year or two.
Yeah, I mean, we're we have researchers thinking about this and trying to connect it. What's
great about Spotify is we're not just building, you know, science for science to say we're really
thinking about the business, thinking about our users, how we can give them the most value and
understand their behaviors as opposed to just building, you know, algorithms in, you know,
in a, you know, isolated way. Yeah, yeah. We're also testing some of these things now in production
and seeing the benefits. So, some of the learnings are now that we've understood these LTV models
and we start connecting them to value functions in RL and Q functions from RL. We're now understanding
how they, how they can help us better make recommendations now that we think about our recommendations
as an RL problem. And what are we trying to maximize in RL? You're trying to maximize the sum
of future rewards and or maximize the Q function really. That Q function now we can start to
understand better and realize for our domain that the Q function is a combination of getting
you to click, but also giving you something that's very valuable for the long term when you do click.
And so this was in the last paper that we presented and it's actually encouraging us to view kind
of recommendation as not just maximize click through rate, but maximize the click through rate
of something that's going to continue to generate let's say a long, long term sum of rewards.
So some high value consumption item. So don't just show me something I'm very likely to click on,
but if I do click on it, it's going to increase my lifetime value by a big amount. And so that's how
we're shifting our recommendations now. That's the optimizing audio recommendations for the long term
paper. That's right. So we're realizing, don't just get things that are clicky, but get things that
are clicky and sticky. So once I click on it, I'm going to keep coming back to it. It's going to be
something that becomes a habit for me as opposed to I click consume and forget. And it's going to
there's no real, you know, change in my long term value once I do click on something. So we're trying
to show you something you're likely to click on and try. But and if you do try it, also will increase
your LTV. And that that's kind of how we're shifting our recommendations now. So can you talk about
the the process of going from the the research to actual recommendations? You, you know, there's
this one idea of hey, you know, we've got these research. They identify these methods. We take
these methods. We implement them against our data. They produce these models and poof. The models
will recommend the constant the content. What you're describing here is the models are informing you
about ways to think about how to make recommendations. And then you make different different
recommendations. I'm not hearing you put models in production that make different recommendations.
Like bridge the gap for me around this. Are we just talking time scales or? No, you're right.
This is a longer process. I'm kind of, you know, jumping to the to the conclusion. But the reality
is the way this starts is we have the ideas who write down, you know, some modeling assumptions
and some, you know, aha moments, maybe a paper. We build a prototype. Then we maybe take that
prototype and refine it with the offline data that I talked about. We get some good offline results.
And we may even put the model through the simulator and see how well it does in simulation.
Then we actually get it to be a productionized model that we can run, run live on real users.
And what we then do is we A, B test it. We say, let's run this model in kind of a side-by-side
horse race against what we're already doing from last year, let's say. So we got model A and
model B running on half users get model A, half users get model B. And then that's really how
we evaluate. We don't just stop offline or stop at the prototype. So then we have these two
production models running side-by-side. And then we actually say, do we see after, you know,
X many days of running this model side-by-side better engagement. Our people sticking around longer,
retaining better after a couple of months of horse racing these models side-by-side. And it turns
out we do see better long-term metrics with these kind of RL-inspired models. And it turns out
what the models seem to do is they have lower click-through rate, the new models. But long-term,
the users are streaming and retaining better. So I've given up on showing something that, you know,
you're going to click on as often. But what ends up happening is they get to show you things that
maybe are tiny bit lower click-through rate. But once you do start clicking on them, then you keep
coming back to them and they become habits. And then you're listening more on Spotify and you're
retaining better on Spotify. And so that's kind of what we're going after. We're going after the long-term
outcomes. It's okay to go from a click-through rate of let's say, you know, 47% down to 45% click-through rate.
What I'd much rather say is, okay, but then two months later, I'm actually getting more listening
total even though my click-through is lower. Because I'm actually building longer-term habits and
coming back to that same podcast. It's a habitual podcast. It's a new way of engaging with Spotify.
Maybe now I listen to a, you know, a meditation podcast in the evenings. And I listen to my,
you know, my news podcast in the morning and my way to work. So all these new habits now have been
added. They might have actually had lower click-through rate in the moment, but long-term they generate
more engagement for that user. The user spends more time on Spotify and retains better on Spotify
at the end of the 60 day or 70 day trial. And then we roll it out so that everybody gets that
better experience. And so, is that cycle something that, you know, the models produced by this
RL approach kind of been through that full cycle and, you know, that happens on some frequency,
or, you know, given that we're talking about long-term value here, is this also a long-term
assessment process? And the jury's still out on the models. You're liking what you're seeing,
but it's not a full flage to commitment to this particular approach. So, yeah, that's it.
That's a great question. So some of these things are actually fully rolled out in parts of our
product. So we've got a fleet of machine learning systems. Sure. Some of them now are now completely
on this kind of approach. So we tested it, AB tested it, it was a win, we rolled it out. And so now
this is the default approach in some parts of the app. Other parts of the app were still testing.
Other parts of the app we haven't even tried it out yet. So the approach has legs.
It doesn't mean it works everywhere, but we're past the stage of just prototyping and trying
stuff in simulation or offline. It's getting real users, giving it thumbs up. And actually,
in some parts of the app, it's actually fully deployed as an approach.
Yeah. So this approach that is kind of being pioneered on the research side, are there
ways that your data scientists and machine learning engineers need to think differently about
modeling to use the RL types of approaches or to kind of embrace what you're doing here? Or
is it just another tool in the toolbox for them? So it's a great question. We're obviously trying
to make some of these things, you know, let's say, easy to reuse and try out in different places.
So you're not starting from a blank slate in other parts of the product. What do you want to try
out these techniques? But really, this is a multi-disciplinary endeavor. We worked first off with
researchers and we spoke to users and got user research even to tell us people liked this idea of,
you know, recommendations that aren't just click-vading for the moment, but they're actually great
for the long term. And then we took those intuitions, fleshed out research prototypes,
and those prototypes have to look promising. We brought in engineers who could build the
scalable productionized versions of them. We A, B test them, we get data scientists to look at
those results. The data scientists say, okay, this is what's happening to the metrics. This is how
they move. This is what we recommend use this setting of this algorithm. That's what we would
recommend rolling out. You know, and product managers are also involved. So it really is
all the expertise is coming together. And it's not just researchers doing great research and
then throwing it over the fence. They really sit down with the engineers, the data engineers,
backend engineers, machine learning engineers. So I would say that's kind of the Spotify way.
It's bring all the skills necessary for the problem to the table. So then we go from end to end,
we go from an idea to an actual user productionized value add. Awesome. Awesome. Those are great
case study and real world applicability of reinforcement learning. It's been an interesting topic
for folks for a while. And I also hope is the first of many conversations. I'd love to have
you kind of close us out with, you know, just what you're most excited about in terms of the future
of this particular work where you think that goes. Well, I mean, I think reinforcement learning is
about doing things with, you know, human feedback and what really matters to people for the long term,
not just building algorithms like click optimization algorithms, which is maybe where the internet started,
but where's it going? It's going to, you know, get the long term user feedback and human feedback.
And we're trying to do that now. It's Spotify. We're seeing other companies do that, you know,
for example, people are fine tuning with RL. They're large language models with human feedback. So
they start to do more intelligent things. So we're really viewing reinforcement learning as a way
to incorporate more valuable human feedback in how the algorithms behave. And I think this is
maybe now a nice and fletching points where RL is moving out of the textbooks into the real world
more and more. So I'm very excited that it will help us build algorithms that are actually more
long-term intelligent and not just kind of clickbait, like myopic click chasers. That's awesome.
All right. Well, thanks so much, Tony. I really appreciate you taking the time to chat with us.
Thank you, Sam. What's up? I'm talking to you today.