All right, everyone. Welcome to another episode of the Twimmil AI podcast. I am, of course,
your host, Sam Charrington. Today, I'm joined by Anima Anam Kumar. Anima is
Bren Professor of Computing and Mathematical Sciences at Caltech and Senior Director of AI
Research at NVIDIA. Of course, before we get going, take a moment to hit that subscribe button
wherever you're listening to today's show. You can also follow us on TikTok and Instagram
at Twimmil AI for highlights from every episode. Anima, welcome back to the podcast. It's been a bit.
Yeah, thank you, Sam. It's such a pleasure to be back and so great to see where how Twimmil
has expanded its audience. It's now even on TikTok. And when we started back then in the beginning
of the AI revolution to where we are now, it's so great to see Twimmil be part of the journey and
helping our viewers and audience to really be up to date with the latest and greatest machine
learning tools. Thanks so much. I'm really excited about catching up with you and digging into
all the work you're doing around AI for science. Since it's been such a while since we last spoke,
I'd love to have you just reintroduce yourself to our audience and share how you came into the field.
Yeah, certainly. It's been such an exciting journey to be part of the AI revolution starting
all the way back when AI was considered more a theoretical concept. People didn't think in our
lifetimes it would take off like the way it has done now. But that also meant I could hone in
on the theoretical foundations from statistics, signal processing, machine learning, probabilistic
models, and ask questions like, how do we extract hidden or latent variables or phenomena
from data without labels? What we call unsupervised learning. And I was working on tensor methods
which conceptually looks at higher order moments of data when people were mostly limiting to
second order moments or linear algebraic techniques. We talked about that back then,
and a lot of my work was saying, no, no, don't just limit to linear models. Don't just limit to
spectral methods that use matrices go beyond, think bigger. And we have the computational
abilities to do that now. We can go to tensors. And that kind of non-linear transformation
is what we also see with neural networks. So we were early in that journey to go from matrices
to tensors. And from tensors now we have all kinds of non-linear mappings learned through
all the neural networks and related tools. And so to me to see that journey and now last year
was the year of Generative AI. And so to me who's been working on generative modeling since my
earliest days in graduate school, it's so great to see that. Come into fruitition and see how
it's having a lot of really important practical implications. That's awesome. And it's been
quite a quite a year for for generative AI. And I'm sure we'll be talking a little bit about that.
But one of the things we wanted to dig into a bit is the work that you've been doing around AI
for science. Tell me a little bit about how you got involved in that. Yeah, certainly,
you know, at Caltech here we founded AI for Science as a campus wide initiative in 2018.
Way before researchers were thinking of it as a mainstream area in AI, right?
Indeed, a lot of the AI development has been driven by industry, by big tech,
and focuses on natural images and text, because that's where we can easily get
web scale data. And they also have a lot of commercial value for building the next generation
internet. You could argue. But when it comes to scientific domains, you know, there's even a
hard question of where do we get started. You know, there's so many challenges that we don't
see in our standard AI domains like Image and Text. I know that starts with the lack of data,
right? You may not have large scale data that's really necessary for deep learning. And you
would not only think about a very specific task, you most of the time required zero-shot
generalization. So you want to go beyond the training domain, you know, a lot of the
sciences extrapolation, right? Not only the data I've seen, what is the possibility beyond?
What are new drugs? What are new molecules? How do I create those? You know, you don't have data
on that because all the design and discovery is about finding something new that doesn't exist
so far in your training. And so that's, to me, that extrapolation and generalization beyond
the training data is such an important aspect that standard machine learning wasn't capable of
doing. But that's where I think now in the era of generative AI, so much of that is becoming
much more possible. You know, just like we can generate avocado chairs, can we generate better drug
molecules? You know, for the viewers, what I'm referring to is like a stable diffusion or
dolly, these models that once they learn text to image mapping can now create entirely new
images that were not in training data, right? Entirely new scenarios, like a chair that looks like
an avocado. You know, you probably didn't see it in training data, but if you learn the concept
of what is a chair and what is an avocado, you can try and mix that together. Do this compositional
generation. And I think these are concepts now that we are coming a full circle is aspects that
can have huge implications in the sciences. And yeah, so a lot of unique challenges, but also
I think opportunities that lie ahead when it comes to AI for science.
I think one of the, one of the areas of AI for science that's received a lot of publicity over
the past year, a couple of years has been around the various protein folding research.
Can you talk a little bit about that and why that's interesting and important?
Yeah, absolutely. Protein folding has already been making such a big impact in our ability
to quickly generate the full three-dimensional structure of proteins, right? So how do you map
from sequences to now three-dimensional structures? And this folding is so important because
that's what will determine how other molecules or other proteins interact and bind.
So if you now have a drug molecule, which is typically a small molecule, I mean, not all the time,
but most of the time it's simpler to design a small molecule. And then the question is how does
it want bind in a certain pocket of the protein? You know, what are the active areas in this protein,
right? So all that's determined by this three-dimensional structure. And that's why for biologists,
you know, this was really critical because you can all use all the knowledge and intuitions
and say, oh, this could be a good binding candidate. But until you have the three-dimensional
structure easily available, how do you determine if that's good computationally? And that's
where you have to go to the lab and do those experiments, which are really expensive.
And now we are going even beyond the folding, right? Even just the protein by itself,
what is the structure? To now, how do the protein and ligands, which are small molecules,
bind together? So in many cases, it's even more complicated, as always, biology is quite
complicated, right? The protein, when it's binding to this small molecule, in fact, changes
its structure. So it's not even a static process. And so that's one of the work we've been
exploring using these generative AI diffusion models is not only to model the static
behavior of how a protein looks in three dimensions, but how does that three-dimensional structure
change when it binds to the small molecules? And so to model that process, and with that,
we can predict better about the contacts. How well does it bind? And that's so crucial for
coming up with much more realistic predictions. And that's just one example. You know,
we're talking a lot about structure. And this is, quoting Frances Arnold, who is Nobel Prize winner
here at Caltech, for directed evolution of protein. So she is quoted in New York Times on
Generative AI for proteins that appeared, I think, about two weeks ago. And so she's asking,
that's great. We're solving all these structure problems, right? We can speed up our prediction of
structure. We can greatly increase the accuracy of our structure prediction. But what about function?
Because ultimately, what we want to understand is, what is the functionalities of different proteins?
And can we create like better proteins, which have functional implications? Because, you know,
if you can create better targets and create drugs for it, we can cure a lot of diseases and
issues that so far have not been able to do through traditional therapeutics. And I think that's
where a lot of the work that, for instance, my group is doing as well as others, is to not just
limit to the structure. Because if you only look at proteins and their structure and create the
foundation models, you know, it's not very easy to talk about the function. But if you go to the level
of the genome, you know, the DNA, right, that determines the function. If you can learn the
relationship between different genes, you know, what is the relationship and how does it relate
to different functionalities of the proteins? Because genes can be mapped to the proteins that
generate. And by understanding relationship between the genes, can we generate better proteins
that are functionally meaningful for different tasks? And that's what we've been doing now. And
and it has so many applications. So in the largest biological language model that we built
of about 25 billion parameters, what we showed was the ability to learn at the genome level,
so long sequences of bacteria and viruses, more than 110 million such sequences. So we consumed
all that into a language model. So in a way, you're understanding the language of the genome. And then
from that, we can generate now new gene sequences, right. And with that, we could in fact predict
new variants of coronavirus, as well as, you know, the ones we had held out, the existing variants that
appeared like Delta, Omicron, right, all those we could predict, even though the model had never
seen that before. What was the text that that model was trained on? Genome sequences. Got it.
So think of now the language is the genome, right. So that's your now alphabet. That's your sentences.
It's longer and that's a challenge. In fact, we used a combination of language model like GPT,
but with the diffusion backbone in the latent space. So it's a hierarchical model that has
both diffusion and GPT components, which is necessary for these long sequence modeling.
And, you know, and that really helped us to understand at the genome level these relationships.
And you could also see organization in the latent space of different latent genes, right. So genes
that are closing that latent space are also functionally similar or related. And I think those
also help us now to design better proteins. This reminds me a little bit of
work that I spoke with Richard Socher about when he was, I think he did this at Salesforce
of all places. Are you familiar with that at all? Yeah, certainly. That was some of the early work on
understanding protein. I think sequence models, if I recall right, or like molecule models, right.
So a lot of work in the last few years has gone first at the molecular level. You know,
how do we generate better molecules? How do we give like condition on various properties and
generate better molecules? And then we said, we can't just look at a molecule in isolation.
We have to look at how it binds to the protein, right. That's the important interaction.
And that's why we went into the protein structure prediction, which is the alpha-fold and
the meta-ESM and all open-fold and all these tools. But then we said, we can't look at the protein
in isolation. We have to look at how the protein and this molecule bind. And that's the joint
prediction. And we also do that dynamically because the protein structure can change as it's
finding. So that's modeling the dynamics. And now we are saying, all this is great, but this
still doesn't tell me the function. You know, what are these proteins doing in our body or in
organism? And that's where we need to go to the DNA level. And so we need to understand the
language of the genome and not only learn those relationships between genes because they map
two proteins, but also potentially generate new gene sequences and through that new proteins and
new targets. And I think that's exciting because we're really going up the hierarchy and then
essentially understanding the code of life, right, life on Earth. So I think it's very exciting times.
Yeah. If the genome encodes the protein structure, how does that get, how does understanding
that get you to function? Because it's at the genome level that you're determining a lot of
functionalities of the organism, right? So it's encoding more than just protein structure.
Yeah, absolutely. Because that's what evolution has endowed with, you know, all the fitness,
right? Like which one survive, which ones are good proteins? You know, that's what is encoded
in all our DNA as well as, you know, the DNA from all the way from viruses to all the higher organisms.
And it's complicated, right? You can't just directly map one to one in higher organisms and that's
why we started from virus and bacteria where it's clearer and simpler to analyze, but I think we can
as these models get bigger as we create foundation models on long genome sequences and
really get into understanding what in the latent space we can encode, right? And what does the
generation of new sequences mean? And, you know, what kind of evolutionary gaps or other things
they're filling? I think we can do a lot more than what we've done today.
You mentioned diffusion a couple of times in the couple of works that you've discussed. Can you
talk a little bit about the relationship between how are you using diffusion and how it's used in
the context of stable diffusion? Yeah, absolutely. You know, last year has been exciting for
generative AI and stable diffusion has really, you know, been a trial blazer in the sense that we
have an open source model, right? Where has found a whole range of an ecosystem of applications
and it can generate seamlessly new image candidates based on the text instruction.
And so what the diffusion model at its core is a generative model that can sample new
candidates, new realizations from a distribution it has learned. And the way it does is to go from,
let's say, a Gaussian distribution, which is simple to sample from to the distribution of images,
which would be hard to directly learn. But by learning this mapping, like think of it as a
slow diffusion, you go from Gaussian noise and you, you know, progressively make it look more
and more like the image. It'll be a noisy image and ultimately at the very end, all the noise
would be filtered out and it would be the true image. So that slow process, how can we model that
through learning these mappings, right? Learning this transformation from a Gaussian distribution to
the image. And similarly, we can do that for scientific domains as well because it can, you know,
the concept is you can learn any arbitrary distribution, probability distribution. And so we can
learn now the probability distribution of how does the pros, you know, how do we create new genome
sequences, right? What is the probability of them occurring, right? Because there is, you know,
we know a lot of like there's high correlation between different gene sequences in a genome.
You know, there's just like a code where some combinations are just not valid or they're not
going to survive. They're not that, you know, relevant for the real world. And that's encoded in
that data set of all known genome sequences that people have collected. And so by encoding that,
we can learn now a better way to sample. And that's true for also so many other applications.
Another setting we're thinking about over the last few years has been to look at all kinds of
spatial temporal processes and the phenomena in science and engineering, right? Think about how
fluids move, how does our weather forecasting change? How does our ability to predict earthquakes
develop? And so so that's another area as well where uncertainty quantification is very important.
And I think tools like this could be very effective when that's something we're working on.
Are you for seeing kind of the diffusion applying diffusion to all the things? Is it a tool that we
kind of stumbled upon for, you know, generating cool images, but it's going to have much broader
implications over the coming years? I think it's one of the tools, right? I mean, the question of
which specific architecture and which specific framework can evolve over time. It was GANS
a few years ago. And we saw like challenges in optimization. And maybe one day will overcome that
optimization challenges, right? And I do think that's important for the scientific applications too
because in sciences, we have a lot of constraints. You know, for instance, one setting we've been
extensively working on is solving partial differential equations. And so they're incorporating the
physics constraints, incorporating, you know, the fact that you should satisfy this equation. So
you penalize if you don't satisfy that equation, right? Our constraints. And so these kind of
constrained optimization frameworks are similar to again, right? Because they're primal dual
optimization. And so we still haven't solved those fundamental optimization issues. In deep learning,
we've kind of swept it under the rug and said, okay, this problem is hard. So let's just develop
a different methodology where we don't have to tackle that at all. And I think in the short run
that gives us some gains, but at the same time in the long run, I think that comes with its own
issues. You know, for instance, diffusion models are slow to sample because they have to
gradually go from a Gaussian distribution to the distribution of images. And one of the frameworks
we've developed to overcome that, you know, to do a decoding in parallel. So instead of sequentially
sampling going from Gaussian to the image distribution, can we directly jump? And can we do it in
a generalizable manner, not just overfitted one setting and then, right, it doesn't work in other
settings. And the frameworks we are using in all these settings has been what we're called neural
operators, which are, I think, a really important concept when it comes to scientific domain
applications. They can solve differential equations like the one used in diffusion models for
sampling. But they can also solve all kinds of other differential equations like in fluid dynamics,
you know, the ability to model seismic waves underground to predict earthquakes to model carbon
capture and storage, you know, as we mitigate climate change. How do we pump carbon dioxide
deep underground? And how does it interact with water? These what we call multi-phase flow systems.
And I think that to me conceptually is different from the standard neural networks. And that becomes
a really important tool for scientific domains. Can you dig into that a little bit more? What does a
neural operator look like and how did you arrive at that? Yeah, absolutely. I think this has been
such an exciting journey because we went about asking, you know, let's say I have the problem of
saying how does the fluid dynamics evolve, right? I start the fluid and I shake it a little.
How does the flow change over time? You know, it sounds very similar to a video prediction problem.
So why not just use all the tools we've already developed to do this prediction? So it turns out
the main challenge is that here the fine scales matter a lot, right? We know the turbulent
phenomena like this. You can't just like filter out or smooth out the fine scales or the high
resolution information. If you do that, you will get come up with bad predictions. On the other
hand, in the natural image domain, we want to all the time filter out, right? All the pixel
is just too high dimensional and mostly useless information. We want to go from pixels to object
localization. And so that means we all the processes to remove all this irrelevant information
and filter out smooth out. And that's what like convolutional filters do because locally,
you're learning these ability to smooth out and extract only the relevant features like edges.
But that's different in so many of the scientific simulations like fluid dynamics
because you cannot just filter out or smooth out the higher resolution information, right?
You have to keep that. And the consequence of that is you cannot just learn your input to
output mapping in one resolution. So think of any kind of image generation or image prediction.
You always specify, pre-specify, what is the resolution of the image you want to either generate
or predict on, right? It doesn't work at a different resolution. People train and the train only
at that one resolution, they use the model only at that resolution. Whereas for the scientific
domains, that would break down. And that's why until now, until these neural operators,
we proposed until that point, people never thought about replacing the full traditional
numerical solvers, right? So the whole point was, let's keep the solvers, let's
get measurements from them and then try to do super resolution on top of it.
Still mapping from one fixed resolution to another fixed resolution. But on the other hand,
we couldn't completely get rid of the numerical methods and the traditional solvers.
And so the way we went about overcoming this fundamental drawback is to come up with now
framework called neural operator. So once you've trained the model using some training data
at certain resolution, at testing time or at inference time, you can test it at any resolution.
So you can give it an input at a different resolution, even a higher resolution than what it
has seen during training. And still, it can make valid predictions. And that's the concept that
makes this both, first of all, important for scientific simulations because people want
the flexibility to choose different measures, different sampling techniques, right? They don't
want to limit to one resolution, one grid. And the other is it also gives it the superior ability
to capture the fine scales, which is so important for the simulation frameworks.
And you mentioned and explaining this convolutional operator is the idea here that the
the neural operator is a kind of an abstraction of that idea and the exact relationship between
the thing that you apply it to and the output is learned.
Absolutely. You know, at a conceptual level, it's very similar to the current neural networks,
right? Could be convolutional neural network transformers. You know, it does also try to learn
a mapping from the input to output. But the difference here is that it doesn't just accept your
input at one resolution. It has the flexibility to accept input at different resolutions.
And which is lacking in our current standard networks. You know, if you take convolutional
neural network, it learns filter at one resolution. So you give it input at a different resolution,
right? It completely fails. And so this fundamentally says that we can now learn
an operator, which is mapping between function spaces. So we are changing our input to a fix
size, right? Could be a vector or matrix like image, which is of a fix size to one that is a
function. And that function, you could sample anywhere in a domain, usually the continuous domain.
So if it's a fluid flow, right? And I tell you, what is the domain? What is its boundary?
You know, you could make your resolution finer and finer, right? Because it's a continuous domain.
So you don't just limit to one resolution. And that's the ability we provide in these neural
operators. Of course, the next question is, how do I make this practical, right? I mean, sure,
this is a wish list. So far, what I said is, this is what I want out of a learnt mapping
that is not present in the standard networks. Now, how do I make neural operator actually possible
that can handle these different resolutions? And so the way we go about doing this is through
Fourier domain operations. So what we call Fourier neural operator. And you can operate the Fourier
transform at any resolution, even any grid, right? So conceptually, it has the expressivity to handle
different grids, different resolutions. And is this where the traditional numerical methods come in?
It is inspired by traditional methods, which also use Fourier transform. But the differences,
we are marrying that with non-linear transformations, like in standard neural networks. That's the
power that deep learning has, right? It's not just linear. You have non-linear activations.
So we are combining the principles from signal processing, signal representation theory that
using Fourier transforms can represent signals at any resolution. But now, you know, if I learn,
like in the frequency domain weights, and I go back to the standard domain, that's not enough,
right? That's just a linear transformation. And so I now do non-linear activations and keep doing
these series of operations again and again, this way I can capture scales at different frequencies.
So I can capture a big spectrum, even though like each set of operations is just linear.
But I have non-linear activations in between. And so in a way, it's a marriage of the old and the new,
right? The old being properties that Fourier transforms have that, you know, people in numerical
methods have been using that as a way to express signal more efficiently. But then they assume
linearity that, you know, you should be able to capture the spectrum of your input
compactly through Fourier transform. And that's usually not true, right? Many of this have high
frequencies. So just doing Fourier transform once isn't very efficient. But if you combine it with
non-linear transformations of multiple such blocks, it is expressive. And in fact, we show that
this becomes a universal approximator for functions basis. Meaning just as theoretically a standard
neural network can universally approximate any function in a fixed dimension,
we can now use neural operators and approximate any operator in a function space. So it can,
it has the expressivity to handle any non-linear operators, like what we see as solutions
of fluid dynamics and other partial differential equations, as an example.
So you've gone from wish list to something that's more tangible, but you haven't,
you know, yet demonstrated practicality. Can you talk a little bit about practicality?
Oh, yeah, yeah, absolutely. And that's where, you know, the last year is where we really took this off
to very practical and real-world large-scale applications. So one of them has been in the
realm of weather forecasting, you know, our ability to predict what's going to happen in the next
week or next two weeks, right? It is so critical. And especially extreme weather events, which are
increasing in their intensity and scale as climate change, you know, intensifies.
And so what we showed is that these framework using these kind of concepts from neural operator,
we can predict whether as good as the current numerical weather models for as long as two weeks,
but be about 45,000 times faster. Wow. And so that's, you know, really exciting. And a hard
benchmark, because currently numerical weather models use numerical solvers sometimes over
thousands of variables of partial differential equations. And, you know, that can take our
some CPU clusters, right? Whereas our model works within a second, in fact, a quarter of a second
on a single GPU. And we've open sourced this model, we've made this available to the community.
And I think that's very exciting to, you know, see this kind of democratization, not just in the
generative AI that's so much in the news, but in these scientific domains, you know, enabling
everybody to run their own weather model and build all kinds of downstream applications, whether it's
for agriculture, you know, can we come up with accurate regional predictions to, you know,
that interest new sensor data, new information, and that can refine the scale locally to provide better
estimates. We can also ask how this information could be used in conjunction with a climate model,
because not just looking at the weather of today, but what about the weather of the future?
How well does it extrapolate? And these are aspects that we are right now working closely with
meteorologists and climate scientists, both at NVIDIA, as well as the broader community,
and that's been very exciting. And that's just one of the examples. The other one that I've mentioned
before has been in carbon capture and storage, you know, so climate change is upon us, and I think
a lot of scientists believe that the only way to completely, you know, tackle this is to mitigate it
through frameworks like capturing carbon, right? Whether it's directly from that atmosphere,
what is known as direct-air capture, you know, people are also trying that from the ocean,
or it's like as it's being produced, you kind of isolate and capture it and pump it deep underground.
And so they're the phenomena that we need to model is how does the carbon dioxide pressure
build up deep underground? You know, as we interacted with water, it's a highly non-linear
gas-plume evolution. And so how do we contain the pressure over several decades? And even there,
we can see benefits as much as 700,000 times faster than numerical solvers. Because here,
it's a very, again, fine-scale phenomena in this wells underground. You need to model how both
carbon dioxide and water, you know, this is called multi-phase because you have both liquid and gas
interact. And so modeling that non-linear phenomena. But also, it's not just in a single well,
it's multiple such wells, but there's some porosity, right? There's some permeability. They're still
interact. And so having a multi-grid approach and the ability to capture both the cores and the
fine-skills is so important in this application. And so that's just another application of
these methods. And yeah, it's been very exciting. We have now, whether forecasting, carbon capture
and storage, you know, modeling deformation in materials, you know, how much can I stretch
this material, right? How plastic it is is also a very non-linear phenomena. And we can, again,
show hundreds of thousands of times speed up over traditional solvers. We're able to
do modeling of lithography process. So how do I go from, right, a mask designed to? What is the
resist to make like what is finally being shown on the silicon wafer? And we also show the inverse
problem, which is really critical in many of these applications because you want to design a better
mask to be able to create the wafer of like desirable properties, right? So inverse problems are
especially hard with numerical methods because if you keep running this forward simulation,
which is very expensive. And but again, this is not data driven. So it's very hard to
make changes or explore the design space. But what we showed with our
neural operator-based methods is that we can progressively self-trainer improve. You know,
we can keep creating better masks and we can train on them. And with that, it can generate better
candidates. And so all of this, what you see with, you know, reinforcement learning or progressive
self-training, all these phenomena, in other general AI applications, we can bring all those tools
here as well. And marry it with neural operators because that gives the right foundation to capture
all the fine scales, which are very important in many of these scientific domains.
It sounds like the various applications you've described all involved kind of research efforts
to apply neural operators to a particular domain. You know, I imagine what you eventually want
is a tool that you take off the shelf and, you know, assuming you know your, you know,
underlying PDE models, you can more, you can readily apply this tool. Can you talk a little bit
about, you know, A, is that a fair characterization, and B, kind of, how do you think you get there?
Yeah, I mean, as all these efforts, right, in the beginning, it's been very important to work with
domain scientists, and that's been the goal of also the AI for Science Initiative when I found
it at Caltech. But now, it's even broader than just the Caltech community, right? We are working
with national labs, we are working with other universities, closely working, with also,
NVIDIA engineers who are enabling and helping scale up all these frameworks and open sourcing
it to the community. And I think that kind of building trust in the beginning is important,
because, you know, Sally Benson at Stanford is considered a leader in carbon capture and storage,
right? And we are collaborating with ECMWF, the European weather agency that, you know, you,
that, in fact, created the data sets for these, you know, historical weather. And so working with
them and asking, what are the metrics that matter here, right? You know, it's not just the short term,
what is the long term behavior? What are the uncertainties? And I think that aspect of the deep domain
expertise being married with AI and fully integrated is important. But you're perfectly right,
as we show that these proof of concepts are really solid, they've already, right, been making
impact in these domains. The next question remains, how do we generalize? You know, how do we create
foundation models for science and engineering? And yeah, and that's a mission that I'm undertaking
now. And I should say it's not straightforward, it's because one is we don't have the data,
like what we do for text or images, right? And even there, it required quite a bit of curation
effort. And here we need to think what that is. The other aspect we've been working really
well on is how to incorporate the right physics constraints. What are the meta-learning and other
approaches to generalize beyond one domain? And we've been seeing really good success. So I do think
it's a great time to scale up, but we need to bring all these pieces together. And that's what I
hope to do this year. Yeah, how different does the application to whether look relative to the
application to carving capture? Yeah, that's a great question. You know, there's some architectural
details that could be different. For instance, one of the newest architectures we are
are experimenting in the weather case involves spherical geometry, right? Because we know we want to
predict the weather on the surface of the earth that's a sphere. So by incorporating that
geometric information, how much better can you do, right? So, and that's always this balance
between, you know, knowing more about the domain incorporating the inductive bias versus
via a generalist model that may know less about it, but with more data could do well.
But the underlying concepts are still same. And I think there is a way to still capture the aspect
that, you know, the underlying, right, if you only look at say the turbulence, right, there is
similarity. But then on the carbon capture and storage, that interaction with water is very
important to model. Whereas in the weather, there's certainly water, we have the oceans,
but that's usually considered a longer timescale evolution compared to the shorter timescale,
wind surface wind and other variables. And so people conveniently kind of ignore some of the
phenomena or simplify it for different domains, which I think is very important for tractability.
But yeah, I do think that, you know, there is a broader range of phenomena that could be
captured through a common model. And it need not be a model that's learning everything all at once,
right? It could kind of provide the seed or initialization for other models to further hone in and
find you and on a very specific domain. When you're referring to your results with weather,
for example, and you have the significant speed up, is that operating under the same
sets of variables, or are you, is the model that you're referring to simplified relative to
the model that you're comparing against. And likewise, one of the big motivations here is the
ability to handle, you know, different resolutions. Are you, you know, when you are comparing those
models, are you looking at the same resolutions, different resolutions? Yeah, absolutely. First of all,
we're even not even currently taking all the information that's available in the historical data,
right, and all the variables. So, you know, in the beginning, when we started this project,
we wanted to do just a rough cut. We thought, okay, let's start with a sub sample of data and
a selection of variables just to see what we get. And we didn't expect it to be producing such
good results with even just that subset. And that's where I think, you know, there is a potential,
and we, you know, see evidence that we can even beat the current weather predictions by training
bigger models on all of the data available. And the weather is a great use case because
we have wealth of historical data available, you know, that's collected since the 1970s,
collected hourly, right, whereas these numerical weather models hardly use any of that data. So,
they're using it to just calibrate a few coefficients or parameters in their numerical methods.
And so, in the sense, they're redoing these computations again and again without having the
a wealth of data being understood and incorporated into the calculations. And I think that's where
the, you know, impressive speed up comes, right? One of the important reasons is because these
AI-based methods can learn from data and they can learn better ways to do these numerical iterations,
whereas the standard PDE solvers are forced to go to a very fine grid. As I said, we cannot ignore
the fine scale phenomena. So, they have to like for guarantees for convergence be operating at a
very fine grid and that makes them expensive. And so, our ability to learn from data better
nonlinear transformations where computations become quicker I think is a key to the speed up.
And regarding your question of, you know, can we predict at higher resolutions? So,
currently the data that's available we've trained on is 25 kilometers spatial resolution, right?
So, it's 25 kilometers proofed across the globe. And so, we are working with regional
weather agencies to see if we can get now, you know, we are in fact getting some of the higher
resolution data. And then we can ask, you know, how do the predictions look? And is there even
potential to further refine those? And I think that's why this kind of a foundation model
is valuable because you can go from being able to predict all across the globe to regional models
where especially countries that don't have a lot of computing capabilities or
technical abilities, right? Could start with a reasonably good model and hone in
on their region and refine in a much more cost effective manner rather than running these
numerical methods which are extremely expensive as you get to the fine grids.
So, just to give you an intuition of how expensive it gets as you refine the grid for these kind
of calculations, my colleague, Tapio Schneider here at Caltech Hours in Climate Sciences
estimates that you need about 100 billion times more computing than what we have today.
If we have to go to the actual finest resolution to be able to capture all these
turbulence in low-lying clouds, which for climate models is the biggest source of uncertainty.
And so that, you know, requires computing at the resolution of one meter.
You know, I'm talking 25 kilometers, right? We need to go all the way to one meter,
spatial resolution all across the globe and one second in time temporal resolution.
And so that's, you know, the more slow is no longer upon us and even all this
acceleration and scaling will not get us to 100 billion times, right? And even if they say,
oh, that's too much, what if we get somewhere intermediate? It's still too large and that's where
I think machine learning is a necessity, otherwise there's no way we can tackle these deepest
questions in scientific domains. With these models, you've referred to the relative speed up.
In the case of the weather, for example, in terms of performance, predictive performance,
how did they, this method compare to traditional numerical models?
Yeah, absolutely. In the case of the weather we are doing, as well as the current weather models
for as much as two weeks, which is considered where, right, it's very predictive. So after that
and a bit longer, you kind of get to the subsisinal and seasonal scales where it's no longer
predictable. So it becomes chaotic and, you know, you can kind of say, right, statistical measures
on average, what it would look like, but not the actual trajectory, the actual weather, what
it is because it's just not predictive. And that's another challenge too with many of these
models, right? So for short term, we can predict, but for the longer term, we can only simulate and
on average get to what's known as the invariant measure, which is the attractor or the right
distribution, right? Because you cannot predict exactly where the trajectory evolves. And we are
also working on now using these neural operators and we've shown their ability not only to capture
short term phenomena, but also the long term behavior by capturing the nature of chaotic
systems and hence, through that, be able to simulate them again effectively.
Do you characterize the failure or error of these models and like compare that to the weight
traditional error models fail, thinking about, you know, whether it's something that, you know,
we, there's kind of this inherent, you know, we joke about how bad weather models are, right? And,
and how, and how, you know, difficult it is to predict the weather, but then a lot of people
count on those predictions in very important ways, thinking about like if we, you know, start
predicting the weather in different ways and those predictions are, you know, generally better,
but occasionally much worse, like how does, how does, do we communicate that to the users of
the predictions? And I'm just curious, you know, how that, you know, factors into the way you think
about the problem, right? And that is a big challenge, right? Like as you said, you know, we need
the uncertainty quantification as well, you know, are we getting to the right, uh,
probabilities? So for instance, if we slightly perturb the initial condition, how does my prediction
change? And so that's an important notion of stability and, and, and also because we have some
uncertainty on our input, right? Like the, what we are measuring from our satellites and how
that is all assimilated has, uh, certainly errors, right? It has uncertainties. And so this kind
of what we call unsombling because you're not just feeding in one fixed initial condition,
but you perturb it and then you ask, even with those perturbations, what is the output now?
And through that, can I get a measure of the uncertainty or probabilities? And so we can also
calibrate our weather models, AI-based ones, um, similar and even better many times than the current
numerical weather models because we are much cheaper, right? So these numerical weather models
will be surprised to use only about 50 ensemble members. So what kind of statistical
averaging do we get out of 50, right? So 50 samples. And but that's so expensive. So, you know,
people are using large clusters even for one single prediction and takes a few hours.
So they are bound by the cost. And that's where this is another big benefit that we are seeing from
AI-based models because it is so cheap. You can now run thousands of ensemble members like we
are doing now. And we're carefully testing how does it do in all kinds of scenarios, right? We
show, for instance, it can nicely capture the uncertainty around hurricane evolution. So many
of the famous hurricanes that didn't appear in the training data, but we are testing them on,
you know, how not just like the single trajectory, right? Because people care about uncertainties.
And that has all kinds of downstream implications, you know, does hurricane hit Florida or go into
the ocean, right? That makes all the difference. And so being able to get to the right uncertainties
is such a big aspect. And that's where AI models are already proving to be superior. And by
honing in all that and giving the right ensemble level estimates very cheaply, I think will make
this so valuable. And that's what we are seeing now and working with weather scientists.
Now, all these applications that you've been talking about have traditionally been, we talked
about kind of the traditional numerical approaches. Those of all driven kind of the development of
high performance computing as a field. And I guess I'm curious what, you know, if you thought of
HPC as a, you know, a pie or whatever, like how much of that pie is, you know, being eaten up by
AI today and in time, you know, over time, does AI, you know, eat all of that pie or their elements,
are the things that we're doing with HPC that, you know, we don't think or you don't think will be
that are incompatible with AI in some way or does AI, you know, just come to be a standard tool
that apply to that type of problem. Yeah, no, that's a great question. I mean, so many now
national labs and other centers are rebranding us HPC AI, right, combination, which is great. And,
you know, that's been our experience too, like kind of to think of that as an integrated approach
to begin with, right? And that doesn't mean like keep the numerical methods as they are, keep an AI
tool as a standard hammer, you know, take something that works on natural images, bring it here,
right? That's not the, that to me is not a winning strategy. When I say hybrid HPC AI, it's really
thinking conceptually at an algorithmic level and say what does an integrated algorithm look like?
And that's how we came up with Fourier neural operator, right? So we know numerical methods
compute in the spectral domain that's efficient and that's also a nice way to create a basis that
works in any dimensions and any resolution because it is having the ability to learn in a function
space itself. So those, you know, thinking and that intuition, we don't need to reinvent from
scratch. We already have so much that's been dealt in numerical methods, right? On the other hand,
we know what's also the downside of numerical methods. They can't be data driven. So you can't
think that computation based on if it's an easier or a harder sample, right? And you can't use all
the existing computations you've done to learn and improve. And that's what AI provides. The other
is all these non-linear transformations, which is right also an effect of being data driven
that we have the ability to learn these non-linear transformations. So I think to me,
ultimately, they'll all come together. But I don't want to get into the debate of what was
numerical method, what was AI? You know, in that I worked like baby, you shouldn't be able to tell
them apart. That's kind of the whole point that they just seamlessly integrate together. That's
my hope and that's what we are working towards. Are there other ways that you see the
kind of advances around, you know, that are happening broadly in AI, kind of driving AI for
scientific applications? Yeah, as we've been talking quite a bit last year has been the
era of generative AI and foundation models, right? So these big models having the ability,
not just to do now one targeted task like we were doing for the past decade, but really be general
purpose. You know, they're not all the way, but if zero short, you can't get a good answer,
you could do few short, right? And you can give some examples. You could even fine tune.
And what we've been very excited is taking one step further and asking how we can use these
foundation models for decision making, you know, using with reinforcement learning,
limitation learning, all the tools, which are conceptually the right thing to adapt to new
environments and make decisions, but are very, very expensive, right? We really haven't broken
beyond standard game settings and still fairly low dimensional action space to one now that is
open world setting. And that's where I think there's been a lot of exciting work and one of the
works that we've provided as a benchmark to the community is called Mind Audio. So it's a suite of
thousands of tasks in Minecraft along with internet scale information about YouTube videos of how
people are playing Minecraft, how they're building structures, wiki, ready articles. So all kinds
of like text, image, tabular data, all the information that you can clean. And from that,
can you now solve not just one task, but thousands of tasks, right? So what we call as open-ended
task solving. And so, you know, if I give the instruction in text-based prompts and say go
minor diamond or go build me a castle, right? So it should figure out how to do it, but it's not
doing that from scratch, like what we saw in Alpha Go, right? Or Alpha Zero, rather we said either it's
some limited imitation data or it is from scratch, both of which are still way too expensive in these
kind of domains. And that's where I think Minecraft is different from other games because it's not
one goal, right? It's all about unleashing creativity and solving all kinds of new tasks coming up with
new structures. You can create a castle, you can create a flying dragon, all kinds of new structures.
But you still need to understand the environment and its complexity is huge. It's not one tool,
it's not killing somebody, it's not trying to negotiate and imitate what we saw in training data,
right? It is having to solve and learn something new. But all the information that's available as
foundation models through videos, through text will help us towards that goal. And that's
where I think that benchmark, you know, we got the outstanding paper awarded Nureps, which I'm
very proud of what the team did. Congrats on that. Thank you. But it also paves the way for the
community to take this as a new challenge, right? And this is in a way much, much harder than any of
the game playing bots we've seen solve. But at the same time is to me very timely and relevant
because all these foundation models are becoming so powerful. But it's challenging them beyond
their current capabilities, right? Because it's not just learning what they've already seen,
but pushing the envelope to create new worlds, new structures using all that knowledge.
And is it a formal challenge in the sense that there's a competition and a leaderboard and all that?
We have the website where all the information is available. We haven't launched a leaderboard
because this ultimate goal is very hard, right? So people are solving there is there was a deep
mind paper that's all only mining diamonds, for instance. And we are building to end our first
work showed that you can, you know, do solve multiple tasks by using what we call a mine clip,
meaning you look at Minecraft videos, you connect it with text. So you create a clip like model
and use that as a way to get dense rewards, right? And so you make progress towards the goal.
And that is just the first step. And so we are working on it. We have no others in the community
are. So as people start solving it, it'll be easy to create a leaderboard. So it's still a bit
you know, out of reach, I would say from what the community is capable. So that's why it's
the challenge for the next decade. Do you expect that the models that perform, you know, best in
here will be based on kind of these foundation models, language models, you know, in some way,
or is that still, you know, a way to open ended a question or I mean the foundation models are a
necessity to begin with, right? Because we are providing text instructions on what to do in Minecraft.
So you're describing the task in text. And it could be entirely new things that, right,
this agent hasn't seen before. And so you need to go to now the foundation models to understand
the text, but also understand what this image means, right? And go to the wiki and see,
oh, this is what a hammer is. Now, how do I go and pick up a hammer where do I find it?
So even to just get started, all this is necessary, right? And so that because we are not pre-programming
all of this, whereas if it's one fixed environment, you just give all this rules beforehand. You set
what the objective is. You design the reward function beforehand, right? So then you let reinforcement
learning do its magic, which can take very long and can be very challenging to do, but it's all
preset. Whereas in mind, Ojo, none of this is given beforehand. So to even get started, you need this,
but it's a great test for foundation models because what can you really learn from it? You know,
I give you everybody playing Minecraft before. You know, what can you lean from it, but still we
are asking for something new beyond that. You know, how well can you do problems solving? And I think
it's exciting to see how that develops. Awesome. Awesome. And I feel like there's a whole interview
just on on that topic. Absolutely. And in fact, with new reps, there was a workshop on foundation
models for decision making, and there's just so much excitement, because I think that'll provide
in my view the right starting point, the right initialization for some of really challenging
the reinforcement learning problems, because I would argue that reinforcement learning has shown,
you know, really fantastic gains, but in highly focused and limited domains, right? It hasn't
become the generalist agent like we see with, say, generative modeling, you know, you can sample
from distribution through diffusion models or GPT-like models very easily, but that's not task-oriented,
that's not, you know, learning online with the reward function. And so these two have to marry
together to bring that generality while being able to learn online, improve, adapt, and make better
decisions. Yeah. Well, clearly, I mean, three plus years is too long between our conversations,
because there's so much to cover. Certainly been an exciting time, and I'm privileged to have
a great team that is enabling me to, you know, think about such a wide range of problems. So that's
been very exciting. Awesome. Absolutely. Well, thanks so much for joining us and sharing a bit about
what you've been up to. Thanks a lot Sam. Well, it's been a pleasure and I hope you have a great
rest of 2023. Absolutely. You too. Thank you.