Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast where I interview interesting
people doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
This show you are about to hear as part of a series of shows recorded in San Francisco
at the Artificial Intelligence Conference, which was hosted by our friends at O'Reilly
in Intel Nirvana.
In addition to their support for the event itself, Intel Nirvana is also our sponsor for this
series of podcasts from the event.
A huge thanks to them for their continued support of this show.
Make sure you check out my interview with Navine Rao, VP and GM of Intel's AI products
group, and Scott Appland, director of Intel's developer network, which you can find at
Twimbleai.com slash talk slash 51.
At the AI conference, Intel Nirvana announced DevCloud, a cloud hosted hardware and software
platform for learning, sandboxing and accelerating the development of AI solutions.
The DevCloud will be available to 200,000 developers, researchers, academics and startups
via the Intel Nirvana AI Academy this month.
For more information on the DevCloud or the AI Academy, visit intelnervana.com slash
DevCloud.
My guess for this show is Paul Tepper, Worldwide Head of Cognitive Innovation and Product
Manager for Machine Learning and AI at Nuance Communications.
Paul gave a talk at the conference on critical factors in building successful AI-powered conversational
interfaces.
We covered this and a bunch of other topics like voice UI design, behavioral biometrics,
and other interesting things that Nuance has in the works.
And now on to the show.
Alright everyone, I am here at the AI conference in San Francisco and I'm with Paul Tepper,
who is the Worldwide Head of Cognitive Innovation and the Product Manager for AI and Machine
Learning at Nuance Communications, the Enterprise Division of Nuance Communications in particular.
I had the pleasure of meeting Paul at the AI conference in New York just a few months
ago and he was kind enough to volunteer to jump in the hot seat.
So welcome Paul.
Thank you.
Good to be here.
Absolutely.
So let's start by having you introduce yourself to the audience and talk a little bit about
your background and how you got into Machine Learning and AI.
Sure.
Well for about a year now I've worked at Nuance Communications with our Enterprise Division.
I lead a team that has a few functions.
One of our main functions is identifying high value problems for which the company doesn't
yet have a solution and working with our large corporate research division to see if we
have new forward looking research that could be sort of productized or prototyped to get
in front of customers as a way to kind of move innovation in product, give the product
manager and teams across the company new opportunities and things to look at there.
I did my PhD at Northwestern, my focus was on computational linguistics particularly
in dialogue.
It's had a lot of work on nonverbal behavior, gesture in particular and I also spent
a few years prior to Nuance working on a startup not around anymore, it was called
Citibon and we focused on building cloud-based NLP platform that really focused on human
and loop computing and crowdsourcing as a way to quickly build data sets out to build
custom models for NLP.
Okay.
I don't think I realized the Northwestern connection, I'm a PhD job out at it.
I was really impressed.
Yeah.
Engineering on my side were you engineering or?
I helped to found this program called the Technology and Social Behavior Program that
was a joint degree in computer science and communication studies of all things but that's
where we ended up in communication studies doing a lot of work at that time.
Okay.
That was super interesting.
Super interesting.
Do you miss Evanston?
I'm more of an East Coast guy.
I am an undergrad at Rutgers and I spent a year in Scotland and my master's out there
so I traveled around quite a bit but I'm definitely an East Coast guy.
Nice.
I think the folks will get a little bit more about what you're up to now if you maybe
spend a few minutes talking about nuance and what nuance is doing.
Yeah.
So nuance is a fairly large complicated company with about 14,000 employees and several
different divisions.
We have a division that focuses strictly on mobility, mobile products, automotive products.
We have ASR and a lot of cars that people drive due recognition for cars, the in-car systems.
We've got a healthcare division that is some of the top systems for dedication for doctors
to do electronic medical records and imaging division and my division in particular focuses
on enterprise communications and we have two main product areas or areas of focus and
that's one IVR systems or interactive voice response and that was one of the first commercial
applications of speech recognition systems that you can call into and instead of doing
kind of dial tone menus you can just say what you want conversationally and more recently
our focus has been on the digital side.
Now they're called chatbots but we've been calling them virtual systems for a long time
and actually there's a lot of overlap in those two technologies.
So a lot of the technology that has been built out for IVR so to recognize intent, to recognize
concepts and do entity extraction inside sentences and then also the dialogue build out the dialogue
flows with other graphs or trees to build through a dialogue.
A lot of that actually works similarly in the chat world.
However in the IVR world the utterances tend to be a lot shorter.
The chat world will tend to talk a lot longer so different complexities there.
That's an actually an active area of research for us so how do we use user experience?
How do we use UX to get people to talk longer in IVR so we have more because the natural
language understanding or NLU as we call it has really far outpaced what people actually
say today in IVR systems so that's an interesting technical challenge for us.
Yeah I think of when I think of IVR I think of call center and I think of the objective
on both the person that's interacting with the call center and the company that's making
it available is to keep the interaction as short as possible and it sounds like the
technology is allowing us to go the opposite direction.
I think the technical terms in the industry are things like containment so keeping the
user contained to the IVR as opposed to transferring to a live agent or using live agents
are more expensive and not just expense it's actually hard to staff them even if you
have all the resources in the world it's hard to hire up call centers that are big enough
for some companies to even handle attractive if they even wait on limited budget.
So containment's a big one and our one's first contact revolution is a popular KPI in
the industry so that you can have a you don't have to call back you know your resolves
within that first call so it's not always about short but it tends to be about can you
build self-service so being able to let the user call and interact with a system that they
can solve their problem automatically and I'll talk about that in my talk a little bit
about some of the statistics that have come out recently showing that today especially
with like younger generations and consumers people really don't care whether they're
talking to a machine or a human they just want to get their problem solved and in some
cases there's even times prefer it prefer to talk to a human you know sensitive situation
sorry prefer to talk to a bot maybe a sensitive situation you know you have to call in and
talk about you know I need a change of flight because of a death in the family or something
in some cases like that you don't it's sensitive and you don't actually want to talk to
a person even though people have this feeling that emotional intelligence is so important
sometimes it's actually you don't want to get into it you just want to get your transaction
done yeah yeah so you mentioned your talk what's the title of your talk I believe it's a long
title I think it's critical factors in conversational interfaces design and commercial interfaces
they don't know the whole thing memorized so kind of lessons learned in best practices that you've
come across along the way yeah it'll be a mix of lessons learned in best practices as well as
some of the newer things we've discovered and developed new ones okay so walk us through walk us
through those yeah sounds like a fascinating topic put me on the spot I don't think they have
them all memorized at the point I think I practiced your talk I've got about I think 10 at this point
that we're going to talk about yeah I think I had previously done a version this talk where I had
six and this talk that talk was 20 minutes so I thought okay 35 minutes I've got to beef it up a
little bit yeah well just expand upon some of the ones that I briefed three to one through so I
kind of go there's like a high level of things like context and personalization so if you're
on a website and you're browsing let's we deal a lot with like banks and insurance and those kind
of enterprises and you're in the auto insurance part of the website and a chat bot pops up and
says can I help you it actually you know that's the typical thing they're going to say right can I
help you but at this point in the website basic UX you know we'll let you know you should say
hi so and so hi Paul how can I help you with auto insurance those basic principles of UX have not
totally been carried over yet into chatbot world so it's those kind of things like building those
integrations into the systems it's the websites and stuff a lot of times these chat bots are
come from a different platform so you have to actually build those integrations between the
companies website and the chatbot and those kind of things basic UX but they're not totally there
yet in the chatbot world it's funny you you mentioned that I've been kind of on the dl evangelizing
this idea that that a lot of you know what we've learned so much about user experience design
in the web world and in mobile and kind of in these other interface technologies that hasn't really
made it into or we haven't formalized to the degree yet or in and around AI and artificially
intelligent user interfaces and I think the you know so I call it intelligent design but that's
kind of a worldwide term. I haven't come up with the ideal the the ideal replacement for that one
but as certainly you know chatbots are the kind of the tip of the spear so to speak but even devices
like your nest thermostat or something like that there's I think there are like unique things
that you need to take into account to you know make sure that users are comfortable with the
fact that this thing has some intelligence and also kind of signal to them how to interact with
the intelligence. That's interesting now nuance has been doing we call vui design for a long time
or voice user interface design and many of the people who design many of them backgrounds in
linguistics PhDs in linguistics even who design the flow of the conversation and we'll do you know
user testing AB testing etc to figure out what the rest flows are and you'll see these people
who the people with this experience are being scooped up now by google and amazon so you look
at the people now who google has a whole vui design team now for a assistant as is amazon a lot
of former nuance people because we've been doing this for a long time in the ivr world and it turns
out like a lot of those a lot of the basic principles of how a conversation works without a screen
transfer over to these note these kind of like iot devices and it's different when you have a screen
when the screen we actually know a lot about a lot about web design ux and that's another problem
right like there's this area of overlap between a non-like thinking of a venn diagram of like
conversational user interfaces on or voicers in a race to sign web user interface design and that
little spot in the middle of the overlap in the venn diagram where this weird world of okay well
the conversational principles aren't going to cover it completely the web principles are going
to cover completely so you have to kind of merge those two together and figure out things like
okay well on this part of the website the person's browsing you know looking at whatever product
the conversational agent needs to know about that stuff that's one of the things i'll be talking about
another thing is security making it easier for people to either authenticate via traditional
password or SSO as well as new ones as voicebound metric product so you can really transfer you over
to say like my voice is my password use a voice print to identify i don't get the sense that that's
very popular i haven't read it no no no it's it's really new cutting edge and it's it's it's
easier than mobile devices from the mobile devices where we're building virtual distance there
where the whole interface is spoken it's a little bit more you know part of the flow but we are
to vote prototype systems now or you can actually voice print if i or a bank on the web or
oh wow yeah that's a huge it's a huge friction point i think of the the places that that
recognize my number and based on my number you know associate me with a record like the airlines
for example have done a really good job of coming up to the speed on this in the past few years
but then there are other places where they're like okay type or say your password and i'm like well
you know it's like 26 characters and it's in my password safe thing or yeah there's no way
i'm either going to type it or say it yeah so and this is this is another it's a big area of
AI machine learning you know is these systems are all AI machine learning driven these voice
biometric systems are sitting there's also face print identification now we do some work there
and we'll start to see other kinds of biometrics too like behavioral biometrics i've heard of this
where the way a person interacts with a website the way they move their mouths this the cadence
at which they type etc that also creates a unique fingerprint of that person very very hard
to spoof fingerprint i think my first experience with that is with coursera like when you when
you're taking a coursera course like the andering you know deep learning course like you there's
an honor code and you have to type out this honor code thing that says that you know this is you and
when you're taking one of their exams you type this passage out again and it uses that to
verify that you're you i didn't see that i think if you don't if it doesn't think you're you
you have to take a picture with your webcam that's cool how okay that's really cool yeah so that's
that's another gets a reducing that friction point and i'll be spending a while talking about
some new techniques that we're using to try to incorporate unsupervised learning into our pipeline
now this is kind of a frontier area for a right now the majority of it's all supervised at this
point but we're looking at methods where you can take in a set of chat logs or voice conversation
transcripts and the big thing with chatbots and with conversational systems is the first layer is
the nlu the intent classification so what are the what's the intent of the burden of saying such
that then you can then you know respond to that intent whether it's like check my balance or pay
a bill or working on looking at data sets and extracting those intense automatically through unsupervised
learning he kind of double click on that and give a little bit more detail there yeah sure so
unsupervised methods one of the big things they tend to do is group things together automatically
yeah clustering or hierarchical clustering or various kinds of methods that bucket things together
so i can't give out all the secrets off there but that's part of it yeah that's part of it involves
that and part of it involves other steps that can actually identify what the intense are of those
cluster automatically so as a first pass this used to have to all be done manually our our
we call them speech scientists and also our data scientists would have to go through the data
to figure out what the intense were in a large data set as well as interviewing subject matter
experts out of company now is the first pass but today we've managed to cut down a process that
you know used to take hundreds of hours down to a few days months down to a few days by using
this new process that we call intent discovery whereby you can bucket the data and then automatically
identify what the intense are in the data then you can use those data use those that bucketing
to automatically label the data so you get a first pass at like a labeled data set and bootstrap a
model or train a model off of that put a model online now the idea here is that the system won't
necessarily have the same accuracy as it would with a hand tuned system so respecting a hand
to just be 85 90 percent accurate one of these bootstrap systems might be like 65 70 percent
accurate but then what we do is we put that system online and for all the questions that the
VA or the bot the vertus or the bot doesn't know we can pass off for one turn to we call it a hidden
agent a person a human in the loop they can then check what the intent was for that and send it
back to the system so the user ends up with this seamless experience of they're just talking to a
bot would be with like a five second delay when it goes to the person or 10 second delay where it says
hold on I'm checking with you know checking with one of my partners then we can use that data then
train in the future and then we won't have to have that you know that missing data that loop in the
future that makes sense no it makes it makes a ton of sense it I'm wondering does this
create a new business model for nuance where we're in previously I'd imagine you're you selling an
enterprise some set of technology whereas now it's you know the technology but also the service
like are you providing the agents yeah that does this or are the you providing a you know a console
that they can have their own virtual agents doing the checking yeah or both so yeah a few years
ago about here two years ago we acquired a company called touch commerce which is a live chat
platform they provide a whole suite of live chat they also they can provide the agents to you
or they can just provide the interface to you so we have that which is really cool too because now we
can if a VA doesn't know if a virtual system doesn't know the answer or chat button doesn't know
the answer we can we could if a company wants to partner with us transfer that way transferred
directly to our live chat but we also talk work with lots of companies who have their own live chat
platforms a big one in Salesforce they provide live chats with really popular one of these days
transfer to those agents we have a console we can provide to allow companies to have this to use
their own pool of live agents to do this human assisted step or we can provide the software and
the agents we've all different ways of working on it it's very you know we can customize and
all different ways with that not to be too salesy here but you know we have all different ways
of working on it and yeah it is it is a new it is kind of a new line of business the new way of
thinking about it okay all right what else oh targeting that's another big area so when do you
have a chat window actually pop up you know I think based on the way it's implemented now always
always right yeah and it seems like and when I use these systems I it just seems like no rhyme or
reason for I feel like a lot of times these systems it's just a clock or something right and like
if you've been on the page longer than 30 seconds it pops up or if you're visiting the site on your
mobile phone do it you know immediately secure everything else yeah see there's the UX that
she's totally worked out yeah we we have a targeting engine that's constantly undergoing new
prototypes and stuff but that's aimed at like when are you interact with the user how do you
interact with the user in what way what language do you use what even down to like the colors and
stuff on the interface and that targeting engine is based on all kinds of things like how long
has the user been on the page is certainly one of them but what what have they put in their shopping
car like they put something in their shopping cart and walked away so there's all these different
inputs to the system that you can use to then tune when you're going to pop up that you know pop
up that chatbot to ask if they want to talk to an agent or talk to Nina's the name of our
registers talk to Nina talk to a chatbot and assuming it's machine learning driving that ultimate
target decision how transferable are the models from one customer one one one website to another
like are you training these models on a customer by customer basis or is there you know you have
industry models or is there a generic model that outperforms just show the chat bottle yeah so
there we do have generic sit generic setups you know for various verticals but when it comes
down to a lot of this is this is a very difficult subject right now these days for us because a lot
of our customers really feel very shown that they don't want the data share they don't even want
the models shared you know so it's a new it's it's a it's even for when their chatbot pops up on
their website anything it's a it's a it's a very tricky area that I think that our company I think
a lot of companies today are having to deal with which is like how do you both be a competitive AI
machine learning company while at the same time protecting the data of your customers in a way
that they're comfortable and they can that like dealing with all the kind of compliance issues
too because a lot of our customers are banks so it may even be that legally you can you know unless
there's actually a specific consent for example we deal with a government agency in Australia and
they I was reading one of their one of their privacy policy documents on our day and I was
saying like unless you have explicit consent from a user like a pilot says I consent to use this
or you sign some checkbox or something they can't use that data for anything else tuning a model
even you know so this is really I think we talked about all you know all the exciting stuff in AI
today and all the amazing things that are happening when it comes down to for a lot of businesses
these are the real problems today it's not how do I scale a deep learning model or how do I
productionize this system and get it working on you know going from one cluster to a thousand
computers or whatever it's like the legal problems how do you actually deal with the data in a way
that's safe for the company and for the user you know it's really like a huge somewhere you know
right yeah I was just reading I forget what I think it was I think it was a particle in someone
in his newsletter or something like that that was talking about how there's this huge gray area
around copyright and data sets and you know basically everyone who's using for the most part
these public data sets is kind of flying under the radar but there's this you know potential exposure
where there's no established you know precedent around you know the extent to which copyright on
a data set flows into the model for example and so potentially someone using this copyright
data set to train the model could be creating a model that's you know has potentially owned or
has some copyright liability with someone else so that's an example of this kind of meta concern
that that your customers are thinking about do you have any perspectives on the you know the rise
of the consumer voice interface devices the virtual assistance your Alexa's and your Google
assistance and things like that yeah it's interesting I think a lot of that stuff it has to do with
their APIs you know with those kind of systems we right now we have our our chat box integrates
with like Alexa integrates with Google Home but there's certain things we can't do there's certain
things we can't do so one thing we would really like to do a lot of our customers like a center
banks right and with thanks this voice biometrics has become very popular recently but one thing we
can't do right now is voice biometrics over Google and Alexa because they only send you text
so at this point there they don't actually send you the audio signal they do all the ASR for you
speech recognition and the TTS for you the text to speech and they have no way of sending out
those signals so I think this is something that we've had huge strides in terms of the openness
and the compatibility of these platforms with Alexa and now with Google Home but for years this was
a big problem with Siri right with Apple if they had no ability to do 30 third party integration
you couldn't say to Siri like you know play a song on Spotify for me so this is this is definitely
like a big topic for new ones right now this idea of we call it cognitive arbitration where you have
agents that sit like kind of Uber agents that sit in the middle of all these different IOT systems
and coordinate those for you and bring that data together bring the systems together
and those APIs together to talk to these different systems I know this is also a vision of Amazon's
as well with being able to sit and like have their agent that has goes out and there's always
different skills that they come to so this is kind of this is a newer topic for for new ones
that are working on more recently is how you can use intelligence and reasoning and other kinds
of machine learning to build agents that can sit in between all these different IOT devices and talk
each other and do you see is there a role or any emergence of like standards or standardized
approaches like for example you know there's tons of work that's been done around federated
identity in the web and now this is you're introducing a whole other layer around biometrics
does any of that kind of work transfer here do you think or we just like to or no no I think it will
I think that this is word in very early days here so it's basically like I don't think the very
beginning of the internet when these kind of standards were being built out you know like what's
HTML and how does it work that's where we are today with AI so these issues the thing like you
brought up with the data that those kind of issues haven't been solved yet like how do you there's
no you know a patchy license for data at this point you know whereas that stuff you know to season
software engineers and product managers now it's just kind of like second language they know
with the with the licenses mean they know which what they can reuse which code can be leverage
which can't what you had to declare what you don't etc but that stuff doesn't exist for data
but it's an interesting point you know I hadn't thought about it but yeah I think that that'll
come about and similarly with with these standards around interoperability I think that's
something that we have teams at nuance we're working on and trying to kind of reach out to
different partners because this is not a problem that's going to be solved by any particular
company just in the same way that like you know JSON standards can't be solved by Google
you know they can't just make a really great JSON parse on everybody take it and put it in
their browsers or put in their systems it has to be you know standards based and community based
so I think we are we are thinking about these kind of interoperability standards at this point
very early days though right any other things that you covered in your talk that you want to
share with us yeah I covered most of it yeah there's a couple of things like in the front
matter of the cover of the talk that I was talking about which is that in this world of chatbots
and virtual assistants it's surprising about how much of it isn't AI and isn't machine learning
and we really there's a lot of companies will have like you know a dot AI in their name
but everything is still like based on regular expressions and rules and that sort of stuff
so or people or people yeah or people big time that's that's not always necessarily a bad thing
but it's it's often part of the company's strategy in terms of you know having everything
the beginning be run by humans as a way to gather data and then over time learn from it
but that's something we try to help educate our customers about is how much of this actually
is AI and machine learning and how much of it isn't today most of the AI and machine learning
for us happens on the language understanding side of things so when the input comes in
we can be able to categorize it using statistical models and LP models in order to route
to the right response you know to give you the right response to a question we can also do
things like energy extraction extractor concepts of you're saying something like you know I'd
like to order a pizza or I'd like to order a large pizza a large vegetarian pizza with pepper
peppers and onions almost at pepperoni be able to identify both that the intent was to order a
large pizza that the toppings and the size and that sort of stuff a lot those categories that
kind of technology now some of that stuff is standard but there's still quite a few you know
different platforms out there for doing chatbites that don't offer that kind of you know that
level of a machine learning and LP but beyond that played with that stuff in the past like api.ai
it's a very manual and tedious process to build out those those entity trees exactly yeah and so
you're it sounds like what you're describing is a way to learn some of that from the after data
itself yeah exactly so that when it comes to when it comes to our intent discovery and bootstrapping
process we're learning the intense automatically and building out kind of you could call it an
ontology the the group of the intense than the various concepts that are associated with those
intents but yeah we try to just like encourage people to be discerning and try to figure these things
out when you're looking at a platform today I think the next frontier is going to be
on the other side though there really isn't any system on the market today including ours
that can automatically learn how to answer the questions especially if they're complicated
back and forth dialogues so if it requires like a back and forth conversation those tend to be
you know built out manually either as an enterprise in the enterprise you know by talking to
subject matter experts or people are doing it themselves by figuring it out themselves that way
that I think is different is the next frontier for this technology is learning how to answer questions
and dialogue and a lot of now there are tons of people who say they can do that yeah there are a lot
of there's what they tend to do though is you have to feed the system question answer pairs
then it can learn to map new questions to those answers right this question answering
but it's not dialogue that's if something exists sort of an FAQ can you identify if the question
takes a different format though that it actually mapped to this question that's in the FAQ that's
about a format I mean it could not be an FAQ it might be like a list of a thousand questions and
answer pairs or whatever but I mean cutting edge research today I don't know if you remember
with like the Stanford squad data set that Q&A data set where it's trying to answer questions
off Wikipedia articles this is pretty cutting edge research at this point there's research teams
across the world competing in this kind of thing but even that still is focused on you know the answer
is in the article you know we're talking the kind of stuff nuanced is working on today that is
one thing I forgot to mention we've got a product a project we're working on now called mean
and knowledge where you can basically push a button to ingest a website or a set of documents
then start doing question answering on it yeah and it it does leverage from the technology that's
being used to answer like those to work with that squad data set but it also leverages technology
from information retrieval search so it combines a few different areas machine learning as well
as NLP and question answering so that and I like to think of this as low hanging fruit really
because these kinds of questions that you actually have just a one shot answer to those are the
candidates for automation today the things that we still really are still very early days in the
research in is how do you actually learn a back and forth conversation that requires multiple
questions and feedback going through a conversation with somebody from data I think it's the next
frontier in the case of this of Nina knowledge so what degree is it you're doing like transfer
learning off of a model trained on squad and applying that model to the website that's being
ingested or is this process including like training up a new model on that website yeah the
process is yeah certainly we start from scratch you know on each one each time we haven't we
haven't gotten transferred learning like that into production yet today but those are certainly
areas of research are working on is so one area where I don't know if I don't know if you'd
call it transfer learning or not but you can certainly do things like learn word vectors you know
from one data set and apply to another that's that is certainly like a form of transfer learning
most people think about transfer learning I think today they're thinking okay I built this big
multi-layer neural network and I'm extracting a piece of it and then using it on another data set
I think it's still early days for that sort of stuff but certainly when it comes to word vectors
or other kinds of vectors paragraph vectors document vectors etc that stuff can be transferred
and it can be very helpful in improving the quality of a model pretty quickly where are we in terms
of you know we've talked a lot about identifying the intent of you know an utterance or something
that's typed into a chatbot but where are we in terms of you know more you may be more realistic
kind of dialogues that have multiple intents or hidden intents or you know things like that you know
and this is maybe a slightly different direction for the question but you know for a while we've
talked about the IVR systems being able to identify the emotion and you know change or escalate
the way the call is handled based on the emotion you know when I'm frustrated I try to make sure
the IVR knows I'm frustrated and it never makes a difference I really love this question particularly
the emotion part of it I really love that question because we've been working on it a lot lately
yeah of what do you do with taxid sentiment right so that's basically tends to be in the
seminar although there are some models now that classify things into like the five base emotions
like anger happiness frustration says is like these you know old models of this there are some
models that claim to be able to do that I don't know how accurate they are but sentiment that's
at least one that you were pretty accurate we can get pretty accurate on that for the most part at
the global sentiment of a sentence that doesn't always sufficient because there can often be two
sentiments in a sentence you know I love this but I hate this what I do there so I'm getting off
on a tangent but the reason I think this is really fascinating is because the real question is okay
great so what do you do with what do you do when you know someone's pissed off what do you do when
you know someone's frustrated and that's a really hard question because it tends to be what a
company what a customer wants to do is figure out a way it's about containment right so how do we
handle this without escalating to a person because that's going to a person's expensive but
when you have a frustrated person the only thing we know how to do to know with the only thing
we tend to do today is escalate to a person so I think what it's going to come down to is understanding
that they're these aren't black and white things that there's just like we have no confidence
scores and probabilistic models that give you a gradient of how sort of of confidence and say you
know a right answer there's gonna be a gradient in terms of like sentiment so if a person is saying
something like you know I'm having trouble with this then you might be able to say oh okay I'm
sorry you're having trouble with this I really you know wish you were doing a better job there but
you know can I offer you this you know tool this troubleshooting step you know this troubleshooting
dialogue where as a person is really upset then yeah you probably just want to say maybe you want
to offer them at least to say would you like me to have a technical support person contact you
directly you can just like hold on and we'll call you or do you want to proceed with our you know
troubleshooting online yeah so I think although we still aren't there 100% with recognizing these
things the question like what do you do with it once you have recognized it might be even a
harder problem to deal with you know because great we can get like we end up with 100% 99%
accuracy of knowing when some how angry someone is but how do you what how does that help you what
your customer does not want to escalate all of those two you know they're most senior rap or
or exactly right so how do you handle it what do you do with it for an enterprise like how do you
actually use that data in a way that's interesting and again this doesn't actually come down to
an AI problem it comes down to like a user experience problem or design problem yeah I wonder if
there's like you know companies all over of Glondon to net promoter scores a way to measure
customer satisfaction but I wonder if there's like a net IVR anger scores yeah you you guys should
do that yeah yeah this our customers ask about this stuff a lot so it's really it's on the
the front of people's minds but you do to the when you go down that dialogue when you go down
that path it's you know okay so then what yeah awesome football thank you so much for taking the
time to sit down with me I'm looking forward to catching pieces of your talk and how you know
their ways that folks can kind of find out about your research or connect you on Twitter or
anything like that yeah my Twitter handle is my name with the first initials switch so okay
it's all pepper to you well pepper on Twitter that's probably the best way to get at me these days
okay nice nice well good luck with your talk tomorrow thank you thanks
all right everyone that's our show for today thanks so much for listening and of course
for your ongoing feedback and support for more information on Paul and any of the other topics
covered in this episode head on over to twomlai.com slash talk slash 52 for the rest of the series
head over to twomlai.com slash a i s f 2017 and please please please send us any questions or
comments that you may have for us or our guests via Twitter at twomlai or at sam charrington or leave
a comment on the show notes page there are a ton of great conferences coming up through the end
of the year to stay up to date on which events will be attending and hopefully to meet us there
check out our new events page at twomlai.com slash events twimlai.com slash events thanks again for
listening and catch you next time