Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast where I interview interesting
people doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
This show you are about to hear as part of a series of shows recorded in San Francisco
at the Artificial Intelligence Conference, which was hosted by our friends at O'Reilly
in Intel Nirvana.
In addition to their support for the event itself, Intel Nirvana is also our sponsor for this
series of podcasts from the event.
A huge thanks to them for their continued support of this show.
Make sure you check out my interview with Navine Rao, VP and GM of Intel's AI products
group, and Scott Appland, director of Intel's developer network, which you can find at
twimbleai.com slash talk slash 51.
At the AI conference, Intel Nirvana announced DevCloud, a cloud hosted hardware and software
platform for learning, sandboxing and accelerating the development of AI solutions.
The DevCloud will be available to 200,000 developers, researchers, academics and startups
via the Intel Nirvana AI Academy this month.
For more information on the DevCloud or the AI Academy, visit intelnervana.com slash
DevCloud.
In this episode, I talk with Ian Stoika, professor of computer science and director of the
RISE lab at UC Berkeley.
Ian joined us after he gave his talk, building reinforcement learning applications with Ray.
We dive into Ray, a new distributed computing platform for RL, as well as RL generally,
along with some of the other projects the RISE lab is working on, like Clipper and Tigra.
This was a pretty interesting talk.
Enjoy.
Alright everyone, I'm here at the AI conference, presented by O'Reilly and Intel Nirvana,
and I've got the pleasure of being seated with Ian Stoika.
Ian is the executive chairman and co-founder of Databricks, and also a professor
at Berkeley and director of the RISE lab.
Ian, welcome to this weekend machine learning in AI.
Thank you.
Thanks for having me.
Absolutely.
So why don't we get started by having you tell us a little bit about your background,
how you got interested in machine learning and what your area of research interest is?
I joined Berkeley in 2001, and at that time I was actually doing networking, and then
I moved around and did a little bit of peer-to-peer systems, and then started working on big
data.
On big data, in the context of another lab at Berkeley called Amplab, we developed a few
systems, including Apache Spark, Apache Mesos, and Alusio, formerly known as Stachion.
Basically, what happens is that we develop these systems because people get more and
more data and organizations ingest more and more data, and then once they have the data
whether it's user logs, machine logs, or any other data, they try to make sense of this
data.
They get to try to get some insights.
So Apache Spark was an effort to process large scales this kind of data.
Now also in the context of the Apache Spark, you look at what people do after they get
some insights of the data, they want to make some decisions to take some actions based
on the data, to improve our targeting, to do medical diagnosis, and things like that.
So now the next step again in getting value out of the data is basically applying AI, machine
learning to get intelligent, actionable decisions.
That's why I am now doing that research in the context of systems and machine learning
and AI.
And as part of that, we just started this new lab at Berkeley called Rise, where Rise stands
for real-time intelligence and secure execution, and this lab is about building systems
and tools and algorithms to support applications which make real-time decisions on live data with
strong security.
Okay.
And in fact, that's one of the areas that Spark really distinguished itself in that real-time,
streaming, interactive decision-making, at least relative to Hadoop, which was kind
of the incumbent system at the time.
Yes.
Definitely.
So the truth, Spark was compared with, at that time, when we created it, compared with
MapReduce, provide great support for interactive queries, iterative computation like machine learning
algorithms, and later for streaming.
So right now, going forward, one big angle we are focusing on is security.
So everyone wants to take and to make personalized decisions.
Right.
So the question here, how can you make personalized decisions without violating the confidentiality
of the users, while preserving the confidentiality of the users?
Okay.
So this is one big challenge.
The other aspect is about, for instance, when you create this, with Spark, you create
these models using deep learning or many other approaches, machine learning approaches,
but this model eventually, you are going to serve that model.
Right?
So the users, you know, when the users contact you, the user make a query, look at the recommendation,
you get, you give back the inference part, it's a inference part, it's a give back right
answer.
So another direction is focusing on building this kind of prediction serving or model serving
systems.
And another direction is that, you know, when you look at the new generation of this machine
learning applications, like for round-dream enforcement learning, they have different patterns.
They do a lot of very small simulations, and you know, we build also systems for that,
which are a better fit for this kind of very fine-grained computations.
Okay.
And here at the conference, you were talking about Ray, which is one of the systems that
you built.
I was talking about Ray, which is in this category.
So think about Ray, is the ability to execute a lot of fine-grained tasks, which are dynamically
connected, dynamically depend from each other, like tasks of milliseconds, takes only milliseconds.
So you can be, you can run millions of this task per second, so it's very fine-grained.
And each of these tasks can be simulation, like simulations you play a game, right?
You move, you know, simulate the moves of the pieces, and then you see whether you own
or you lost, right?
And one of the workloads is reinforcement learning, which reinforcement learning, you can see
something like a generalization of supervised learning in which the labels of the action
you make is sparse, as sparse, not every action has a label, it's good or bad.
Like for instance, when you play a game, when you make a move, you don't necessarily know
whether this move is great.
You need to wait until the end of the game, maybe to see whether it's good or bad.
Also the feedback is delayed, right?
In supervised learning, in many times you know whether I show you some picture and you
give me, say, this is a cat or a dog, I know instantly whether it's good or bad.
And also it's about reinforcement learning, it's also assumed that you interact with
the environment continuously and you change the environment, right?
Like with, again, with playing games, self-driving cars or dialogue systems, right?
This is a dialogue, right, and you need to, it's continuously interacting and building
the context about our conversations and based your next actions, you know, next answers
and questions based on this context, right?
So that's basically, it is, and this reinforcement learning in many, one of the workload characteristics
all requires to handle this very small fine grain simulation.
Okay, so, yeah, we've actually talked about reinforcement learning on the podcast quite
a bit.
We've had Peter Avil and Sergei B.
Yeah, yeah.
That is an expert, I'm not sure how they cannot do that.
Well, you know, so what the question that comes up for me is, how does Ray compare to an
environment like OpenAI Gym or OpenAI Universe that are used also in context of reinforcement
learning?
It's very complementar, the OpenAI Gym and they provide you with virtual worlds, right,
and so forth, the simulators, the Ray which provides you with a plumbing to execute those
simulations and to get the results and to update the policies that is mapping between
the state of the environment or the observation of the environment and the action you are
going to take at large scale.
So, is it too simple to say that Ray is like a dupe for reinforcement learning, it sounds
like you've got a bunch of tasks or you're less than about a cluster and then mapping
the results back?
Yeah, you can say that in the first approximation and then you take the results and you update
the policy.
Right, right.
And then you repeat until the policy, you're happy with the policy, the policy converges.
So, you mentioned this attribution problem, right, you're playing this game, you've got
this reinforcement, this learner that's involved in this environment, a game, for example.
And you can't really know whether it's action, you know, is positive or negative until
much later on.
If you don't know the ultimate benefit, how do then do you gain any knowledge from these
micro simulations that you've been describing?
Yeah, because a simulation each game, it's, you take some actions after each action, you
have a state which is a modified state of the environment and eventually you have a reward.
With sometimes you do not know whether the reward can be zero, you don't know it's good
or bad, right?
Right.
And after you take, according to the current policy, you are going, which again, you fill
the state, takes the action, you get the next state and the reward, you feed again the
policy, you get the next action and so forth.
So, you get these trajectories, which is a succession of states and rewards.
So, now, eventually at the end, you are going to see whether you achieve your task or
not, whether you want the game or you lost the game.
If it's a robot, whether the task say you're moving on objects or a successful or not,
right, or solving a puzzle, right?
So then, once at the end, you, for instance, see that eventually see whether you're successful
or not, then if you are successful at a very high level, you are going to go back and
reinforce all these actions you've taken, meaning, reinforcing, meaning that next time
when you try, after you update the policy, it's a higher chance to take these actions.
If the actions led you to say, losing a game, then you are going to weaken these actions.
You make them less likely to be taken when you are in a similar situation.
That's basically what it is.
It's like humans, right?
It's like you play a game and so forth, and if you own, it's likely that you are going
to repeat some of the kind of moves you might.
If I'm playing Tik Tok To, the opening move is always in the middle.
That's very true.
I imagine a big part of what it's, or at least one part of what it's trying to do is,
and this is also, in a lot of ways, a dupe-like, is managing the state because you're shuffling
state for all of these little simulations that you're running all the time.
Human is a state as well.
There is an object store, so you keep that state in the object store, so tasks which run
on different nodes can have access to the state.
You also try to provide full tolerance if the node fails, so you make sure that the
computation still is going to make progress and doing that correctly.
These are some of the issues you need to deal with.
You were presenting on RAY specifically, so maybe what were some of the main points that
you wanted to lead with the attendees that you're talking?
Yes.
I think the high level point is that right now, over the past 10 years, there has been
a tremendous progress in AI, right?
Many great applications.
Right now, as we look forward, the application becomes more and more sophisticated.
While most of the applications we develop so far were based on supervised or unsupervised
learning, the new applications, we believe, they are going to be more and more
based on reinforcement learning, and again, the reason is that the new applications are
more about interacting with the environment, around them, learning from this interaction
and affecting the environment.
We talk about games, we talk about dialogue systems, but you can look, think about the
health applications.
You know, they're constantly monitoring you and then give you health services.
How about the next level of detail, so you talk about the experience of using RAY or
architecture?
Yes.
So basically, that's what I've started, but it's again, like you said, you know, for instance,
if you do not have a feedback after each action, after each move, that means that the space
you need to explore in terms of solution space is larger because I need to make a series
of moves because I know it's good or bad, right?
So more possibilities to go wrong, right?
So that's one of the characteristics.
The computation requirements are increasing, and that's why one way, if you cannot for simulations,
that's a very good way to do because you can do the simulation fast.
So now, like for instance, playing games or things like that, you do a lot of simulations,
right?
Even with robots, you try to simulate the physical world, right?
Because you can learn much faster, right?
So that's the key.
So the key is basically, then, the computation pattern is basically saying, I have a policy,
I'm going to evaluate the policy by running many simulations, right?
And I'm going to feed in their outputs, these trajectories, right, what happened, and update
the policy, and run again, right?
So that's kind of, it's a pretty regular computation because different simulations they can take
different amounts of time, like for instance, if you play a game of chess, I can lose in
three moves, or it may take 60 moves to win, right?
And you want to learn as soon as some of this simulation happen, you want to learn from
them and update the policies.
You don't want to, you know, if I run 100,000 simulations, evaluate the policy, I don't
want to wait for all of them, right?
So this is kind of a computation is more irregular.
Also, the other thing is that, you know, many of these policies are implemented by neural
networks, neural networks, which run on GPUs.
So you want also to support more heterogeneous hardware, and also the kind of patterns, you
are talking only about simulations, but then you want to search to be able to search the
space, the solution space, and things like that.
So you end up basically with a very fine grain computation graph, you want to execute on heterogeneous
hardware.
So that's what raised.
So how it's really achieving that, it's using this in memory object store to share the
data.
So it's very fast on a single machine, you share memory.
On the back end is a scheduling, where it totally distributes a scheduler.
Each note can schedule locally, and then when it's overloaded or the inputs of the task
are not available locally, it's only then it's going to contact a global scheduler.
We also replicate the global scheduler, so we do a lot of these kind of things to try
to scale and to have very high throughput.
And finally, we also provide the bindings in Python.
Why Python?
Because most of the AI community develops in Python, and now it seems to be the most popular
language.
Right.
Where Spark is Java and Scala, and also has binding, it was developed in Scala, so obviously
has API in Scala, but also has in Java and Python.
And Python actually is very popular API and of course SQL.
I guess early on I had the impression that some of those early efforts with Python were
kind of like second-class citizens, has it evolved to be more?
We're not evolving.
I think that a very large percentage of users use Python, so they're improving fast.
So where is Ray on the maturity cycle?
You know, it's still an early project.
We had a first release a few months ago, we are going to have soon the second release,
but it's still early, so we have just a few users.
But we believe that going forward, this reinforcement learning will play a major role in the future
of AI, and I think that the usage adoption of Ray will grow as well.
What size environments have you tested?
Oh, we tested these over hundreds of nodes, so we are at that level now.
But it's again, maturity is not only about how scalable it is, there are vastness, and
there's a kind of features you need, monitoring, and things like that, you need really to have
to deploy something like Ray in production.
Does Ray lend itself to being deployed in cloud environments?
No.
You can deploy equally like Spark and many others, you can deploy in the cloud or you can
deploy on-prem.
Okay.
Does it work with Spark in any particular way?
Of course, of course.
What are the uses there?
I mentioned about this object store, so actually for the object store, you use Apache
Arrow.
So it's easy to Apache Arrow to exchange the data between Spark and Ray.
So Ray has a much lower level API, it's again, it's targeted for this particular reinforcement
learning and distribute AI applications.
Well Spark has a higher level and it's in general, it's very, very mature API, very easy
to use when it comes to processing big amounts of data.
And thinking about that API, what's the kind of fundamental unit of work, or the unit
of work is a task.
A task, so you can add a decorator on a task and basically that task will be your Android
module.
Okay.
Moving from a task to reinforcement learner is all of that in user code or it is Ray provide
any abstractions for reinforcement learning in particular.
For reinforcement learning, right now, we are in the next release, we are going to add
a new library of reinforcement learning algorithms.
Okay.
It will be a small library as the beginning, but we are going to implement, it's going
to offer the implementation of some of the most common reinforcement learning algorithms
and we'll take it from there.
Okay.
And so you will be able to kind of use that with the same decorator model, you decorate
your task and then it will be, yeah, it will be some function calls, right?
So it will be an idea.
Okay.
Great.
Based on your experience with Spark, how do you see Ray evolving?
So you know, it's very hard to predict, right?
I mean, when we start this Spark, we never thought that he's going to become so popular
and it depends a lot of things.
So for us, for now is that we want to build as with Ray, we want to build a platform which
allows us to speed up the research and the application in reinforcement learning.
So that's our first goal.
And it's again, we are talking about only us at Berkeley, but obviously across the board,
you know, it's academia and industry.
So that's kind of, you know, our goal.
So your focus is on making a tool that helps accelerate research and if, you know, the
Spark-like success comes and the Spark-like success comes, but, you know, your focus
on the kind of the user problem is excellent, excellent.
Are there any companies offering like commercial support for Ray?
No, not yet.
So early for that.
There are some companies that are playing with it, but yeah, it's like I mentioned, in order
for someone to put in production, it still has a little bit to go.
Okay.
You know, we are moving fast.
It will take a bit of time.
Yeah.
So you mentioned some other projects around security and other things.
The projects all kind of tie together, like, can you think of like the Ryze Lab is creating
this platform and the security thing, talks to Ray, talks to the next thing, or are they
more or less?
So there are a bunch of projects.
I was actually surprised, like, you know, considering Ryze's relatively new lab, there
were a huge number of projects on the website.
Yes.
We have quite a few people.
Quite a few students.
But it did start on this year, generally, officially at least.
So we have a few other projects.
Actually, there are some projects also, like you mentioned, you know, in the Spark-wise
also about real-time and so forth, streaming.
We have a few projects in the context of Spark.
One is about accelerating and reducing the latency of streaming, called Rizl.
And actually, there is a talk later today from Intel, which we collaborate with this platform
big deal, which is experimenting with Rizl and they are going to present some results
today.
And then there is another project called Tegra, it's about how to process time-evolving
graphs.
So you know that Spark also has graphics, which is in graph frames, which are some libraries
to provide graph processing.
So Tegra takes that at the next level and basically saying that most of the systems today
are processing static graphs.
So you want to process the graphs as they change.
And also, you want to be able to ask questions about past instances of the same graph.
So what are your friends, you know, January 15th this year, right?
And how are these friends changing over the former spirit, right, who are the new friends
you got, who are the friends, you know, like, so this is the kind of questions you want
to answer.
The Tegra project tried to answer.
On the security side, I would say it's one project called opaque.
So opaque, it actually, it's again, it's like taking Spark SQL and making it more secure.
What do I mean by that?
You know, today there are solutions, you encrypt the data address, maybe in motion, but
still they do not defend, for instance, if the operating system or other applications
are compromised, right?
So opaque uses, you know, new developments of hardware enclaves, which now is used by
many companies, right?
Also Apple is their Morrison announcement for this cheap, bionic chip right on the iPhone
to run their neural network.
But these enclaves basically defend the application, the code you run within the enclave, even
if the operating system high-pipervisor are compromised.
So basically we try, so zero, opaque is about providing Spark SQL, taking Spark SQL and
providing Spark SQL functionality, but now it's secured against this kind of very strong
attacks.
By running in a hardware enclave, running part of it, like the operators running the hardware
in place.
Okay.
Oh well.
So, and the last one, maybe I want to, well, there are two and one.
I want to mention one is Clipper, this is about prediction service, so there we develop
this very modular architecture, so you can serve models which are developed with very different
systems.
Like, you know, of course, Spark, it will be actually probably the first prediction serving
system which will provide native support for Spark models and develop in others, in many
other frameworks like TensorFlow and others.
So that's all that Clipper and the last one I want to mention is ground.
So ground, it's about managing the metadata.
This is one of very important problems, right?
You have data which is generated and modified, you know, think about an enterprise, different
source is different people.
So it's about really tracking the metadata and answering, being able to answer the questions
who create this data, where the data is coming from, who modifies the data, who do
it is the data, and then on top of that, of course, you can have access control and authorization.
So this is kind of a few projects we are working on.
Ground makes me think a little bit of, like, it might be an interesting blockchain application.
There's a blockchain application, there's another project which is based on blockchain
which is doing about authorization, yes, it's called WAVE.
WAVE?
WAVE.
Okay.
Interesting.
Great.
Well, before we finish up, is there anything else that you'd like to leave listeners
with?
Well, I think you're very nice here, as far as this question says, I know you don't
want to stay with this guy, hey, so I'll save something for the next time.
Great.
Well, thanks so much, Ian.
It was a pleasure having you on the show.
Thank you.
All right, everyone, that's our show for today.
Thanks so much for listening, and of course, for your ongoing feedback and support.
For more information on Ian, or any of the other topics covered in this episode, head
on over to twimlai.com slash talk slash 55.
For the rest of this series, head over to twimlai.com slash AI SF 2017.
And please, please, please send us any questions or comments that you may have for us or our guests,
via Twitter, at twimlai or at Sam Charington, or leave a comment on the show notes page.
There are a ton of great conferences coming up through the end of the year, to stay up to
date on which events will be attending, and hopefully to meet us there, check out our
new events page at twimlai.com slash events, twimlai.com slash events.
Thanks again for listening, and catch you next time.