Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast where I interview interesting
people doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
We are back with our second show this week, episode 2 of our Autonomous Vehicle Series.
This time around, we're joined by Jinsheng Shao of AutoX, a company building computer
vision-centric solutions for autonomous vehicles.
Jinsheng, a PhD graduate of MIT's CSEL lab, joins me to discuss the different layers of the
Autonomous Vehicle Stack and the models for machine perception currently used in self-driving
cars.
If you're new to the Autonomous Vehicle space, I am confident that you'll learn a ton.
And even if you know the space in general, you'll get a really interesting glimpse into
why Jinsheng thinks AutoX's direct perception approach is superior to end-to-end processing
or mediated perception.
Our Autonomous Vehicle Series is sponsored by Mighty AI, and I'd like to take a moment
now to thank them for their support.
Mighty AI delivers training and validation data to companies building computer vision
models for autonomous vehicles.
Their platform combines guaranteed accuracy, with scale and expertise, thanks to their
full stack of annotation software, consulting and managed services, proprietary machine
learning, and a global community of pre-qualified annotators.
If you haven't caught my interview with their CEO, Darren Nakuda, in the last show,
we'll talk number 57, please make sure to check it out.
And of course, be sure to visit them at www.mty.ai to learn more, and follow them at at Mighty
underscore AI on Twitter.
Before we jump in, if you're in New York City next week, we hope you'll join us at
the NYU Future Labs AI Summit.
As you may remember, we attended the inaugural Summit back in April, had a great time and
shared some great interviews, which we'll link to in the show notes for your listening pleasure.
This year's event features more great speakers, including Karina Cortez, head of research at
Google New York, David Venturelli, Science Operations Manager at NASA Ames Quantum AI Lab,
and Dennis Mortensen, CEO and founder of startup x.ai.
For the event homepage, visit aiSummit2017.futurelabs.nyc, and for 25% off of all tickets,
use code twimmold25.
We'll be at the summit happy hour on Monday the 30th, and the summit itself on Tuesday the
31st, and we look forward to meeting you there.
And now on to the show.
All right, everyone, I am on the line with Jensheng Shou.
Jensheng is the founder and CEO of AutoX, a company that is doing some interesting things
in the autonomous vehicle space.
Jensheng, welcome to this week in machine learning and AI.
Thank you, everyone.
Great.
Why don't we get started by having you introduce yourself and tell us a little bit about your
background and how you got interested in autonomous vehicles and ML and AI more generally.
Yeah, sure, sounds great.
I got my PhD from MIT.
I spent four years at MIT in the computer science and artificial intelligence trying to
get my PhD.
My research area is in computer vision and robotics.
So I have been working in this space for quite a while.
So after I graduated from MIT, I went to Princeton University as a professor.
I was the founding director of the computer vision and robotics at Princeton University
at the Department of Computer Science.
OK.
Our research is about trying to make computer sees, enable them to interact with the physical
world.
For example, these days we have images like from camera or from other sensors, this kind
of sensor input, and then we try to pass what's going on in order to make it get an understanding
of the physical world about the traffic situation, about people working around in order to make
sense of the world.
And after that, we can interact with the physical world, we can design robots.
So in our way, we were designing all kinds of robots, including, of course, like my big
self-driving cars, as well as a smaller robot working around, moving around inside an indoor
space and have robot hands to grab objects and so on.
So that, for example, I will participate in the Amazon Picking Challenge last year with
a robot arm together with a team of experts from MIT.
We have a joint team together and we get pretty good score in the final competition for
robot picking challenge as well.
Oh, wow.
Is this the first time you've participated in the Picking Challenge?
It was the first time, yeah, but also the last time.
So after that, I started this company, AutoX, working on self-driving car and we focused
on, we are being very focused.
So right now, we focus on trying to make the self-driving car technology really good
enough for practical usage.
Uh-huh.
What I've learned about the company, just from some of my background, reading is that
you are really focused on trying to enable self-driving cars based strictly on vision-based
technologies as opposed to LiDAR and some of the other sensors that, you know, we think
of when we think of like the Google self-driving car, is that the case?
Kyle, it's not exactly like that, but we are, our solution, I would say is camera-first
solution.
So we are not against any other sensor, we are very open to use any sensor.
But at the same time, we primarily focus on using camera as our primary sensor.
One of the reason is that, that's two reason, one is the cost factor.
Camera displays the battery go cost, but other sensors, such as high resolution LiDAR,
they are very expensive.
Right.
So if we are to make a product that can really be used by every citizen, by everyone, it has
to be go cost enough so that financial actually makes sense to have the self-driving car.
Because if a self-driving car is way more expensive than a car plus a few full-time driver,
then it doesn't really make any sense, particularly.
Right.
So for us, we are camera-first solution, that's one thing.
The other thing is also technicality, it's not just the cost.
Technically, typical camera has very high resolution, but even a very high-end LiDAR, for
example, a very expensive 80,000 US dollar LiDAR, is still have only 64-bing vertically.
The resolution of a high-end LiDAR is simply too low so that it cannot be used for many
situations, such as, like, CT, in CT downtown, variable 5 urban driving, it has to be able
to recognize those subtle details, small objects, complications in order to be able to drive
safety.
But high-end LiDAR simply doesn't really have the inner resolution compared to a camera
to do this task.
And you said that LiDAR with the 16, did you say 16 by 16 resolution, or what, how did
you?
LiDAR, a lot of LiDAR these days, they are springing LiDAR, so they have 360 degree coverage
horizontally.
But vertically, they have a fixed number of bings.
The LiDAR was deferring to, it's the highest and LiDAR, it's 64, 64.
64.
Got it.
And you said that was, how much do those units cost?
Those units cost 80,000 US dollar now.
80,000, wow.
Yeah, 80.
Yeah.
And actually, it's not.
The other problem is, it's not automatic grid.
That means if you keep using the LiDAR in high temperature, in low temperature, it's
going to break in a few months.
Like for any hardware that can be installed on the vehicle, actually, people are spouting
it has a lifetime of like 15 years.
Okay.
And also on your website, you talk about your goal being to try to enable self-driving
cars with just $50 worth of cameras.
And in fact, you, you've got off the shelf webcams in a picture mounted on the hood of
a car.
I think they're the same one that I have, the Logitech C920.
Yes.
Of course, that's not for final production, but yes, of course, the initial experiment
we're actually using those Logitech webcams, they're very old cars.
But to moving towards production, now we're upgrading our camera with the other camera
that is not webcams, but they're actually a similar price level, they are not much more
expensive.
Okay.
Maybe we can dig into, you know, what are some of the things that you're doing or the
ways that you're thinking about the problem that enables you to take this camera first
approach?
Yeah.
That's a very good question.
A one thing that we try to emphasize is camera actually have a lot of potential.
Like for example, a lot of people say that then can your camera be system dry at night?
Actually, yes.
Because a lot of camera displays the feature is actually much better than human eyes.
The way it's actually missing for the camera-based solution is really a very good software.
It's very sophisticated, very advanced AI algorithm.
That's what is missing to make the camera-based solution desirable.
That's for example, human use the guide on our two eyes.
We don't have a spinning ride out on top of our head shooting leaders, but we can still
drive very safely.
So that's why it's missing really about the software.
This is where our key innovation comes in.
In our company, most of us are software engineers, all researchers were working in this space
trying to develop a very advanced perception system as well as a very robust printing system
and decision-making system in order to work together side by side to have a robust solution.
So maybe I can start with the general pipeline of the architecture first.
So that three major-style autonomous driving, in the autonomous driving software step.
One is the perception, the other one is the printing and decision-making, and the third
one is the control.
Perception is deferring to the part that will take the image and other sensors as input.
Trying to make capture what is going on in the physical world, get the traffic situation,
and trying to have the software to understand, okay, this is an object.
This object is moving, and this is a traffic sign, and this is a traffic light, and get
a sense of the world.
And that's the perception part.
And then after that, that's the decision-making part.
It's like, even now the computer can understand what's going on in the physical world.
Now the computer needs to make this decision.
Should the car stop or should the car go, how fast it should go, how much it should turn,
or all these are the decision-making and printing part.
And after it made a plan, now finally, we need to execute the plan.
That's the control part.
We need to control the vehicle, actually going to execute the plan and behave accordingly.
So these are the three major building blocks, three major steps, you know, full-step software
for autonomous driving.
Okay, perception, planning, and control.
Exactly.
And the different schools, how to do this, there's one approach that is more traditional
Google based approach, or we know now, based approach is try to do every step separately,
complete separately.
So the perception part will focus on making a very good understanding of the physical
world, make sure everyone everything is perfect.
In particular, you're trying to get, I would say, a point cloud variable or pixel-wise
level, like for each image, or each pixel in the image, they try to make a perfect understanding
of what the object is, like is this pixel beyond to a car, or is this pixel beyond to a
road surface to help pixel-wise understanding.
And then, given this pixel-wise understanding, they try to have a 3D understanding of the
physical world in order to support that decision-making and printing.
That's one typical approach, which we call mediated perception.
Mediated perception?
Yes.
Okay.
So that's another approach that is recently populated by a media, is trying to do end-to-end,
everything end-to-end together.
Remember, we are talking with a 3-step, that perception, that's printing, that's control.
The immediate approach is trying to fuse everything together.
They no longer use a modularized approach.
They just put everything together into a huge gigantic neural network, so they take the
sensor, such as the image at the input, and the neural network just output directly the
control.
How much break you should apply?
How much stealing talk we should apply to the stealing world?
So that's the end-to-end approach from the media.
Okay.
But both approach have a lot of problems, I would say, at least some problem.
Maybe we're talking about end-to-end first.
The end-to-end first, the problem is everything is working like a black box, it's very difficult
to provide input.
That, for example, if a computer drives a car to an intersection, now you can turn left.
Now you can also turn right.
But it's actually very difficult to tell the computer to turn right.
Because the computer will look at this intersection, and it will make up its mind, because it's
a black box.
I then automatically tell you, okay, I'm going to turn right, I'm going to just turn
right.
So it's very difficult to control what's going on inside, everything is just a black box.
That's one major job out there, end-to-end approach.
If I can jump in, that's an issue I've never really thought much about is when you're building
systems that are controlled by neural networks, the ability to, for example, override the system
or provide user direction, is that a software engineering challenge, like you have systems
that take the neural network input and take the user input and just prioritize the user
input, or is that a neural network challenge where you're providing the neural network input
in, and you have to train the system to prefer it.
I'll say it depends on the detail.
For this cloud end-to-end approach, if everything is completely end-to-end, then that is not
just a software engineering problem, it's really a more research-generated neural network
problem.
Because the neural network will decide everything for you, you don't really have a choice.
Whatever the computer, the neural network decides, that's the result.
But if you are able to use the neural network in a more modularized approach, use the neural
network to do certain tasks and the other part to do, another neural network to do certain
tasks, and then eventually you have some way to combine it together.
In that way, the user actually can have more input.
So that's actually, that's a very good question, that point of the one job of the completely
end-to-end approach.
It's like now the computer decides where you are going to go, where you are going to
stop.
That's obviously not usable for us.
And another problem for the end-to-end approach is the amount of data required to have this
system up and running.
You can imagine that to cover the space, to change a good neural network, we will need
to cover pretty much all the use case, all the potential traffic scenarios in the changing
data in order to change the neural network to behave smartly.
But this kind of approach is very difficult because you can imagine that even in the same
role, in the same role intersection, for example, or in the same highway merging point, there
could be many different kind of traffic, that could be different numbers of cars, those
cars could be a different position, each car can have different size, each car could
have different color, each car can have different speed, each car can have different reaction
tongue, all these are different, now we need to cover the whole space, we need to have
enough changing data to put forth all the space, and this is still assuming at the same traffic
merging point, if you have different role, different role condition, different language,
different, that makes the number of changing data requirement is so big that probably
even like the whole human society catch a data for thousands of years, we may not still
have enough data to change a good neural network to cover all the space.
That's another typical job of the N2N approach, is the amount of data you require is really
gigantic.
I mean, just as maybe a counterpoint, the impression I'm getting from folks that are doing
things that are more like the end-to-end approach in video and Google is that they're making
a lot of progress, right?
I'm not getting the impression that they think it's going to take thousands of years to train
you know, these systems to be operable.
That's not really true because the Google approach, they are not end-to-end, we're talking
about.
Yeah, the Google approach is the second, the next approach I'm going to describe is the
mediatic perception approach, they are the operative end-to-end, they cut the end-to-end
into many, many different small steps, into so many steps, basically, and each step,
they will do something very, just very, very small step.
The mediatic perception approach typically is that, take the sensor input that I remember,
the end-to-end is about merging the perception, training, control, all into one single step.
Now, the mediatic perception is different, they're not only separate them into different
steps, even each step they separate into many sub-steps.
For example, when Google's approach, in this kind of approach, they take the image as
the input, and then they try to get a pixel-wise recognition of each pixel in the image, and
that's not useful for driving, so that's the first step, and then after that, they convert
this pixel-wise segmentation into a more 3D understanding of the world.
For example, they will get a 3D building box, a box to contain each card, each vehicle
will have a box to contain the card.
So sound, meaning you've got from your LiDAR sensor, you've got a point cloud, and you've
got from your image a two-dimensional view that identified that some two-dimensional set
of contiguous pixels as a car, they would fuse those two to determine a 3D bounding
box for the vehicle based on both the point cloud and the image data.
Yes, that's right, but you can see about this, there's a lot of information in this process
that we're trying so hard to get, they're not particularly useful, that for example,
the height of the vehicle, we don't really care, no matter how tall the vehicle is, we
don't want to hit them.
So that a lot of information is...
But you want to know how tall the clearance is for a bridge that you're trying to cross
under, or an overpass?
Yes, that is.
So that certain information that is useful, that certain information that are not useful
for us to try, so that's the point exactly we're making.
In Google's approach is the optical end to end, they try to get everything, no matter
it's useful or it's not useful, they all get it out, and whether it's going to be
useful or not.
I would say this approach is safer, but it's overkill, it's a lot of redundancy that
we can squeeze out.
Because every big of information we shred, that's always a cost, that's a cost of computation
on board, if you extract a lot of information that's not useful, it weighs a lot of computation.
Secondly, it's also a lot of engineering and research time, because if we spend so many
engineering efforts to get those information and actually they're not being used, there
is a waste of time as well.
And certainly it's a waste of changing data, because then you'll get a lot of changing
data with a lot of heavy annotation in order to get something that's not really useful.
So that's another problem.
Auto-X will count in between.
We feel that mediatic perception have some advantage, but it may be overkill.
We see the different problem of end-to-end perception, an end-to-end approach that is
completely end-to-end, that's a lot of problem, but the good thing is it's more simple and
more elegant.
So we design something called the Degrad perception, which is flowing between, is that we're
trying to only get those information that are useful for driving, and we're not getting
those that are used these for driving.
A lot of information that in the mediatic perception approach, they get out is useful
for other tasks, that if I'm a bird, I'm flying around, definitely I need to know how
high is the car.
So it's a lot of useful information for other applications, but not for autonomous driving.
So for our approach, we're trying to identify the needs of information that are useful
for autonomous driving, and we ignore those that are used these for autonomous driving, and we only
focus on spending the computation power, spending the engineering effort, spending money
on gathering training data for those useful information, and we call those useful information
for those indicators, for example, I can give you a example, this is terminology that
is dedicated for robotic audit, for example, if I give you a mark that you can do water,
a mark, whether the mark you can have a handle, typical mark have a handle, the handle
will afford you to grab the handle so that you can raise the mark.
So a fordance means the environment or the object allows you to support you to do certain
action, intelligent agents to do certain action.
So that's what we call a fordance, and in the autonomous driving scenario is the same,
is that is the current traffic situation for you to do certain tasks, that for example,
is the traffic, now it's a traffic jam, that means the fordance of this current traffic
situation cannot afford you to speed up your car into a 60 miles per hour.
So the autonomous driving, what we actually need is, we need to get the affordance, can
the current traffic situation, can the current road condition, can the current physical condition
allow you, can afford the autonomous driving car to perform certain action.
So this is the list of essential things that we really need for autonomous driving.
I guess one question that comes to mind for me is that affordance as a key metric seems,
it's alright what to say this, it strikes me as it's like a, it's a planning metric.
Like if I have a route that I'm trying to pursue and I want to plan, you know, my next
step, whether it's change lane or turn or something like that, does the current situation
allow me to do what I want to do.
But there's also a requirement that these vehicles be, you know, reactionary to things
that happen.
And I'm wondering, you know, when I think just the way affordance sounds like it doesn't,
it's not necessarily as applicable in those types of scenarios, is that the case?
In the now sense, maybe yes, but you know, the general sense, because when we say affordance,
it's not static, it's a dynamic signal, but for example, in the more computer sounds
language, the computer is making a decision 30 for a second.
That means every second the computer is making 30 decisions.
That means the computer is changing that my quickly, very quickly, point five thing to
me.
So if you, so if the car cuts me off, then, you know, I'm still, I still need to figure
out if I can afford to go straight, for example, and that's happening at 30 frames per second.
Yeah, so then suddenly the affordance becomes very reacting, because if the situation
changes a little bit, the affordance changes and then it's basically being very reacting.
So in the general sense, the affordance is deferring to all these reacting behavior
as well.
Okay.
Thanks.
Yeah.
So what we do is we take the existing auto driving approach and we squeeze out and we
see which part is really essential, which part is, which affordance is very necessary
for auto driving and we are focusing our energy on making those very reliable so that we
can have very robust auto driving solution.
That's basically the unique part of our technology.
It sounds like then in the mediated perception world, they are, are they ultimately trying
to get to affordances as well, but they're, they haven't pruned the, the universes of affordances
that they care about or is there not really the concept of affordance there?
I believe that's a concept of affordance there is just like when they designed this system,
it probably, it was like that a girl, this kind of system, at that time they didn't seem
too much about this, they spent a lot of time probably focusing on other aspects.
So the system design was a little bit no longer the greatest way, no longer the most
arrogant way to do the technology.
So I also believe that maybe in the future when they were also mixing about this, people
passed them out, they're also impressed as well.
When we're talking about affordances and this direct perception, trying to focus on
only the most relevant affordances, is there an enumeration of those, is there, you
know, are there a 10, are there a 20, are there hundreds, does that question make sense
or is it more like, you know, is that more, is it less a high level concept and more
something that's implemented, you know, in the software that's like some vector of,
you know, affordances that's determined on the fly?
Yeah, that's made sense.
It does, if you numerally at least, it's probably less than 200, it's 100 something.
Of course, a different traffic situation is not like you have the whole 100, it always
does only a subset that makes sense.
So we'll classify the traffic scenario into different subset, and then each subset, we
will derive a smaller number of perception indicator, the affordance indicator in order
to try the car and to have the car behave appropriately.
Okay, and so since you call this direct perception, does that mean that the planning and the
control layers of the stack remain the same and they're just getting inputs from this
different kind of perception, or did those also change to accommodate direct perception
and affordances?
Yes, and yes, in the sense that if we just focus on talking about the repossession, but
mediatic perception, yes, this part of the difference only on the perception, but there's
another dimension of technology that is different from other companies that we mentioned at
the beginning of the conversation is we are focused on using camera instead of radar.
The mediatic perception, the repossession, they can both apply to radar and camera, but
if we are talking about camera, that's another way of difficulty, because for camera, because
it's not an active sensor, it's not shooting up laser, the distance measurement is usually
more noisy, so there will be more noise in the distance measurement.
So we have to model the uncertainty of the object distance, object speed, and so on.
And that means the decision making planning and control path have to be more robust as
well.
Therefore, in a sort of way that the decision making and the planning path will also spend
a lot of time making it to take the uncertainty from the perception needle into account as well
in order to have a battery or bus auto-redriving system.
And so when I think of a system that is looking at images, trying to calculate distances
of from the car to objects in those images, and then applying another layer of uncertainty,
that calls to mind some type of Bayesian type of system, is that what you're doing underneath?
It's not exactly Bayesian, but Bayesian is one of the many ways to encode uncertainty,
but in our environment, it's a lot of other ways to encode uncertainty as well.
It's not necessarily a fully Bayesian framework, because technically Bayesian framework
will have some technical requirements of being Bayesian, but at least will still cut it
into the uncertainty into account.
As for a lot of other systems for traditional auto-redriving systems, they actually don't
get into uncertainty into account, that planning and decision making is completely decisive.
But if this is going to happen, then what will happen is a pure if-else statement only.
But for our solution, it's much more robust because we consider the uncertainty of the perception
needle, we take uncertainty into account, assuming the perception needle is not perfect
and we are able to make use of the uncertainty estimation in order to make a plan that is
doable even if that something is going to happen.
So when you talk about the if-else kinds of constructors, is that that's specific
to mediated perception, like end to end, there would just be a neural network that's doing
something that doesn't involve if-else.
But with a mediated perception, you've got some control system that is taking in perception
inputs and the planning is based on if-else or I guess I don't think of these systems
as very if-then-else, very traditionally rules-based as opposed to based on train networks.
Yes, if I do, I say if-else statement is referring mostly to mediated perception system.
The reason why it's that is because I was saying 99% of the companies working in this space
are still using mediated perception.
The end train approach is mostly on the research side, still very difficult to be practically
used.
Okay.
Yeah.
And so at what layer of the stack do you find the if-else, you know, the rules-based parts
of the system and a mediated perception approach?
It's usually on the decision-making, like after the perception and big for the control,
the planning and decision-making, usually people have to manually write down all the rules,
it's hundreds of thousands of rules.
For example, if a car is kind of encroaching on my lane, you know, from the left then,
you know, turn right.
And what's the granularity of these rules, I guess, is what I'm trying to wrap my head
around?
Can you give me examples there?
This granularity of the rule is valid detail, it's not just so general.
It's more like if the car is approaching you from the left then, you need to estimate
the size of the car, the distance of the car, and the speed of the car and the acceleration
of the car in order for you to decide what to do accordingly.
So depends on different speed, different size, different rows, structures, are we turning,
we have turning right or is on the street or is on the curvy or they are all different.
So you have to encode all this information and they have many different combinations
in order to encode all these rules.
That's why there are so many rules has to have to be returned out.
Right, right.
So it strikes me that, I mean, you, I'm trying to put together these three approaches that
you've mentioned end to end pixel wise direct perception.
It strikes me that you can have a system that is, you know, there are still more degrees
of, you know, the flexibility of kind of inserting machine learning into different layers
of this.
For example, you know, with mediated perception, a company could start with a mediated perception
system and swap out the planning decision making, you know, with the train neural net,
you know, for example, without changing the way the perception works.
Is that, where does that fall apart?
Why aren't people doing that?
It's possible.
That's possible, but just particularly very difficult to make work that right now the
neural network is still performed very well, mostly on the perceptions that for the other
like decision making and so on, it's very difficult to still have the neural network working.
That has been some research, for example, using the enforcement learning, some tiny by
similar to AlphaGo, to purchase, to do design tasks, but it's not at the level of maturity
that most people are willing to use for production here.
So it's still mostly in the research stage, it's not ready for the work product.
And even non deep learning machine learning models, I guess the, what I'm trying to wrap
my head around is intuitively, you know, after you've gone through the perception step,
you've got, you know, a set of, you know, a set of features that represent what you've learned
about, you know, 3D space around the vehicle, the vehicle dynamics and all that.
Is it that the, you know, the dimensionality of that is too high for either traditional
machine learning models or deep learning, or is it something else that is really the
main challenge?
The difficulty is not about the dimension or the size of the data.
The difficulty is about the space is not fixed mapping.
Let's put it this way.
For neural network, a lot of traditional machine learning such as the very famous support
vector machine, what they are trying to learn is a function.
You give me some input.
I have a mapping tool to output, so it's a function.
You give me, you change your input, my output change, and so on.
But when we talk about robotics, when we talk about autonomous driving specifically,
it's very regarding what's going to happen in the next step, depends on what I do now.
If I speed up my car, suddenly the car you found me making scare, me speed up as well.
And since I'm not predictable, it's not just me changing, it's not fixed mapping.
Is everything going to happen in the future depends on what's happening now.
So there's a sequential causality in between.
That makes it a fixed mapping, that mapping function f, mapping x, f to get y, that's very
not very, not degraded applicable to this kind of application.
So that's why people have to imagine something new, more fancy stuff, try to do this.
Okay.
So tell me a little bit about the progress you've made, is how far along are you?
Yeah, we are a young company, we get started 13 months ago, just a little bit over a year.
Sparkling in the past year, we already made a lot of progress.
So people from our website, autox.ai, you may see that our car already shows an initial
prototype driving on the street, doing a lot of demos, can drive safety, using camera
to achieve almost all the driving behavior that will require.
So we are moving very fast, our plan is to in a very near future, we can really have
a product, made the technology so perfect, good enough to have a little product out to
the market very soon.
And we are working with a lot of partners, several major partners, such as car manufacturers
or just companies, try to commercialize our product as soon as possible.
And it doesn't sound like the model is one, like I think what Kama is trying to do, that
to have like an aftermarket kit that you can just deploy on your vehicle.
Yeah, we are not interested in aftermarket at all, because aftermarket, in some sense,
it's almost not doable, there are two aspects that may not be doable.
The first is the, because we need to set up the camera, we need to set up a computer,
the modification of the car is a lot, quite a lot, and most people simply do not have
the skillset, or they just don't want that car to look really ugly with the things dangling
around.
It's just not very safe as well.
What happens if the camera falls to the ground and then while you auto-drive it, it's
just simply very not very easy to do that.
And there's also a even more fundamental problem that nobody point out is that most vehicle
available today on the market already get bought by the customers, they do not support
drive by while.
That means the steering wheel, the brake, the throttle, the acceleration, they all have to
control manually mechanically.
There's no way, no adequate way, no easy way that you can have a computer to control
that for you.
If that's the case, most people, and they have this aftermarket kid, they still cannot
control that car.
But for example, if you look at Commodore AI's modification of the car, if you read the details,
it actually cannot control the car under battery or speed.
It can only take over the control of the car, for example, about 20 or 25 miles per hour.
If you are driving at 10 miles per hour, the computer cannot control it.
So there's always some certain limitation for those cars, for aftermarket retro 15.
So that's why we're focusing on our company, we put safety as the primary goal for deployment
or any autonomous driving technology.
So we're not only the software have to be smart enough to be safe, but the hardware,
it has to be good enough to provide redundancy as well as provide very solid hardware that
can run at least a few years, I would say, for autonomous driving.
Instead of a drive for three days and a camera for on the ground, then what happens now?
Yeah.
Right.
Okay, great, great.
Well, I really enjoyed this discussion and learned a ton about the autonomous vehicle space
in general, not to mention what AutoX is doing.
Is there anything else that you'd like to share with us?
Yeah, sure.
Like I mentioned, we're a very young company and we're still quickly growing, but right
now we have a member of 30 and we're trying to go to at least a hundred in a year.
So we're actively recruiting, so if the audience are interested in exploring or also working
together, the cutting edge research to really make a difference to the world, please come
to the virus.
You can visit our website, www.autox.ai to learn more about our opening.
Thank you very much.
Awesome.
Thanks, Jen Shaw.
I really appreciate it and it was great chatting with you.
Okay, great.
That was.
Thank you very much.
All right, everyone.
That's our show for today.
Thanks so much for listening and for your continued feedback and support.
For more information on Jen Shaw or any of the topics covered in this episode, head on
over to twimlai.com slash talk slash 58.
To follow along with the Autonomous Vehicle Series, visit twimlai.com slash AB 2017.
Of course, please, please, please send us any questions or comments you may have.
For us or our guests, be a Twitter at twimlai or directly to me at Sam Charrington or leave
a comment on the show notes page.
Also, be sure to check out our last show, twimletalk number 57, with Mighty AI, co-founder
and CEO Darren Nakuda at twimlai.com slash talk slash 57.
And check out some of the interesting things they're working on at www.mty.ai.
Thanks again for listening and catch you next time.