Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast where I interview interesting
people doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
A big thanks to everyone who participated in last week's Twimble Online Meetup, and
to Kevin T from SIGUP for presenting.
You can find the slides for his presentation in the Meetup Slack channel, as well as in
this week's show notes.
Our final Meetup of the Year will be held on Wednesday, December 13th.
Make sure to bring your thoughts on the top machine learning and AI stories for 2017
for our discussion segment.
For the main presentation, prior Twimble Talk guest Bruno Gonzalez will be discussing
the paper understanding deep learning requires rethinking generalization, by Shi Huang Zhang
from MIT and Google Brain and others.
You can find more details and register at twimbleia.com slash Meetup.
If you receive my newsletter, you already know this, but Twimble is growing and we're
looking for an energetic and passionate community manager to help expand our programs.
This position can be remote, but if you happen to be in St. Louis, all the better.
If you're interested, please reach out to me for additional details.
I should mention that if you don't already get my newsletter, you are really missing
out and should visit twimbleia.com slash newsletter to sign up.
Now, the show you're about to hear is part of our Strange Loop 2017 series, brought to
you by our friends at Nexusos.
Nexusos is a company focused on making machine learning more easily accessible to enterprise
developers.
Their machine learning API meets developers where they're at, regardless of their mastery
of data science, so they can start cutting up predictive applications immediately and
in their preferred programming language.
It's as simple as loading your data and selecting the type of problem you want to solve.
Their automated platform trains and selects the best model fit for your data and then outputs
predictions.
To learn more about Nexusos, be sure to check out the first episode in this series at
twimbleia.com slash talk slash 69 where I speak with co-founders Ryan Sevy and Jason Montgomery.
Be sure to also get your free Nexusos API key and discover how to start leveraging machine
learning in your next project at nexosos.com slash twimble.
In this episode, I speak with Sam Richie, a software engineer at Stripe.
I caught up with Sam right after his talk at the conference where he covered his team's
work on explaining black box predictions.
In our conversation, we discuss how Stripe uses these predictions for fraud detection and
he gives us a few use case examples.
We then discuss Stripe's approach for explaining those predictions and briefly mention Carlos
Guestren's work on the line paper, which he and I discuss in twimble talk number 7.
Well hey everyone, I am here at the Strange Loop Conference in St. Louis and I've got the
pleasure of being seated across from Sam Richie, who is a software engineer at Stripe.
And Sam was in to talk about just so stories for AI, explaining black box predictions.
And in fact, he just jogged over here from delivering his talk and it's like five blocks away
at hustle.
So welcome to the show, Sam.
Yeah, thank you.
Thanks for having me.
Why don't we start by having you tell us a little bit about your background and how
you got started working in AI and machine learning?
Sure.
Yeah, you want the just so story of exactly.
So this is fairly new, I guess less year and a half I've been at Stripe, as I said, working
on machine learning infrastructure.
How did I get here?
We were talking before this started about, you know, my kind of initial coding background
is coming up in the functional programming world years ago, I guess the first thing that
led to this was this large scale like deforestation monitoring system I worked on.
This got me into like Hadoop and closure and this is sort of it was a machine learning
application, I had no idea what I was doing when I was on this, right?
And where were you working on that?
So this was just a freelance thing with a guy I used to race like flat water kayaks
with.
And he moved off to the data science world.
I was making apps like in my apartment in New York, I had a year in New York city.
And yeah, just wanted to, well, the real, okay, so the reason I, it's like hard to put
a narrative together in my life, man.
The deforestation monitoring system was just this collaboration with a buddy who was doing
work for the World Bank though, right?
Okay.
So the idea was to build like a model that could, on the basis of these studies that happen
every like five years or so, build a logistic regression that could predict for certain pixels
in the tropics.
The idea was like any spot you looked at, the goal was to get out some prediction of the
chance that that piece of forest would be deforested in the next month, right?
Okay.
And you're starting with satellite imagery?
Exactly.
Okay.
We came out every two weeks.
The training data for this, again, I didn't know what I was doing at the time.
The training data for this was a study that this guy Matt Hansen had done, which looked
at, modus data from the year 2000, same data again in the year 2005.
Okay.
And then he just went through a manually like selected which pixels they thought were deforested
in which work.
So this is useful in the back, like a lot of policy, and there's a lot of work on, you
know, reforestation and things like this, a lot of money that went out from this study,
but the plan was to do it every five years.
And so a lot of money went into Indonesia, for example, to like work on deforestation
there.
The next time he did the study or when our model came online, it was clear that like Indonesia
was actually looking pretty good.
It was not talking to charts anymore.
Okay.
And like me and Mar was now the issue.
So the goal was to get new data every two weeks.
So what we did is this is where the, you know, big data, functional programming stuff came
in.
Right.
And then from satellite data, like time series of what was happening during that five
year period, right?
Okay.
So use that as the training data.
The prediction variable was what this guy Matt Hansen had said deforestation was.
Right.
And then we just marched the time series forward and predict, does this now look like deforestation?
Does this now?
You end up with a map that you can scroll through that just shows the trends of deforestation
moving through the world.
Oh wow.
It's really amazing.
Interesting.
I don't know what's happened with that, but I think it's now the World Resources Institute
was the organization that was sponsoring us.
I think this is out as I can open data set now, but that's kind of my first taste of.
And now I came at machine learning from the statistics side a little bit.
And it turns out that these are like the same field.
They just have different words for things.
Right.
So you move from one of the other.
You don't really know if you can bring anything over.
But yeah, that was the first thing.
That took me, you know, I took all this like wonderful, non-profit, amazing work I was
doing.
And I let Twitter like recruit me to go do the same stuff on ads.
The best minds of our world, that people put ads, right?
That's it, man.
Yeah.
So it sold the soul for a little bit.
But, you know, had a few years there building open source tech to do, again, like effectively
the same sort of Hadoop based stuff that we were working on before.
We ended up open sourcing a lot of that work as this library called Summingbird, which
is, again, as we were saying, it's like all monads all the time.
It's a library that lets you write these like big streaming data computations and then
run them on Hadoop or on like a real-time streaming system or on both.
And basically, like, separates what you want to compute from where you want to compute
it.
And it's only relevant really because the final piece of this puzzle is what drew me
to stripe is that I was interested in machine learning.
I was doing a lot of work on my own and studying and just trying to get up to speed and like,
stripe had pulled this library in and was using it for their feature generation pipeline
for a lot of their models internally.
Okay.
So it was like, I'm not the most qualified, like, I don't have this amazing like data science
background.
I did have a hook in the infrastructure side.
And so a lot of the work I do now at this intersection between how do you make features?
How do you run the stuff at production scale?
How do you ship models?
The intersection between that and like, what models are even worshipping?
What should you care about?
What should you put in the product?
Super interesting for me and it's been a really fun, like, year and a half or so.
Leading now to some work on this stuff we were talking about today.
Okay.
Awesome.
So why don't you tell us what you were talking about today?
Yeah.
So the talk today was on, in general, it was on this idea of how to explain the predictions
that black box models make.
Right.
This is like a term that's tossed around like a black box model is a model, like, a neural
network is a black box model, a random force is a black box model, right?
Like, it's just kind of this term meant to express how, like, powerful and complicated
these things are internally.
The internal structure is very rich and varied.
You know, a black box model is typically seen as difficult to understand or hard to explain.
That's like, it's hard to know what that really means, right?
Like, what does it mean to explain a black box model?
So that was the general theme.
The specific things I started with were the work we do at Stripe on fraud detection.
You know, we use models that are as accurate as possible to try to catch fraud for merchants
who sign up for Stripe.
At the same time, this black box property of, we're just going to block charges and, you
know, you as a merchant, like, you might know more about your business.
We might block a charge that you think is a legit customer.
And if we're just sort of telling you like, look, the world is a better place if you accept
our decisions.
It's not totally appropriate.
And people don't trust us with this and often what they've done is not used our product
and gone to the system of very manual rules.
You know, you go in, you say what you think fraud looks like.
You're probably like cutting a lot more tissue out than you should.
But you know, you feel good about it because you made the decision.
So there's a tension here between a black box model making decisions for you that you
don't understand.
And something is not as effective, just strictly, like, a merchant does not know as much about
fraud as some like a big company that is dealing with tens of thousands of merchants can.
So the talk was about some tech we developed at Stripe to give people alongside our internal
sort of suggestion or decision about what we're going to block, an explanation of why we
did that.
Okay.
So this is a subtle problem.
It was about the solution we came up with for that.
And then about why that solution is kind of not great and why it's not a real explanation,
is it not?
And then we talked about a bunch of other techniques that the goal was to build up in
the mind of, I mean, I guess we'll talk about it here, like, there's a bunch of techniques
to do this.
And it turns out that black box models often are like the most explainable models.
They have such a rich structure that you can ask so many questions that really tease
apart subtleties of an individual example in a way that you absolutely cannot with something
like a logistic regression or a very simple model that you can just simulate in your
mind.
As a human.
That's counterintuitive.
It is.
Then a black box model, you'd consider black box models be the most explainable model.
Yeah.
And I mean, I do it by just taking the definition and twisting it a little, but I would argue
that it's, it's fuzzy what people mean when they talk about this.
Right.
There's a number of ways to frame this problem of is a model explainable or not, right?
And so when you, how are you defining it leading up to the conclusion you've drawn?
So I think the way in which people think a black box model is not understandable, you
know, is it's the same way that like, you could say, if you asked me why I decided to
go or get straight for something else.
And I just like printed out the contents of my brain and showed you the state of every
neuron and every connection.
This is not understandable, right?
Like, it's the truth.
This is why I did it, like the physical state of my mind just, I couldn't do otherwise if
you buy a sort of free will argument.
But that's not what people mean really when they talk about human explanations, right?
Like, when you talk about a human explanation, you want to know, okay, well, give me some
narrative, give me some plausible reason why in this case, like not the entire, your brain
has information from everything you've ever done.
Give me for this example, you know, maybe, maybe one way to explain the decision is what
would have had to change to make you change your mind, right?
So that's a form of explanation.
That's a kind of question that you can sort of ask of a logistic regression.
You can ask of simple models when you get to things like image processing, where the
features, the inputs to the model are tens of thousands of different pixels, each of which
has individual weights in say a logistic regression.
Like, that ability to look at a feature and see how much it affected the output, that
kind of stops being helpful, right?
Whereas with a neural network or something like this, you can, for an individual example,
you can start one technique I talked about in the talk, it's called line.
And the idea here is that-
That's Carlos Gastron's work.
Yeah, yeah, it's so good.
So the idea here is that for an individual example, you can probe the model and see what
would have happened had any individual thing changed, right?
So you can build effectively like a little local linear model inside of this wild space that
the neural network is trained, right?
So because of this rich internal representation, overall, totally with you, like, it's hard
to explain why the model is doing what is doing in aggregate, just like it's hard to say
why like, you know, the entire population of a country is doing something more.
But for any individual case, you can, in fact, build a story or build more technically
like a local linear model, which will tell you what the most important aspects of that
particular example were.
And it's been a while since I've talked to Carlos about this.
We'll put a link to the podcast I did with him in the show notes.
But I wasn't even impressed in that the line work, at least at that time, which was a year
and change ago, like wasn't really being applied to neural nets.
It was for, you know, other types of models.
The stuff that we, that I mentioned in the talk is we're not using neural nets at strike.
But the examples he's got are, like, his techniques don't really depend on, my understanding,
the underlying model.
The models themselves.
Okay.
Exactly.
So you can sort of probe a neural net in that if you train a neural net, the example I
showed in the talk was that he has actually in his paper, you have a neural net that recognizes
Huskies, say, versus wolves.
And so he had a beautiful example of a husky that was misclassified as a wolf.
Right.
And so you look at it and you go, yeah, they look kind of the same, like, I get why this
is happening.
Yeah.
So the explanation that Lyme produces shows you the most relevant pixels to the decision.
So like, what pixels that they change to have the most input?
And in this pathological example, it's like the snow underneath the husky.
Right.
Interesting.
Yeah.
One example, and you can, it's clear that like the training set you used clearly just
had every wolf associated with snow marked up on the wrong pattern.
So you, you've explained this deep property of the neural net through one explanation, like
just one image, right, which exposed this rich structure.
Okay.
One last thing.
I'm not trying to make like a, this is this controversial claim that black boxes are actually
easy to explain.
It's more just for the things that we would care about at Stripe, which is how, like, that
you care about with an image, like, why is this particular image misclassified?
Right.
Or why is this particular merchant getting blocked or why is this particular charge?
You can come up with a much richer story about why that's true.
And that seems to often have the property that if you look at enough of these and they're
different enough, you can leach out some understanding of what the model is doing without
actually having to go, you know, look at every path through every tree or the weights
of every neuron.
So you can treat the thing as a black box and get some insight into what patterns it
extracted from the data set you gave it.
Okay.
So the, the line approach is doing what, I guess, sounds like almost like sensitivity
analysis for the inputs, right?
Is that maybe what I think about it?
And then there are also approaches that are based on, you know, kind of introspecting the
layers of a neural network, like deep dream and these other things trying to get, well,
this, this network's looking at edges.
And so if it's misclassifying something, it's because it sees an edge wrong or something
like that.
Did you develop your own technique or, okay, so tell me a little bit about that.
Yeah.
So the technique that we developed, the ones we were just talking about are really
good for actually understanding, for some particular example of fraud or some merchant,
why the model did what it did.
So, or what would have to change to change the decision?
Yeah.
Now, you know, building a product that is meant to block fraud, you know, unfortunately,
some of the merchants that sign up for Stripe, sign up to go just run stolen credit cards
through the system and collect money.
The whole issue is that there are people who are testing cards who are sort of committing
fraud in this network, and because we're one level behind merchants, we have to be a
bit careful about what we expose in terms of our explanations of why the models are doing
what they're doing.
If we were just to give, for every charge, our best sort of most beautiful explanation
of what would have to be different to not get blocked, you know, there's, you could probably
wait this, per merchant by trust and start to expose more and more as they're with you
longer.
You do that through, you know, individual like customer relationships, but as far as
a product, like, what do you want to see on the screen when your card gets blocked?
Like, the explanation that line produces is almost too good.
It's like easy to game, right?
Okay.
So, the system we developed internally, I'll develop it here.
It's a way that you can come up with an explanation for basically a post-hoc explanation
of that looks like a rule that the merchant could have implemented themselves, where if
they deployed that rule, like, it would have caught the charge and it would have agreed
with the model in some high percentage of cases, right?
But it's not necessarily tied to anything internal about the model structure.
So I guess the subtlety here versus the other system is, and this is the title of the talk
is just so stories for AI.
The idea here is that you can develop a sort of, you know, ahead of time, it's hard to make
predictions.
That's why we have to use these models with rich internal structure.
Once you know what's happened, once you know that the model thinks that this charge is
fraudulent, it's much easier to go back and say, okay, given that I know that this is
what the model said, I can go come up with an explanation for why the model did what it
did.
So, like, conspiracy theories are kind of an example of this, right?
Once you know that the model went off in this particular building, you can come up with
some crazy tale about how it got there and it's like a much easier problem.
There's also different, many explanations that will fit some are more credible, some
are less credible, but it's a much easier task than actually predicting a decision.
Is what you're ultimately doing some form of, like, dimensionality reduction or dimension
compression?
Like, you've got all these internal variables in your model, but you're trying to, it sounds
like you're trying to map your story down to, like, these four public facing, what aggregate
thing.
I wish it was, I'll tell you the algorithm, it's, yeah, I think it's a little as disciplined.
Okay, so the simple way to say it, or the first pass of it, is that what we're trying
to do is train, like, a decision tree on, it's basically a bad version of the model that's
meant to predict what the model is going to do, right?
So, we want it to look like a decision tree because we want to be able to present some,
like, the form, the, the output, I guess, of this model, we want to be some set or, some
rule that the user could, could see, or any, of course, using a decision tree because
it's explainable.
It's explainable, right?
Exactly, exactly.
It's not very good, but so, that's the shape of what we want and what the model looks
like is basically a can set of potential explanations, any one of which, if it applies to some
charge you give me, like, any one of which has a high precision with respect to what the
model would have chosen, right?
So, if my rule, if my explanation applies to some charge of the model calls fraudulent
in the test set, I want to be sure that it also would have applied to many other charges,
right?
So, if you just tell me, like, if the explanation is, well, there was a charge on the card,
this is very high recall, it catches a lot of fraud, it has incredibly low precision,
right?
There's no sort of information contained in that statement.
So, again, the explanation model is a list of possible explanations sorted by their precision
in descending order compared to the models, like, what the model claims.
What we do then is, when a charge comes in, if the model claims that it's fraud, we then
go to our explanation model and we just start looking through the explanations, and we find
the first one that applies to the charge that has come in.
So basically, like, what's a path through the decision tree?
Looking at all the paths, not looking necessarily first at the features, just taking the outcomes
and, like, trimming out anything that doesn't apply, which is the explanation that, as you
go down the list, has the highest precision, but also applies to this one.
That's the thing we exposed to the user, right?
So, it's sort of like a decision tree, and then it has, it has the same structure as
a decision tree, but you don't independently ask the explanation model and the forests
and then present both of these.
This probably wouldn't match, right? Because a lot of these explanations won't necessarily
match up, but if you know what the model did, you can take your kind of bad model, your
decision tree, you can trim all the paths that don't agree with the model and then show
the highest precision path down to some leaf.
Okay, so you've got your high fidelity model and your low fidelity model, the low fidelity
model, the decision tree, you are, I mean, it sounds like you're running both of them parallel
along your input data.
Yeah, you run the first one and then the second one gets features as input, it runs its
thing, and again, like, exactly like you're saying.
So I'm not super clear on the part where you're trimming off the, like, you're pruning this
decision tree in some way or...
Okay, so let's see if I can, let's see if I can elaborate on that.
Let's take a step back. So the input to this, the second model decision tree is, it's
not your input data and it's not the output of the first models, the features of the first
model.
Are you talking about the training or the prediction process?
The prediction process.
So for prediction, yeah, it's, yeah, so the input is in fact, yeah, okay, let's step back
and frame this.
So your first, like you said, first model is the black box, right?
Second model is the decision tree or another way to look at this list of predicates, right?
So what you need to evaluate the second model is the output of your first model plus all
the features, right?
So the output of the...
And my features are we referring to the inputs or, like, weights or some internal...
Sorry, good call.
See, again, the statistics machine learning, crazy terms, by features here, I mean, like,
the things we know about the charge, like the dictionary, the inputs to the black box.
Got it.
Okay.
So forget what's going on in the black box.
You're totally right.
Got your features as well.
Okay.
We're going to evaluate the charge, the variables.
We first send those into the black box, we get out some decisions from the black box.
Right.
And we've chosen a threshold in advance, so all we care about is does the model think
it's fraud or not?
Right.
Okay.
Now, we take that, we go to the second model, we take the same inputs to the black box,
and we go through this list, which is ordered from high precision to low precision, and
we find the first path through the tree, again, like, it's important that they're ordered.
We find the first path through the tree that one evaluates the true as well, so agrees
with the black box model.
Well, that's it.
That agrees with the black box model.
Okay.
There might be multiple paths that agree with the black box model, right?
So this is the difference between just evaluating the decision tree.
So we find the one that has the highest precision that does agree, and we return that as the
explanation model, or as the explanation user.
Okay.
How do you even measure the results from, I mean, if we're talking about, if we're talking
about, you know, whether the fraud is the transaction as fraudulent or not, the easy to measure
the results are.
How do you measure like the explainability of the result?
There's a couple answers to this.
One is, I think, a good answer.
One is kind of unfortunate.
The first answer is the way you can evaluate your explanation model is you want each individual
explanation to have high precision.
You want overall the entire set of explanations to have I recall, right?
So you want for any charge that comes in, you want a very high probability of having an
explanation available, right?
And then for each explanation that you give, you want that to be as high precision as possible.
So internally, like, that's one way you can evaluate this.
I think what you're actually getting at is like, what's the point of this?
Like how can you evaluate the effect of giving these to merchants and seeing if they actually
mean anything?
That we were just kind of at the early days.
We don't do a great job at this now.
We don't have, I believe, much built into the product now to evaluate the actual thing
we're trying to do, which is to take something that feels like a black box decision and give
people some way to kind of relate or build a model in their mind for what this black box
model is doing.
Because again, each individual instance of fraud, they might be in a domain where they understand
what's happening, right?
They might be a charity site that is dealing with card testing.
And if they see an instance of this and then the model gives them an explanation that's
a rule that, you know, maybe it's not why the model did what it did, but it actually
happens to match up in a lot of ways with the decisions the model would make for charges
that look like this.
Like that's a valuable piece of information that a merchant could then take that would
one give them some insight into what fraud looks like and two, and this is probably the
real thing you want down the road is to have people just trust what the model is doing
in decision they understand less, right?
Right.
Now, a little bit of what I talked about in the talk is that this is a kind of pathological
by itself, like you have to know, the explanation is there to get you to trust the black box.
Right.
But you shouldn't trust the explanation unless you have some reason already to trust
the black box.
So it's, it's like when Twitter says, oh, you should follow this person because, you
know, Sam follows him and Oscar does too.
Right.
That's not a reason.
It's just, there's sort of an implied reason, but it's not what's actually happening behind
the scenes.
Well, I mean, part of what I was getting at was, you know, there's all kinds of questions
that it raises, like how granular you want your explanations to be.
The degree to which people actually care about the explanations, like there's, you know,
the book influence, Robert Chaldeini, you know, basically we rejected this charge because
we rejected this charge, like it's putting the word reject there.
Yep.
Just has a huge, you know, provides a huge degree of acceptance, just based on, you know,
human biology and so how do you, how do you wrap your head around, like how granular
you need these explanations to be or is it just like you started somewhere and that's
kind of how much are you investing in that process, I guess?
So internally, we care, well, we care internally and externally, but like the initial reason
we created these, these kinds of models was to try to give our risk analysts and our,
I guess account managers, some way to understand as deeply as they can, like what's happening
with some decision with, you know, a charge that a merchant called to ask about.
So this is a case where you're not really trying to persuade the risk analysts, they,
they have a vested interest in learning as much as possible about this so that they can,
you know, sound knowledgeable or be knowledgeable like when they're talking.
But you still don't want to give them the internal representation of the black boss model.
That's right.
The case I've just described leaves it up to the, you know, the person on the phone to
like hide information that seems sensitive.
Right.
Whereas when you have the model do it, you know, I don't have a great answer for this.
We're not like, it's a, it's a really interesting question.
What level of granularity, you know, what you're really trying to do for a merchant?
How you, how you have them, how you give them the ability to like let you know what they
care about or maybe you give them the ability to, you know, sort of request more information
that you can expand this thing.
Right.
How many explanations do you have?
Each model has roughly like 80 possible explanations.
That usually gets like full coverage on this thing.
Okay.
There's like 80 possible explanations that could apply.
I'm comparing it to like credit reporting.
Yeah.
There's like what all of eight explanations and these are ones that you commonly see.
And this, this might help us out that like the rest of the world is just like, there's
a sort of argument by authority for like scary thing is happening in the world.
Yeah.
Go ahead and deal with it.
So this is, I mean, the reason I kind of, I was interested in giving this talk and
doing this work is, these are a lot of the open questions in this, in this field, right?
Like, there's the goal here of getting a customer to trust us.
That doesn't mean anything without some internal, you know, sense of accuracy or reason to
actually trust the model.
If you've got the Husky snow dog problem going on internally, but then you're talking
people into accepting the decisions, that's kind of pathological.
And so with the talk, what I, what I was interested in after this that kind of expands
beyond stripe is that, though we probably will have to deal with this, or I probably will
personally in the next year or so, you know, the EU has this, what's it, the general data
GDPR?
GDPR.
Exactly.
The GDPR, the GDPR gives you this, you know, right to an explanation.
This is one of the clauses.
Now, after working up to this talk and giving it one of the messages I have is, it's, it's
not clear what this means, right?
There's two forms of explanations, there's many forms, but of these two, if people are having
a right to this sort of explanation, like you said, to just have some emotionally triggering
word like rejected in their explanation that's meant to convince them of something that's
going on, this is actually not good, like, I don't think this is the intent of what's
in that law.
Absolutely.
And the other hand, on the other hand, if you're giving people like incredibly detailed
explanations about why the model did what it did, well, this is good, but it's potentially
gameable, you know, like, I guess the core issue here is that you started.
There's an element of, I mean, like domain appropriateness for lack of a better term.
If you, you know, you could, you know, one way to, you describe one way of kind of scurrying
GDPR is by, by, you know, having just this, you know, this, you were rejected.
That's the explanation, right?
That's certainly not in the spirit of the law.
You know, but on the other side, if you say, well, the, you know, the third neuron and,
you know, layer five of our neural network, you know, spit out a 0.6, you know, that's
why you're rejected.
That's also inappropriate, even though it's way more detailed and way more granular.
So I didn't really mean, though, it's, it's a good characterization of it.
I wasn't necessarily saying that that would be a way to skirt the rule, though it certainly
would, right?
If you give people these, okay, you've been rejected, you know, that character of explanation
though about, hey, we don't know why the model worked, but here's a plausible explanation.
I guess in, in thinking about this, I think the problem with that, if you did, if that
was what was adopted by say the courts or, you know, a car, for example, having to spit
out an explanation of why it did, but it did the cost and damage.
This doesn't teach you much about the core problem of, that I think we're trying to solve
here, which is there are things we care about in the world.
And then there are the goals that we give to our models when they get trained, right?
You have some prediction target.
And it's just the fact that we don't, we don't know enough about ourselves about what we
care about, about how we work to encode all of our ethics, all of these things in the
goals of a model.
And so when you can ask a model, like, I think my understanding here, my interpretation
of this is, when you can ask a model for an explanation of why it's doing what it's doing,
what you're doing is you're monitoring whether or not it picked up the things you actually
care about from the data that was easy to encode, right?
And what do you do then?
What you do if you find a mismatch, the only thing that makes sense is to take the thing
that wasn't quite there and to figure out how to encode that in the goal of your model
that you're training, right?
So you have, on the one hand, this, again, kind of pathological case where models start
optimizing for whatever they're optimizing for, right?
Once you start feeding data back, like, model decisions back into its own training set,
you start to get this odd effect of, like, putting a copy on the copy over and over.
And then you've got this other parasitic model that's, like, just justifying whatever's
happening under there.
This is not good.
Right.
That's the downside.
So we're forced to really clarify what we care about in technical terms, right?
Like, you can take these ethical concerns, this is what I guess the law attempts to do
through almost like your sidecar model is like a, almost like a unit test for your regular
model.
Is it encoding the kind of the way of thinking about the relationship between the transactions
and the judgments?
Yep.
Like in a conversation, if you explain, you say something to someone, they repeat it back
in a slightly different way, what's the point of this?
Or you're just demonstrating that you've absorbed the content, right, stating it in a different
way.
And if you go, yeah, totally get it, you know, and just say something insane, right?
We get to talking again, you know?
So that I think is what's so interesting about this tension between the different kinds
of explanations, the subtleties of what's going on inside the model.
Right.
So one example of, like, an ethical concern that people have been talking about, there's
a couple of folks internally, it's right, where actually speaking of the GDPR, like one
concern for a model is that it's going to pick up on some kind of implicit like pattern
in the data and start treating like people of different genders, different race, like
different groups.
It's going to have different considerations for them.
Now this first kind of model, there's a Peter Norvik quote I gave in the talk, can give
you an explanation that just kind of ignores what's actually going on and gives you a plausible
reason why, you know, somebody might have been rejected from a job, like say it's right,
we start turning a model loose on hiring, right?
If you can figure out what is different about what you care about, which is this sense of,
this kind of vague sense maybe that everyone like deserves a fair shot, et cetera, you
find that your model is not doing that, you're then forced to encode this more formally.
So Google has a great post which says this in a nice way, which is like one way to encode
this is to say that along any split you care about, along any group, along any like business
type or something like this, let's make sure that the false positive rate is identical
across all these things.
And so this then can get fed back into the, like once you realize that if this is not happening,
you can then feed this back into the training process for your black box models, they then
will kind of formally encode the ethics you care about in the world and then you move
on to the next problem, of course, right?
Yeah, it's really interesting, even circling back to the kind of the beginning, the notion
of explainability, the model you're describing, like the second model, you could argue it's
not really explaining the first model, it's explaining, it's offering a justification,
right?
And you kind of said that, but we talk about this broadly as solving the explainability
problem, but it doesn't necessarily offer any insight whatsoever to what's actually
happening inside your model.
That's right, which I guess, you know, we're kind of getting into semantic land here,
but you know, explainability of the model versus explainability of the output.
But I think they're, you know, at the very least, I think, you know, for folks that are,
you know, thinking about this stuff, it makes sense to at least try to be clear on which
one you're trying to achieve.
I think that's a great takeaway, I mean, to wrap back to what you, when you were talking
about like, if you give someone an explanation on the state of the neurons, you know, one
thing that comes up a lot in these, in these papers, these papers that are trying to talk
about how to formally encode explanations is this idea that, or these casual references
to how humans reason and how humans explain their own decisions.
And it's just kind of taken for granted at this point that the way we work is separate
from the explanations we give for our actions, right?
And so this is one thing that comes up when you read about the GDPR is that one critique,
I guess, of this clause is that we're asking for things from our black box models that
we don't ask from judges, because there's just no conceivable answer, right?
So it's like you said, it's sort of getting into semantics is kind of getting into sort
of whatever philosophy I can sort of pull out of a software engineering career.
But I think it's really important to contrast the two, right?
And say, you know, what do we mean?
What are we asking for?
There's this naive idea that because it's a model, because it's an algorithm, there's
like a clear answer to why it did what it did, or because it was something you could turn
the crank on.
Right.
But that's not right at all.
It's much more subtle than that.
Awesome.
So is any of the work that you've done in this area published?
We're planning in the next few weeks on writing more about this, and I think publishing
the algorithm.
Okay.
That'd be great.
Yeah, I'm sure folks would be very interested in learning more about it.
And once again, we'll drop the link to Lime and the conversation with Carlos.
And are there any other efforts at explainability that figured heavily into the work that you
did there?
I'll give you some links to put in the show notes too, but we've got, I mean, there's
so much stuff going on.
There's a DARPA program now, an explainable AI, Stuart Russell at Berkeley has, I think
it's called, I cannot remember the name, not human compatible, maybe human compatible
AI.
Okay.
There's a track at MIPS about this issue.
I mean, this is really coming up as, of course, we have to get into this, it's coming up
as one of the core approaches toward this problem of like AI and algorithmic safety, right?
Which can often be this fuzzy, scary conversation.
For me, I think there's grounds it very heavily, like what are we worried about kind of one
thing is the leaching of meaning from just letting things that are loose that are really,
really accurate, but haven't encoded the things you care about in the world, right?
And explanations are kind of our tether on this.
Yeah.
So I'll send more links and I'm going to do some writing on this next week that I'll
send over as well.
Okay.
Just the full brain dump.
Awesome.
Looking forward to it.
Well, thanks so much, Sam.
Always very to have another Sam on the show.
Yeah.
Thank you, sir.
Enjoy the rest of the conversation.
Thank you, Sam.
All right, everyone, that's our show for today.
Thanks so much for listening and for your continued feedback and support.
For more information on Sam or any of the topics covered in this show, head on over
to twomolei.com slash talk slash 73.
To follow along with our Strange Loop 2017 series, visit twomolei.com slash ST loop.
Of course, you can send along your feedback or question via Twitter to at twomolei or
at Sam Charrington or leave a comment right on the show notes page.
Thanks again to Nick Sosis for their sponsorship of the show.
Check out twomolei.com slash talk slash 69 to hear my interview with the company founders
and visit NickSosis.com slash twimmel for more information and to try their API for free.
Thanks again for listening and catch you next time.