Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast where I interview interesting
people doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington, a bit about the show you're about to hear.
This show is part of a series that I'm really excited about, in part because I've been
working to bring it to you for quite a while now.
The focus of this series is a sampling of the really interesting work being done over
at OpenAI, the independent AI research lab, founded by Elon Musk, Sam Altman, and others.
A few quick announcements before we dive into the show.
In a few weeks, we'll be holding our last Twimble online meetup of the year.
On Wednesday, December 13th, please join us and bring your thoughts on the top machine
learning and AI stories of 2017 for our discussion segment.
For our main presentation, formal Twimble Talk guest, Bruno Gensalves, we'll be discussing
the paper, understanding deep learning requires rethinking generalization, by Shi Juan
Zhang from MIT and Google Brain and others.
You can find more details and register at twimlai.com slash meetup.
Also, we need to build out our 2018 presentation schedule for the meetup.
So if you'd like to present your own work or your favorite third-party paper, please
reach out to us via email at teamattwimlai.com or ping us on social media and let us know.
If you receive my newsletter, you already know this, but Twimble is growing and we're
looking for an energetic and passionate community manager to help managing grow programs
like the podcast and meetup and some other exciting things we've gotten store for 2018.
This is a full-time role that can be done remotely.
If you're interested in learning more, reach out to me for additional details.
I should mention that if you don't already get my newsletter, you are really missing
out and you should visit twimlai.com slash newsletter to sign up.
In this show, I'm joined by Jonas Schneider, robotics technical team lead at OpenAI.
While in San Francisco a few months ago, I sat down with Jonas at the OpenAI office during
which we covered a lot of really interesting ground, including not just OpenAI's work
in robotics, but also OpenAI Jim, which was the first project he worked on at OpenAI,
as well as how they approach setting up the infrastructure for their experimental work,
including how they've set up a robot as a service environment for their researchers,
and how they use the open source Kubernetes project to manage their compute environment.
Check it out and let us know what you think.
I really enjoyed this one, a quick note before we jump in.
Support for this OpenAI series is brought to you by our friends at NVIDIA, a company
which is also a supporter of OpenAI itself.
If you're listening to this podcast, you already know about NVIDIA and all the great
things they're doing to support advancements in AI research and practice.
What you may not know is that the company has a significant presence at the NIPPS conference
going on next week in Long Beach, California, including four accepted papers.
To learn more about the NVIDIA presence at NIPPS, head on over to twimlai.com slash NVIDIA
and be sure to visit them at the conference.
Of course, I'll be at NIPPS as well and I'd love to meet you if you'll be there, so
please reach out if you will.
And now on to the show.
All right, well, hey everyone, I am here at the OpenAI offices and I am with Jonas Schneider.
Jonas is a member of technical staff here as well as being the technical team lead for
robotics.
Welcome to the podcast, Jonas.
Hey, glad to be here.
It's great to have you on the show.
Why don't we get started by having you tell us a little bit about your background and
how you got interested in artificial intelligence?
Yeah, so my background is actually, so I work on OpenAI's robotics team, but my background
is actually in software engineering.
Okay, my background is neither in robotics, like classical, like academic robotics, nor
machine learning, which is of course like OpenAI's big focus.
And so in the robotics team, we kind of have a couple of different skillsets coming together.
So in the robotics, there's of course machine learning experts and also software engineering
people like me.
So before OpenAI, I was actually software engineering intern at Stripe.
That's also where I met our CTO, Greg Brockman, who is now a CTO at OpenAI.
And so basically, yeah, and so that was actually, like, while I was still in college.
And so after I was done with college, I actually reached out to record and was like, so what's
up these days?
What kind of stuff are you working on?
And so he introduced me to OpenAI.
Fantastic.
Yeah.
So I actually got started working on OpenAI Gym.
So that was kind of like my, I was a contractor for OpenAI there, basically working with Greg.
And so that's how it kind of got started thinking about all these AI ML things.
And then eventually I got started working on OpenAI's robotics team.
Awesome.
So tell me a little bit about the work that you do on the robotics team.
Yeah.
So the goal of the robotics team basically is to enable new capabilities for robots.
So today's robots, they're really good at like very specific tasks, for example, like
in a factory robot, you have an assembly line and you have a robot that can place one
very specific screw into one specific location on the part that you're assembling.
For example, then robots are great at that.
They're really good at that.
They can, they have very, very high precision.
They can, like, they can repeat this movement, like, tens of thousands of times.
And they, yeah, and they, they never get tired or anything.
But the issue is that these environments are very constrained, of course, because like,
that's how a factory is.
Like, everything is super precise.
Whenever something like unexpected happens, you just abort.
Right.
And you like, and the human goes in there and like, figures it out and it resets and then
it goes on again.
Right.
But so that's very different from, for example, like a home environment where like, if
you're trying to clean up someone's apartment, for example, where like unexpected stuff happens
all the time and you're like, something like falls over, then you have to like react to
that and pick it back up.
Yeah.
So this is like a very simple task, but it turns out that like today's robots are actually
not that great at operating these unconstrained environments.
And usually the reason for that is that they are pre-programmed, basically.
So when you, when you're, when you have this factory setting, someone, like, when you
set up the robot initially, someone goes in there and like, and basically like programs,
this exact movement pattern for the robot.
But of course, and that works great in this constrained environment, but in an unconstrained
environment, you actually can't really do that because you have to react to what, what's
happening in the environment.
And so that's why today's robots are like, very pre-restricted in these kinds of environments.
And we're, we're trying to embark on solving that.
Nice.
So it sounds like the, you know, we're talking about the environments as being constrained
and unconstrained.
But in a lot of cases, it's my sense that the constraints themselves are artificially
imposed.
Like the, you know, the factory environment is constrained because it has to be because
that's the way they can get the robots to work.
Like, do you look at applying this stuff in the industrial settings as well?
Well, so the thing is, like, yeah, you're of course exactly right, that basically, basically
today's automation, like basically everything, like the way these factories are designed
is exactly so that the robots can function.
I think for the most part, it will be, or at least with the current state of, of like
capabilities of ML-based systems, it will actually be pretty hard to be better than
this constrained environment, if, if basically your, like, your application or your business
is like fine with operating in a constrained environment.
So for example, like while it might be nice to, let's say there's a Tesla, there's a Tesla
like robot that moves the auto bodies around.
Right.
And then, and then let's say like it, like of course it would be nice, for example, like
if, if it would be smart enough to react to, if it like drops the thing on the floor,
if it could like pick it back up and just pick when you're going on, but these events
are so rare that, and basically of course there's like a lot of other engineering factors
there where like you got to be sure that if the robots in this like reaction mode that
it doesn't, doesn't accidentally, I call like more failure somewhere else in the system.
And basically just because these events are so rare in, if your environment is already
constrained.
So we're like, we're not really looking at that, I guess like in the, definitely in the
short, short and medium term.
I'm thinking about applications like pick and place types of applications where I've
seen a number of research is kind of in the context of, you know, today, a robot that's
being used to bolt stuff in, right.
It's getting these bolts that are like preloaded into, you know, a very constrained like a harness
that basically it can bolt in, right.
But some of the examples show that in some instances you might want to just put a box
of bolts and let the robot kind of grasp the bolts and then from there bolt them in.
And I guess the question is, have you, have you looked at the, you know, is that really
practical?
Like, is that where you see the application of this kind of stuff or it's like, no, the
industrial environments, you know, we've got that kind of figured out.
People probably aren't going to, you know, switch from using these, you know, the very
rigid environments to the more unstructured environments to save a little bit of that
upfront cost.
Yeah.
So I think there are definitely, there are some opportunities, basically, specifically
in the areas you mentioned, like machine tending, basically where like, you have this
inbound, like box of parts and they come from like a, like a some vendor and you basically
have to like feed them to the machines correctly, like unpack them.
And that is again, because it's kind of an unconstrained environment, you don't really
know, like they might change like their shipping material and suddenly it looks different
and you have to process this package differently.
Mm-hmm.
And also one, one other, one other kind of interesting example is actually plugging in cables.
So that's something that, that all these industrial robots are also very bad at, it turns
out, because like cables are deformable and basically there again, you might have to
react like if the cable is bending weirdly, you have to like poke it so it falls into the
correct place.
And so this is actually something that consumes a lot of time, in, for example, like auto
assembly, where basically you can do the entire frame, it's all, all the body size and
all super nice.
And then you have a bunch of people like installing all the stuff in the interior, for
example, and that includes, actually, it really is like one very specific task that
people have tried to automate using the classical robotics, it's plugging in these
like connectors basically, or I guess maybe like a day-to-day variant of this would be
like plugging in a charger into, like plugging your phone into like a phone charger.
But it turns out basically for these problems you also, you actually, like, these are surprisingly
hard, because you have to like figure out the like exact positioning for the charger
and then plug it in for like a year.
So we built USB-C and like lightning reversible ones to make it easy for robots to charge
our phones for us.
Yeah, so I think definitely like for the industrial applications, like, it, why it might be hard
to basically, in the short term, improve on the stuff that is already handled by robots,
there are definitely a lot of fringe cases that, like, there's, there's no way that you
could currently even, like, get close to automating it and new technologies could enable
that.
Okay.
So tell me a little bit about some of the areas of research that you're pursuing to kind
of enable this, this vision.
Yeah.
Basically, the thing we're very interested in is basically acting on, and reacting on feedback
from the real world.
So basically this, and this kind of feedback is really also what gives, what gives humans
this super good, like manipulation, like super good, like robotic skills, basically.
Okay.
So one, actually one, one quick experiment you can verify that is if you try to, to, if
you put both of your index fingers out, like horizontally, and doing this, yeah, yeah.
And you try to move them, move them together and like touch the fingertips.
That's very easy to do, and you can always do it.
Yeah.
But so, but, and now try doing it again with your eyes closed.
Mm-hmm.
And it turns out this is actually, it's actually really hard.
Ha, ha.
Yeah.
And like, after a while, you can, like, if you have, like, the touch feedback.
But basically, so the thing there is that, like, actually human motion is not very precise,
but it is very good at, like, figuring out, oh, I'm, like, off in this, in some direction
and then going for it.
And going for it.
Going for it.
Exactly.
And so that is actually a thing that, that, like, again, these, like, industrial robots,
like, they don't really do that on, like, a higher level.
They do it on, like, a very, like, very low level of, like, am I in the right place?
But this gets harder if you have, like, other objects or something that you're interacting
with.
And so this is what, like, this is one area that I research focused on, basically, taking
data from the real world and using that, like, online in the loop to have the robot be
able to, like, react to what it's doing and what, like, the things it's interacting
with, which could be, like, a block or, like, like, whatever object that you're working
with is doing.
And like, if you're, like, grasping it correctly, for example, or if you're moving it
to the right place.
And so how do you do that?
Yeah.
That's a very good question.
So there we're, we're building on, on the, on the large body of work that has, that
has been done in the computer, like, in the, like, ML-based computer vision areas.
So basically, we take, we take a convolutional neural network that's been, that's been trained
on ImageNet to do this, like, image recognition challenge.
And then we basically slice off the, the last layers of that network where it, where it
does this thing of, like, classifying an object into categories.
Right.
Yeah.
And the parts we want from that is basically the lower level features of the network,
like figuring out, like, where edges are, where, like, these, like, small features are.
And then we instead train it to predict the state of the world, basically.
So, so we're using this, this, this machine learning pipeline, basically, to, to feed
an image from, like, a normal webcam or something like that that's attached to the robot.
And then have, have this neural network that uses this image to predict, like, where,
like, where am I?
And where is, like, what state am I in?
What, where is the object that I'm interacting with?
And then we use that to, to correct the movement of the robot.
Are we close to doing this?
It seems like it would be helpful to do this in three dimensions, like, are we close
to that at all?
Right.
I think so, so maybe not for the general case, but probably if you have, like, basically
something where you, where you know, at least a little about, like, what kinds of objects
you're dealing with, then, then I don't think anyone has done it yet, but, but it's, like,
we think it would probably be doable.
So, so the work, the work that we've done.
So we use this technique called domain randomization, where we basically, so, so questions, of course,
how do you train this network?
So what I just mentioned earlier with, like, predicting the position of things.
And the way we do it is basically we create chaos in simulation.
Because the problem is, if you just feed it images from a simulator, the real world
will look different.
And then it will just get confused and be like, this is weird, why is there, like, a pixel
in the back that I, that is now, like, bright, where, where it was, like, dark always
before. And the way we get around that is by basically randomizing everything in the
simulator.
It looks pretty crazy because we basically replace all the textures in this, like, 3D rendered
scene with random textures, like random colors, random patterns.
It looks, we just call it the disco, because it's just random colors everywhere.
And basically this, this kind of makes the network robust against, like, variations
in the environment.
And so this is actually, and, and basically you can measure that, like, if you do this,
then in the real world will look as just, like, another incarnation of, like, of the
random, of this random setting.
And it will work.
And if you don't, it will just be, like, completely off of it.
Okay.
Yeah, one of the projects that Peter Beelow is working on is, like, tying a knot, using
a robot to tie a knot in some string.
And there's a, he's got an interesting video about this.
But one of the comments in the, in the video or the commentary on the page is, like, you
know, it works great if the rope is on a green table, but it totally fails if the rope
is on a red table, or if the rope is, like, striped or something like that.
It sounds like this domain randomization is, you know, trying to solve for that same kind
of problem.
All right.
Yeah.
Yeah, totally.
I think so, so for the, for the, like, rope, like, for the, like, rope stuff specifically.
So the reason why, like, why people do this at all is, is because a rope, like, similar
to the, to the phone charger, like, the phone connector, is that because the rope is flexible,
like, does not, like, just, like, like a block or something.
And basically, to tie a rope, you have to, like, either, you have to have some, like,
some internal model of, like, how is it going to bend if I, like, if you, like, turn
it this way?
So I guess people just, like, work on this, and, like, it's a couple, like, it's a couple
from the, like, perception way.
But this is very plausible for you, like, put these, put these two results together to
create something that can, kind of, in an arbitrary colored environment.
Yeah.
What makes me think of is, is Apple's recent CVPR paper, where they use GAN approach to
take simulated images, like, from a video game engine, and kind of make them look like
real images, so that they would perform better in the real world.
Like, the ultimate goal is to have this robot perform well in the real world.
You are trying to, trying to avoid overfitting by, kind of, doing, you know, randomization
of your backgrounds and, you know, funky colors and all that kind of stuff.
But do you still then have the problem of, hey, this doesn't look like the real world?
And, like, how do you approach that?
This is actually very interesting, like, high level questions that, like, I don't think
there's a different, different answer to.
It's basically the question of, like, do you, basically, should you invest time in making
your simulations, like, super nice and photorealistic, basically, to have, like, special rendering
artifacts of, like, light reflections and basically just make your, make your, make your
simulation be almost indistinguishable from the real world, or whether you can actually
get away with having really lacking simulation, basically, that is, like, very rudimentary,
just has, like, the geometry and, like, edges and the couple of, like, 3D lights.
And then you can use, like, neural network, regularization techniques to basically use
that to make the network robust against it.
And more generally, in the case of, of your research, you know, what, using the domain
randomization, like, what kind of performance have you seen in the real world, and have
you explored ways to enhance real work performance beyond the domain?
Are there specifics to the simulation environment that calls your training to kind of overfit
on simulated looking images?
Yeah, yeah, so, like, like, I remember that's, when we're initially doing this domain
randomization work, so, so the setting that we did there was, we basically had a table
off, like, different colors, like, wooden blocks.
And then we had the robot, basically, you could give it to commands of something, like,
stack the green block on top of the blue block.
And then it would, like, basically correctly localize these blocks.
And this was with an accuracy of, I believe, a couple of millimeters.
So it was pretty decent for, like, given that this was really, like, just a normal, like,
HD webcam, like, basically, nothing, basically, nothing that's, like, super specialized
robotics equipment, but I actually remember that initially, sometimes it was just failing
randomly.
And we didn't really know why.
Okay.
And then it turned out that if there was someone standing in the background, then casting
shadow or something like that.
Exactly.
Or just having, like, a leg or, like, a foot in the image that threw it off.
And that is actually, basically, like, these kind of things encourage us to just make the
simulation crazier, basically.
And then if you have this, these random distractors appear in the background during the
training as well, then it will actually be, again, robust to that.
And so how did you characterize the performance gains, you know, after using the domain randomization?
The way we measured it actually is we just had, like, an actual, like, object tracking system
and just measured the error from that.
But, of course, it's also just reflected in the, like, success rate of, like, how often
could you, like, stack the correct block, like, on top of the other one.
And basically, if it didn't do the domain randomization, it would just, like, run it to the
table or something.
So it was, like, it was, like, very, very, very off.
And basically, to your performance metric was bad versus good, sort of, sort of, yes,
what's the sort of?
Yes.
So, like, basically, what we did initially when we did work during the domain randomization
is we actually, one of the researchers, Josh spent a very long time basically just moving
around pieces in the real world and, like, adjusting the, like, camera position and basically
just fine tuning it.
So it would be, like, just right.
And it would, like, appear to work, but then as soon as you, basically, like, you could
see that it wasn't really working.
Like, it was only working if you, like, basically, like, manually overfitted to, like, one,
one very specific instance.
But basically, the, the, the main randomization helped, like, helping with that.
Okay.
And so did you build a custom simulator to do this or did you use some off-the-shelf thing?
Yeah.
So pretty much all of all of what we do these days is in, is running in Madroco.
Okay.
Madroco?
Yeah.
So tell me about that.
Um, Madroco is this physics simulator developed by University of Washington professor,
M.O.
To Dora.
Okay.
And it's pretty much the, I would say, the standard in, um, and basically these, like,
kind of, like, robotics and, like, robotics-related tasks.
It's also used for all the physics-related environments in, in open-air gym.
And so basically, if you ever seen the, like, yellow, like, humanoid, humanoid walking
around, that's, that's Madroco.
And basically having these, like, capsule geometries.
And the good thing about Madroco, as opposed to, like, of course, there are many other physics
engines, like, game physics engines.
There's Nvidia physics.
Right.
There's a bunch of, yeah, like, from an Unreal engine, they all bring their own Nvidia.
They announced some new simulation engine at the last GTC.
I forget.
The Vinci or some kind of name thing.
Flex.
Flex?
I don't know.
I thought it was a person who has a whole bunch of them because they really like making
beautiful things.
So the thing that game engines do for the most part is they are often not super concerned
about accuracy or physical realism, which is totally fine.
They just, they're just working on making something that, that looks great and is performance
too.
And Madroco kind of comes from a different perspective there, where it comes from, like,
robotics people, basically.
And they, and they are using this for, like, optimal control, which is kind of the analytical
way of, like, how do you control the system to achieve a given task?
And it has pretty good features for accurately describing an actual physical robot, like it
can do things like friction and, like, tendon-based or a way you pull on cables to move the robot
around.
Okay.
It has a bunch of these things that, like, you could, you could implement them, like, on
top of the game engines for the most part, but they just don't come with it.
And also Madroco is just, like, engineering-wise.
It's pretty practical.
It's just, like, a library that you link against, and then you can use it.
Mink against, so it's, like, C++ or something.
Yeah.
Exactly.
So, like, it's not open-source.
It's commercial, unfortunately.
There's, like, a lot of the popular simulators are, like, is there a dominant open-source
simulator?
Yeah.
It's bullet.
Bullet is pretty popular.
And we've actually been looking at it, like, maybe switching to that, just because it's
open-source.
Yeah.
That's pretty much it.
Because it's just, like, on, like, a day-to-day, it's just very convenient to be, like,
what is happening?
This is weird.
Let me just dive into the code and see what's going on.
But also, I would think to make it easier for other people to replicate your results and
to, you know, try to build on the kinds of things that you're doing.
Yeah.
You don't have to say, well, you have to first go get a license.
So, I believe they do have, like, pre-favorable agreements, at least for students.
So, I think as a student, you can get it for free.
Okay.
Yeah.
But so, like, the good thing about Madroco is that it's basically that it's, like, wild
kind of, like, a walled garden.
Yeah.
It's a pretty nice walled garden.
And it's, yeah, and things.
Yeah.
Said every walled garden maker.
Well, we're not doing it.
We're not garden makers.
No, I'm putting a word in Madroco now.
That's true.
It's true.
The one thing where we've actually been eyeing some of the game engine fitting simulators
as well is actually exactly like dealing with these deformable objects, like a cable or
the rope or liquids, even, like stuff like that.
That is something that Madroco can't really deal with because it's entirely, like, a rigid
body simulator.
And it basically, like, it's performance scales with the, like, basically, it gets slow
very quickly if you have a bunch of things, like, moving around.
Okay.
Basically, like, of course, a scale thing doesn't matter at all because it's just, like,
meshes and just numbers.
But if you have, like, if you have, like, a bowl of, like, a thousand pearls or something,
there would be, it would be pretty, pretty gnarly in which awkward probably we haven't
tried it.
But we have tried, like, I believe you've basically tried to do, like, a jenga, kind
of, like, a jenga set up.
And it was just, like, jiggle around and then eventually, like, kind of explode or just
fall apart.
Yeah.
So I think it's, like, a limit of, like, maybe, like, a couple hundreds of, like, of
basically, of, like, rigid individual bodies flying around or not flying around but moving
around.
Is that rigid body simulation or something that learns itself to distributed compute
or does that not work so well?
Or does it just Madroco not support that?
That's a good question.
So I think the, I believe, I believe the creators of Madroco have tried to basically run
it under OpenCL, so to, like, GPU accelerated.
But I think the main problem with that is they're actually, it's very similar from the
computer computation you would, you would run for, for running a neural network where it's
basically just like a bunch of, just a bunch of, like, matrix multiplies or, like, related
related things.
But for the physics simulation, you actually have a lot of branching because you run, like,
a collision detection system and then you do something, it's like, if there's a collision,
then do these things and you do that for, like, all the collisions in the scene or something
like that.
And that is something that, like, at least, take two days to use, I can't deal super
well with that.
I think actually in the, this was, like, a long time ago, but I think in video, they
used to sell something, like, a physics processing unit, a PPU.
Actually, I'm not sure if it was a video, but, like, some, like, some, some vendor, and
they basically try to make it, like, an established, like, hardware accelerated physics.
This was, like, marked to gamers, I really, I don't think, I don't think it ever really
took off because eventually people realized, actually, CPUs are pretty good.
The screws are pretty smooth, and especially with, like, with, like, today's where you
have a bunch of cores, you could just have a physics core, and, you, and at least in
the, like, game setting, it just works pretty well.
That being said, basically, today, or, like, at least a bit more joke with us, it's, it's
just a single thread CPU processing, it's, it's, it's pretty fast, but I think you'd
probably be hard pressed to distribute that specific architecture.
Actually, probably some of the other, like, basically, if you had something like a, like,
some of the game engine, similar to our particle base, so, for example, Nvidia's flex.
And basically, they don't represent bodies as, like, like, a rigid mesh.
Yeah, it's basically, it's literally just, like, just, like, a bunch of particles that
have some, like, basically, some, like, stickiness, what they stick to each other applied.
I believe there have been some attempts at, like, distributing that, where basically
we have, like, cells of the world, and every, like, every node basically computes all
the particles that are, like, in this specific cell, then they, like, hand it off to some
other node.
Okay.
But we're not using that today.
Interesting, interesting.
So, I think we're going to talk about simulation and tell me a little bit about the, I guess,
the process for, you know, the relationship between your training data and your simulator
and, like, how you load all that up and, like, how you build the simulation and, you know,
are there things that you've learned about integrating simulation into AI training pipeline
that are maybe, you know, not intuitive or, you know, maybe, you know, stimulators weren't
really designed to do this.
And so, it was kind of hard, but we figured out how to do X, Y, C.
Yeah.
So, I would say for the simulation, and this is actually kind of following the, like,
the, like, what we're just talking about with the distributed aspect of it.
One reason why we're not, like, pushing out, pushing out super hard is because we actually
can just horizontally scale it.
So actually the way we, we basically do our training, which is basically running a lot
of simulators.
So you can do, you can distribute it in this way.
It's just that the simulators are all independent of each other.
Like, they do, they all simulate the same, like, the whole scene, but they all have, like,
different, like, they all basically run, like, different, like, they all run the same
scene or some randomize version of it.
But they, they basically, basically, instead of, like, serializing all the attempts, we
just paralyzed, like, 10, or, like, actually more, like, a thousand of them.
So the way we actually run our training is we have, like, one box that actually does
the, like, tens of flow, like, the computation for actually training the network and
like, taking in the data.
And then we have a bunch of, like, worker or, like, evaluator machines that basically
like, take in the current best guess for, like, for the policy, which is, like, our
trained neural network.
And then they basically roll that out in a simulator, which basically just means they run
it over and over again.
And so this happens on, like, hundreds or thousands of machines, like, in parallel.
And, but they don't really talk to each other.
Like, they just do this on their own.
And then they actually send this experience back to the optimizer node.
And that's basically where we, where we transfer numbers to actually improve the policy.
So you, you generate a policy, generate a network, you push it out to a bunch of different
nodes in parallel.
Like, what's, what's the input to those nodes?
Are you giving each of those nodes specific input or are they just kind of running things
in random and, you know, computing a function or something like that across a random
distribution?
Yeah.
So, so the worker nodes, they basically receive, they receive the parameters for the
policy.
And there's like some shared configuration for, like, what's the kind of scene I'll be
running?
Like, what's the robot and like, where, like, where are the objects that we're interacting
with?
Like, what's their, what's their initial positions?
There are actually a couple different ways of, of how to communicate the results back
to this, like, central, like, mastermind machine.
So one way is if you actually have the workers do the, do the gradient computation.
So they basically, they roll out the physics simulators.
And then they figure out some kind of reward or cost function for this.
And like, what's this a good roll out?
Like, we end up in a good state where, like, for example, when you're moving these blocks
around, like, the, the right block, end up on top of the other right block.
And then the workers figure out, okay, if my parameters were like tweaked slightly differently,
I would have gotten a better outcome this time.
Yeah.
And then the other, the other approach is to, is to just send over the raw, like, what
happened in simulation to the, to optimize the machine and then let, let the, the optimizer
figure out what the, what the parameters should be and like, how we should change them.
Okay.
And which do you tend to do the, both or, yeah, so right now we do the, we do the sending
over the experience or the latter thing, which is just because it's simpler for the most
part, because then the basically the workers are kind of dumb and they don't need to worry
about that much.
But there's a situation where this can actually be problematic, especially if you're, like,
if your observations are big, for example, if you're, like, if your observation, which
is like what your, what your policy or your agent is, is using to make a decision for
what to do next, that is something big, like an image from a simulated camera.
Then you don't want to send that over the network, just because there's so many of them
and just clogs up the entire bandwidth.
Where we'll probably look into the, and just switching to the sending over the gradients
over the network over, over the next few months, especially as we move to these more
like high dimensional observations.
And is the, the infrastructure that you're doing all this with, like, is this all hand
crafted stuff or, like, I had a conversation with Ian Stoica about Ray the other day,
like, you're using something like Ray to do that.
So we're actually using Kubernetes.
Yeah.
So, so we, I believe we had a, we did like an infrastructure blog post about this a couple
months back, but basically we run, we run lots of Kubernetes clusters across all of the
major clouds as well.
Like, we're running on, we're running on Azure, we're running on AWS, you also have some
stuff running on Google.
So yeah, there's a, there's a, there's a lot of compute.
The way actually we went is using these tools is actually somewhat simple.
You, you basically just tell, tell Kubernetes in our case to, here's this batch job, run
this thing once for the GPU optimizer and run this thing once for the couple hundred
worker machines and it just kind of goes in, does it?
But there is like, there is a ceiling there where like, where you can't, just because it's
not really the original use case for Kubernetes, I believe the, like, what they, what they
recommend as a limit is like, not more than, say, 10,000 nodes, which is just a lot, of
course.
And have you bumped up against that one?
Yeah.
So we have bumped against previous limits where the limit was something like 5,000 and
then it won't crash, but it will just become like more and more unhappy and just stop
responding and like, basically things will become weird in the cluster.
And how long are these simulation jobs?
Are they, you know, they're not like on the order of training jobs that are days and
days.
They're much shorter.
Is that the case?
Yeah.
So, yeah.
So basically, so one specific cycle is much shorter.
Like a one specific cycle of basically get the current policy parameters to a bunch of roll
outs and then back.
That's something like maybe like a second, but the way we actually start them is we, we
basically just keep the keep these like rollout machines around the same way that we keep
the training.
So they basically they just want like temporary cluster basically.
Okay.
And that cluster will just stay around for the duration of of the entire training, which
is like maybe like a day or a day.
Okay.
Interesting.
And so, you know, all this is to help you develop a kind of a better model, the simulation.
Like, what do you do when you want to test that in the real world?
Ah, yeah.
This is going to be a pretty important question for you.
Exactly.
So, yeah.
So the kind of interesting thing is that a lot of other areas in machine learning, they
just kind of stop short of that.
And they're like, well, this is a model looks pretty reasonable.
Right.
So it's fine.
We're done here.
And so we're actually really adamant about like dumping through all the hoops to actually
to actually make it run on the robot.
Okay.
Because we found that it helps like keep us honest.
Basically it's like very easy to be impressed by like cool stuff happening in a simulator.
But usually there's some caveats that make it harder.
For example, like if like some of the like robots meshes, like aren't actually like touching
each other or something into a robot mesh.
So basically that's kind of just the shape of like some like part of the robot, like a
limb of the robot.
Okay.
And usually for example, for the for when you're determining whether like the robot is pushing
something, you do this like collision test of like is the robot colliding with an object
and if yes, then you push the object away.
But the thing is like while like while you have to super nice like visual rendition of
the robot with like a nice like models, all the aspects and excrues or something.
Yeah.
Often the geometry is actually used for this collision check, which actually determines
what's happening in the like physics wise might be like a like a simple version of this
geometry.
Like it might just be like a cylinder where the actual robot is something super complex
like it with like rounded corners or something like that.
So your angles are all off and kind of this power.
Yeah.
So like this gone, so like kind of like tricky and just thinking of thinking that something
works.
Whereas it doesn't actually work if you try it in the real world right now.
And so the so the way we run we actually run run our policies on the real world.
We have developed our system called robots as a service, which basically means that the
robot goes onto the network and then people can connect to it and like run like run specific
algorithms or like the models that they trained on the robot.
And so there's some like specific like technical things that they think is like non trivial
because it is like a real time environment and you can't just basically it's much harder
than just simulating like a piece of software like people often do with like Atari games.
For example, for training, you have to be careful if you don't miss like a cycle because
otherwise your policy will get super confused because your time step will just be longer
for example.
So basically like working on all these artifacts has actually turned this robots as a service
system into into a pretty big engineering project here.
So the example you gave struck me is something that is more of a training artifact and training
issue as opposed to deploying it to the physical robot like how is it how does it manifest itself
on the physical robot in such a way that you could do something about it there.
Yeah.
So the specific example of like so in simulation, it would start at like T equals zero.
Then you get some like current state to decide what you want to do and you set the action.
But basically while you're thinking about this simulation stops right it's paused.
So basically you do this computation then you get your output and then you advance a simulation
by one step and then you repeat you think again and you step again.
In the real world of course all of this happens like simultaneously and you I just don't
get the chance to just like pause and think for a while.
So you've got inertia and continuous variables and all the stuff that exactly exactly.
But you raise a very interesting question like is it a training problem or an evaluation
problem and actually for most of these things these things it can be both like like sticking
with the like timing discrepancy example.
There's basically always like this is pretty much like a decision we have to make for like
every every issue so much of this that comes up is like are we okay with like investing
time in actually like ironing out this issue in our like in our software stack or should
we just be like oh well I mean if there's some fluctuation in the time step then we
can just train with that and basically just add that to this to the set of things that
we randomized in simulation right and basically there's always a balance of these two choices
like either make the simulation harder or make your your real world system more predictable
to execute and so this is kind of it and this is kind of an area where you have to pick
your battles to some extent right because if you like if you have if you just have too
many unknowns then it's while like there's like a theory radical it should be theoretically
possible for for you to be able to learn a model that can cope with all of these uncertainties
it will just be very hard to practice to debug it and inspect it and see if something
was wrong and you can't and then you will basically you will see a break and then you'll be like well
so why did it break and basically they're getting to the bottom of that requires you to exactly
do this part where you remove like as many of the unknowns as possible but you surely read that
basically it's in the end our policies eventually we want them to be capable of basically you put
them on your robot that is very terribly instrumented or has like really weird software that causes
like lags and delays and just figure it out I don't think we're there quite yet okay okay
and so you call this robot as a service do you have is it like on demand like you have a
a bank upstairs of like thousands of robots just swinging around and or do you have you know
a robot or two connected to the network that folks can like you know there's a calendar
an outlook or whatever that they schedule their robot time with like how cloud like is this
I really wish it would be the former but but it is in fact closer to the latter so we actually
thought about and actually some others so some folks over at Google I think this was circulating
they they actually did this they bought a bank of robots they bought I think like around 50
or something like robot arms right and just had them do these like grasping grasping tasks
yeah we thought about doing that too but at least with the current setup it's it's exactly
that like we have a fetch we have a couple big we have a couple other of other robot arms
and these are like individually connected to the network and we usually do the scheduling by like
whoever is around the robot at the time um so scheduling by proximity exactly exactly okay the
main reason why they actually need like a specific system for like accessing the robot there is
that so these robots all come with software right they come with some kind of software they come
with either like they come either with some integration for Ross which is the robot operating system
which is a big open source effort to to provide like a like a very like unified framework for
you're not a bit Rosscon that's going on now I think oh is this going on right now and bank
over oh great well shout out to Rosscon so we're actually not using Ross
yeah so we found that like Ross actually really great if you if what you have is you have a robot
and then you have a bunch of like other things around it that you want that that you want to use
for example you have your robot arm and then you might have like some like like a light
I think I've got a bunch of modules and yeah exactly exactly just so many yeah and and you have
and you have like tracking cameras or you have like maybe you have like one one robot that is your
arm and then one robot that is your gripper and they need to be independently controlled or
something like that and we found that that is that's really great that like all these things
already ship with with the ship with drivers for Ross and you can just plug them plucking together
and they will and they will just work pretty much out of the box I think for us it it kind of comes
back to the issue we we talked about before this where where they are just timing uncertainties
basically and you don't really know what's what's going on inside the system for example if you had
this this case where you have a robot and you have some external sensor and in Ross they
would just appear like here you're about to use the sensor great you're all set but actually
there might be like subtle things there were for example the timing updates for both of these
systems might be out of phase where like the robot updates and then there's delay and then the
sensor updates and then then you will have like a timing lag there and while this wouldn't matter
in like for a lot of the like like classical applications where you do something where like
you collect data over 10 seconds or something and you're basically doing this in a very slow
way and then then you don't really care about what what the what this is like tiny differences
it cause problems for our case where we basically we try to instantly react to like if something
changes in the in the environment you might be at tens of milliseconds before we feed this back
into like into the policy to correct correct for that and so this is why we actually have to be
like super careful about like what are the exact timing like timing phases of all these sensors
and so so we found that a better lot of the lot of the Ross abstractions are actually they
can encapsulate this and hide it from you which is actually great I think for the majority of
use cases it just doesn't work that well for us so we actually do need full control over these
things okay so do you did you write your own operating system or is it more like less like an
operating system more like a thin layer that you know I'm assuming that at the bottom of this it's
all kind of just your controlling step promoters and stuff like that through IO ports and you know
there's got to be some kind of you want some kind of software layer there to make that a little
easier did you just roll that around yourself exactly so it's pretty much like a layer of middleware
basically so we didn't we didn't really write right our own OS or something right so for some
of our robots we actually we basically get rid of all the software that they ship with yeah and
just basically like if there's some firmware on like some embedded microcontrollers on the robot
then we will we usually won't touch that because that and that will because that will also usually
be fast and predictable like well defined yeah but so the issue with the with the off-the-shelf
option was like code path lengths or you know you know variable because they're accounting for
plugging in like external modules and all that kind of stuff is it that well yes so there's
certainly a lot of complexity in that like they like they basically have this this entire framework
for being like plug and play but but like they're actually also like real operational issues where
like for example like this the the timing issue I just mentioned like wouldn't be because they like
it's not that crazy basically that we have to like make sure that our code has like constant
execution time or something it's just you have to like for example like usually these like systems
have some kind of trigger signal okay and you have to you basically just have to to lay your
code out in a way that like now my cycle starts you trigger all the systems basically you synchronize
all of them and then you like read out all that data or something like that and that's how you
synchronize synchronize all these things so it's not so much like really like dark magic of like
performance optimization it's basically for the most part we just have like a very specific usage
pattern that requires like carefully thinking about like basically when like when when do we do what
and so pulling this all together you're trying to develop a technique that allows the robot to
you know be more like the human and can kind of do you know fine tune course correction you know
as it's operating and you train all these models and simulation like how do you then use that
with the robots and do you know do the inference to make those course corrections like how does
all that part work yeah so so basically right now what we're like what we're still like aiming for
is that we actually don't do any don't do any fine tuning basically of our model in the real world
so so we train our model simulation and then we we basically just rolled out on the real robot like
you'll be gathered all your sensor data like from the robot and from your like internal from
external like cameras and tracking systems and stuff like that and you feed that into the policy
you do the inference and then you react to that and so the basically the adaptation loop
for like figuring out like differences between the the real world and the simulator right now
is actually like at least for us it's pretty much manual still so there are lots of like there are
lots of ideas for for basically doing this kind of like metal learning where you learn to learn
to adapt to a new environment and we've had some initial success with that for basically
imitating a human doing some behavior and then you would you would figure out it's like oh what
are these the what are the semantics that the human intended to achieve with with this task
I think it's probably like like more like a more like a general segment is like this stuff is
still pretty early both in the in the robotics and the like ML communities but it is super
interesting and and eventually we'll want to do something where like we have a bunch of the
different simulators we talked about might even have like different kinds of robots and
basically just increasing the like breadth of this distribution so you encapsulate like more and
more things and and really hope that your that your policy gets to the like gets to the bottom of
like I see this is how I learned to like control a new robot in an entire new environment
okay so this is something we're super excited about and eventually we're hoping that like
this will enable a robot that can that can truly solve a variety of like very complex tasks
on a variety of different robot platforms okay and so if I wanted to learn more about
this dig into the details like see it in action like have you published code on this or like
you know what is what would be required for someone kind of you know play with this and try
to replicate what you did yeah so we did a pretty big release a couple months ago where we basically
put some of the things we talked about together like the domain randomization part and the part
where you where you observe your human and figure out okay I want to do like this specific task
and like the robot imitates this in like a new setting we have a release there where we basically
show like like show how it works like show how how the networks are aligned and like how they like
basically how we feed the data from one to the other and how they train okay and we'll probably
be be publishing at least parts of this robot as a service layer that they just talked about
together with like our next set of research results there like we figured it doesn't really make
sense for them to just be the kind of on their own because then you there's a lot of moving parts
right exactly exactly and so the the issue there is that like even if you open source the code then
it's like well great you can get started today just add a really expensive robot to the mix but like
we'll definitely be as we publish our research we want to release like both the research and the
infrastructure parts required for it okay cool awesome well Jonas thanks so much for taking
the time to chat with me about this is really cool stuff awesome thank you for having me for sure
all right everyone that's our show for today thanks so much for listening and for your continued
feedback and support for more information on Jonas or any of the topics covered in this
episode head on over to twimlai.com slash talk slash 76 to follow along with our open AI series
visit twimlai.com slash open AI of course you can send along your feedback or questions via
Twitter to add twimlai or at Sam charrington or leave a comment right on the show notes page
thanks once again to Nvidia for their support of this series to learn more about what they're
doing at nips visit twimlai.com slash Nvidia and of course thanks once again to you for listening
and catch you next time