Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast where I interview interesting
people, doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington, we've got a special treat for you with this show.
This episode is actually part of the OpenAI series of shows we ran last week, but because
it features hot off the presses research, we weren't able to release it with those shows,
but your weight is now over.
This episode features an interview with Dirk Kingma, a research scientist at OpenAI.
Although Dirk is probably best known for his pioneering work on variational auto encoders,
he joined me this time to talk through his latest project on block sparse kernels, which
OpenAI just published this week.
Block sparsity is a property of certain neural network representations, and OpenAI's work
on developing block sparse kernels helps make it more computationally efficient to take
advantage of it.
In addition to covering block sparse kernels themselves and the background required to understand
them, we also discuss why they're important and walk through some examples of how they
can be used.
I'm happy to present another fine Nerd Alert show to close out this OpenAI series and
I know you'll enjoy it.
Support for our OpenAI series is brought to you by our friends at Nvidia, a company which
is also a supporter of OpenAI itself.
If you're listening to this podcast, you already know about Nvidia and all the great things
they're doing to support advancements in AI research and practice.
And as you'll hear in this show, Nvidia's DGX1 deep learning supercomputer was instrumental
to Dirk and his team's work on the block sparse kernels project.
If you happen to be at Nips this week, be sure to check out Nvidia's booth at the Expo,
as well as the four accepted papers being presented by their team.
To learn more about the Nvidia presence at Nips, head on over to twomlai.com slash Nvidia.
And now on to the show.
All right everyone, I am on the line with Dirk Kingma. Dirk is a research scientist with
OpenAI.
Dirk, welcome to this week in machine learning and AI.
Thank you very much.
It's my pleasure.
It's great to have you on the show.
I am looking forward to learning a bit about your background and what you're working
on.
Why don't we start with the first of those and have you tell us a little bit about how
you got involved in machine learning and AI research?
Sure.
So, I started, I think, my first research position when I was doing my master's degree.
I emailed Jan Lecun out of the blue with a couple of research ideas.
I had no clue where he was.
He responded.
And, you know, it was welcoming me into his lab for six months.
So I looked up where he was and turned out to be New York.
So I was very happy with that, of course.
I'm happy.
Like 2009.
Was that for, like, a postdoc or not a postdoc, but like a research position or?
Yeah.
So I was very interested in AI.
I did a master's program in Utrecht in the Netherlands and a friend of mine was studying
in Cornell and he got me interested in a couple of topics.
So I spent about a year, you know, reading about the various ideas in the field and quickly
discovered, you know, the Jan Lecun had a lot of interesting research going on.
So I applied for a position in his lab and was accepted happily.
So this was, you know, about three years before the learning resolution started.
And I had a great time there.
So that was, yeah, that was, you know, 2009.
I published a paper with him.
I decided to do a start-up afterwards with a friend of mine in the Netherlands.
We did that for a couple of years and then I decided to go back to research and I spent
again about half a year in Jan Lecun's lab and applied for a PhD position with Maxwelling.
So he's a professor in, we just started and answered them and before he was a professor
at Irvine and my girlfriend at the time was still studying in the Netherlands.
So I, you know, preferred to have a position there.
So I was very lucky to get a position with Maxwelling in 2013.
And I was his first PhD student there.
So basically, when you start as a professor, you get like a free student as your first,
you know, student.
So I was his free student.
And because of that, I was also lucky to not be bound to a particular research direction
or topic.
So I had, you know, relative freedom to pursue my interests from the start.
So what I was interested in was combining probabilistic models with deep learning.
So I thought this was a field that was sort of underappreciated, you know, the combination.
And the first paper I published with Maxwelling was on the variational autoencoder, which
is a paper that sort of introduces a way to combine Bayesian inference in a natural way
with deep learning.
And this method allows you to train generative models in a principled way and a scalable
way.
So it skills you have to large data sets and to large models.
So that's for the key advantages, okay?
And we've talked about variational autoencoders on the podcast a few times, but I'm looking
forward to digging into that topic with you.
What else did you work on there?
Right, so, you know, the variational autoencoder that sparked a wave of various application
papers and extensions also in our lab.
So we worked on trying to get uncertainty estimation work well in deep learning models.
So as you know, most deep learning models all you do is basically learn a single value
of the parameters that need to, you know, good predictions on your test set and your
training set.
Right.
But it doesn't necessarily give you a good sort of estimate of how certain you should be
about your predictions given your limited data.
And the combination with variational inference, a potential way to achieve that.
So deep behavioral variational autoencoders introduced a trick called reprimerization trick,
which was also applicable to estimating a posterior distribution over the parameters,
which is basically gives you a quantitative estimate of the uncertainty over your parameters
given your training data.
So we did some like a paper on that.
And yeah, so that was one extension we did.
And also I, because of the variational autoencoder paper, there was a similar research direction
within the lab of deep mind that happened about at the same time.
I happened to publish my paper a bit earlier, but so they developed independently a very
similar trick.
And because of this coincidence, we started also collaborating on this topic.
So I went to deep mind in 2014 and we collaborated there on applying this method to the problem
of semi-supervised learning, which means that if you want to train a classifier from
training data, but not all your training images are labeled, then you would want to make
use of the unlabeled data to get better predictions than what you would get if you would solely
train on the labeled images, right?
Okay.
Yeah, so we basically proposed a method using variational autoencoder.
And the results that we got at the time were, you know, state of the art, but of course
we're, you know, quickly eclipsed by, you know, a wave of other papers and, you know,
that's how it happens, right?
Yes, that's how it happens.
But I mean, the variational autoencoder effort that come up in so many different contexts,
it seems like, I mean, you mentioned that even in your prior lab, you know, the initial
paper was followed up by a bunch of applications, papers that you worked on, but a lot of folks
have worked on papers using that papers and methods, I should say.
I think, you know, one of the first places I saw it was in the context of, like, generative
models for texts.
Is that a popular, am I collecting that?
Is that a popular place to use variational autoencoders, or maybe it was, there was another
one where someone took a, I think they took a bunch of, like, movie videos or movie clips
or something like that and ran them through a variational autoencoder and tried to, you
know, generate a movie clip, which was kind of interesting as well.
Before we dive into variational autoencoders, we haven't gotten yet to open AI, have we?
Right.
So, in the end of, or I think somewhere in mid 2015, I was approached by Rick Rubman, who
was assembling sort of an initial team for open AI.
And to me, it was very intriguing because, yeah, it matched very well with sort of my own
philosophy that I think it's good to, you know, to publish and to, you know, to write open
source code for your experiments, but also to, you know, put emphasis on, you know, maximizing
the probability of a positive future with AI.
Right.
So, yeah, there is, of course, currently a lot of concentration of talent in the field
at a small number of places.
And I thought it would be good to have more of, you know, to perhaps, you know, safeguard
the, you know, the openness of the field and the collaboration.
Right.
So, yeah, there is, because of the inflow of talent into, you know, commercial labs,
there is a risk that eventually, you know, a lot of these labs will, you close up and
that, you know, the benefits of the field might not be as evenly distributed as we would
like.
So, that is one of the goals of open AI, you know, to make sure that the benefits are distributed
eventually in a fair way.
Yeah.
Also, it was, of course, located in California, which is not a lot of bad place to live.
Not at all.
And you've been at Open AI for how long?
Since the start, basically, so the first few months I was still working from Amsterdam.
Okay.
And then I moved here in 2016.
Yep.
Awesome.
Well, one of the things that I wanted to ask you, given that we're recording this the
week before NEPs, and I am going to NEPs, actually for the first time, is I'm assuming
NEPs is like your home conference, so you've been there many times.
I wanted to, you know, get a sense from you both, you know, if there's anything in particular,
you're looking forward to about, you know, this particular conference or, you know, any
tips on approaching NEPs as it's become, you know, quite a large conference.
Yeah.
So, this has indeed become an enormous conference.
As you probably know, the field is still more or less doubling every year.
I think the, the attendance of NEPs, you know, follows a similar trend.
So, you know, personally, for me, it's also a big, you know, social event.
Of course, it's probably, you know, the biggest conference in our field now.
So, all your friends and other colleagues come all over the world, you know, assemble
at a single place, and this is a great, you know, moment to discuss collaborations
or to discuss the newest results, you know, have a beer together, etc.
In terms of preparation, I would recommend people to read just, you know, through the agenda
and make sort of a list of, you know, papers they think are most interesting before they
go to the conference, because, you know, like whenever you're there, you're, you know,
it is overwhelming.
So, there, like you will have, you know, no time to, you know, to orient.
Yeah.
And the agendas are overwhelming, to be honest.
There's a ton of stuff going on there.
Yeah.
Yeah, absolutely.
And of course, one, I think the interesting thing is that a lot of the work that you
will see is already published at archive, right?
Right.
So, as soon as you see a paper, you know, you can actually already read it, you know,
long before the paper has been published on the NEPs website.
And often, you know, you follow up work has already, you know, followed the archive.
So, some papers are already outdated, you know, at the moment you see them at NEPs, which
is a bit tragic.
That's funny.
And you're publishing some work next week as well?
That's right.
Yeah.
So, with two of my colleagues, we worked on, you know, publishing a set of your kernels
to GPU kernels, which is a software for the GPU, which allow you to train and build
models with block sparse layers.
So, block sparse GPU kernels.
Maybe you talked to me before we dig into the block sparse element of this.
Tell me a little bit more about GPU kernels and where they fit in in the kind of the software
stack.
I think about, you know, at the lowest level, I think about, you know, frameworks like
TensorFlow and things like that at a much higher level, where the kernels fit in.
Right.
So, GPU kernels are, you can view them as sort of middleware.
Okay.
So, they are libraries that require you to, you know, program on the fairly low level.
And they allow you to sort of maximize, you know, usage of, you know, GPUs, which are,
of course, you know, it is hardware that runs very parallel.
So, it requires you to specialize software to make full use of that.
Basically, they are a set of middleware that is, you know, typically already implemented
in your framework.
Okay.
So, you basically call in various functions that make use of, you know, office kernels
when you build your models.
Right.
So, for example, when you, you know, when you implement the convolutional network in
TensorFlow, then you typically use, you know, various pre-built layers that themselves
call, you know, GPU kernels to efficiently evaluate, you know, the forward path and the
backward path and the gradient computation on the GPUs.
Are you developing the kernels in CUDA or at a lower level than that?
Right.
So, I did not develop the kernels myself.
Okay.
So, this was all done by Scott Gray, who is a GPU kernel expert.
Yeah.
So, he basically wrote all the kernels.
So, like, all the credits go to him.
Right.
I guess I was more asking like, well, I guess I should have asked, does one develop kernels
in CUDA or is this at an even lower level than something like a CUDA?
I'm just trying to get a sense for where they fit in.
So, these kernels were developed both at the C level and at the assembly level.
Okay.
So, fairly low level.
Yeah.
And then you mentioned, brought up convolutional neural nets as an example.
Can you give some examples of the types of kernels that, you know, a framework might implement
is this, like, for things like tensor operations, or they add a higher level or lower level
than that?
Okay.
So, your question is, like, how you can use these kernels in your models?
No.
So, I guess I'm still talking about GPU kernels generally, and, you know, what operations
they tend to represent in, for example, the case of a CNN in a framework that's, you
know, it's calling down to a bunch of lower level kernels.
I'm just looking for examples of what those kernels might be.
Right.
So, in a typical CNN, you know, you have a GPU kernel for, you know, the forward convolutional
computation, right?
So, you have a convolutional layer in a convolutional network, which is basically a linear layer
that applies, like, a convolution or the inputs.
Mm-hmm.
And the result is the output of the layer.
So, that's where you use, you know, GPU kernels.
And then there are, for example, GPU kernels for elements-wise operations.
Okay.
Yeah.
Got it.
And so, the kernels that you are publishing are for block sparse operations.
What are those?
So, block sparse operations.
So, what we release is it is a generalization of the usual matrix multiplication and convolutional
kernels you typically use.
Okay.
So, typically, what you have is when you use a convolutional layer in your model is a
weight matrix or, like, a weight tensor, which is dense, meaning that all the entries in
the weight, in tensor, a weight matrix, like, have a non-zero value.
Right.
So, there is that in, you know, as you increase the width of the network, the number of weights
increases quadratically.
By width.
You mean the number of features?
The number of features.
Right.
So, there is a quadratic relationship between the number of features and the number of weights.
Mm-hmm.
If you use a dense, your kernel, like, a dense weight matrix, an obvious solution to this
is to, instead of using a dense weight matrix, you use a weight matrix where not necessarily
all blocks, you know, or all your weights in the tensor, have a non-zero value.
So, what the block sparse kernels allow you to do is to define which of, so you basically
define your weight matrix or your weight tensor into blocks of either 8 by 8 or 16 by 16
or 32 by 32.
And then you can say beforehand for each block, whether that block has the value of zero
for every entry in the block, or actually has an actual, you know, learns, you know,
weights value.
Right.
Yeah. So, basically if the weight values are zero, which is equivalent to having a block
is, you know, all zero, then you don't, you don't have to compute, you know, that block
because the output of the layer of the operation is not a function of that block.
So, you can, you know, skip that computation.
And so, you would use this in a scenario where, or maybe I should just ask you to give
us some examples.
Imagine that, you know, what you're essentially saying by using a block sparse matrix is
that you don't care about the relationship between some features and some layers.
Is that the idea?
It gives you more flexibility in choosing how your neurons are connected between layers.
Mm-hmm.
Basically in all the existing architectures, you've given a particular layer, all the input
and output features are connected.
Right.
But this is not necessarily, you know, the optimal way to use your parameters, right?
So, given a particular budget of parameters, you might want to use, for example, a wider
network that where not all features are interconnected, but only like half of them are interconnected.
Mm-hmm.
Or, you know, 25% of them.
Or you might want to say that, okay, I'm going to just use, you know, connecting a half
of the neurons with each other and I'm going to increase, you know, the depth by a factor
two.
So basically by introducing sparsity, given a certain parameter budget, you can have either
much wider or much deeper networks.
So this is one particular application that we investigated.
But there are, you know, much more applications possible that we haven't even touched upon.
So there's a whole, like a whole series of papers that are coming out now that show that
after training a neural network, it is typically possible to remove, you know, 99% of the weights
without significantly affecting performance.
Right.
Which is, you know, it is a curious finding, like turns out that most of the weights are
useless, you know, for prediction.
These kernels, they will allow you to actually make use of this redundancy.
So after training, you could potentially just move all the ways, you know, they're useless.
That's how you have network that is much faster to evaluate.
So it would give you a speed up and, you know, future work would also involve, you know,
learning the connectivity, right?
So this is something we have not done yet, but we hope that we or others will do a future
work.
It's basically a bit similar to the brain, you know, the neurons should be connected,
which, you know, should not be connected.
So basically this is a forum of learning the structure of the model, you know, beyond
just the value of the weights, you also, you know, you also learn where, you know, where
you have weights.
Right.
And yeah, we also have some preliminary work that we did with Ristus, so we just, an
internet was here this summer.
Okay.
So right now, you are saying before training, you're specifying like where the sparsity
blocks are.
Yeah.
Is that correct?
And then.
Yeah.
And then you're suggesting that there's, you know, work, you're hoping to see work where
that's learned as part of the training process as opposed to being specified up front.
Yeah.
So this is something where we have some preliminary work, but I think this is a very exciting
direction that we or others can pursue in, you know, future work.
Yeah.
So determine where the, where the spars blocks are currently or conversely where the connections
are.
Is it, you know, is it essentially another kind of hyperparameter or a meta hyperparameter
or something that you are training and evaluating, you know, with regard to some optimization
that you're trying to make or some, you know, or the performance of your, your network
as a whole or is there, you know, some set of heuristics or intuition that tells you,
you know, where you should have the connections.
Right.
So in choosing the sparsity pattern in our published work, we took inspiration from the field of
the small world networks.
Small world networks.
What are those?
Yeah.
So small world networks, they are a type of graph basically that you find various systems,
including the brain.
Okay.
So you also find it in social networks, right?
So you or any person on earth is connected to any other person on earth in a small number
of steps.
Right.
Six degrees of Kevin Bacon.
So this means that even though, you know, the number of connections you have and the number
of connections that any person, you know, in the world has is relatively low, you are still
connected to any other person in the small number of steps.
And you find the same property in the human brain at a functional level at least.
So, you know, the functional modules in the brain are often mostly locally connected,
but there are some more or less random long range connections.
And due to these more or less, you know, long range, long term connections, you know, the
whole brain is connected in the small number of steps, which means that information is
spread throughout the brain relatively quickly, even though you have a huge number of neurons.
So this is something we took inspiration from when choosing, says, you know, a disparity
mask in our networks.
There are very simple algorithms for generating graphs that have this property.
So these are called small world graphs.
They basically, they just, you know, require you to have a certain percentage of your connections
in your random.
And so this is indeed a hyper parameter, but we do have the guarantee that information
mixes in the relatively small number of steps.
So even though you introduce varsity in your network, so for example, we train, we
have trained a big LSTM that is, you know, 98% sparse, which means that, you know, 98%
of the connections between type cents are not there, right?
So any neuron is only connected to about, you know, 2% of the neurons in the previous
time step.
So even though it's only, you know, it's only 2% in a small number of steps every neuron
is connected with every other neuron, which means that we basically do is we introduce
a number of internal steps in the network between external time steps that allow information
to spread through the whole network before you process a new input.
Can you say that last part again?
Right.
So because of the small world property, right?
We basically only need to introduce a small number of intermediate steps between inputs
to basically have a network that is fully connected.
So after we see an input at a certain time step, you want the, you know, your brain to
basically, you know, integrate that information across, you know, all neurons.
And because of the small world property, you only need about, you know, 5, you know,
steps of the internal time steps in order to make sure that the information is spread
through your, yeah, your whole network.
The time steps are our property of LSTMs.
Does this apply to other types of models as well, like CNNs?
Yes, definitely.
So we, we applied the same technique, you know, to convolutional kernels.
So in this case, you, you know, we, it's your sparsity in the feature dimensions,
convolutional kernels, and we also found there that indeed helps you get better performance.
So yeah, we've done a couple of experiments.
So one is on, so basically what we showed is that if you take an existing architecture
with an existing convolutional kernel, so you take in a, like a res net or, you know,
the pixels CNN and you replace the regular convolutional kernels with locks, spars kernels
and then you eat or widen or deepen the network, you know, while keeping a number of parameters
the same, you get better performance in many situations.
What's the analog to introducing additional time steps in the LSTM and the convolutional
network?
Right.
So in the convolutional network, you can, for example, in a res net, what worked well is
that we, we simply doubled the, you know, the depth of the res net.
So a res net, you know, consists of a couple of stages and between stages, you down sample.
So in one experiment, we took a res net for, you know, C410 and we, we doubled the depth
of the network and we introduced 50% sparsity, the 50% of the weights are not there anymore,
which means that, you know, the total number of parameters is approximately the same as
before.
Right.
And because of the additional depth, you still have a good mixing of information.
And so the rest of, so we kept the rest of the architecture the same, so the same
murder rates, the same, you know, the same hyper parameters, we kept, you know, everything
fixed and we saw that it led to an improvement of the accuracy of the model.
The smart world model that's giving you, that's giving you an algorithm that you can apply
to determine which 50% of the data you're basically getting rid of and which you're keeping.
Or is it giving you a, you know, some kind of bound or guarantee that if you get rid
of, you know, X percent of information, you'll still have the number of, you know, a given
degrees of connectivity or convergence or something.
What exactly is that telling you?
So we're, we're not actually getting rid of any data, right, because the, so the state
is still, is still dense of the model.
So all we're doing is introducing sparsity into weights.
So we're not, we're not, you know, removing any, any information from, from the state.
While you're not getting rid of data, strictly speaking, you're still kind of getting rid
of data in motion in a sense, like you're making it harder for the network to, to learn
or to get a piece of data in a given step, right?
You mean that the number of weights per step is, is reduced by a factor two, so the number
of revenues is reduced by a factor two?
Right.
I guess, I guess what I mean is that, you know, ultimately when you do this, the network
is still operating on less information than it had in a fully connected sense.
Maybe before you, you know, do things like add time steps and, you know, broaden, broaden
or deepen your network, just if you were to have a fully connected network and then you
use zero out some of the weights, like the network is then, is it fair to say that the
network is operating on less, less information than in the fully connected sense?
Yeah, so it is important to note that this is something we do before training, right?
So we actually train with the sparsity, right?
So yeah, so before you deepen or widen, you remove half weights, then indeed you do simply
have half the capacity, you know, to store anything in your weights, obviously, right,
right?
So it is, it is important, I think, to do, to keep the number of, you know, parameters
at least equal, it's just basically you are assigning your parameters in a different
way to the model.
Okay.
So the model I still, in principle, the same capacity to store information, it's just
that the, the way it uses the parameters is a little bit different.
Just to summarize that, you, you are indeed reducing the model's capacity to store information
when you remove half, let's say, of the weights, but you're compensating for that by either
increasing your breadth or your depth.
Yeah, that's what we are indeed doing.
Okay.
And then in the future work, I have, you know, believed that we can figure out how to,
you know, learn the sparsity.
And, you know, actually, you know, during training, be able to remove a large percentage
of the weights, you know, without getting worse performance.
So that's division.
How sensitive are, well, in the case where I think with the LSTM, you said you got rid
of 98% of the weights, I would imagine that which weights you get rid of is very important
or, you know, conversely, which weights you keep are very important.
But do you have some way of measuring the sensitivity of a given networks performance
to which weights you remove?
So we choose a particular sparsity, you know, pattern before training.
Right.
And then we use either, you know, a wider or a deeper network, right?
So then we train the weights, so the model has to sort of figure out what meaning to design,
you know, to each neuron and to each weight.
Right.
So we leave it up to the model to use, you know, the given sparsity pattern.
So what we found that worked well in case of LSTM is the so, you know, so called Borevelsi
Albert Rav, which is a type of small world network where you have a small number of neurons
that are connected to a very large number of auto neurons.
Mm-hmm.
And then you have like a long tail of neurons that are very sparsely connected.
We found that it, you know, that this worked, you know, really well for text.
So what we did in this case is that we increased, you know, the size of the state of the LSTM,
right?
So you have a much wider model, which also gives you a longer memory of the past, right?
Because you get, you know, to fit more information into the state of the LSTM than otherwise.
And what we found is that if we trained a sentiment classifier based on that state, so we first
train an LSTM, completely unsupervised on text, and then we train a linear classifier
on the state of the LSTM to predict the sentiment reviews.
And then so what we found is that we get state of the art results in predicting sentiment
based on that model.
So the previous state of the art was published by Alec Redford, which is also co-author of
this paper.
Okay.
A couple of months ago.
But now we found that if you train a much, you know, wider network to this sparse, you
get even better results.
This basically, you gave us a state of the art results on like five benchmarks of just
playing sentiment in text.
Right.
And so this is an example of how, you know, within the same parameter budget, reconfiguring
the way you use that parameter budget can give you much better results.
Exactly.
Yeah.
And is there any intuition as to where you're likely to see that effect or where you
would likely want to apply block sparse kernels, or is it something that, you know, will
just have come out of experimentation?
Yeah.
So, you know, the space of possible architectures that you can train with these kernels is so
huge.
And there's just no way that, you know, we can explore it all.
So, yeah.
Is it what we aim, you know, with this release is to basically, you know, give it to the world
and let everyone experiment with it because, you know, you know, we're way too small to
explore this useful space.
So yeah, I have, you know, some limited intuition.
Mm-hmm.
And what is that?
What's your intuition telling you that where my folks want to look first or where would
you like to see folks looking to apply this?
Right.
So, Scott is building in the capability now of actually having like a dynamic sparsity.
So hopefully this will be finished before the release, you can see, meaning that varies
during training.
Yes.
So, you can actually learn the sparsity mouse during training.
Okay.
And you could then potentially optimize it, you know, to get more performance.
Right.
So, in other humans, it's, you know, we know that the way our own neurons are connected
is also learned.
Right.
It's based on data.
Yeah.
So, so this is, this is a way of, you know, learning the architecture of your model.
So, personally, I think this is, this will be a very interesting area of research.
Yeah.
So, you know, maybe I'm kind of beating a dead horse here.
But it sounds like there's really two things that could be accomplished here and that they're
kind of different.
And I'm wondering if, you know, there's some way that you think about these one is, you
know, given a parameter budget, you know, re-architection your network using block sparsity
to improve your results.
But separate from that, there's this, you know, issue of this whole, you know, finding
the right 2% of parameters that actually matter and then using block sparsity as a way
to implement the network that, you know, just has what matters and presumably the result
is that you're able to compute those, you know, much more quickly.
Right.
And I'm thinking about that the right way and are those, you know, do you think of those
as the same problem or are they, you know, kind of, you know, two different problems,
you know, that are enabled by this block spars kernel approach?
I think you have right.
Yeah.
And these are indeed two problems that you can, you know, now tackle.
And indeed, yeah, so either, you know, static sparsity, which is what we have done in our
experiments or dynamic sparsity, which is sort of where you allure the sparsity pattern.
Yeah.
That is also an interesting application of this.
And so it strikes me that a big part of the reason why you care about any of this at
all is because of computational limitations.
Is that the main idea?
That's the main idea, but that's, that's I think the main idea of the whole field of
computer science.
Right.
Too sure.
You know, that was a little bit of a segue into in spite of the fact that, you know, we're
getting around computational limitations here.
You actually had access to some, you know, pretty fancy hardware to kind of try this
out on.
Can you talk a little bit about, you know, kind of the specific problem that you, you
know, the problems that you were looking at to kind of push the, you know, the, the
limit and then, you know, how the experimental results you saw on the, you know, the hardware
that you were using?
Absolutely.
So one of the problems that we wanted to solve is to train a huge LSTM on a very large,
very large data type of text and then the Amazon reviews.
Okay.
And we were so lucky to have access to an NVIDIA DGX1, which is hardware from NVIDIA
that allowed us to train much larger models than we could have trained otherwise.
So yeah, this, this was something that enabled us to basically get state of your performance
on the Amazon reviews data set.
And this was also instrumental to get the results I talked about on access to flying sentiment.
What was it about the LSTM that made it huge?
So the Amazon reviews data set is just a very large data set of reviews on Amazon obviously.
Do you remember how many reviews, how many reviews are in that data set?
I don't know, like Adam has, but it's, it's like a large portion of all of them.
So basically the model that you could fit on this data is like an order of magnitude
larger than anything we tried earlier.
So you also need, you know, hardware to be able to fit such a model.
And if you weren't using the DGX1, what would you have used otherwise and how did the results
that you saw compare?
So if you wouldn't have had a DGX1, then we would have had to use a cluster of GPUs.
So recently it has become clear that for some problems, it is possible to, to train with
very large mini batches or, you know, to spread out and training a close, you know, cluster.
But then you, you will still get into problems of your number of parameters so that is not
ideal still.
And typically, you know, still need to, you know, fit your parameters on the single GPU.
So even if you can, you know, split your mini batch data across multiple machines, then
you're, you know, still bottlenecked by the memory of all of the single machines.
Okay.
And do you have a sense for at the end of the day, you know, well, how long did it take
you to train your models and like how, do you ever sense for how much faster it would,
you know, it was relative to what you would have done otherwise?
I think it allowed us to train the model about twice as fast as otherwise.
So it's still true, I believe, about, you know, two weeks to train the model.
Oh, wow.
Wow.
It sounds like a really interesting project with some potentially broad applications that,
you know, I'll be keeping an eye out for clearly, I'll be publishing a paper around this.
Are you also publishing code or is it more the, the research results that are the important
takeaway for folks that want to build on it?
Yeah.
So it's a second.
So we are actually publishing the code.
Okay.
So we are publishing the GPU kernels.
I think this is by far the most interesting part of what we release because this actually
allows practitioners and researchers to do, you know, completely new things very easily.
So it's just basically a matter of importing a new library and, you know, replacing your
existing conclusions or matrix applications with, you know, the block sparse ones and
they're good to go.
So yeah, it is actual software to use for others.
Okay.
Do you at this point have a place that you can point folks to or do you know where folks
will be able to find this work once it's published?
You can find a work on OpenEI.com and you go to the blog posts there.
You will find a blog post on this topic and a link to get up.
Okay.
Fantastic.
Great.
I really enjoy chatting with you.
Is there anything else that you'd like to leave the audience with?
Yeah, I think we had a very interesting conversation.
Thank you for inviting me to the show.
And yeah, I encourage everyone, you know, to keep sharing results, you know, to publishing
source code, all of your experiments and keep an eye out on the research of OpenEI.
So that's it.
Great.
All right.
Well, thanks.
Thanks very much.
Okay.
All right, everyone, that's our show for today.
Thanks so much for listening and for your continued feedback and support.
For more information on Dirk or any of the topics covered in this episode, head on over
to twimlai.com slash talk slash 80.
To catch up on our OpenEI series, visit twimlai.com slash open AI.
Of course, you can send along your feedback or questions to me via Twitter to at Sam
Charrington or at twimlai or leave a comment right on the show notes page.
Thanks once again to Nvidia for their support of this series.
To learn more about Nvidia and their presence at nips, remember to head on over to twimlai.com
slash Nvidia.
And thank you once again for listening and catch you next time.