Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast where I interview interesting
people doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington and we are back.
First things first, happy new year everyone and welcome to 2018.
I had a great holiday but I've definitely been itching to get back to the show.
As most of you know, at the end of last year we held a listener giveaway to celebrate
hitting one of our biggest milestones to date, 1 million plays of this podcast.
Thanks to everyone who entered.
We sent out an email to entrance a few days ago so please be on a lookout for that.
If you haven't heard from us yet, just reach out to us at teamattwimlai.com so that we can
get you your swag.
Next up, the details for our January meetup are set.
Next Tuesday, January 16th, we'll be joined by veteran Twimble guest and Microsoft researcher
Timnett Gebrew.
Timnett joined us just a few weeks ago to discuss her recently released and much acclaimed
paper using deep learning and Google Street View to estimate the demographic makeup of
neighborhoods across the United States and I'm excited that she'll be joining us to
discuss her paper and the pipeline she used to identify 22 million cars and 50 million
Google Street View images.
I'm anticipating a very lively discussion segment as well in which we'll be exploring
your AI resolutions and predictions for 2018.
For links to the paper or to register for the meetup or just to check out previous meetups,
visit twimlai.com slash meetup.
Finally, a bit about today's show.
I'm joined by David Venturelli, Science Operations Manager and Quantum Computing Team
Lead for the Universities Space Research Association's Institute for Advanced Computer Science
and NASA Ames.
David joined me backstage at the NYU Future Labs AI Summit a while back to give me some
insight into a topic that I've been curious about for some time now, Quantum Computing.
We kick off our discussion with a review of the core ideas behind Quantum Computing including
what it is, how it's applied, and the ways it relates to computing as we know it today.
We then discuss the practical state of Quantum Computers and what their capabilities are as
well as the kinds of things you can do with them.
And of course, we explore the intersection between AI and Quantum Computing, how Quantum
Computing may one day accelerate machine learning and how interested listeners like you
can get started down the Quantum Computing Rabbit Hole.
And now on to the show.
All right, everyone, I am here at the NYU Scorbal Center backstage just as we're finishing
up the NYU Future Labs AI Summit.
And I have the pleasure of being seated with David Venturelli, who's the Science Operations
Manager for the Research Institute for Advanced Computer Science at NASA Ames.
David, welcome to the podcast.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
It's great to have you on the show.
And I am really looking forward to this conversation because you are doing a ton of work
in an area that I know very little about, but keep hearing a lot about.
And that is Quantum Computing.
So before we get into me peppering you with questions, why don't you just tell us a little
bit about your background and how you got into Quantum Computing yourself?
Yes.
So I'm a physicist.
I'm a theoretical physicist.
And I did study Quantum Mechanics like every physicist does.
Back when I was PhD students in 2008, 2007, there was hype on inside the physics community
about Quantum Computing, but it's nothing but it's nothing like what we have today.
What I did, I did study Quantum Information Science, I did study nanotechnology.
And of course, I have seen in front of me unfolding the opportunities of actually not only validating
the theories on pen and paper, but now experimenting with real world quantum machines.
So I joined Quantum Artificial Intelligence Laboratory in 2012 as one of the founding members.
NASA, Google and USRA, University Space Research Association, decided to create this
group to investigate the near-term impact of quantum computing for computational problems
of national interest.
And that was, you know, what I've been doing in the last five years.
We managed the projects, collaboration with government, academia, and with, of course,
the principal stakeholders, the private sectors as well, to understand, really, if in the
next five to ten years, there could be an acceleration of computing because of quantum
technologies.
Great.
I guess the place to start is on quantum technologies and quantum computing.
Like, I imagine that it is something that many in the audience have heard of, but don't
fully understand, you know, not just what the big ideas are, but what are the foundational
ideas upon which it's built.
And I'm hoping maybe you can walk us through some of that.
Yes.
The idea comes from the 80s when one of the gods of physics, Richard Feynman, made the observation
of the conference, the casual observation that if we were able to create a computer which
worked with the laws of quantum physics, then simulating quantum systems would not be
very difficult, while today it's very, very difficult to do that.
We need supercomputers and blah, blah, blah.
So this observation changed the world because the idea of processing information with the
fundamental laws of nature as APIs, as elementary building block of the algorithms, really got
every physicist excited, some early discoveries on the fact that the mathematics of quantum
mechanics is fundamentally more powerful than the mathematics we employ when we process
information in standard digital computers, really got everyone excited.
Can you give us some examples of that?
Yes.
People have discovered in 96 that you can search a database, an unstructured database where
basically all the information is not arranged by any sorting, normally to search such database
you do not have any smart way to do it because you just have to randomly make queries.
And if you're unlucky you will find what you're looking for as the last attempt of your query.
And that means that the problem has linear complexity meaning that if you have n items
you need n trials to get to the item you want in the worst case scenario.
Now if you had the quantum database and the ability of doing quantum queries and you exploit
all these effects of preposition, interference, entanglement, you are able to find the item
you want in a square root of the number of items.
So this means that instead of for example 100 queries you need only 10.
And this quadratic speed up is a very interesting phenomenon which shows by itself that quantum
computing is more powerful than classical computing because there's no way you can beat this
without quantum mechanics.
But what people is really after is exponential speed up.
So the opportunity to devise algorithmic strategies that are able to accelerate exponentially
problems.
There are some examples in cryptography in chemistry where we know how to exponentially
bypass the bottlenecks of computation so that problems that could be solved today in
billions of years they would be solved by a quantum computer in seconds.
Well this is not the case for a lot of things that we want to solve and we are investigating
and it's so difficult to investigate these algorithms without having a quantum computer
that in some sense we want to build quantum computers to understand whether it was worth
to build them in the first place.
So is it fair then to say what I took away from that is that quantum computers isn't
the idea of kind of going piece by piece and replacing the various components on a current
system board with you know quantum versions.
It's not like you know shrinking down the physics is it is a fundamental new way of thinking
about compute that's built around the.
It's a new paradigm.
It's not incremental improvement is really a different fundamental way to process information.
Of course quantum effects are already very well taken care of by the silicon industry in
the integrated circuitry already but today they kind of bother you because you want to
shrink things you want to make them more faster.
Now what we're talking about is assigning a functional role to the quantum effect and
actually assigning logical states and variables to quantum states and then very finely very
delicately orchestrate their quantum dynamics so that we do mathematical operations on our
logical assignments and this is a new paradigm.
It is operating on probability distributions which are weird because they're not over
real numbers they're over complex numbers so there are imaginary units involved and it's
very interesting mathematically and funny enough for the listener of this show you don't
really need to know physics to become a quantum algorithm person.
It's actually linear algebra so as long as you accept why quantum mechanics works you can
study it in an after what if you have the mathematical background you can study it fast and
just you don't know why it works it doesn't matter but you can start writing algorithms
because it's just you know matrix multiplications and things like that.
What are some of the you kind of rattled off some quantum primitives that you know upon
which this math and these computers are built can you kind of give us the next level of
detail and to you know some of the most important ones.
Of course the main paradigm which is explored today is to use binary variables so bits basically
but generalized in the quantum world so the idea of using quantum bits or qubits so you
do identify a physical system it could be a superconductor or it could be an atom it
could be an electron it could be a photon anything anything which is sufficiently small
cold protected from the external environment follows the laws of quantum physics even cats
and boxes apparently so as long as you are you're able to to find that then you you look
at the states of the system and then you identify what is you're called zero and what you
call one for example it could be more states in a quantum system yes but you choose two
of them.
Oh really?
You say you say okay this electron can have spin up or spin down for those that know physics
or this photon can have polarization in one way or in another this superconductor can
have a clockwise current or counterclockwise current and then you look at how you can act
on the system so similarly as you do in chemistry if the system is quantum you can manipulate
their state like in chemistry you can do chemistry reaction but this time you need to be very
controlled so if it is an atom you need to shine a laser if it is a circuit you need to
apply a magnetic field and all these kind of things and when you do that you know how
your state will change the fun fact is that it is totally true in quantum mechanics that
you can have a state which is not zero not one it's kind of a superposition of the
true and is represented by this abstract vector in a complex number subspace where you
represent zero and one at the same time now when you look at it it will be zero or it
will be one with some probability but if you don't look at it then it's both and you
can operate on it like if it is both until you look at it.
So the algorithm the job of the of the programmer is to figure out the way to operate on this
ensemble of qubits in such a way to orchestrate the probability at the end to be the solution
of the problem you want to solve but that's a complex job because you know if you have
and qubits what you are really describing is a state which has an exponential number of
degrees of freedom so and you need to to basically describe it with true to the power of
and complex numbers and there's no way you can simulate this in a machine you need a
quantum computer to experiment most of the time.
So it sounds like one of the fundamental realities of quantum computing is this chicken and egg
problem like how do how do we get beyond that?
Yes you're totally right we are getting beyond that we decided I don't know the chicken
or the egg what we decided but we decided it's worth it's worth to do it and we're starting
there are companies I IBM, Riccetti, Google, Intel, they're all building chips and they're
making them available to the research community and people are trying to use them in the
short term to learn about quantum mechanics to validate the theories that are on pen and
paper have been devised in the last 30 years.
So now we are we are really using quantum computers as tools for improving our knowledge of
quantum information processing.
Yeah so IBM and tell some of these companies that you've mentioned have been talking about
this forever like in in kind of research mode I think the thing that really caught my
attention recently was I think it was their build conference one of the Microsoft's recent
technical conferences there was I think it was a keynote like their main announcement
such in Adela came out and had some researchers and they kind of you know brought out this
I'm not even sure what it was it looked like a GPU to be honest they brought out this board
that was their first attempt at a quantum computer or something you tell me what exactly
that was and what's its significance.
Yeah no Microsoft as well as IBM as you said like everyone had some quantum computing
expertise since the beginning of time meaning since when the field has a name and for good
reasons I mean good physicists kept an eye on the idea since the beginning and and this
company is higher the very good people now what changed now is that people are confident
that we can achieve great results very fast great results in terms of science not not
necessarily an applications yet because in Microsoft for example it's interesting because
they decided to they always had a very good group on architectures and quantum operative
systems and quantum compilation methods but now they decided to expand and go experimental
as well their approach is long term they want to do a topological quantum computing which
is a complicated mathematical theory which is allowing this type of computer to be automatically
protected against the noise of the external world so it would be amazing if it ever works
however as far as we know nobody has ever even created a single qubit so everyone is really
looking at what they are thinking of doing because even the announcement of a single qubit
would be would be interesting.
So let me just hit pause on that so the the qubit is the fundamental unit of this computer
it's it's the bit in contemporary computing yes and we've not produced one yet no no
in the approach that Microsoft was they didn't now for to give you access so IBM as 16
qubits operational allowing researchers to use them and we'll use a 16 qubits does that
mean 16 bits just 16 is not 16 that's an array of 16 oh okay no no you you can not
even solve a Sudoku with that it's it's nothing okay Google has nine but 22 under testing
49 announced then Regeri has about eight now D wave has two thousand which is oh my
god D wave is so far ahead this is D wave is a Canadian company which kind of schooled
the world in the fact that you can't try to build a quantum computer and they did before
everyone and that's even why my group exists because Google decided to buy one of these
machines a D wave machine at one of the D wave machines yes okay and to host it at NASA
and that we operated and this analogous to you know mainframe computers where it takes
a huge black box which of 40 bits no it's a 2000 but 2000 there's a catch there so first
of all so this is a huge machine it operates with cryogenic temperature saw a 13 milli Kelvin
we're talking about less than the temperature of space it requires a vacuum it requires a
helium it's a compact machine but it implements one strategy of computation which is quite
unknown meaning that not so so well studied which is called quantum annealing which does not
have all the requirements of the other kind of computation but at the same time it's unclear
the power of it so they decided indeed to create it to to experiment and and and NASA and
Google and us array decided to support the project and then after this Locked Martin bought
a machine Los Alamos bought a machine so now they're doing quite well how much does one of
these machines cost? Street price is from 10 million to 15 million I don't want to
ask them for the latest quote I don't know but it's it's actually I want to advertise in this
show everyone can use this machine a us array has a program a collaboration program for which 20%
of the machine time can be outsourced to any researcher which is submitting a proposal it's just
the five pages proposal so the the website where to find it is www.usra.edu slash quantum
and slash RFP request for proposal but so us array quantum d wave if if you google it people can
find and we have about 80 people 80 80 groups 80 research groups from all all kind of universities
around the world which are running on the machine or they they propose some of them are running
some not yet but it's a very successful problem wow and is all is all of the research that's
happening on this machine about how to build more machines like it or they are people doing you
know how far we in in terms of doing things with it can we add one plus one yet with this machine
yeah now we can we can do more than that but not much more than that no you're totally right let's
say 90 percent of the really invested research is of fundamental nature we need to improve our
understanding get different mindset and figuring out how to improve these machines themselves
at the same time I say that the programming this kind of machines using this kind of machines
can often lead to new ideas in classical computing because you need to change the mindset to frame
the problem in a different way in order to be attacked by the quantum computers so very
there are a lot of anecdotes of you know people coming up with the quantum algorithm that is
beating every possible classical algorithm that every classical algorithm was created before
and then the classical guys came back say wait a second I can improve my algorithm and then
they improved and they baited the quantum again and so on any any examples that come about yeah
but it's very nerdy example there's a recent recent recent result on QAOA which is
baptized by us the quantum alternating operator and that algorithm okay which is shown to basically
have a particular scaling which seemed to be better to what was before known on a problem which
E3-Lin it's basically connected to satisfiability but the point is like a very specific problem it
seemed that this algorithm was was beating it and then the people and then the classical computer
scientists came back and they improved their own algorithm so this is the latest example in general
I mean it's it's fun quantum computing because there's so much room for improvement in our
understanding that it's really fun for instance chemistry chemistry is the only grave of quantum
computing because we can simulate molecules much faster and and people were were writing on the
back of the envelope calculations seven years ago six seven years ago on how fast the quantum
computer would solve for example the molecular ground state of interesting molecules such as
ferrodoxin I remember it's a fertilizer it's interesting and people were we're trying to
calculate it and say okay it would still take some billions of years okay it's not very interesting
because okay with the classical computer it's impossible we'll take trillions of years one
to be able to take billions okay it's not very very worth doing it but then you know new postdocs
looked at the problem and say now wait a second it's not scaling as n to the power of 11 it's
scaling as n to the power of nine because I can do this mathematical tricks and then new postdocs
and PhD students look at the problem say wait a second why don't I do this transformation before
and I represent the problem with Gaussian waves instead blah blah blah and then they put it down
to a few years say well it's still you know not very interesting but then in a matter of like
I don't know a few months other groups improved improved improved and now we're talking seconds
wow so on that particular project on a specific molecule that people investigated you know
the initial estimates based on quantum mechanics understanding were so improvable that they brought
that they brought down n to the power of 11 to n to the power of three and and make the things
much more tractable and so now what does that what are the requirements of implementing this algorithm
that they've designed in terms of a quantum computer does our d wave 2000 bit thing get us anywhere
near that or no so d wave as I was mentioning before they can attack only some specific algorithms
combinatorial optimization with the specific method and it's unclear what the performance of
this machine can be we are investigating them early results is that it's comparable with the
Intel chips on these small problems now we would like to investigate them on large problems so
that we really could see the difference because now we're still talking about problems you can
solve in seconds so it's not really clear the overhead how much it counts and blah blah blah but
this this is interesting for d wave because again every every machine in the release is a little
bit more powerful in the previous one also on a qualitative level they give you more knobs they
give you more physical effects to experiment so that's interesting but to run the algorithms
of for chemistry for for database search that discuss our cryptography you need the computers
such as the ones which are created by now by ibn google which right now are at this nine qubit
16 qubit stage because they're much more difficult to build because they give you much more control
and they're called the universal digital quantum computers as opposed to the d wave which is an
analog quantum annealer it's a little bit different flavor so this if I could paraphrase the
architecture of the this d wave computer is limited in some way so that it can only you can only
implement these quantum annealing algorithms and that's a sounds like a smallish subset actually
we don't really know exactly we don't know what types of algorithms will be easier to build the
computers but much more limited in their algorithmical encoding to to give you an idea with 2000 qubits
we can more or less solve the problems of that you can classical problems you can encode in
50 bits roughly okay it could be 60 sometimes 100 it depends on the compilation
and is that like is that 2000 bits or the 50 bits is this the entire state of the computer like
including like a traditional computer has you know there's state in the CPU there are registers
there is all of these yeah so yes no different yes no it's let's say no no no no your your
question is on point the end to end solvers will be hybrid you know system which have a classical
co-processor quantum processor so after all you can decompose your problem pre-process it divided
in chunks so that the quantum computer just solves the combinatorial aspect of it and the other
does something in parallel so we're way behind in figuring out what's the best way to solve
you know a full problem we are experimenting right now on on on very specific special purpose
problems and in that case yes we can use only this little memory and but it's improving at every
at every stage okay so the next generation machine probably will be much better than the previous
one and how many bits do we need to get to on the universal side to be useful yeah
that's a good question so it depends on the approach for example the Microsoft approach could be
could be a few hundred for the Microsoft approach but they don't even have one okay
but for the the other approach is like the ones which are superconducting we likely need
almost a million oh wow almost I mean we're at nine yes I mean the scalability is there
what is more difficult is the error correction the error correction we have very good theories
but we need to get the fidelity of the operations to a certain level of precision but there's no
fundamental reason why we shouldn't be able to do that with good engineering you need to understand
that the quantum engineer job is a new job I mean everyone which worked on this is physicist and
physicist do not know how to you know build products yeah yeah so I mean and so now engineers
are getting are getting to this game so I believe that we will have very interesting machines soon
and there's not only the big players that are startups which come out spun off of universities
for example ion cube out of Maryland is doing an amazing job with the ion trap ion cube ion
cube cube ion cube okay they're they're trapping atoms with lasers and manipulating them they're
very very very good at this there's a University of Bristol group I mean in the UK which
has some stealth operation on fully photonic computers so basically a lot of lasers so I believe
in the landscape one year from now will be already different from significantly from the
landscape of today wow wow and that's fun so we haven't even gotten to AI yet like what's the
intersection between you're at the quantum AI lab what's the intersection between quantum computing
and AI it's a very very good question so our name is might be a little misleading we have a
is it quantum slash AI no no no like quantum AI it's quantum AI first of all AI is not only
machine learning there's a lot of methods that are considered AI since even before the
hype on machine learning took off so we do a lot of optimization it's part of the AI we do a
lot of planning and scheduling which is one of my personal work where we actually have to
take decisions of how robots operate on distant planets okay how to take the robust decisions
that's the problem that you you need to solve by model based algorithmics so so that's that's
why there's an AI in our name because we do pay particular attention to problems where
there's not good solution yet and we need expert artificial systems to solve them but the
intersection of quantum computing and AI is interesting even beyond what we do in the quantum
artificial intelligence laboratory the intersection could be on a technical standpoint on machine learning
there are approaches which are being investigated this is a very new field so we're talking about
only a few years of research where you can apply some algorithms of quantum computing to gain
polynomial speed ups on certain aspects for example training the neural networks there are
approaches where you can use quantum correlations to implement quantum neural networks okay I mean
this requires a huge number of qubits of course but people are actually looking at this kind of
and and this quantum neural networks might be very good at learning quantum problems so again
it's a little bit to self-referential but but that's that's another approach that is being
investigated and I must say there's an intersection on the other point of the arrows that there's
a lot that AI can do for quantum computing okay so the payoff will come afterwards quantum
computing will pay back in 10 years or something but for now what are some of those ideas do you
think even compiling a problem into a quantum computer is a big problem and you need and you need
method optimization on steroids calibrating a quantum computer is also a pain in okay I mean
it's crazy and again laboratories are our training neural networks and they are they are
employing heavy heuristics to be able to do that so there is an opportunity on both ends to
imagine what quantum computing can do for AI and how to employ AI to enable quantum computing wow
we're getting to the end of our time but is there a kind of a canonical reference or a place
that people can start if they want to learn more about quantum AI or not quantum AI but quantum
computing yes there are a lot tutorials which have been published over over the years not like
build your own qubits no with a 3d printer really it's really not that inaccessible as it was
few years ago okay so my suggestion is to look for the reviews and the lecture notes of the most
prominent professors in the field I suggest to look at the for example John Preskyl's lecture
notes Caltech that's a good start there's another very very skilled evangelizers of quantum
computing is Scott Aronson he has a fantastic blog which is very followed where he discusses
a lot of aspects of quantum computing so I'm sure that if the listener to this show are motivated
they will find their way and of course please feel free to contact me my my email is Davide David
with the near the end dot venturelli at nasa dot gov okay great well Davide thank you so much for
taking time out to chat with us I learned a ton but there is so much more to learn about this
I really enjoyed it thanks bye bye
all right everyone that's our show for today thanks so much for listening and for your continued
feedback and support thanks to you this podcast finished the year as a top 40 technology podcast
on apple podcasts my producer says that one of his goals this year is to crack the top 10 and to
do that we need you to head over to your podcast app rate the show hopefully we've earned five stars
leave us a glowing review and share it with your friends family co-workers the barista at Starbucks
your uber driver everyone every review rating and share goes a long way so thanks so much in advance
as you know I love to meet Twoma listeners this week I'll be at the CES show in Las Vegas
so if you're in the area and would like to meet up ping me at at sam charrington on twitter
last but certainly not least for more information on Davide or any of the topics covered in this
episode head on over to twimmolai.com slash talk slash 93 of course we'd be delighted to hear
from you either via a comment on the show notes page or via twitter at at twimmolai thanks once
again for listening and catch you next time