Hello and welcome to another episode of Twimble Talk, the podcast where I interview interesting
people doing interesting things in machine learning and artificial intelligence.
I'm your host Sam Charrington.
Just a couple of quick announcements today related to the Twimble Online Meetup.
First, the video from our December meetup has been posted and it's now available on our
YouTube channel and at twimbleai.com slash meetup.
It was a great meetup, so if you missed it, you'll definitely want to check it out.
But you definitely don't want to miss our next meetup either.
On Tuesday, January 16th at 3 o'clock Pacific, we'll be joined by Microsoft Research's
Timnett Gebru, who will be presenting her paper using deep learning and Google Street
View to estimate the demographic makeup of neighborhoods across the United States, which
has received national media attention for some of its findings.
Timnett will be digging into those results as well as the pipeline she used to identify
22 million cars and 50 million Google Street View images.
I'm anticipating a very lively discussion segment as well to kick off the session, so make
sure to bring your AI resolutions and predictions for 2018.
For links to the paper, or to join the Meetup group, visit twimbleai.com slash meetup.
Alright, now a bit about today's show.
In this episode, we hear from Siddha Gangesu, data scientist at computer vision startup
deep vision.
Siddha joined me at the AI conference a while back to chat about the challenges of developing
deep learning applications, quote unquote, at the edge.
In other words, those targeting compute and power constrained environments.
In our conversation, Siddha provides an overview of deep vision's embedded processor, which
is optimized for ultra low power requirements.
And we dig into the data processing pipeline and network architecture process that she
uses to support sophisticated models in embedded devices.
We dig into the specific hardware and software capabilities and restrictions, typical
of edge devices, and how she utilizes techniques like model pruning and compression to create
embedded models that deliver needed performance levels in those resource constrained environments.
We also discuss use cases such as facial recognition, scene description, and activity recognition.
Siddha's research interests also include natural language processing and visual question
answering, and we spend some time discussing those as well, and now on to the show.
Alright everyone, I am here at the Artificial Intelligence Conference in San Francisco,
and I'm with Siddha Gangesu, who is a data scientist at deep vision.
And Siddha, welcome to the show, it was a pleasure to have you.
Hi, thank you very much, thanks for having me.
Absolutely, absolutely, so why don't we start by having you tell us a little bit about
your background and how you got interested and started in machine learning.
So I think I got started in machine learning during my undergrad days.
So I had gone to a hackathon and I met this mentor there, his name is Anirth Kohl, and
we worked on a project there which was called orphan locator, which is basically trying
to locate missing children using the police databases, and we used a very simple image matching
algorithm there.
So I think that was my first introduction to machine learning, then after the hackathon
when I came back to college, I was like, I want to know more about it, so I think like
everybody else I started doing the Coursera course on machine learning.
The Enduring course?
Yeah, I guess after that I applied for a master's degree in data science, so I just graduated
this year from Carnegie Mellon with a master's in data science, and then at CMU I worked
on what is called visual question answering.
So that's an AI hard task which basically provides an image to a computer and a user
or a human is expected to ask a question about the image.
Now this question can be about any activity or the number of people or something related
to the image or the scene within the image, and the computer or the AI system is expected
to provide an accurate answer to that question.
Okay.
Now there are many uses of VQA of visual question answering.
One is obviously for the visually impaired, but another use is for people in situationally
impaired, for example, like if you're in a car and you're driving, so you don't want
to be looking at your phone, so your phone can basically give you a description of the
images that somebody just sent you, or if you're a security analyst then you don't have
to comb through hours of video footage, you can just query like what did the man take
from that shopping mall.
So you can just you know, you can just describe the situation sort of to a system and the
system can provide you those frames in which that happened.
So these are some of the examples of VQA, and our research was focused on how can we
use visual questions as a form of supervision for improving computer vision models, because
in the future it will become common for humans to ask visual questions to computers like
where did I leave my keys or what breed of dog is this.
Now if you look at this question, there is a lot of information already provided in
the question itself, like the object or the animal we're talking about is a dog, and
like, etc.
So that's primarily where the research was focused.
Okay.
Yeah.
Okay, interesting.
And here at the conference, you're you did a talk, or you're I forget you're doing
or you did it yesterday, right, right, right.
And but that talk wasn't on VQA, that talk.
Yeah.
That was actually on embedded deep learning, which is how you can take deep learning algorithms
which are compute intensive, and they are pretty, they are pretty big in size, and how you
can take them to embedded devices, because embedded devices have limited compute available
and they have limited storage.
Right.
So how can you run these algorithms at inference time on these devices?
So this is basically the work that I'm doing currently at my company deep vision.
Okay.
And is that the focus at deep vision, or is that just one of the many things that the
company is working on?
So that is the focus of deep vision, basically, to tell us a little bit about the company.
Yeah, sure.
So the company was founded by two Stanford PhD graduates, Rehan and Vajahad, and the
hardware or the processor that they developed was during their PhD itself at Stanford.
And this hardware is basically, it has high performance per watt.
At the same time, it is programmable enough so you can run a wide range of algorithms,
which includes both traditional computer vision algorithms and deep learning algorithms
on the same device itself.
Okay.
So if you look at most of the processor these days, if you want high performance, then
it's ideal to develop what is called a custom hardware or a fixed function hardware, which
is built basically for that one particular operation that you want.
And on the other hand, if you want a broad spectrum device, which is programmable, so
you can run a lot of things on it, it will be not as efficient as the fixed function hardware.
And an example of programmable devices are the GPUs of the graphical processing units,
but these have a high cost, so they're expensive.
And they're also really big, so you can't actually put them on embedded devices.
So they were able to figure out a way to bridge the gap between performance and programmability
through which they developed this processor.
Okay.
Interesting.
And so does the company compete with or play in the space, same space as the Intel Movidius?
It's actually a little different because we are building both the hardware and the software.
Okay.
And I don't think Movidius follows that plan.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, but the hardware is specifically focused, I'm inferring from the name DeepVision on visual
types of problems and like CNNs, for example.
So we can run like CNNs, we can also run LSTMs on it, so it's not particularly just the
convolutions.
Okay.
So yeah, like a broad range of deep learning basic systems can be run on it.
So why don't you walk us through your talk and the major points that you were trying to
convey to the audience there?
Sure.
As I already mentioned about the hardware innovation, which is bridging the gap between the
performance and the programmability.
So one of the basic ideas behind this is that the convolution operation that basically
belongs to one of the classes of those computations for which it's possible to build efficient hardware
when you build it in ASIC format or application specific integrated circuits.
So that's basically what they did and they were able to basically optimize this convolution.
Now if you look at traditional computer vision methods, most of them have like a overlapping
stencil or like a sliding window on which they run operations, which if you think about
it is similar to a convolution.
So and additionally, it's also similar in like MapReduce operations.
It's also like a window and you're repeating the method over and over again over different
windows.
So this is basically how they got the idea to optimize this one particular class of functions.
And it has wide applicability over traditional computer vision and deep learning algorithms.
And the other thing that I mentioned in the talk was that why are we focusing on embedded
devices or edge devices? And if you look at the data available for embedded devices, it's
approximately more than 150 zetabytes of video data.
So if you think about where this is coming from like airports, surveillance cameras, traffic
light cameras, basically all the cameras that you see anywhere, they have embedded devices
in them and they need someone to be looking at the videos right now.
But it is a hope that these can be automated eventually.
So that's where you will need these devices to be intelligent enough to perform real-time
analysis.
So the idea is that you've got tons and increasing amounts of surveillance data all over from
security devices, you know, home security, you know, down the home security and eventually
maybe our phone cameras will be always on right now.
I don't know.
You know, there's some people worried about scenarios like that.
But yeah, in any case, there's just tons and tons of video data all over the place.
And right now people are reviewing that manually and you would, the company is kind of building
towards a model where you're training models to, you know, identify various, you know, features
like, you know, objects or people or things like that and you would deploy those models
out to devices, inference engines that live at the edge and can basically raise flags when
different things are happening.
When more thing is that the models that you train like for home security, it will be
different than for example, airport security because in home systems, you need to recognize
like five or six people, not more than that.
But in airport, you need to recognize like thousands of people instantaneously.
So the way of training the models and developing the models in both these scenarios is completely
different.
So we're also looking into how to train each one and how to make each one dense enough
so that the model is extremely small so that we can fit it onto these embedded devices.
At the same time, they should be accurate enough that we are getting the correct results.
So is the, you mentioned the number of people that you're, that you're trying to identify.
So it sounds like one of the main use cases is, you know, in the security scenario, you
know, I see this person, you know, in this frame here, pull up other frames and videos
where that person appears, where you're, so the salient point being not just, you know,
identifying one there are people, but it's identifying specific people like maybe what
are the specific use cases or, you know, that tie to specific kind of model classes, I
guess.
So I think once the technology is in place, the possible use cases are endless, but right
now we're focusing on two main ones. And again, I talked about both of these yesterday.
So these are face recognition and scene description. So face recognition is basically finding out
the name of a particular person based on the image of that particular person.
And scene description is giving out a caption or a description for a scene, which is within
the image. Now scene description has uses in home security systems, because right now
the home security systems are such that they alert you that there is motion detected
outside your house or something is happening, but they don't tell you what is happening.
And sometimes for example, the UPS is here with the package.
Yeah. So like our system can say, okay, the UPS guy is here with the package and it's
dropped on your front door or like similar things like that. And again, face recognition
can say if like say you save your son or your daughter's face in your system, you know
that they're coming home. And so the system just tells you, okay, this person has reached
home.
Okay.
So that's another use case.
Yeah.
It's interesting. I think at least for me as you were describing, you know, what you
were trying to do, it's easy to get carried away and imagine like tons of use cases, but
they're all when you think through like the kinds of models that they would require, they're
all really different. And so you have to really focus at least now on some very specific
use cases.
Yes, that's true. But another thing is that in order to develop, say even activity recognition,
you need to have some basic recognition capabilities. For example, you need to define
like what an arm is or any other body parts. So that recognition capability comes from
like what is possible again in face recognition? Okay. So what I'm saying is, yeah. So that's
basically like when you have one face recognition model in place, the only thing you have to
do is tweak it a little bit to make it into activity recognition. Like in place of images
in face recognition, you would need a time sequence or a frame sequence in activity recognition.
Are you talking here about transfer learning, meaning you've trained a model on on faces
and now you can use it to identify arms or are we talking more about sequence related
things or something totally different? I think it's something totally different. Yeah.
Great. So what I mean is that once you have the basic capability in place like being
able to recognize faces, it is just parts of this algorithm or parts of this model that
you would be reusing in other models like activity recognition. Now you won't be using
the exact same weights because that would be completely different and you would have
to retrain the or actually not retrain trained from scratch, the activity recognition model.
But that said, the basic elements in both of these are the same like the convolutions
or the LSTMs. Okay. So you're building up the model architecture
share a lot of common characteristics? Yeah. Something like that. Something like that
would not quite that. I didn't actually understand what you said.
So the model architecture share a lot of common characteristics, meaning you're using the
same general model architectures, you know, the different types of layers. Yeah, that's
a very easy way to explain it. Yeah. Okay. I should have said that. So interesting. So I
guess what I'm curious about is you develop models. I'm assuming that the the way that
you would go about this is you want to develop facial recognition models and you, you know,
survey the literature, figure out what are the best performing model architectures to do
that, you know, implement those, train those. And then you've got this this model that probably
doesn't fit on your embedded device. Yeah. And so there's a process that you go through
to go from that model to one that fits like walk us through, you know, how how much of that
is art and how much of that is science and walk us through like the thinking as you do that.
Yeah, sure. So this process is actually called pruning. So how you can go from like a big
model to something that is just 11, like reduced to 11 times its original size. So the way
to do this is so pruning basically has three different steps in it. Well, I think there
are three different steps. So first is you need to statistically analyze your model to
ensure that the weights follow a bell curve distribution, like a normal distribution.
I get that part. I think you're responding to me looking up like, okay, why is it important
that your weights are distributed in that way? Because when you're going to prune it,
you're going to use some thresholds. Now you calculate these thresholds using the standard
deviation. And the assumptions of standard deviation are that it needs to be a bell
curve. Right. And is it is it typical or common that your weights do follow the bell curve?
Yeah, for all the models that I've tried it with, they almost always fall into a bell
curve. Okay. Yeah. So once you know that it's a bell curve, you move on to the next step,
which is the actual pruning stage. So you calculate the standard deviation of the weight
matrices. Then you find the quartiles of each weight matrix. So that's basically standard
deviation multiplied by one, two, three, four, and so on. Now for each weight matrix,
for example, if you're using a scene description model, that will have an image model and a language
model. So for each of these, you will calculate their thresholds. Then you can remove all
the weights, which are less than that threshold. So like the first threshold you calculated
said was zero. So any number less than zero, you can remove it. Okay. So this is essentially
a technique to identify and rank the contribution of individual weights in your model. Yes. Yes.
Yeah. Okay. And so then you rank order these weights in terms of their contribution and
you have some cut off and you just remove the weights that are that fall beneath that cut
off it. Now it, I'm imagining when you do that, there are ripple effects in terms of
your. That's why you need to load these weights back into the model. Okay. And then retrain
it. Okay. Yeah. All right. And then so then you, was that your third step? Yes. Retraining
is the third step. Yeah. Yeah. And then you can basically repeat this entire process
until you reach the most dense model. Okay. And is there empirical work that shows that
pruning leads to optimal compact solutions relative to, you know, some other process
that, you know, maybe starts from a smaller, more compact model and trains those from scratch
or something. So there are actually different kinds of pruning strategies available. So I
remember there's, there are a couple of papers from Stanford that talk about this method
and there are a couple of papers from University of Washington and Allen Institute that talk
about just removing one complete branch. So zeroing out everything in one convolution.
Okay. And then retraining it. So it really depends on what kind of model you have and
what results you want to attain. Okay. Yeah. All right. Interesting. Can you give us a sense
for the kinds of results where you mentioned that your, your models after the pruning process
can be like 10% of the size of the original models. What, you know, in real numbers,
like what is that? Sure. So, so if you talk about the scene description model that we,
we worked on, it's average inference time. It came down from eight milliseconds to two
milliseconds. And the accuracy also increased. So for scene description, there are different
metrics like meteor blue, rouge and cider. So there was an increase of approximately five
steps on these metrics, blue, rouge, and cider. Yeah. CIDR. Yeah. And BLEU. So these are
some image captioning metrics. Okay. These are originally machine translation metrics,
but they have been adapted to image captioning metrics. There's also a new metric called
spice, which is used for image captioning. Okay. And so you're saying that you can train a model,
measure it against these metrics, prune the model, and then increase performance. Yeah,
because you will have a dense network. Like you can change some things in a network,
like change the image model to something smaller and retrain it. And because you're starting
from like trained weights, so you have a good initialization in your system when you retrain
it. So that basically helps in going above the previously attained accuracy level.
And just to make sure I'm understanding the previously attained accurately accuracy
level for an unconstrained by size model. Yeah. That is counterintuitive to me. I, the
way I envision this is that, you know, the best performance you're going to get is when
you've got a model that's not constrained by, you know, memory power, et cetera. And
then you prune it and you make some compromises and you get adequate performance, but with
a foot, a model with a footprint that can fit on your embedded device. And what I hear
you saying is that you can actually increase your performance and shrink your model down
at the same time. Is that what you're saying? Yes. As an example of, again, the same
description model. So if you start from something like neural talk, that has a VGG network
for its image model and a pretrained LSTM for its language model. Now, if you remove
this VGG network and replace it by something smaller, like GoogleNet, and GoogleNet and
VGGNet both lie within the same top 1% accuracy range. But if you use GoogleNet and the
same pretrained LSTM and retrain this entire system, you can actually get a higher accuracy.
And so for, you know, folks that are doing research in this area and are, you know, competing
on accuracy, why don't they all just add another step in their process of pruning to come
up with a better performing model or at least try that? Because I think that's not their
main aim. Like accuracy is their main aim, but pruning is not their main aim. Right,
but you're saying accuracy can improve, but it calls you prune. Yes, that's true. But
that's, I know that because I tried that out as an experiment. Okay. So I mean, if you're
a PhD student, I doubt you will have time to experiment with pruning just for fun. Okay.
Yeah. And so how, so that I'm not making assumptions here, are you are serving that? Yeah, maybe
I'm jumping to conclusions and you're not asserting that increased performance is or
accuracy is a general result as opposed to just having to see this. It's not a general.
Yeah, that's true. Yeah, I think that's general result. It's not going to happen all the
time. It's not going to happen all the time. But there are some cases like in this case,
because the accuracy of both image models lies in the same top one person range. That could
be one possible reason why we're seeing the increase in accuracy. But if I would use
some other image model, the same results might not be repeated and the accuracy might actually
decrease. Okay. Yeah. That makes more sense. Yeah. Okay. So were there other things that
you covered in your talk? So you went through your three steps. Yeah, that's pruning.
And I think that's about it. I mean, there were a lot of other things, but there's not much
related to what we're talking about right now. Okay. Yeah. What were the other things? So
like for the face recognition pipeline, that is mostly two steps like face detection and
the actual recognition part. Okay. So can you improve on each one of these individually?
Mm-hmm. So for face detection, if you use a standard library or a traditional computer
vision system as opposed to something trained on neural networks, can you improve the accuracy,
the inference time and the model size? So for face detection, we saw improvement on all these
three verticals. Okay. And on face recognition, we trained different models using somewhat similar
architecture. Mm-hmm. So Google had released a face net paper which describes the NN2
architecture. So we built several models around the NN2 architecture and trained it with different
input sizes and saw that, you know, there's different inference time, different accuracy that
it attains and different model sites that all of these three, oh, sorry, all of these two parameters
can change. So that's something that I also mentioned in the doc. Okay. So the takeaway there is
then that if you are developing a pipeline for something like facial recognition or some of these
other, you know, let's maybe generalize it to, if you're developing a pipeline, generally,
and you want to get that pipeline to run well in an embedded environment. Yeah. You want to be
optimizing like each portion of the pipeline individually. Right. Yeah. As opposed to just optimizing,
you know, being fixed on your, your, your end pipeline and optimizing that. But that said, it's
important to like after you're optimizing each little bit of it. Right. You need to go over,
over like a retraining step for the entire pipeline. Okay. That like this end step is,
I think, the most important step. Okay. Okay. So you don't want to skip optimizing the individual
pieces. Yeah. But you want to once you've done that. Yeah. Optimize the end piece. And
is the idea that you start your optimization of the end to end system with better initial weights
for the individual pieces. Yeah. That's what I understand. Yeah. Okay. Based on like all the experiments
that I've done. Okay. All right. Interesting. Interesting. Can you walk us through? We talked a
little bit about VQA. Can you walk us through? Is that something that you work on at deep vision as
well or is it? So I think VQA will come in eventually because like I said, a scene description
is something that we use right now. But eventually you would also want people to be asking questions
to the system so that the system can give you an answer. Okay. Yeah. And can you walk us through
kind of what the, what the current state of the art is with VQA? What are the approaches
the folks are using and kind of generally how they take on that problem? Sure. So I don't quite
remember what is the state of the art now. But generally the approaches that you take an image model
and you somehow interface or communicate it with a language model which takes the question
as input. And when you're interfacing these two matrices together, the result will be a single
vector which will be the answer to the question that you have. Okay. So you can replace the image
model with ResNet, Inception, GoogleNet or basically anything or like a combination of all of these.
And the language model usually is an LSTM or you can also have it as a bag of words vector
or any other representation of the text. Now most of the work from VQA is coming from
Devi Parikin through Batra's lab. Now they also started using reinforcement learning in this.
So they're just trying to give adversarial answers and questions and having the other computer
or the other agent within the same environment, trying to figure out which of these is incorrect
and which of these is correct. Okay. So that's sort of like a brief overview of what's happening
in VQA. Okay. Yeah. Interesting. Interesting. And there are some, I don't remember the,
maybe you can remind us the name of them. There are some popular datasets that folks are using
from VQA. For VQA? Yeah, it's called the MSCoco dataset. MSCoco? Yeah, it's released by Microsoft
and it's the common objects in context. Okay. Now the images in MSCoco are actually really different
from ImageNet because ImageNet focuses on one particular object in image and whatever the
object is in focus, it usually occupies most of the area within the image. But in the cocoa images,
they're like normal scenes, like say this room, for example, it doesn't have a specific object
or there's no specific person in focus. It's like random, not random, but scenes which have a lot
of information in them. And in fact, there's also a release of the second version of the MSCoco
dataset that happened this year. Okay. So that dataset actually fixes some of the errors in,
not the errors, but actually the biases in the first dataset. For example, in the first dataset,
if you had a number of questions like how many apples are on the table, most generally the answer
would be three, or if the question is what color is anything, most generally the answer would be red.
So if you train on this, you develop a model that overfits on three reasons. So they actually
trained like an image blind model, which never saw the images, only saw the questions and the answers.
So this kind of model would just learn that if this is the question, this is the most probable answer.
Okay. And even that performed considerably well. So that's why. Yes, exactly. Yeah. So that's
why they developed the MSCoco version two dataset. Yeah. Great. Great. Awesome. Well, thank you so
much for taking a few minutes to chat with me. I really appreciate it. Thank you for having me.
And I didn't mention this at the intro, but we initially got connected because you listened to the
podcast. Yeah. I had actually listened to Chelsea's podcast, Chelsea fans. Yeah. And that's how I
really got interested. And I listened to, there was an NLP podcast from someone. I don't remember her name,
but it was pretty recent around Chelsea's podcast. And I was like, wow, there's so many things that I
don't know. Okay. That was Ornita. Yeah. Maybe. Yeah. It was a difficult name for me to remember.
Yeah. Awesome. Awesome. Well, thanks so much for listening. And thanks very much for, you know,
spending some time. Yeah. Well, thank you for, for having this great idea. And thank you for
having me today. Awesome. Thank you. All right, everyone. That's our show for today.
Thanks so much for listening and for your continued feedback and support. Thanks to your support.
This podcast finished the year as a top 40 technology podcast on Apple podcast.
My producer says that one of his goals this year is to crack the top 10. And to do that,
we need you to head over to your podcast app, rate the show. Hopefully we've earned your five stars
and leave us a glowing review. And more importantly, share the podcast with your friends,
family, co-workers, the Starbucks barista, your Uber driver, everyone who might be interested. Every
review, rating, and share goes a long way. So thanks in advance. For more information on SIDA
or any of the topics covered in this episode, head on over to twimmelai.com slash talk slash 95.
Of course, we would love to hear from you. Either via a comment on the show notes page
or via Twitter to at Sam Charrington or at Twimmelaii or at Twimmelaii. Thanks once again
for listening and catch you next time.